<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-24">July 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Fear of the Poorhouse</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-24">July 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">FEAR OF THE POORHOUSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The peasant class in all countries has an entirely horrifying fear of the public poorhouse. This is not the case with the poor of the nobility class. They have their own havens for the aged poor and you never hear of a suicide of an inmate of the "nobles' poorhouse."</p>
   <p>Outstanding in America--including Chicago--are various lodges and churches which start their own poorhouses as one of their first and most important activities, only they call them Homes for the Aged or Orphanages. To enter, for instance, a Home for the Aged is no disgrace, as compared with entering a poorhouse. Friends are permitted to call on the inmates, and groups who help sponsor each Home arrange for especially pleasant and happy Sundays by sending out favorite pastors, laymen, choirs, musical groups, and so forth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0149.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our government has built special homes for our army and navy veterans. Admission into one of these homes has no shame connected with it nor is the dignity of a veteran attacked in any way.</p>
   <p>In labor circles there is much well-directed and justifiable agitation favoring old age pensions for members of various unions, who are no longer able to work. Regardless of the name, their system is another phase of aid to the poor.</p>
   <p>The extensive pension system, regardless of methods of financing, is fundamentally nothing but aid to the poor, though not advertised as such. Neither is this classed as charity.</p>
   <p>While pleasing reports from every institution, except the average poorhouse are being appreciatively received, one often hears of disturbances and suicides in the public poorhouse. One also hears of improper care, poor food, suffering from heat or cold, [evils which are] inefficiently contended with at poorhouses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0150.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Such conditions and a lack of sympathy from the superintendent of a poorhouse are undoubtedly the reason why so many poorhouse inmates commit suicide.</p>
   <p>Poverty is a product of our economic system; if the care of the old, helpless, and impoverished citizens were turned over to our churches and lodges, and if these were financially supported by the general public as well as the organizations, fear of the poorhouse would soon be eliminated and suicide of an inmate would seldom, if ever, be heard of.</p>
   <p>There are two sides to the question of the poorhouse, the good and the bad; both should be thoroughly examined. The prospects of the writer are that he will die in a poorhouse, in case of an extended old age and inability to work. By that time, we hope that the example set by church and lodge homes, are followed in regards to the poorhouse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
