<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-07-21">July 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish National Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-07-21">July 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH NATIONAL SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish National Society of Chicago held a general membership meeting last Monday night. Mr. John E. Ericsson presided.</p>
   <p>The first item which came up for discussion was a proposal by the chairman of the charity committee, Mrs. Beda Anderson, that a festival of some kind be held in the fall for the purpose of raising funds for the distribution of Christmas baskets and presents for underprivileged Swedish families in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was agreed upon to give the committee a free hand in arranging such a festival.</p>
   <p>During the discussion, several speakers pointed out that the chief purpose of this society was to promote the well-being of our nationals in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was also disclosed that the organization's financial situation is better now than ever before, and that it is well able to take care of its obligations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0279.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The meeting ended with a speech by Mr. Gude Grindal, the head of the Swedish department of the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grindal first outlined the chief aims and working methods of the American Red Cross. He showed by a few concrete examples what this organization has done in times of great national disasters, such as floods, devastating fires, and other acts of God.</p>
   <p>He then turned his attention to the opportunities for real service, which this organization offers to the various foreign groups--Swedish and others. He declared that he knew of no other single line of endeavor, in which nationals of foreign origin had a better chance to display the finest type of American citizenship, and the Tribunen-Nyheter is here to say that in making this statement he took the words right out of our mouth.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grindal gave a historical survey of the role played by foreign groups in the work of the American Red Cross, and it was gratifying to note that the contribution made by such groups is becoming more and more appreciated by the mother <pb facs="5423404_4_0280.jpg" n="3"/>organization.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. Grindal, there was a time when foreign departments were looked upon with some degree of distrust, not to say dislike, but that is now a thing of the past; and at the present time, the American Red Cross considers its foreign departments among its most highly valued co-workers.</p>
   <p>The speaker presented a very interesting picture of the great humanitarian work done by the American Red Cross in foreign lands. When famine hits Chine, or starvation threatens the millions of India, the Red Cross hastens to the scene.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grindal concluded with an appeal to all Swedish-Americans, particularly in Chicago, to dig deep into their pockets when the American Red Cross asks for contributions. In this the Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter heartily concurs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
