<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-10-30">Oct. 30, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Notable Visitors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-10-30">Oct. 30, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NOTABLE VISITORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bishop K. G. Von Scheele and his retinue arrived in Chicago Saturday. They were met at the station by the Swedish-Norwegian Consul, representatives of the Chicago Tribune and Record Herald, and the Swedish press of Chicago represented by F. A. Lindstrand, Dr. J. Bondgren, Dr. J. A. Enander, Editors Schon and Elstram, Messrs. J. E. Carlson, Strandberg, Ranseen, Chudblom, and others. The Bishop came from New Haven, Conn., direct to Chicago.</p>
   <p>He and his wife were taken to the home of L. C. Abrahamson, 2823 Princeton Avenue, where they will be guests during their stay in Chicago. The Lutheran pastors of Chicago gave a banquet the same evening in their honor.</p>
   <p>A reception was later held at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Olgens, 843 Chase Avenue, Rogers Park. The Bishop preached last Sunday at the Immanuel Church on Sedgwick Street and in the Salem Church. The Augustana Hospital was visited.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1486.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While preaching the Bishop wore the gala robe typical of Swedish bishops, with a cross adorning his breast.</p>
   <p>After a trip to Geneva and Rockford, he and his wife will go to Minnesota.</p>
   <p>The Bishop seems to be a very human, altruistic and highly educated person. He and his wife will visit Chicago again in the latter part of November, after their return from Minnesota.</p>
   <p>See you again!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
