<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-25">July 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0737</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0737.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-25">July 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Forty-two real-estate transfers took place in Chicago last week, in which the buyer, the seller, or both, were Scandinavians as follows:</p>
   <p>J. C. Erikson to Herman Brand, Crystal Street, east of Spaulding Avenue. Price $4,850.</p>
   <p>A. Johnson to Louis Hammarlund, Humboldt Street, corner of Cornelia Street. Price $6,500.</p>
   <p>J. V. N. Standish to J. August Anderson, Claremont Avenue, South of 58th Street. Price $1,000.</p>
   <p>M. E. Bergstrom to Henry S. Saxe, May Street, South of 58th Street. Price $3,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0738.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>P. H. Seabloom to Herman Blomguist, 60th Street, east of Union Avenue. Price $3,500.</p>
   <p>O. F. Olson to John Olson, Sangamon Street, south of 57th Street. Price $6,500.</p>
   <p>E. P. Waters to G. E. Hanson, Washington Avenue, south of 63rd Street Price $2,000.</p>
   <p>A. F. Adams to Charles Anderson, Winchester Avenue, south of Cullom Avenue.</p>
   <p>R. M. Fensholt to Peter A. Stenguist, North 42nd Avenue, north of Wabansia Avenue.</p>
   <p>H. P. Anderson to Jens N. Jensen, Sacramento Avenue, north of Grace Street.</p>
   <p>J. Nordstrom to Jennie Borman, Oak Street, west of Milton Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0739.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's Note: In connection with the last four transfer records, the price is not mentioned in the paper].</p>
   <p>Carl Carlson to Richard Mahien, Sangamon Street, south of 61st Street. Price $1,900.</p>
   <p>George Anderson to H. Peterson, Haddon Street west of Rockwell Street.</p>
   <p>E. Hjelte to Nels Swanson, Thomas Street, west of North 44th Street. Price $1,000.</p>
   <p>E. M. Peterson to Carl A. Sandell, Farragut Avenue, east of Paulina Street. </p>
   <p>J. M. Carlson to S. M. Anderson, Melrose Street, east of Leavitt Street.</p>
   <p>S. M. Anderson to Johanna M. Carlson, Sheffield Avenue, north of School Street. Price $2,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0740.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A. Carlson to Cornelius E. Siebs, Wallace Street, north of 31st Street. Price $5,000.</p>
   <p>O. F. Olson to Chas. Anderson, Laflin Street, south of 61st Street. Price $1,200.</p>
   <p>N. W. Mutual Life Insurance Company to William Nelson, Superior Street, west of Western Avenue.</p>
   <p>C. J. Lindberg to Henry G. Roeder, Carmen Avenue, West of Evanston Avenue. Price $1,750.</p>
   <p>A. M. Ahlsson to Mollie Florsheim, Foster Avenue, east of Southport Avenue. Price $6,000.</p>
   <p>O. B. Jacobson to Mollie Florsheim, Foster Avenue, East of Southport Avenue. Price $600.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0741.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Jessie M. Powell to Peter J. Youngquist, Summerdale Avenue, west of Winchester Avenue. Price $8,400.</p>
   <p>William T. Johnson to Mabel E. Johnson, Alice Place, east of Leavitt Street. Price $1.</p>
   <p>M. Dunn to Gustafson &amp; Nelson, 59th Street, west of Union Avenue. Price $3,300.</p>
   <p>O. L. Johnson to August Zink, Erie Street, east of North 48th Avenue. Price $3,000.</p>
   <p>W. O. Olin to Wells H. Frost, Talman Avenue, south of Marianna Street. Price $1,200.</p>
   <p>O. H. Johnson to Nels Johnson, Thomas Street, west of North 44th Avenue. Price $1,850.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0742.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Christina A. Melin to Minnie A. Johnson, Perry Avenue, north of 66th Street. Price $18,000.</p>
   <p>Axel W. Carlson to Edely Gustafson, Balmoral Avenue, east of Robey Street. Price $4,000.</p>
   <p>C. C. Anderson to Fred Norlin, Farragut Avenue, west of Southport Avenue. Price $1,750.</p>
   <p>F. Norlin to Per G. Larson, Farragut Avenue, west of Southport Avenue. Price $1,350.</p>
   <p>Christian Hillstrom to Alexander Avio, 117th Street, west of Indiana Avenue. Price $1,500.</p>
   <p>M. J. Johnson to Wm. A. Small, Center Avenue, north of 56th Street. Price $2,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0743.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Susie Seeger to Axel Hanimer, Green Street, south of 65th Street. Price $6,750.</p>
   <p>W. Bellinghausen to Alma O. Carlson, Harvard Avenue, south of 72nd Street. Price $3,000.</p>
   <p>Edwin M. Clark to Charles A. Anderson, Lakeside Terrace, south of Harvard Avenue. Price $4,200.</p>
   <p>L. A. Anderson to Alex Glanz, Campbell Avenue, corner of Dunning Street. Price $2,000.</p>
   <p>J. L. Lee to Andrew H. Lundberg, Humboldt Street, south of Garter Street. Price $4,500.</p>
   <p>M. Larson to Charles Marden, Monticello Avenue, south of LeMoyne Street. Price $2,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0744.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Geo. W. Stewart to John R. Linn, Diversey Boulevard, west of Pine Grove Avenue. Price $25,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
