<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-04-18">Apr. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">National Society Forms Branch Here</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-04-18">Apr. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL SOCIETY FORMS BRANCH HERE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A branch of the Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in Foreign Countries was established in this city last Monday. At a meeting in the clubhouse of the Swedish Engineering Society, which was attended by some fifty people representing a variety of occupations, it was decided to form a branch organization, and everyone in the audience signed up as a member.</p>
   <p>A. G. Witting, engineer, who presided over the meeting addressed the gathering, and told of the activities of the Society and its purposes.</p>
   <p>A set of bylaws for the local organization, which had been prepared by a committee headed by Dr. C. G. Wallenius, was adopted with a few minor changes. These bylaws are similar to those laid down by the mother organization. Two general membership meetings are to be held each year, and at the first of these, which is to be held in the month of February, new officers are to be elected. The annual membership <pb facs="5423404_4_1099.jpg" n="2"/>fee is one dollar, which also entitles members to the monthly periodical published by the national organization and to its yearbook.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected: president, A. G. Witting; vice-president, Dr. C. G. Wallenius; secretary, S. H. S. Leonard; treasurer, Fritz N. Andren. The following were elected to the Board of Directors: Consul Carl O. De Dardel; Reverend C. A. Lindvall; C. G. Axeli, engineer, John A. Sandgren, secretary of the Svithiod order; Dr. Alfred Rundstrom, attorney; C. H. Jalmar Lundquist; Dr. Julius Lincoln; Carl Festin, a former Grand Master of the Vasa Order; Emil Anderson, president of the Swedish Singers' League; Mrs. Carl O. De Dardel; and Mrs. Hilma Victorin.</p>
   <p>The date of the next meeting will be announced later. The Swedish Engineering Society has generously offered its clubhouse without charge as a meeting place for the new organization. [Translator's note: The correct official name of this local branch or of the national organization is difficult to determine. In <pb facs="5423404_4_1100.jpg" n="3"/>an article in the issue of April 11, 1923, the name of the latter was given as the National Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture, while in the present article it appears as the Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in Foreign Countries. The mystery may be solved in some future article.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
