<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-04-10">Apr. 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[Swedish National League Holds Annual Meeting]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1371</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1371.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1906-04-10">Apr. 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[SWEDISH NATIONAL LEAGUE HOLDS ANNUAL MEETING]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual business meeting of the Swedish National League was held on Monday April 1. Officers for the coming year were elected as follows: president: George S. Olson; vice-president: Henry Schreil; recording secretary: Albin Fridell; financial secretary: John G. Hultgren; treasurer: John Sandgren; sergeant at arms: Charles Johnson; guard: Justus Tengberg; trustees: Hjalmar Hedin, Charles Gustafson, and E. T. Carlson. As directors of the Old People's Home in Park Ridge, the following were elected: Henry Schreil, Gust Flodin, John Hultgren, Oscar B. Svanson, Mrs. Gust Johnson, and Miss Alma Anderson.</p>
   <p>Twenty new (additional) delegates were welcomed by the president, making this the largest number of delegates ever to gather at an annual meeting.</p>
   <p>The new delegates represented ten new lodges or societies joining the League, bringing the membership of the groups up to forty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1372.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee handling the annual picnic reported that this year's picnic is to be held in Elliott's Park on Sunday, June 10, and that no effort will be spared to make it a success in every way. The secretary was instructed to draw up and send to the Svithiod Sangarklub (Svithiod Male Chorus) a resolution of appreciation for their co-operation for sponsoring the great concert during December of last year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
