<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-04-30">Apr. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-04-30">Apr. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> IMMIGRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If our lawmakers in the Senate really had the interests and the well-being of the American working class in mind when they, on April 21, voted to reduce the annual immigration quota from 150,000 to 120,000 they acted wisely and deserve credit for taking such a stand. They really used their heads that day, for they also voted to nullify the national origins clause of the Immigration Act, which now serves as a basis for the quota computations. However, the satisfaction which that latter decision caused throughout the country was shortlived, for yesterday the Democratic senators George, of Georgia, and Caraway, of Arkansas, succeeded in forcing through another vote, with the result that the controversial clause remains on the statutes. One single vote decided the issue.</p>
   <p>It is only fair that the millions of unemployed American workers, many of whom have been out of work for a long time, be taken care of before the European <pb facs="5423404_2_0297.jpg" n="2"/>surplus of labor be admitted here. For the same reason it is also of great importance that immigration from Central and South American countries be strictly limited by definite quotas for each one of them. As provided by the Harris bill, which will be considered by the Senate within the next few days. If the senators really desire to protect the American workers and their high standard of living, which has been so much publicized throughout the world, they will have to pass this bill, or something akin to it.</p>
   <p>With conditions on the labor market as they are at the present time it would seem sound, common sense policy to stop immigration altogether if it could be done without causing too many complications. It would be a boon to American workers, and theirEuropean brethren could not lose much by it. Times are bad in Europe and they are also bad here. Opportunities for work are not plentiful in any country at the present time, not even in the so-called "Workers' Paradise," Soviet Russia, the propaganda of the Bolshevik agents notwithstanding. The hard times are also being felt in Sweden, though that little country seems to fare better than most others during this world-wide crisis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0298.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As far as Swedish workers are concerned, they are better off staying home for the time being. They are not likely to go to Russia in appreciable numbers. They have too much sense to be swayed by the rosy pictures painted by Soviet agitators. But they do like to try their wings, and they are attracted to the land in the far west, the land of great resources and opportunities. As every Swedish-American knows, this attraction is hard to resist, and many follow the call. For a large number of them, the result is simply a change of abode, and also disappointment and broken illusions. They leave friends and relatives, and everything else that is dear to them behind, without being able to attain a compensating improvement in living conditions for themselves. But the average American seems to have the idea that everybody who comes here does so because conditions in his own country are unbearable.</p>
   <p>From an economic point of view, Sweden will, perhaps, be less effected by a reduction of immigration quotas than most other countries. But we Swedish-Americans, those who came from the old country as well as descendants of Swedish pioneers here, are thankful for what this country has done for us and are deeply <pb facs="5423404_2_0299.jpg" n="4"/>interested in its future welfare, and it is our duty to do what we can to have the national origins clause removed from the statutes. And we are grateful to those lawmakers who are making an effort to bring about this change in the immigration regulations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
