<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-11-23">Nov. 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish-American Farmer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-11-23">Nov. 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH-AMERICAN FARMER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are getting accustomed to finding a considerable sprinkling of Swedish-Americans among the delegates to conventions which meet to discuss state and national problems of a political and social-economic nature. Thus Governor Eberhart of Minnesota was noted as a participant in the farm congress which met in Chicago a few days ago. He addressed the congress on the subject of "The North Star State," and was heartily applauded. Among other things he declared that his state still has twenty million acres of good land available for energetic and progressive farmers.</p>
   <p>It is only fitting that Swedish-American opinion should be heard at state and national farm conventions. Swedish immigrants have made valuable contributions to this country's agriculture, a fact to which many happy and prosperous farm communities in Illinois, Minnesota, the Dakotas, Iowa, Kansas, Nebraska, and other states bear witness. Many depleted and abandoned <pb facs="5423404_2_0596.jpg" n="2"/>farms in New England have again yielded good crops under the skilled hands of a Swedish farmer. Among Swedish immigrants we find not only highly skilled mechanics in all trades, but also excellent farmers. The many Swedish-American students who attend the agricultural schools in manhattan Kansas, Lincoln, Nebraska, and other places,show that our nationals also appreciate the value of theoretical knowledge and modern methods as applied to farming.</p>
   <p>If one wants to see idyllic and happy home life one should visit some of our old Swedish colonies. Besides contentment and good living one will find intelligence which has been sharpened rather than dulled by the hard work in fields and meadows, and an interest in and understanding of the problems of our times which are rarely encountered among the general farm population.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
