<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-04-08">Apr. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Art Exhibit Opened in Cafe Idrott</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-04-08">Apr. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ART EXHIBIT OPENED IN CAFE IDROTT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the art society, Swedish Artists, opened an interesting exhibit last Saturday in the co-operative Cafe Idrott's building, 3206 Wilton Avenue. The exhibit is comprised of oil paintings, aquarelles, sculptures, and etchings, altogether some eighty numbers.</p>
   <p>By again opening its doors to an exhibit of this kind Idrott's management is following its laudable policy of encouraging Swedish-American art, just as it is always ready to lend its support to adult education projects and other cultural activities.</p>
   <p>The exhibit is housed in the south room on the second floor, where a large number of artists and art patrons gathered Saturday night for the opening ceremony. The Swedish Consul, Ekblad, and Einar Soderwall, honorary president of Swedish Artists, delivered brief addresses. Fridolf Spolander, who himself is taking part in the exhibit, entertained with a few song numbers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1342.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A total of forty-seven oil paintings are being shown, including landscapes, marines, portraits, and still lifes. The portraits are few and none of them are of outstanding merit. But there are a number of landscape paintings that are attracting deserved attention, among them, Ahlman's "Lake St. Mary Glacier National Park," and "The Farm in Winter"; Alfred Jansson's "Motif from Sweden" and "Fall Landscape"; Martin Lundgrens "The Passing Summer"; and Signe Palmblad's "Red, White, and Blue". Mary Peterson is represented by three canvases of which one, "Faces," is a remarkably fine piece of work. "Summer Day" and "Autumn," by Axel Linus, are very good. Among the other artists in this group we noted A. Hessell, M.J. Ahlstromer, Gustaf Dahlstrom, C. O. Erickson, Ed. Hanson, Helga Hessell, and Victor Tiberg. The latter exhibits five paintings with motifs from Sweden.</p>
   <p>Thomas Hall makes his debut as a flower painter and his "Still Life" and "Roses and Fruit" are very good.</p>
   <p>There are ten aquarelles by Nels E. Dahlsrom, G. Kruskopf, Florence M. <pb facs="5423404_2_1343.jpg" n="3"/>Ruden, and Axel Westerlind, and in the sculpture group we noted the works of Axel W. Akesson, P. Anderson, Herman Cederblad, Carl Farnquist, Lars Johnson, and Ernest G. Olsson. The latter exhibits four wood carvings. Hallsthammar's name is in the catalogue, but we were unable to find his exhibit, though we looked all over the place for it. Akesson's "Bird" is a very decorative piece. P. Anderson, who modeled the base for Milles' "Diana," and who has done much fine decorative sculpture on buildings here in Chicago, is represented by some very fine samples of his art.</p>
   <p>There are six etchings by H. Kronberg, Anna Anderson, and Gustaf Dalstrom.</p>
   <p>This review is based on a hurried survey of the exhibit. It must be seen to be appreciated. It closes April 19.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
