<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-03-08">Mar. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Children Must Be Protected</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-03-08">Mar. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN MUST BE PROTECTED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who are opposed to the exploitation of child labor, and who have been hoping that protection of minors could be achieved by legislation have suffered a great disappointment by the recent decision rendered by Judge Boyd of North Carolina. He ruled that the Federal Child Welfare Act is unconstitutional. The ruling affected only two factories in the state, but it is feared that it will be upheld by the Supreme Court. For this reason, effective child welfare legislation is now being pressed in every state in the Union.</p>
   <p>At the present time, four states allow children under fourteen years of age to work in factories and canning plants, and in twenty states children under sixteen may be employed in mines and quarries. Seventeen states permit children under sixteen to work more than eight hours a day, and in seven states they may work even on night shifts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It should be clear to everybody that such conditions constitute a danger to the growing generation, and that they must be remedied. But the individual states cannot be depended on to do much about it, and it would therefore be highly regrettable if the Federal Child Welfare Act should be voided by the Supreme Court. If this should happen, it will become necessary to add an amendment to the Constitution. Such action should be possible to achieve, for nothing is more important to society than the health and welfare of its children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
