<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-06-21">June 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted North Side Businessman</title> [Half-tone, one column--sixth of a page, picture of Eric E. Skoglund]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-06-21">June 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted North Side Businessman</title> [Half-tone, one column--sixth of a page, picture of Eric E. Skoglund]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known North Side Swedish-American businessman, Eric E. Skoglund, has been made a director of the newly established bank, the Builders and Merchants State Bank, which is to be located in the heart of the great Swedish-American district of Edgewater. But this is not the only reason why we have made Mr. Skoglund the subject of the week's Foreground article. Those who are at all acquainted with the Swedes in Chicago know that he has for a number of years been among the more prominent Swedish businessmen in the city; and within Swedish Methodist circles here he is held in high esteem, both as an active church member and as a generous giver. His generosity was again demonstrated recently when he donated a considerable sum to the organization's pension fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0865.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Skoglund was born in Kumla, Sweden, September 21, 1878 and came to America at the age of nineteen. He studied drawing and architecture for some time here, and then began to work at his trade--that of stonecutting, which he had learned from his father. The district of Kumla, from which he came, was not only a shoe-manufacturing center but was also well-known for its stonecutting industry.</p>
   <p>About seventeen years ago, Skoglund bought a stonecutting yard at Clark and Ainslie Streets, but the place soon became too small and he moved his business to 5555 North Lincoln Street, where his plant is now located. His business has grown steadily, and is now one of the largest of its kind, in that part of the city.</p>
   <p>Skoglund is a member of the Bethania congregation in Ravenswood, of which he is also a trustee. In 1909 he married Anna Nelson of Alingsas, Sweden.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
