<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-08-07">Aug. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[The Farm Still Has Loyal Friends]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-08-07">Aug. 7, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">[THE FARM STILL HAS LOYAL FRIENDS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For many years, especially in the east, a complaint has been rumbling that our farms are being run on a stepmother system. The younger generation is constantly flocking to the city where they invariably make more money than is possible on the farm. Thus the farm today is being sadly neglected.</p>
   <p>During Solomon's time, there was no limit to the writers of books; now there is no limit to the building of cities, villages, and stations in America. There is a surplus of these, while large farms are often set aside as townsites and the good old land lies idle year after year.</p>
   <p>The old farm, however, has its loyal friends. The agricultural branch of <pb facs="5423404_2_0613.jpg" n="2"/>Cornell University boasts of its 193 students who seek more knowledge that will enable them to run a farm on a more profitable basis than in the past. Interviews with a number of these students revealed several reasons for their attitude toward the farm. Some of these young men were born on the farm--as were their fathers and grandfathers before them--and it was in their blood to love the farm.</p>
   <p>Others figure that the farmer is the most substantial man on earth. If his farm is a failure, it is his own fault. The farmer is a slave to no man and his free life in the open air is the ideal life in every sense of the word. In every respect it is better than city life. One consolation is that what the farmer produces belongs to him, not to some money king. Life on the farm is quiet and peaceful--none of the city hustle, bustle and noise--and one feels closer to mother nature, night and day.</p>
   <p>Let those who live in the city put all their energy and brain into <pb facs="5423404_2_0614.jpg" n="3"/>scraping up and hoarding gold; health, happiness and contentment do not go hand in hand with their strife.</p>
   <p>On the farm, rain and shine, grass and flowers, field and meadow, trees and fruits, all serve the farmer and, as we stated previously, the good old farm still has faithful friends in every community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
