<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">Oct. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Women and the Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">Oct. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN AND THE ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To what extent will women make use of their franchise at the coming election? Leaders of the campaign committees of the political parties would give a good deal to know the right answer to this question. In many quarters it is believed that the next presidential election will be decided by our women, and nobody can say now whether or not this will turn out to be true.</p>
   <p>There are two groups of states in which the women voters will not exert any considerable influence on the election result. The states comprising the "solid South" form one of these groups. Public opinion in that part of the country does not sanction suffrage for women, and in all probability only a few of them will go to the polls. These few will not actually influence the final result since the Democratic election officials always see to it that their party gets an overwhelming majority of votes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0503.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The second group is made up of the states in the western part of the country where women already had been granted their franchise, before the constitutional amendment went into effect. In those states the reform is not likely to cause any great upset.</p>
   <p>As for the rest of the states, it is generally believed that the native-born women will make use of their newly acquired right to vote to a greater extent than will their naturalized sisters. There are exceptions, however. Leading politicians expect that Scandinavian women will go to the polls in great numbers, while women from other European countries, the English women excepted, are likely to stay home on election day. This is supposed to be particularly true of the largest group--the German women. But this view is being opposed by the German-American press. These newspapers declare that ordinarily the German women would not take a great deal of interest in the election; but this time they find themselves in an unusual situation. The German women have many grievances against the Democratic party, the chief one being the high cost of living; and they will make use of their right to vote in order to bring about a change of <pb facs="5423404_2_0504.jpg" n="3"/>administration in Washington. Time will show to what extent this prediction by the German press is correct.</p>
   <p>Women from the Latin and Slavic countries have never taken much interest in politics, and comparatively few of them are expected to exercise their franchise.</p>
   <p>However, last year a movement was started for the purpose of organizing Polish women's clubs. Even though these clubs have the interests of Poland in view rather than those of the United States, the fact remains that Polish women are being urged to vote. The idea is to support the party whose victory is most advantageous to Poland.</p>
   <p>Then we have the Jewish women. What they will do, nobody who is not of their race should even try to predict. It is reasonable to assume that in keeping with the patriarchal mode of life among the Jews, the head of the house will tell the womenfolk either to stay home, or, if they vote, to vote as he does.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0505.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If, therefore, the Jewish vote is distributed fairly evenly between the two major parties, the same proportion will be maintained whether or not the women go to the polls. But if the Jews should unite for the purpose of supporting one party, then the Jewish women's vote would carry considerable weight.</p>
   <p>Women socialists, of which there are quite a few, will not pass up this opportunity to go to the polls and cast their vote for Debs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
