<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-26">July 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Dark Side of Industry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-26">July 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE DARK SIDE OF INDUSTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Children's Bureau, which is a subdivision of the Department of Labor, recently published a report that throws a revealing light on the deplorable conditions existing in the oyster and shrimp canning industry, where a large number of women and children are employed. The Bureau has made a survey of nine communities in the states of Mississippi, Louisiana, and Florida, where the bulk of this industry is located. It has studied not only the working methods and conditions, but also the home life of the mothers and children employed in the industry. The survey comprised 423 families with a total of 1,350 children under sixteen years of age, of whom 544 work in the canning factories, while 332 are between the ages of six and fourteen.</p>
   <p>According to the report, most of the work in these places is extremely dirty. The workers have to stand up all the time, and they often cut their hands and fingers on the sharp shells. The work is tiresome, and accidents happen frequently because of wet and slippery floors. Diseases are easily contracted <pb facs="5423404_2_0328.jpg" n="2"/>in the damp and cold quarters.</p>
   <p>Most of the work is done by women and children. Of the latter, sixty-four per cent work full time, while the remainder are employed before and after school hours and on Saturdays. Many of the children can neither read nor write. A considerable number do not attend school at all, and regular school attendance does not exist in any of these communities. Wages are, of course, low. The survey shows that two thirds of the children earned less than five dollars a week, and that more than one fourth of them earned less than two dollars.</p>
   <p>The survey also includes 269 children whose mothers worked in the factories. It was found that in forty-nine cases the mothers took children along with them to their place of employment. Some of those children were less than a year old. Those children who were able to walk or crawl about were often victims of accidents of various kinds. Some mothers left their small children in the care of other families, and in eighteen cases children were left at home without any supervision whatever. Of the 1,350 children covered by the <pb facs="5423404_2_0329.jpg" n="3"/>survey, 9 were born in foreign countries, 473 were colored, and 668 were native whites.</p>
   <p>The report further discloses that the families live in squalid surroundings, and that unsanitary conditions prevail in the homes. The ground is swampy and damp in the districts where these canneries are located, and flies and mosquitoes abound. Utter poverty is the rule, and it is considered necessary that children be put to work in order to help support their family.</p>
   <p>Each year, employers import families from the north in order to secure an ample supply of workers who can be easily controlled.</p>
   <p>An enlightening report, indeed!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
