<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Working Women</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">WORKING WOMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The employment of women in fields which were formerly reserved exclusively for men is by many people considered an important contributing cause of the current extensive unemployment. There is some truth in that assumption, but it needs amplification. It cannot be denied that women have replaced men in certain types of work, either because they are better adapted to that particular work, or because they are willing to accept smaller pay. They have thus undoubtedly reduced the number of jobs available for men. That does not mean that they have caused an actual increase in unemployment. And it should be kept in mind that the male himself is responsible for the present state of affairs.</p>
   <p>In this man made world the home was formerly considered woman's special and only sphere of activity. But when men no longer were able to offer women <pb facs="5423404_2_0485.jpg" n="2"/>enough of that kind of work, the latter naturally had to look around for something else to do. The law of supply and demand is not easily defied. The majority of women who are now employed outside would undoubtedly prefer to work within the four walls of their own homes. Right now a good many of them are taking care of the home and they are at the same time holding down some outside job, thus helping the man in keeping the home together.</p>
   <p>In 1920 the number of gainfully employed women in this country was found to be 5,319,397. They were employed in agriculture and industry, in stores and offices, and made up eighteen per cent of the working population of America, both sexes included. Of this number 2,095,449 were engaged in house work. According to the 1930 census, the number of employed women was 10,778,794, comprising 22.1 per cent of all workers in the country. In other words, the number of working women had increased by 4.2 per cent during a decade. It is also reasonable to assume that fewer women were engaged in house work, due to labor saving devices in the home and to modern living conditions in general.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0486.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Women have followed the trend of the times, while men have doggedly held on to the past, refusing to accept changing conditions, and employers have taken advantage of the situation and have secured cheap help. The male workers have aided them in this effort. If they had supported instead of opposed women's demand for equal pay for equal work, many things would be different now.</p>
   <p>If rationing of work and working hours goes into effect in the not too distant future, which is quite likely, measures should be taken so that there will be at least one wage earner, regardless of sex, in every family. Then the percentage of women working outside the home will not be so important, if the men will only support them in their struggle for maintaining wages above the starvation level.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
