<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-09-19">Sept. 19, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Shame of Civilization</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-09-19">Sept. 19, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE SHAME OF CIVILIZATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Statistics inform us that about 2,000,000 children, ages five to sixteen years, are working in the factories in the United States. A large percentage of these are under twelve years of age. How depressing these facts are for all those who have been working, hoping, and dreaming of a day when children were to be permitted to remain children until the struggle for existence is rightly due to start. What dark and sad shadows this child labor casts on the road leading forward and upward towards the sunny heights of civilization and humanity. What does our hypocritic twentieth century possess to boast about? It permits religious persecution and race hatred; it looks coldly on while people murder each other for the sake of miserable winnings, while negroes are burned at the <pb facs="5423404_2_0403.jpg" n="2"/>stake, while whipping, a relic from barbarism, is again being introduced into our prisons, while swindlers on a large scale are being coddled by the representatives of law, while the representatives of the people are selling their honor for gold; while honesty is being ridiculed, virtue is being soiled; while children are made the pawns of the money vendor; while Satan laughs at the whole.</p>
   <p>A picture from past centuries meets our eye, a picture so attractive, and so truly human, so pure and so divine, the picture of the great reformer, who on his way through Judea once said, "Suffer little children to come unto me and forbid them not, for such is the Kingdom of Heaven." The Man of Nazareth read in the eyes of the children innocence and purity; but His disciples have not been <pb facs="5423404_2_0404.jpg" n="3"/>able to perceive what He saw in the children, or, if they have seen it, they have not dared to announce it. Cowards they are, these present day pupils of Jesus; without raising their voice against the greatest crime of the century, they calmly observe how our modern slave drivers, like leeches, suck the red blood out of the bodies of the children, make their cheeks pale, and deprive their eyes of their sparkle all of this in order that they themselves may be enabled to lead a life of ease and pleasure, sustained by the labor of others.</p>
   <p>And yet we brag about our christian civilization, and of the great things we are accomplishing for the poor children in heathen lands. Go on, you Christians, spread light and sunshine to the poor Africans, they need it, but do not forget that in your own city, perhaps only a few hundred feet from your own homes, pale and wan <pb facs="5423404_2_0405.jpg" n="4"/>little boys and girls are compelled to work hard when they ought to be at school, instead of at the factory bench. The heathen children are living under far better conditions than the 2,000,000 child-laborers at factories in the United States. They are as near Heaven and much farther from Hell than the child slaves are under our civilization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
