<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-04-19">Apr. 19, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A Sermon by a "Learned" Man</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-04-19">Apr. 19, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A SERMON BY A "LEARNED" MAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>His name is Eneas B. Goodwin; he belongs to the Roman Catholic church and is a professor at St. Cyril's University in Chicago. Last Sunday, speaking at the Ravenswood Roman Catholic church, his topic was: "No Room for additional Immigrants," and a precious sermon it was indeed. In the sermon the speaker displayed his enormous ignorance of the education and culture which have permeated the Scandinavian people and made the Swedish, the Norwegian, and the Danisk workers take their place among the best trained mechanics in the whole world.</p>
   <p>In his remarkable sermon he pointed to just the Scandinavian people as being non-desirable immigrants, designating them as "poor, narrow-minded foreigners." He had no remarks to make against immigrant Jews from Russia, but he informed his audience that the "Scandinavians left their countries <pb facs="5423404_2_0419.jpg" n="2"/>as a result of the persecution of Jews in Russia," a most profound statement.</p>
   <p>In one of his brighter moments he let his listeners know that the immigrants from Scandinavia are not exactly poorhouse inmates. But then his mind became clouded again and he added: "Nevertheless it is a fact that poverty and hopeless misery have set their marks on the pale faces and the fallen-in cheeks of these immigrants."</p>
   <p>We do not know whether the professor ever ventured near enough to the ocean to get out upon one of the docks where the immigrants from the Scandinavian peninsula land. If not, then he ought to do so as soon as possible. But when he does, he ought to take care to leave his immigration sermon at home, for if he were to give expression at the dock to the thoughts contained in the sermon, it is quite possible that some one of these "hopeless, unintelligent foreigners" might undertake to teach the priest that the capacity for understanding of these people is unusually keen..... and that they are strong <pb facs="5423404_2_0420.jpg" n="3"/>enough to defend their good name and reputation.</p>
   <p>The prelate professed his friendliness to labor in his sermon. His objection to the Scandinavians as immigrants had nothing to do with the fact that they were protestants. Far from it! Only his warm interest in the welfare of the native American workers prompted him to speak as he did; these foreigners were willing to work for and subsist upon one fourth of the amount required by the native workers.</p>
   <p>We have no right to impose upon the time of the precious professor, but if he would spare us a fraction of the time which he used to disseminate his infernal lies, we would take him to plants in any field of industry which he might designate, and produce facts to show that not only do the Swedes at work demand and get as high wages as do the native workers, but in hundreds of cases they get more.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
