<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-12-14">Dec. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Our Public Health</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-12-14">Dec. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PUBLIC HEALTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There has for some time been much talk about establishing a new department of our Government in Washington, namely, a department of public health. A bill providing for such an innovation will shortly be presented by Senator Owen of Oklahoma. The chief purpose of the department will be to protect and improve the national health.</p>
   <p>At the present time Uncle Sam is better informed about the state of health of the cattle on American farms than he is of that of the citizens. He can tell anybody who cares to listen exactly how many hogs died in America last year, but he does not know how many babies died or were born, or just what should have been done to keep more of them alive.</p>
   <p>There are in our capitol various departments where a close watch is being kept on almost everything one can think of, from chinch bugs to hoof-and-mouth disease, and where officials are busy investigating and giving information <pb facs="5423404_2_0631.jpg" n="2"/>to exporters about business conditions in foreign countries. Valuable aid is given farmers, and immense sums of money are being spent every year on experiments for the development of better and deadlier weapons with which to take human lives, but, officially, there does not seem to be much interest in saving the lives of people.</p>
   <p>It has actually reached the point where it can truthfully be said that John D. Rockefeller has done more to protect the public health than has the United States Government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
