<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-09-27">Sept. 27, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery</title><title level="a" type="sub">Axel L. Ericson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-09-27">Sept. 27, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Axel L. Ericson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To our gallery of Swedish-Americans who have achieved outstanding success in their chosen lifework, we have today the pleasure of adding a Vermland man.</p>
   <p>We have previously commented on the fact that so many of the ablest and most successful Swedish building contractors came from Vermland, to be more exact, from Sunne Parish in Frykspalen. And we have given credit to the excellent People's High School in that district, founded by Anders Fryxell, and now under the direction of Professor Ortendahl, for turning out so many builders.</p>
   <p>The late Pastor Swensson of Lindsborg, Kansas, always stressed the happy Vermlander, but to us this seems somewhat onesided. We would say that his most apparent characteristics are good will, good humor, and a certain irresponsible carelessness, from which spring many of his good and some of his not so good qualities. His hospitality and readiness to help has become a <pb facs="5423404_2_1063.jpg" n="2"/>byword in Sweden.</p>
   <p>Axel L. Ericson is a young man who was born in Norra Arneby on August 30, 1868. Like all other children of the common people, he went through the public school. Fortunately, the school which we have mentioned above was located in the vicinity, and he took advantage of this opportunity to complete a full course there. This gave him a solid foundation on which he has built further by studying in his spare time.</p>
   <p>The Vermlander has a somewhat restless disposition and likes to go to faraway places in search for work and more excitement than he finds at home. This trait prompted Axel Ericson, at the age of nineteen, to set out for the promised land, America.</p>
   <p>He started in as a building carpenter in Chicago, and worked as such with several firms for five years. During this time, he studied the building and contracting business, so that in 1892, when preparations for the World's Fair were well under way, he was ready to go into business for himself. The fact that his word can be absolutely depended upon won for him the confidence not <pb facs="5423404_2_1064.jpg" n="3"/>only of the building public but also of banks and dealers in building materials, so that his credit now may be said to be almost unlimited.</p>
   <p>During the last twelve years, he has not only completed a great number of jobs, but most of them have been of the kind that requires the highest quality of workmanship. His activities have not been confined to Chicago. Last year, he built nine residences of the expensive type in Columbus, Ohio, and at present, he has under construction a $150,000 hotel in that city.</p>
   <p>The many jobs he has done include the First Methodist Church at Ashland and Greenleaf Avenues in Rogers Park and the Swedenborgian Church on California Avenue. Considering some of the exceptionally fine buildings he has erected, Mr. Ericson truly ranks among those who have contributed much to the beauty of our city.</p>
   <p>It would be a mistake to think that he is interested only in big contracts. Like most other building contractors, he will just as soon bid on a comparatively small job.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1065.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>His office is in suite 214 at 145 La Salle Street, and he is, of course, a member of the Carpenters and Builders Association. Having been too busy to look for a life partner, he still enjoys the pleasures of single life.</p>
   <p>Equipped with a robust physique, good health, a happy disposition, and plenty of ambition and energy, Axel Ericson should go far in this country, so rich in opportunity. He has made a fine beginning, and Svenska Nyheter wishes him continued success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
