<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Ladies of Harmony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE LADIES OF HARMONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ladies of Harmony is a new society with about sixty members, which was organized last Friday evening. As the name indicates, this society is composed of women only, and its foremost aim is to assist the Harmoni Sangarklubb at its affairs. Both of these societies have rented the Viking Temple for "Fyra Qvallar Pa Skansen" (Four Evenings on the Redoubt) to be held March 17 to March 20, inclusive. A bazaar, carnival, concert, and dance will be featured at this time, and no expense has been spared to make this the most pleasant and best variety program of the season. Harmoni is known for its originality and certainly will maintain its reputation by the presentation of this affair. The opening will be on Saint Patrick's Day and the members of these two clubs expect to welcome many old friends and lovers of Swedish songs. The officers of the new society are: Chairman, Mrs. Anna <pb facs="5423404_2_1622.jpg" n="2"/>Bolling; secretary, Mrs. Albin Pearson; treasurer, Mrs. Hanna Linwall.</p>
   <p>On March 7, the Harmoni Sangarklubb will celebrate its twentieth anniversary with a magnificent concert at the Viking Temple. First-class talent has been secured for this concert and the chorus is to give a number of new songs, including "Come Where The Lilies Bloom" and "Moder Svea" (Mother Svea). The latter song is written by Hugo E. Jansen, member of the Harmoni Chorus, and arranged by Gustaf A. Carlson, the conductor of the Chorus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
