<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-08-04">Aug. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Exhibition in Chicago Art Industry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-08-04">Aug. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH EXHIBITION IN CHICAGO ART INDUSTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1........The promised Swedish Art Industry Exhibition will be open to the public from August 9, to October 14 inclusive.</p>
   <p>Tuesday August 9, the long talked of Swedish Art Industry Exhibition will be opened at Chicago Art Institute. This exhibition has been shown at the Metropolitan Museum in New York, and at Arts and Crafts Society in Detroit, and has in both places been praised by the public and the press.</p>
   <p>Chicago will be the third and last city in America, where the celebration will be exhibited, before it is returned to Sweden, and all signs point towards an event of the first class. The Swedish Art Industry, has during the last years, reached the pinnacle in international ranks, and certain of its products such as the cut and engraved "Orrefors-glass" is unsurpassed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1187.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The exhibition, which will be shown in three rooms on the Art Museum's upper gallery, will include books, furniture, textiles, ceramics, glass, silver, tin and iron. An idea of the collection's magnitude is understood when we say it arrived here in eighty-six large chests.</p>
   <p>Among the Swedish firms represented we find: Gustafsbergs, Karls Krona and Galve Porcelain Factories; Bobergs Fajance (Delft) Factory; Nordiska Kompaniet and Swedish Furniture Factories; Kosta and Orrefors Glassworks; Bergmans Art Foundry; Nafvekvarns Works; Firma Swedish Tinn; Gold-Smith Stock Company of Stockholm, and Hallbergs Gold-Smith Company; Friends of Handi-Work Society and Home Industries Societies National League, etc. Isolated objects have also been borrowed from Stockholm's National Museum and from Stockholm's State House. The American exhibitions are under the protection of H.R.H. Crown-Prince Gustaf Adolf, and have been organized by a committee; Prince Eugene is Honorary President; among the members of the committee we find Sweden's leading artists and industrialists. Sweden's Manual Training Society and the Swedish Art Industries Central Organization <pb facs="5423404_2_1188.jpg" n="3"/>have chosen the objects for exhibition, and its director, Dr. Gregor Paulsen, is acting as General Commissioner for the American exhibition. As Commissioner for Chicago, as he was for Detroit, Tage Palm will serve, assisted by John Sjunneson.</p>
   <p>The credit for having the exhibition moved to Chicago, in spite of the many obstacles, financial and otherwise, is in first place due to our Counsel Carl O. de Dardel and a number of generous countrymen; also to the warm interest for Swedish Art shown by the Art Institute.</p>
   <p>The exhibition will continue through October 14, and will be open to the public every day without any extra charge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
