<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-01-09">Jan. 9, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">New President of Builders &amp; Merchants State Bank</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Paul C. Mellander]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0829</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0829.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-01-09">Jan. 9, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">NEW PRESIDENT OF BUILDERS &amp; MERCHANTS STATE BANK</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Paul C. Mellander]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a directors' meeting in the Builders &amp; Merchants State Bank, Foster Avenue and Clark Street, Paul C. Mellander was elected the new president of the institution, to succeed the late Gustaf Hallbom, the bank's first president and one of its founders, who died last spring.</p>
   <p>The directors have been in no hurry to choose a new president, and in the meantime the bank's affairs have been conducted by Charles Bosrom, chairman of the Board, and Vice-president Carl J. Johnson.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mellander is an experienced banker. Immediately after finishing school, he got a job in the St. Charles National Bank, of St. Charles, Illinois, and remained in that city for a number of years, during which time he served <pb facs="5423404_2_0830.jpg" n="2"/>the community in various capacities. He was secretary of the St. Charles Commercial Club, and also city treasurer. From St. Charles he moved to Chicago to become assistant cashier of the Madison &amp; Kedzie State Bank, and a few years later he came to the State Bank of Chicago as assistant cashier. It was from this position that he went into the presidency of the Merchants &amp; Builders State Bank.</p>
   <p>Mellander is a son of the late Pastor John Mellander and spent his early years in Chicago. His wife was Miss Lydia Swenson. They have two children.</p>
   <p>The Builders &amp; Merchants State Bank was established in 1922 in the Summerdale-Edgewater district, where so many Swedes have their homes, and has enjoyed a healthy growth. Its directors, with but one exception, are Swedes, as are most of its functionaries. As of December 31, 1928, deposits amounted to $3,581,150.47.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
