<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-09-28">Sept. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Better Agricultural Methods</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-09-28">Sept. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">BETTER AGRICULTURAL METHODS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American farmer is gradually beginning to realize that his old methods are not up to the requirements of rational, modern agriculture, and that the intelligent use of the aids which science and research have placed at his disposal would make his life more comfortable, and increase his income.</p>
   <p>Thanks to the encouragement of the Government, thousands of farmers have already acquired more knowledge along these lines, but they still have a long way to go before their farms yield the limit of their possibilities. Experts calculate that by 1950 the United States will have a population of two hundred million and, in view of the present steady increase in prices of farm products, it is doubtful whether the future agricultural <pb facs="5423404_2_0604.jpg" n="2"/>output will keep up with the increase in population. It is certain that it will become necessary to use the most up-to-date methods in order to obtain the highest possible yield, and this necessity will become more marked as the available acreage suitable for cultivation decreases.</p>
   <p>The Department of Agriculture in Washington has been fully aware of its responsibilities in this respect, and has widened the scope of its activities to such an extent that it is now one of the most important agencies of our government. Wise leadership on its part is necessary if the many problems arising as a result of a rapid increase in population are to be successfully solved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
