<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-10-29">Oct. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Before the Presidential Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-10-29">Oct. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">BEFORE THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before the next issue of the Tribunen is off the press, the battle at the polls will be over, and the American people will have decided who is to be its Chief Executive for the next four years. The outcome of a Presidential election is always uncertain, and it is particularly difficult to predict the result of this one. It is even quite possible that neither of the three leading candidates will receive a decisive majority, and in that case the decision will rest with the Congress. If that happens, we shall probably experience a period of widespread uncertainty with a consequent slowing up of business and industry and a decrease in employment.</p>
   <p>The present situation is very similar to that which existed in 1912. A third party has appeared in the political arena, and its leader is Robert M. LaFollette, the Senator from Wisconsin. He is more than seventy years <pb facs="5423404_2_0540.jpg" n="2"/>old, but is still full of vigor, and during his long political career has sponsored many splendid reforms. He has many followers, and must be considered a strong candidate. Much of his strength is due to the fact that he has been endorsed by the leaders within the American Federation of Labor. He is also supported by the more moderate Socialists.</p>
   <p>The circumstances which led to the formation of a third party are readily understood. When the Republicans, under the late President Harding, took over the government four years ago, they inherited from the preceding Wilson administration heavy financial commitments, which were excessive even as measured by American standards, and also a much too costly administrative machinery. The Democrats had spent money freely, by the billions, on the assumption that the war had to be won regardless of cost. The hard task of ending this destructive waste fell upon the Republicans, and there is no reason to doubt that they undertook the task with a sincere desire to do what they considered best for the nation. But unfortunately, when the unavoidable deflation set in, it hit first and hardest those who should have <pb facs="5423404_2_0541.jpg" n="3"/>been spared to the last, namely, the farmers, and the result was actual distress among a large portion of our agricultural population, followed by a reduction of industrial activity.</p>
   <p>This was the situation when Calvin Coolidge took office after the death of President Harding. Since then, much has been done to aid the farmers, but, in the opinion of many, not enough. And not without reason has the present administration been criticized for acting too slowly and for applying half measures. This is the background of the third party movement. The party has included in its platform many timely reforms, and has for that reason been accused of radicalism. But such accusations are groundless, and should be disregarded.</p>
   <p>However, it should be remembered that the Republicans have accomplished much constructive work. Taxes and the cost of government have been reduced, many expensive bureaus have been restored in our financial affairs. In its foreign policy, the administration has taken <pb facs="5423404_2_0542.jpg" n="4"/>a position which has strengthened the nation and increased its prestige, without involving it in dangerous alliances.</p>
   <p>The thinking citizen will ponder with sympathy many of the planks in the platform of the third party, but at the same time he will appreciate the achievements of the present Republican administration, and realize that the oil scandal, bad as it was, fades in comparison with some of the scandals which occurred during the previous Democratic regime. A return now to a Democratic administration would be truly unfortunate. To all appearances, Coolidge is the strongest candidate, and he seems able to prevent a repetition of the happenings of 1912 and the next few years thereafter. It behooves the voters to consider this when they mark their ballots next November 4.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
