<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-09">Mar. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Singing Swedish-American Industrialist</title>
[Half-tone, one column, fifth of a page, full-face picture of Oscar Borg.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-09">Mar. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A SINGING SWEDISH-AMERICAN INDUSTRIALIST</title>
[Half-tone, one column, fifth of a page, full-face picture of Oscar Borg.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If a businessman is to succeed it is almost necessary for him to have a thorough understanding of human nature. If he does not possess this asset, he will have difficulties picking the best men and women to work for him, and will soon find himself trailing his competitors, who have the ability to put the ablest individuals in the most responsible positions. This is especially important in regard to new enterprises that have to enter into competition with older and well-established firms.</p>
   <p>When the Knight Light &amp; Soda Fountain Company was established about ten years ago it had the good luck to select exactly the right man to superintend its factories. Due to his inventive talent and general ability the company has become one of the leading ones in its line in the country. The man is our countryman, Oscar Borg.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0887.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Borg was born in Vastervik, Sweden, June 19, 1889, and remained in his home town until he was 19 years old. Even as a boy he liked to be around steam engines, and when the time came to look for a real job he sought one which would give him an opportunity to learn more about them. He had several such jobs in his home town, and after some time he went to Visby, where he worked for the Swedish Government as an assistant engineer.</p>
   <p>In 1910 he came to Chicago, and obtained employment at the great department store, The Fair, as an engineer, in charge of the ice-freezing machines. He remained there until 1911, when the above-mentioned soda fountain company was being formed. Borg took a job in the new undertaking, starting in as a general machine worker, but his employers soon discovered that he was cut out for more responsible positions. He made one invention after another, all of which were patented. The company's products improved consistently, and sales rose beyond the most optimistic estimates of the management. Last fall a new plant, the third, was built <pb facs="5423404_2_0888.jpg" n="3"/>at 2701 North Kildare Avenue, at a cost of half a million dollars, and with working facilities for five hundred employees. Borg, who was a foreman for several years, became superintendent three years ago.</p>
   <p>As we have already indicated, Mr. Borg loves songs, and is himself an active singer. He was among those who founded the singing club "The Comrades," and is its president at the present time. He is also a member of the Swedish Engineering Society. </p>
   <p>In 1912 Borg married Miss Hanny Johnson from Gamleby, Sweden. They have two children, and the family lives at 821 Newport Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
