<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Law and Treason</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAW AND TREASON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What the Constitution provides in this connection, and what constitutes Treason: - Treason against the United States shall consist of being hostile to it; or of sharing confidential material to or conspiring with the enemy, or aiding or supporting them in any way.</p>
   <p>(U.S. Constitution. Article 3-See 3. The framers of the Constitution were desirous of making reasonably certain of the difference of rightful liberty and rights. It was not unknown to them, either in theory or in practice that the right to change Treason was a necessary power of the Government. They thought it wise to make this a crime, to make it conspicuous in the Constitution. It is one of the most seriously known law, and so accordingly they set it forth clearly and precisely; so that only those who specifically choose to violate this Constitutional provision, could, and should, be held for Treason.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0231.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following sentence in the same paragraph provides what is necessary in order to establish proof in connection with this most serious charge: - Two witnesses are required to testify that the act took place (should the defendant not plead guilty). Many persons misinterpret the word"Act". On expression of what is seen, is as much of an act as the striking of a blow. Whatever constitutes a spiritual or corporal act(it makes no difference whether it is thought or action). Put together with a contrary situation not to act when condition warrant that action be also had constitutes an "Act."</p>
   <p>There is also considerable misconception regarding what constitutes an overt Act? Many believe it to be a direct physicial Act. This is not so a thought can be an overt Act, though one cannot see a thought only through its effect.</p>
   <p>We do not want to give the impression that words favorable to the enemy necessarily constitute Treason. But we must remember that words and acts jointly if it squares with the prohibition does constitute Treason.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0232.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For Example: Anything spoken or written if it has to do with the number of troops, or supplies, which are to be used in a specific battle, constitutes Treason. To adhere to the enemy is a difficult term to make clear. One who has an opinion - or conclusion - favorable to a person or a nation at war with the United States, does not in itself constitute Treason. One must not only in thought adhere to this nation, but also with "Acts" - give them support - to aid and abet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
