<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-11-02">Nov. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Sunday in the Swedish Theatre</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-11-02">Nov. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SUNDAY IN THE SWEDISH THEATRE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Theatre owners and directors are continually complaining, that the "movies" draw the people from the theatres, and that the legitimate stage has lost its attractive powers. One theatre man, however,has no reason for complaint in this respect, the veteran Chr. Brussell, who Sunday evening with his party gave "Vermlandingarne," a Swedish comedy play, at Powers Theatre. The theatre was not only a "sell out," but many hundreds were turned away. Before the curtain went up editor Malmquist's stately person appeared on the stage and gave us a short biography of the author of this play and a description of his birthplace. Anders Frederick Dahlgren was born in the same house as Erik Gustaf Geijer (not Gustaf Erik, Frithjof!). It was also pointed out it is just now a century since this event took place. After the prologue came the play. However often this play has been presented on the Swedish-American Stage, it has seldom, if ever, been better rendered. Most of the actors have many times played the same roles, so it was only to be expected, that the play should "go <pb facs="5423404_2_1505.jpg" n="2"/>off" without a hitch. It was gratifying to note, that the acting of roles had been proved. "Anna" outside of the church was the best performance we have seen of that part, and rose high above the amateur "standard." No professional has ever acted that part better. Both Anna and Erik (Hedvig and Verner Melinder) have received the God-given gift of song in ample measure, and it was here put to its fullest use. Against the masquerading (if such it was) of the minister, we might say, that it was rather accentuated by his weakness for strong liquor; this is not indicated by the author. The imbibing minister, no doubt, did not strike home with many. "Lopare-Nisse" was very good, the best we ever saw. Co-ordination and co-operation was good and the national dances performed by the society "Frihet" (liberty) were received with a storm of applause. The most tragic scene in "Vermlandingarne" always creates mirth in the theatre, but this should not offend the actor. The spectators remember how this scene is carried out and it is with thrilled expectations they anticipate what is to follow, which starts the laughter in the most tragic moment - whether or not that which is expected happens. This point of view should also be taken by the actors, as it is the right one and also the most serene.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1506.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Finally the hundreth anniversary of the birth of Anders Frederick Dahlgren was celebrated in a fitting manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
