<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title><date when="1915-05-20">May 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Calm and Sensible</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0262</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0262.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Courier,Weekly)</title><date when="1915-05-20">May 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CALM AND SENSIBLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Note:- Under this heading the Kuriren on May 20, 1915,published an editorial against excitement during the time of crisis caused by the sinking of Lusitania.) A part of it follows:....</p>
   <p>We can conceive that occasions may arise when even a so peace loving nation as the United States will feel the urge to take up arms. Individuals as well as nations may meet with offensive behavior of a type that makes fight necessary, and at such times the one who is "too proud to fight" will rightly be ridiculed and scorned.</p>
   <p>But no such occasion is at hand now. We do not need to appeal to any such pride as others are unable to understand. We merely need to say that simple prudence and carefulness impel us not to take part in a conflict which does not concern us in the least; in which nobody is threatening our security, far less our existence. But if we want to remain neutral, we need to remain such definitely, alike as <pb facs="5423404_2_0263.jpg" n="2"/>in regard to both parties, and without a trace, even, of partisanship in our official attitude. The feelings of the individuals demand their sway here as elsewhere. But can anybody with reasonableness lay claim to united action by the American people, composed of so many different elements, when the question is of a war of attack in regard to which the inescapable consequences would be that brother would be put to fight brother.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
