<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-05">July 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish-American in the Building Industry</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Andrew Nilsson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0861</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0861.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-07-05">July 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Swedish-American in the Building Industry</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Andrew Nilsson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to reports from several quarters, the current speed-up in the building industry is more pronounced than in any other industry. Numerous large buildings are going up in all the larger cities throughout the country, and more are being planned. It seems as if better times are on the way. In regard to construction activity, no city is experiencing a greater upswing than Chicago. Architects and contractors are working to the limit of their capacity. One architect told us the other day that he had just been forced to turn down a job which would have been very profitable to him. But he already had so many rush orders on hand that he could not take on any more.</p>
   <p>It is by now a well-established fact that the Swedes are the leaders in the <pb facs="5423404_2_0862.jpg" n="2"/>building industry in Chicago. One of them, whom we have selected as the subject of this week's Foreground article, is Andrew Nilsson, the head of the plumbing firm which bears his name.</p>
   <p>Nilsson was born in Surteby, Sweden, January 18, 1868, attended the public school near his home, and, after having worked at various jobs, came to America at the age of eighteen. Nine years later we find him at Oak and Orleans Streets in Chicago, where he opened a plumbing shop in partnership with his brother. He has remained in the plumbing business ever since.</p>
   <p>This first shop soon became too small, and in 1900 it was moved to Lake View--to the corner of Clark Street and Belmont Avenue, to be exact. An increasing volume of orders continued to pour in, and this shop also became too cramped. After six years, the business had to be moved again, this time to its own building at 901 Belmont Avenue. A few years later, another expansion <pb facs="5423404_2_0863.jpg" n="3"/>became necessary, and the shop was moved to a specially-constructed two-story building at 3222-24 North Halsted Street. In 1912, the business was incorporated under the laws of the state of Illinois, and is now one of the largest of its kind in the city.</p>
   <p>Nilsson is an esteemed member of the Bethania Swedish Methodist congregation, of which he is also a trustee.</p>
   <p>In 1897 he married Anna Ekdahl.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
