<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-03-12">Mar. 12, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Registration of Aliens</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-03-12">Mar. 12, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">REGISTRATION OF ALIENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of registration of aliens in the United States is again up for consideration by our lawmakers. It is felt in some quarters that such registration will make it easier to detect and deport foreigners who have entered the country illegally. Those who favor this procedure claim that it will also afford additional protection for regular immigrants by providing them with proper identification papers, and that it is to the advantage of the law-abiding residents that persons who have entered illegally be deported.</p>
   <p>Three proposals have been submitted to the Congress. The bill introduced by Congressman Aswell of Lousiana provides for annual registration of all foreigners, and the payment of a fee of two dollars the first year and one dollar per year afterward. The registration certificate would include a <pb facs="5423404_2_0305.jpg" n="2"/>photograph of the registrant, signature, and other means of identification, and the owner would be required to show it upon request by the police and by representatives of the Department of Labor. He, or she, would also be required to report any encounters with the law, change of name, and other activities of importance. After having been duly registered for five years an alien would become eligible for citizenship without taking out the so-called first paper.</p>
   <p>The bill submitted by Congressman Cable of Ohio does not differ essentially from that of his Lousiana colleague. He would make the registration fee fifty cents per year.</p>
   <p>Senator Blease proposed in his bill that every alien who enters the country legally, and intends to remain here, upon the payment of a five-dollar <pb facs="5423404_2_0306.jpg" n="3"/>fee, accompanied by photograph, signature, address, and other means of identification, shall be given a certificate by the Commissioner-General of Immigration, which certificate shall be considered adequate proof of legal entry.</p>
   <p>Aliens who enter the country illegally should, of course, be arrested and deported, and the procedure would undoubtedly be made easier by compulsory registration of all foreigners. But why should all those who have complied with all immigration regulations be inconvenienced just because the government is unable to prevent abuses? It is not fair to the majority of immigrants who have complied with the law, and who came here in good faith, to submit them to constant supervision, segregation, as it were, and make them the subjects of petty espionage and possible abuse by overzealous officials, just because a comparatively small number of foreigners succeed in smuggling themselves into the country. Many of them are, by the way, able to <pb facs="5423404_2_0307.jpg" n="4"/>do so because of inefficient control, or by bribing minor officials who, for a remuneration, are willing to look the other way.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, people who enter the country illegally may be counted as wily; they employ all the tricks at their disposal to avoid registration. In order to prevent such action it has been suggested that all employers be instructed not to hire any alien who cannot produce his registration certificate. That might help some, but such measures cannot be one hundred percent effective. One may be sure that the racketeers, who specialize in alien smuggling,are also capable of forging registration certificates, and the practice of enlisting the aid of employers might, in the end, do more harm than good.</p>
   <p>A compulsory registration law cannot be said to be absolutely necessary at this time, and we feel that it would be better for everybody concerned if the bills now pending were laid aside for the present. If immigrant <pb facs="5423404_2_0308.jpg" n="5"/>smuggling and other abuses of immigration regulations should threaten to get out of hand under present enforcement agencies, laws necessary to cope with the evil may be enacted at any time.</p>
   <p>Citizens as well as law-abiding aliens are better served if compulsory registration be voted down now, and in order to bring about such a result voters should write their senators and congressmen to let them know how they feel about the matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
