<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">"Health Fever"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">"HEALTH FEVER"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is often jokingly said that the present generation suffers from "health fever," and many people seem to think that we would be better off if we paid less attention to our health and concentrated on improving our lot in life in other respects.</p>
   <p>These critics are wrong, for health is the most important thing in life, and the world needs healthy people, sound in body and mind. In the old days the doctor was something like a mixture of a miracle man and an oracle, but now he is both a healer and a preventive educator, and the general public is becoming more and more interested in health instruction. This interest is, naturally, most marked among women, for they are concerned not only about their own well-being but also about that of <pb facs="5423404_2_0635.jpg" n="2"/>their children, and it is up to them to give the latter a good start in life from the point of view of health. It is agreed that in childhood the foundation is laid for the individual's happiness and success in later life.</p>
   <p>The young woman, the future mother as well as the young man who is later to take over the responsibilities of a father, should know and observe the fundamental health rules and take an active interest in sports, gymnastics, and outdoor life in general, both for their own sake and for the sake of the race. Physical and mental hygiene are coming into their own, and medical science is humanity's best friend.</p>
   <p>The importance of regulations and laws pertaining to health is now becoming more widely recognized. The passing of the pure food law, so bitterly fought and denounced by manufacturers, was an important step in the right direction. Another sign of the times is the provisions <pb facs="5423404_2_0636.jpg" n="3"/>made by the Health Commissioner of the state of Pennsylvania for sanitary instruction and improvements in country districts, particularly as they affect schools and other public institutions--prevention of contagious diseases, water purification, etc. It is well known that up to now public health measures have been neglected in rural communities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
