<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-10-26">Oct. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">City and Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-10-26">Oct. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CITY AND COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The majority of farm boys long to go to the city, and the flight from the country is a phenomenon which has caused considerable worry among statesmen and other national leaders in most civilized countries.</p>
   <p>Governor Ralston of Indiana discussed the problem in a recent speech, and in discoursing on the various reasons for this trend away from the farm and country, he expressed sympathy with many of these dissatisfied farm boys, pointing out, somewhat sarcastically,that not all of these youngsters were endowed with enough brains to become successful farmers. This statement recalls a similar one made by a Swedish professor, who declared that Swedish farmers tended to send to the university those boys who lacked the qualifications for more demanding occupations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such statements as the two mentioned above, even though somewhat strong, do represent a reaction against the attitude which is at the bottom of the regrettable "flight from the farm". They indicate a return to common sense and to the unchanging truth that those that till the soil form the nucleus of a nation. This fact is generously acknowledged before an election, but no sooner are the votes counted than the farmer is dropped back into the obscurity to which he has become accustomed.</p>
   <p>However, the governor and the professor can hardly be suspected of just fishing for the farm vote with the statements cited above. They simply called attention to the evident fact that intelligence and good judgment are just as much needed on the farm as in any other sphere of activity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
