<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-02">Feb. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Alaska--The Land of Gold</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-02">Feb. 2, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">ALASKA--THE LAND OF GOLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alaska, the Land of Gold, is undoubedly richer in gold than any other country in the world. Many people have won riches there, and as everybody knows, many Swedes have become millionaires. Still others, have laid the foundation for great wealth by investing money in gold mines in Alaska. Although millions in gold have been taken out of Alaska's mines, mining engineers insist that hardly a real beginning has as yet been made; that billions and still more billions lie hidden in the soil. The chance of earning a fortune in Alaska is better today than at any time before. Means of communication are better than ever; wages, the cost of living, and other costs are lower, etc.</p>
   <p>The Swedish-owned gold mining corporation, the Scandia Mining Syndicate is <pb facs="5423404_2_1114.jpg" n="2"/>the owner of sixty-eight claims covering a total of 1,360 acres of rich gold fields in Alaska. These claims border on the richest mines, out of which millions have been dug. Railroads which are now being built everywhere in Alaska are running close to this Company's claims; this makes the transport of machinery and necessities a simple matter. Tests made upon the claims of the company reveal that the gold yield per cubic yard has a value ranging from three dollars to two hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>Compare this with the yield from the gold mines in California, which amounts to merely three cents per cubic yard; yet these mines are still being worked today at great profit.....It is then possible to make an estimate of the profits in store for Swedes who put their savings into this mining undertaking. For the purpose of raising capital for the construction of a canal from Casa de <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>aga River to twelve of the Company's claims which, when the canal is finished, are to be worked on a larger scale by means of hydraulic machinery, the company now offers to Swedes a limited amount of stock at the low price of <pb facs="5423404_2_1115.jpg" n="3"/>fifteen cents per share, the minimum to be sold to any one person being one hundred shares.</p>
   <p>The capital of the Scandia Mining Syndicate is $2,500,000; par value of the stock is one dollar per share. The officers and directors of the company are---prominent Swedish businessmen. Do not neglect this opportunity; write at once to</p>
   <p>Scandia Mining Syndicate, 608 Stock Exchange Building</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
