<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-07">Mar. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Concert</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. and Mrs. Frederiksen to Give a Concert of Scandinavian Music, at Auditorium Recital Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-07">Mar. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN CONCERT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. and Mrs. Frederiksen to Give a Concert of Scandinavian Music, at Auditorium Recital Hall</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The artistic couple, Mr. and Mrs. Frederik Frederiksen, have given two concerts at the Auditorium Recital Hall which have proved of greater success than most concerts, even at that Hall. The third, and last, concert of the season will be held at the Recital Hall on Thursday at 8:15 P. M. This concert will be of special interest to Scandinavians in Chicago, because the program will consist exclusively of Norwegian, Swedish, and Danish numbers, as follows:</p>
   <p>(1) Sonata in E Major, Opus 27 (for piano and violin).............Sinding Mr. and Mrs. Frederiksen</p>
   <p>(2) "Kung Heimer och Aslog".............Soderman Mr. Gustaf Holmquist</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1256.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(3) Sonata for piano and violin (first time in Chicago).............Peterson - Berger Mr. and Mr. Frederiksen</p>
   <p>(4) a. "Nar stjerneharen blankar".............Hallstrom</p>
   <p>b. "Jag ar ung".............Hallstrom Mr. Holmquist</p>
   <p>(5) Trio for piano, violin, and violincello, op. 53.............Lange - Muller Mrs. Frederiksen, Mr. Franz Wagner, Mr. Frederiksen</p>
   <p>As lovers of music will notice, this is a most select program of works from the greatest Scandinavian composers. Sinding's sonata represents Norwegian music; Mr. Frederiksen is a personal friend of the composer. The two studied together in Berlin, and Mr. Sinding was a frequent guest at Mr. Frederiksen's home in London, England. Often, the two played together the compositions of Mr. Sinding. The Peterson-Berger sonata is representative of Swedish music. As a curiosity, we may mention that the music sheets to be used at the concert <pb facs="5423404_2_1257.jpg" n="3"/>are a gift from the composer to Mr. Frederiksen. The sonata met with great success when it was played in London by Mr. Frederiksen some years ago. The Lange-Muller trio represents Danish music. As music lovers know, Lange-Muller has given the world many beautiful melodies. Mr. and Mrs. Frederiksen were accorded great acclaim when they played the Lange-Muller trio in London a few years ago.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Gustaf Holmquist and Franz Wagner are well-known musicians, and their appearance on the program will add to the interest of the concert.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
