<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-12">May 12, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[The Largest Swedish Men's Store]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-05-12">May 12, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[THE LARGEST SWEDISH MEN'S STORE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The largest Swedish store handling ready made suits and other articles of clothing for men is operated by Mr. John M. Erickson, whose spacious and well supplied store occupies 130 feet frontage at the corner of Division Street and Clybourn Avenue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Erickson started his career as a businessman more than twenty years ago. For many years his store was located on Chicago Avenue, where he won a steadily increasing circle of customers. The reason for this was his principle of honesty in business, combined with a spirit of friendliness and accommodation, such as few businessmen can boast of.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Three years ago, Mr. Erickson moved his business to the place it occupies at present. Already the store was considered one of the largest on the North Side, and the space was needed for the customers from Chicago Avenue and adjoining streets who sought out their compatriot in his new location. To these were added the Swedish speaking inhabitants in the new district into which the business had been moved. Both groups co-operated in purchasing articles of men's clothing as they needed them. Soon the new store became too small. Mr. Erickson is not exactly a "bird of passage," and he had no desire to move once more. Instead he used the plan of the large businessmen downtown when needing larger space; he bought the neighboring store and united this store with his own. The new addition is not quite finished yet, but on Saturday, May 16, it will be opened for business. On that day, a so-called "Grand Opening" will take place in the large store, and the thirty salesmen in Mr. Erickson's employ will display all the rich stock of ready-to-wear clothes and other articles of clothing for men. A practical and attractive souvenir will be presented to any one visiting the store on the day of the Grand Opening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
