<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-02-09">Feb. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Society's Duty Toward Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-02-09">Feb. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY'S DUTY TOWARD CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the final analysis children are of even greater importance to society than they are to their own parents, and it is therefore only proper that certain precautions, safeguarding their health and normal development, mentally as well as physically, be taken at public expense. This point of view is being advocated by our energetic and able Commissioner of Health, Dr. Evans, and we believe he is absolutely right.</p>
   <p>Public opinion supports the laws which make it compulsory for children to attend school, because experience has taught us that the ignorant man or woman is a danger to society, and often becomes a burden. A child in poor health is also a potential danger and burden.</p>
   <p>It is generally agreed that it is every child's right to receive a certain <pb facs="5423404_2_0642.jpg" n="2"/>amount of knowledge and schooling at the expense of the state. We have not yet progressed to the point where it is being conceded that a child's rights also include good health to such extent as good health can be secured through medical and surgical treatment, now at our disposal. But the day will come when it will be considered a matter of course. When it does, every boy and girl of school age will be examined regularly by competent doctors, and such defects and tendencies detrimental to health as are discovered will be treated and cured, if possible, and there can be no doubt that a generation which has benefited from such a procedure, will be superior to its predecessors, mentally, physically, and morally. It will be a step closer to human perfection.</p>
   <p>Society imprisons criminals and maintains special institutions for insane persons, and it is its duty and right to do so. But on the strength of the same authority by which it executes a murderer, it should take such measures as will promote a desirable development of the individual, and it is only logical to begin with protecting the physical and mental health of the child.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
