<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-08-17">Aug. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Tenant Farming</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0573</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0573.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-08-17">Aug. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TENANT FARMING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The rise in prices of agricultural products, which took place during the war, resulted in an increase in the number of tenant farmers in the Middle West. Many farmers found that they could rent out their land as profitably as they could operate it in normal times themselves. But when prices began to decline most tenants were unable to pay the high rent, and the owners themselves had to go to work again.</p>
   <p>It may well be said that this is one beneficial effect of the general economic depression which set in after the war, for, to a large entent, tenant farming tends to upset the stability of the nation. There is no real incentive for the tenant to improve the land, for not he but the owner benefits from the increase in value, and, what is even worse, a competitor may come along and offer the farmer higher rent, and the original tenant is out. He is, therefore, inclined to exploit the land to the limit of its yield from year to year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0574.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even before the war, tenant farming was on the increase. Those that first took homesteads cultivated their own fields and raised the generation that, together with the immigrants, constitutes the backbone of America. In most cases the second, third and fourth generation went to the cities, where they hoped to earn more money and live an easier and more comfortable life, and the old homestead was given over to a tenant. Mortgage firms also have come into possession of many farms, which have been rented out to tenants , when no buyers could be found.</p>
   <p>In general, it can truthfully be said that it is poor business for a farmer to rent out his land, and from a national point of view the practice is a dangerous one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
