<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-31">Aug. 31, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">National Referendum</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-08-31">Aug. 31, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONAL REFERENDUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the early days of our republic opinions were sharply divided in regard to the extent of the respective powers vested in the executive and the legislative branches of the government, and there was a tendency within the latter gradually to take on the aspects of a monarchy. In order to prevent this tendency from spreading it was decided that neither the Congress nor the executive department should have the authority to add any provisions to the Constitution or make changes in those already existing. A Supreme Court had been instituted, but since its judges were appointed by the President its powers were of necessity limited to deciding whether or not certain laws were constitutional. Even with such safeguards it is doubtful if the states would have ratified the Constitution were it not for their absolute faith in the honesty and patriotism of George Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0382.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But it was soon realized that future developments would make it desirable and necessary to make additions to the Constitution, and it was agreed to subject such additions to referendum, thus permitting the people to make the final decision. An amendment to the Constitution becomes law when it has been approved by three fourths of the state legislatures. And what is this procedure if it is not a referendum, which really means an expression of the will of the voters? Nevertheless it is considered in some quarters as a somewhat dangerous experiment of a slightly socialistic, not to say anarchistic, nature. It is true that the people do not vote directly, but they are speaking through their representatives who are supposed to be close to the people, to know what serves their interests, and to act accordingly.</p>
   <p>While we have lived through four wars, one of which was a bloody and exhausting civil war, and while we have created a general prosperity unequaled in history in spite of the abuses of a powerful money-aristocracy, little use has been made of the national referendum. The Constitution has undergone slight <pb facs="5423404_2_0383.jpg" n="3"/>changes on fifteen different occasions, and strong public opinion has been required to bring about the changes. It has been thirty-nine years since the fifteenth amendment, which granted the Negro the right to vote was incorporated into the supreme law of the land. Since then, certain conditions, caused by the formations of powerful trusts and the concentration of wealth in comparatively few hands, have become serious problems. A privileged class has emerged which is not paying its just share of our governmental expenses with the result that an unduly heavy tax burden has to be carried by the less privileged citizens who are least able to carry it. These people have footed the bill for wars, and are actually paying for the upkeep of a financial aristocracy, which in turn exerts pressure on legislatures in order to maintain its own supremacy.</p>
   <p>In our constitutional amendments and their practical application we have taken measures to protect the rights of the individual who is under arrest, accused of a crime, and those of the strikebreaker, the Negro, and the millionaire. Another amendment, which will operate for the benefit of the common, ordinary <pb facs="5423404_2_0384.jpg" n="4"/>man, who hitherto patiently has accepted his fate, is now under discussion. It is aimed at a more equitable taxation system, and will, in essence, empower the Congress to assess a direct tax on incomes. It is possible that such an amendment will be subjected to a national referendum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
