<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-08">Jan. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Needed Legislation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-08">Jan. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NEEDED LEGISLATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From an esteemed subscriber in Rockford, we have received the following letter regarding the question which should be of interest to the great majority of our readers.</p>
   <p>The standpoint which the writer takes on this question is undoubtedly shared by many but it does not alter our own conception, for which we make reservation to advance further reasons. The letter received reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Under the heading, 'Necessary Legislation'in your honored newspaper on New Year's day, you say, among other things: 'No matter how much one may deplore and seek to counteract the inconveniences which arise through strikes, particularly in enterprises and institutions upon which the <pb facs="5423404_2_0348.jpg" n="2"/>undisturbed progress of the entire community life is dependent, we still believe that the prohibition of strikes by law constitutes an encroachment upon the personal liberty which is guaranteed the American people by the constitution'.</p>
   <p>"If I may, I should like to make a few remarks on this matter. How can it be possible to consider it a constitutional right and liberty to strike in such enterprises and institutions upon which the undisturbed progress of the entire community life is dependent?</p>
   <p>"Where does the personal liberty and right of the community come in under such circumstances?</p>
   <p>"Shall not the Constitution be a protection and a defense for the law-bound <pb facs="5423404_2_0349.jpg" n="3"/>freedom of all individuals?</p>
   <p>"What can be considered more important, to have the right and liberty to work,or to have the right and liberty to go on strike?</p>
   <p>"During the latest coal strike many other workers were, to a certain extent, thrown out of work, which means they were deprived of their full right and liberty to work in consequence of the fact that the mine workers had the right and liberty to strike. If there had been no coal strike, then, of necessity, other workers would have had their right and liberty to work undisturbed, and there would have been no necessity for the people as a whole to be without coal.</p>
   <p>"Now, if all railroad workers should decide to go on strike, of course, <pb facs="5423404_2_0350.jpg" n="4"/>other workers and the people as a whole would then suffer great difficulties. I doubt, if the Constitution of the United States, at least heretofore, has ever given a number of organized groups the right and liberty to plague and harm the remainder of the citizens, and at their cost, force special privileges and liberties for themselves which are not given to all the other workers within the land.</p>
   <p>"What is a strike other than a kind of war or fight to do harm? If there is ever to be peace on earth then all wars and fights must cease, and the people, in controversial matters must submit their grievances to responsible or just courts of arbitration.</p>
   <p>"It is strange that just from the quarter where one now hears such a high-sounding cry for personal liberty and the right to strike that <pb facs="5423404_2_0351.jpg" n="5"/>these organizations, in an overwhelming measure, seconded the brutal and immoderate policy to rob the people of the traditional right and liberty hallowed by Christ's teaching, the right of self-determination of the individual in the matter of food and drink.</p>
   <p>"Freedom! Yes, but let us have freedom, bound by law and order, which is consistent with our reputation of being a Christian and free land. But then one should also learn to live harmoniously.</p>
   <p>"A happy New Year!</p>
   <p>O.F.N.</p>
   <p>Our objections to the forgoing will be brief.</p>
   <p>We have only treated this matter as a question of principle in its <pb facs="5423404_2_0352.jpg" n="6"/>relation to the Constitution of the United States. It is clear to us that the right to strike, which is to say lay down one's work or to refuse to work in an expression of the personal liberty which is guaranteed to the American people by the Constitution. The Constitution can be changed, but only in the manner which is therein prescribed. And by reason hereof we have thought, and we shall continue to think, that prohibiting of strikes can only be initiated through an amendment to the Constitution.</p>
   <p>The reasons which the contributor has advanced, and the inconveniences which he points out, are so evident that no objections can be made against them. But they are directed mainly against the disproportions which arise <pb facs="5423404_2_0353.jpg" n="7"/>not through the refusal of the majority to work themselves, but their refusal to allow others to work. According to our conception, this disproportion is dependent upon the fact that labor unions have been able to engage a reserved peace so that they are not economically responsible for the damage which they effect. This is without doubt an injustice as well as a flaw in the legislation which can very easily be righted without taking the troublesome, circuitous route of an amendment to the Constitution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
