<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-04-27">Apr. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Fifty Years Later</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-04-27">Apr. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTY YEARS LATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About fifty years have elapsed since a funeral procession moved across the country, carrying the remains of the assassinated President Lincoln to his final resting place in the city of Springfield, Illinois. The Union was in deep mourning, fully realizing the cruel loss it had suffered when the beloved chief, in the moment of victory, was struck down--victim of a bullet fired by a fanatical, sneaking murderer.</p>
   <p>In the light of history it is readily seen that the martyrdom of Lincoln put the finishing touches to the work of liberation. Hate among brothers, old feuds, and the unnatural, sharp dividing line between North and South all seemed to become insignificant when the news of the revered President's death at the hand of a killer spread like a prairie fire throughout the country.</p>
   <p>Lincoln is one of the outstanding personalities and heroes of history, whose glory will never fade, but rather become more distinct and inspiring as time passes. He was really too great a man to be fully understood at a time when <pb facs="5423404_2_0470.jpg" n="2"/>the nation was split into factions filled with hate toward each other. And it was only when this chasm was bridged that his real stature could be appreciated.</p>
   <p>The Union was personified in Lincoln. He was born in the South and raised in the North, and his mind was open as the western prairies. He was the head of a divided family, but to him there was no North and South, only the Union. It would be a fine thing for our country and people if our present-day statesmen acquired more of the spirit of Lincoln.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
