<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-07-04">July 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Power of Public Opinion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-07-04">July 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE POWER OF PUBLIC OPINION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not so long ago, the Federal Council of Churches issued a protest against the twelve-hour day in the steel industry. Simultaneously, it published a letter from the president of the Colorado Fuel and Light Company in which he stated that his organization had introduced the eight-hour day five years ago, and that the arrangement had proved very satisfactory in every respect.</p>
   <p>This incident caused the steel king, E. H. Gary, to write a letter to the secretary of the Lord's Day Alliance, declaring that he was less concerned about the practical aspect of the twelve-hour day than with popular opinion regarding it. He expressed the hope that a shorter workday would be established in the "comparatively near future". In this letter, he says, in part: "We abolished the seven-day week immediately following the war, and have maintained a six-day week ever since. I do not know of any exception to this rule, and, <pb facs="5423404_2_0320.jpg" n="2"/>if any should be found, it will be corrected without delay. We do not advocate a seven-day week. As a matter of fact, we are even against a twelve-hour day, and hope to see it abolished in the comparatively near future."</p>
   <p>On the occasion of the publication of this letter, Reverend F. Ernest Johnson, who is directing the Council's investigation of industrial conditions, remarked that the twelve-hour day in industry is a moral crime, a challenge to the churches in their own field. He accepts Gary's statement at its face value. And why not? Even steel kings may realize that "the voice of the people is the voice of God".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
