<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-14">July 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Child Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-07-14">July 14, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">CHILD LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new law abolishing child labor in this State, which becomes effective July 1, has not won the universal acclaim of parents and employers. The law, of course, is touching directly the economic interests of various individuals, and such interests are as precious these days as the apple of one's eye. It is quite natural that the father or head of the family, who must supply food and clothing for seven or eight children, should not feel pleased at the news that his thirteen year old boy is to be compelled to quit work, and must go to school. The wages of this boy have been used advantageously, both father and mother have counted on this factor when buying the necessaries for the family. But the father who looks further into the future, and who is concerned for his <pb facs="5423404_2_0442.jpg" n="2"/>children's welfare will not complain of the law. Only he, who is short-sighted, who tries to harvest in the evening from the plants he set out in the morning, will say the law is causing him a loss.</p>
   <p>If, however, the poor father who only receives about nine dollars per week for his labor fails to grasp the social importance of the law, it is easy to excuse him, there are reasons for his point of view. But what reason is there for the employer to oppose the new order? He calls it class legislation, "violation of the rights of the individual." He considers that a "healthy, strong boy of eleven or twelve will not be hurt by working during his vacation," and he paints in dark colors the dangers of having the boys run about streets and alleys during the days they are off from school. The employers who thus criticize the new law profess warm interest in the future of the growing generation, but behind this display of tender feelings hovers selfishness and greed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0443.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What does the employer care about the son of toil? What does he care if the twelve years old son becomes a wreck, physically and morally, as long as he is permitted to turn to himself the fruits of the boy's labor with little costs. It is indeed time to stop the wheels of this mill even though greedy employers do oppose the act.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
