<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Noted Swedish Manufacturer and Inventor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0813</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0813.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">NOTED SWEDISH MANUFACTURER AND INVENTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The industrial firm of F.F.Backstrom &amp; Son has been doing so well during its seven years of existence that its original quarters at 825 South Kilpatrick Avenue have become too crowded, and the concern has just moved into a newly erected factory building at Twelfth Place and 47th Avenue, where it also owns enough land to permit further expansion.</p>
   <p>F.F. Backstrom &amp; Son was established in 1922 by master mechanic Fridolf Backstorm, well known in Swedish circles here, and his son, Frederick A. Backstrom; in the course of a few years they have earned an enviable reputation as makers of specialty machines, and for their experimental work and inventions of time and labor saving devices. Among their customers are some of the largest industrial concerns in the country, such as the Wm. Wrigley Company, the United States Tobacco Company, the Acme Felt works, and others.</p>
   <p>Fridolf Backstrom was born in Dalarne (Dalecarlia), Sweden, May 12, 1369, and <pb facs="5423404_2_0814.jpg" n="2"/>came to Chicago in 1892. He received his early mechanical training at De Laval's separator manufacturing plant in Stockholm. Upon his arrival here he found employment in the machine line, where he soon became known as an excellent mechanic and inventor of new and improved mechanical devices, and many machine firms benefited from his inventions.</p>
   <p>In 1909 he became shop foreman with the Western Felt Works of this city, and remained there until 1922, when he established a factory of his own in partnership with his son, who was born in Chicago, a fact which does not detract from his Swedish heritage. Born in 1894, he showed unusual mechanical ability from early childhood. After having completed his formal training at the Crane Technical High School, he became his father's assistant at the Western Felt Works. His career was interrupted by the World War, during which he served in the artillery of the Rainbow division, and was cited for bravery. When the war was over he served with the American occupational army in Germany, returning to Chicago and to his old job with the Western Felt Works, in 1919.</p>
   <p>These two countrymen are typical examples of what Swedish energy, devotion to work, <pb facs="5423404_2_0815.jpg" n="3"/>and inventive genius can accomplish in this country. There is every reason to expect that Backstrom &amp; Son will continue to progress and prosper in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
