<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Old-Age Security</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">OLD-AGE SECURITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish-American Congressman, Frederick Lundin, is the outstanding champion of old age security in the United States, and the arguments which he presented in his speech in the House of Representatives last June have reverberated throughout the country. It is evident that the Congressman has made a thorough study of this subject, and spared no trouble in collecting dependable and instructive data from countries where the pensioning of aged people is already in operation.</p>
   <p>This issue has already been on the agenda for a long time in several countries, but here in America we have not even made the preliminary motions. Congressman Lundin has proposed that a commission be appointed to study the question from all angles, and he intends, if re-elected, to continue his efforts in behalf of this cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The American social consciousness is not very alert in this respect, and the national conception of a just and equitable society is not clearly defined. It is, therefore, often easy for the financially strong to exploit those who are financially weak. In this country there is also an official attitude of indifference toward the hardships of old are, and a vigorous educational campaign is much needed: firstly, to inform the public as well as our officials of actual conditions among indigent old people, and, secondly, to let them know what other progressive countries are doing for their old people.</p>
   <p>There are signs that the public is becoming interested, and Congressman Lundin is receiving many sympathetic and encouraging messages. There is reason to believe that the commission, the appointment of which he proposed, will materialize in the near future.</p>
   <p>Quite a bit is being done through private efforts, but it is not adequate and it is not what we want. We want an official pension, granted as a right, not as charity. Under present conditions it is often humiliating and degrading <pb facs="5423404_2_0368.jpg" n="3"/>for old people to apply for help, but a state pension, provided by law, will enable aged dependent persons, most of whom have worked hard all their lives, to face their declining years without fear of absolute destitution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
