<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-02-01">Feb. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Congress and the Eight-Hour Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-02-01">Feb. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONGRESS AND THE EIGHT-HOUR DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everybody will agree that the United States Government should afford those people that are working for it just and humane treatment, and it certainly is in a financial position to do so. This was recognized by the Congressmen themselves when, not so long ago, they raised their own salary from five thousand to seventy-five hundred dollars a year, an increase of fifty per cent. They did so in spite of the fact that they are on the job in Washington for only a few months every year, and already enjoyed free transportation to and from the Capitol, free postage, free office help, and other privileges. However, most of us feel that the people's representatives deserved this salary increase, and their action did not draw severe criticism from any quarter. An able Congressman is entitled to a good salary so that he will not have to supplement his income from <pb facs="5423404_2_0374.jpg" n="2"/>other sources. The same can be said of our judges.</p>
   <p>The bill providing for an eight-hour day, which is now pending in Congress, certainly does not demand the impossible. On the contrary, it is very reasonable and allows for exceptions for certain types of workers, such as railroad mail clerks. According to this bill, contractors doing work for the government will be required to maintain an eight-hour day on such jobs wherever possible, and favoritism in this matter is guarded against.</p>
   <p>As might be expected, the bill is meeting plenty of opposition. At a public hearing held last year by the committee in charge, representatives of government contractors voiced strong objections. Superintendent Mull of Cramp and Sons' large projects in Philadelphia, denounced the proposal, declaring that "many workers would be better off morally, physically, spiritually, and financially if they were required to work <pb facs="5423404_2_0375.jpg" n="3"/>fifteen hours a day." Such statements must, of course, be regarded only as relics of the days of slavery; they are of interest as reminders that those days were left behind not so very long ago, and may God forbid that they catch up with us again. It is regrettable that the official representative of a big employer should express such views.</p>
   <p>At the same meeting another gentleman stated that labor is really a commodity, and when it is much in demand a worker should be thankful for the chance to work ten or even twelve hours a day. At other times, when there is no demand for his services, the worker just naturally does not work at all. This idea of classifying labor with brick, furniture, and other wares has also had its day in our legislatures, but should now be a thing of the past. It is the time to take another step forward, and while we are planning to make the eight-hour day universal, embracing all workers, it is fitting to start with government employees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
