<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-09-07">Sept. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Sign of the Times</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-09-07">Sept. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A SIGN OF THE TIMES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last week's issue of this newspaper we commented on the progressive political movement in America, and pointed out that the hope entertained in reactionary Republican circles that this movement has already spent its force, and will not become a factor in future campaigns, is entirely misplaced.</p>
   <p>The progressive ideas have thoroughly aroused the popular conscience, which will not be silenced even if the political party which took it upon itself to champion these ideas should be dissolved. The masses have greedily absorbed the liberal and progressive doctrines; these ideas are already deeply rooted, and a return to the old boss rule is unthinkable.</p>
   <p>Our analysis of the political situation has now been supported by no less an authority than Ex-Senator Elihu Root, of New York, who has recently come out as a champion of political reform. In a speech before the New York state constitutional <pb facs="5423404_2_0073.jpg" n="2"/>convention last week, the Senator denounced political boss rule, and "invisible government," along with their far-reaching influences. He is in favor of the so-called "short ballot," and considers it a great step forward.</p>
   <p>Senator Root's speech is encouraging, and shows in which direction the political wind is blowing. It indicates that the more farsighted smong our statesmen of the old school are beginning to realize that the days of the dyed-in-the-wool conservatives are over, and that progressive and liberal ideas are on the march.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
