<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-09">Apr. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Art Exhibit</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-04-09">Apr. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE ART EXHIBIT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twelfth annual art exhibit at the Swedish Club was opened last Saturday, and will remain open until next Sunday night. The purpose of these exhibits is to encourage Swedish-American artists, and to arouse in the public, especially in the artists' own countrymen, a benevolent interest in the works of sculptors and painters of Swedish nationality.</p>
   <p>Throughout the years much has been written about these exhibits. In general, American art critics have been very complimentary in their comments, and have often suggested that other national groups follow the example set by the Swedes. The Norwegians of Chicago have done so, and are arranging a similar exhibit every year.</p>
   <p>It has been said of these Swedish art exhibits that they are typically Swedish <pb facs="5423404_2_1417.jpg" n="2"/>and at the same time American. The older artists received their training in Sweden, and therefore belong to the Swedish school. And they choose Swedish motifs whenever possible. However, their close association with American artists has, in many instances, influenced their style. This influence is of course more evident among the younger artists, but even the latter are inclined to choose Swedish motifs when they have the opportunity.</p>
   <p>But the language of art is international, and is understood by everybody who appreciates beauty. These Swedish exhibits, therefore, have a mission to fulfill, and they deserve the support of the public, particularly of the Swedish group.</p>
   <p>Like the singers, the Swedish-American painters and sculptors carry a message to their countrymen. How are the latter to receive this message unless they visit the exhibits? Those who can afford to do so should even purchase one or more of the art objects. There is no better way of encouraging both the artists themselves and those who sponsor this annual event. The artist's struggle for <pb facs="5423404_2_1418.jpg" n="3"/>existence and recognition is usually pretty hard. Here is a fine opportunity to give him a hand. And the buyer benefits as much as the artist himself, if not more. For art has an ennobling quality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
