<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-12-13">Dec. 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Theatre</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1529</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1529.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-12-13">Dec. 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH THEATRE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are so often being told, in speeches and in writings, of all that our Swedish churches, church schools, societies, choirs, and the Swedish press, are doing for the preservation of our mother tongue, to prevent it from becoming lost in our great American melting pot. But there is another factor in this nationalistic and cultural endeavor, which is of great importance, particularly in our larger Swedish-American communities, and which is not receiving the attention it deserves, namely, the Swedish theatre.</p>
   <p>The deeply religious may not admit that anything good can come from the theatre; the indifferent bystander may doubt it, and the ministry may denounce everything theatrical, but it still has not been proven that the Swedish theatre in America does not rank with other institutions as a guardian and preserver of our Swedish language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1530.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have due respect for the dignity of age and willingly admit that the theatre belongs to a younger generation, and the church to an older one, but this younger generation has grown strong and beautiful. And we Swedes greatly admire strength and beauty.</p>
   <p>Swedish organizations established the Swedish theatre in Chicago, as well as in other of our large cities, by presenting short plays as part of the entertainment on special occasions. These efforts were so well received by the public that a few men with talent for stage work, but poor in worldly goods, were encouraged to rent occasionally one of the city's theatres for the presentation of plays depicting Swedish life and written by leading Swedish authors. But these pioneers could not make a financial success of it, and Swedish dramatic art was again relegated to the lodges and dance halls. When the minister in "The Vermlanders" was consoling the unhappy "Anna" the audience scoffed, and when "Jan Hanson" mourned the death of his daughter, it sought solace in its beer, which was being served during the performance, and disturbing noises filled the house.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1531.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is clear that the performance would suffer under such circumstances; the actors were handicapped during the rehearsals as well as during the actual performance of their roles. If they forgot their lines the audience laughed loudly and the actors would laugh with it. Swedish dramatic art in Chicago was at low ebb.</p>
   <p>But finally the Swedish Theatre Company was born and a little later the Swedish Dramatic Society. Mr. Chris Brusell organized and still heads the former; the latter was established by Ernst Behmer. But two such organizations depending partly on the same scenic talent and entirely on the same public, were one too many. The Dramatic Society was dissolved; Behmer went into partnership with Brusell, and under the leadership of these two able men the Swedish theatre gained a secure foothold in Chicago. Many excellent dramas were presented, and a responsive public filled the theatre to capacity.</p>
   <p>Then the partnership broke up, with the result that the two directors became, and still are, competitors. Nobody knows what the final outcome will be, but we do hope that never again will a fine Swedish stage play <pb facs="5423404_2_1532.jpg" n="4"/>be presented in a dance hall.</p>
   <p>The public's taste for the best in dramatic art must be catered to, and this cannot be successfully done before an audience which is impatiently waiting for the dance band to strike up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
