<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">About Taxation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT TAXATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tax question is again becoming the subject of heated discussion, and it is likely that arguments will continue to be thrown back and forth until Congress finally settles the issue. But unless a special session is called no action can be taken until next year, when that body is scheduled to convene.</p>
   <p>Of all the proposals thus far submitted, none is more important than the one presented by the progressive bloc, which is determined to see it through. This bloc advocates a law which would authorize the Secretary of the Treasury to make public all income-tax returns. These returns certainly should make interesting reading for the millions of Americans who have had to suffer under the coal shortage and the consequent high price of coal. To the intelligent section of the American public, the tax returns of the mineowners and the middlemen should clearly illustrate the difference between fair profits and shameless <pb facs="5423404_2_0322.jpg" n="2"/>profiteering.</p>
   <p>In addition, the taxation measure proposed by the progressives advocates an amendment to the Constitution providing for the taxation of hitherto tax-exempt bonds. It also calls for a tax on stock dividends, an inheritance tax, a tax on gifts, and a retroactive tax on excess war profits. Such taxes certainly would ease the burden on the great masses of the people, who are now being called upon to pay the greater share of the cost of the war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
