<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A Zander Institute in Chicago</title>
[Half-tone, one column, Sixth of a page, pictures of Henry Bowman and Gustaf Flinck].

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0675</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0675.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A ZANDER INSTITUTE IN CHICAGO</title>
[Half-tone, one column, Sixth of a page, pictures of Henry Bowman and Gustaf Flinck].
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week, one of our staff members was invited to inspect a new institution which, under the name of the Swedish Zander Institute, has just opened its doors to the public, and is located in the Bowman Building, 75 West Van Buren Street.</p>
   <p>We had already heard that our countryman, Henry A. Bowman, owner of said building and of the Automatic Addressing Company which is housed in it, during his last visit in Sweden had bought complete equipment for such an institute, but we had no idea that it already was open for business. The event is specially interesting since there are only one or two other authentic and fully equipped Zander institutes in America, and this is the first one in this part of the country. Mr. Bowman is thus a pioneer in <pb facs="5423404_2_0676.jpg" n="2"/>this field, and we look forward to seeing his institute, whose treatment of patients is based on the principles of therapeutic gymnastics, becoming very popular among Chicagoans, even though the Zander system at the present time is almost unknown on this side of the Atlantic.</p>
   <p>The institute occupies the entire second floor of the building. Our man was first shown the tastefully furnished reception room, which leads into the various offices and examination rooms of doctors and attendants. The most interesting feature of the institute is the large gymnasium, which is equipped with sixty-two pieces of apparatus, all of which are electrically operated, and can be adjusted to fit the needs and general condition of the patient. Each one of them has its special purpose. They are operated by experts who understand the requirements of the individual patients, and, all in all, the institute is as complete in every respect as its counterparts in Sweden and other European countries. Besides therapeutic gymnastics, patients may also receive light, electrical, and water treatments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0677.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The official name of the organization is the Swedish Zander Institute and Mr. Bowman deserves much credit for his initiative. During his last visit in Sweden, he accidentally happened to meet Gustaf Flinck, the director of Zander Institute in Gothenburg, who explained to him the merits of the system. Bowman became interested, and finally was convinced that Chicago ought to have such an institute, so he bought the Gothenburg outfit out-right and brought its entire equipment over here.</p>
   <p>Highly competent experts are in charge of the work. Gustaf Flinck directs the gymnastic treatments, Albert Hultgren is physical director, and Dr. E. J. Hoglund the medical adviser. Hultgren received his training as a masseur in Sweden. In addition, Mr. Bowman has secured the services of a physiotherapist, Borje H. Klingberg, who also received his professional training in Sweden. There are, of course, also a number of trained nurses who attend women patients.</p>
   <p>The institute is open for ladies from 9:00 A. M. to 12:30 P. M., and <pb facs="5423404_2_0678.jpg" n="4"/>for men from 12:30 to 8:00 P. M., and appointments may be made by calling Harrison 5589.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
