<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-03-05">Mar. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Reformers Were Right</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-03-05">Mar. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE REFORMERS WERE RIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the United States Steel Corporation initiated the eight-hour work day in all its plants in August of last year, and the majority of independent steel companies declared themselves ready to follow this example, the innovation attracted much attention throughout the country. Many large employers shook their heads doubtfully, declaring that the new system might lead to disastrous results and that surely the workers would soon discover that the shorter work day meant reduced earnings for them. And they further predicted that the three-shift system in the steel plants would so increase production costs as to cause a decrease in the demand for steel and decreased production in other industries. The final result, they declared, would be widespread unemployment.</p>
   <p>Six months have passed since this reform was put into operation, and opinions <pb facs="5423404_2_0310.jpg" n="2"/>as to the result may now be based on actual facts rather than on guesswork. A report which was issued from Pittsburgh last week indicates that conditions in the steel industry are very satisfactory. Relations between employers and employees have improved, efficiency has increased, and the standard of living of the workers is higher than ever before.</p>
   <p>To be sure, the predicted decrease in the earnings of steel workers has come true. But the effect of this decrease has not made itself felt to the extent that might have been expected. This is shown by the fact that the general living standard among steel workers has been raised, instead of lowered. And bankers in the steel district announce that savings deposits have not declined; in fact, they have increased in some instances. Steel workers seem to handle their money more carefully than heretofore, and many of them are buying homes. The increase in the cost of production of steel amounts to not more than two to three dollars per ton.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0311.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When it was first announced that the eight-hour day was to be introduced in the steel industry, the news was hailed as a great victory for organized labor. And so it was. But reports now coming in show clearly that this reform, like all other good reforms, benefits in the end not only the particular group most immediately concerned but society as a whole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
