<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Singers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1697</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1697.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SINGERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Svenska Nyheter:</p>
   <p>I read today in your paper an editorial under the heading "Professor Ortengren and Swedish Singing in Chicago," and, being greatly interested in Swedish singing, I cannot refrain from adding a few words to your statement.</p>
   <p>It seems to me that there are other reasons for the retrogression in Swedish singing in Chicago than the so-called laziness of the singers. Is it not possible that the leadership is slightly out of date? It seems to me that you are "praising the general at the cost of the soldiers."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1698.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The singers are probably not as unwilling as one might imagine. The fact is that the leadership has retrograded so as to become merely trade-like and a matter of self-satisfied habit, which does not imbue the singers with enthusiasm and love of singing. The leading men of the Swedish Singing Association during this year, have proved so completely immersed in pride and self-worship that as a result, the fiasco at the song festival in Chicago this year, became a great disappointment for the public which had expected a great and inspiring festival. Your correspondent was saddened to the very depth of his soul, sitting in the merely half-filled Auditorium, hour after hour, listening to all those long drawn presentations of genuine mediocrity so-called artists as well as the choruses, performers who might do very well in our little affairs such as church socials, but who are altogether out of place in a great Swedish song festival. Add to this the absence of the orchestra, the half-filled hall, and the lost singers' <pb facs="5423404_2_1699.jpg" n="3"/>pride, and we of Chicago have a reason to feel insignificant.</p>
   <p>In the meanwhile, we read in the papers the most flattering statements about the leading men in this doleful occurrence; how they hold socials in honor of one another; how they give presents to each other, pat each others' backs, lauding their own performances. For no one need to imagine that the singers, the plain chorus members, were to blame for the failure of the program and the rest. To think so, would be a mistake. The only gleams of light are to be found in the fact that Mrs. Hellstrom and the grand chorus saved the festival from complete fiasco.</p>
   <p>The statements made here are severe, but they are true. There are as many fine singers as ever in Chicago at the present time, and without doubt, once again Swedish singing will blossom forth and find its best home in <pb facs="5423404_2_1700.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago. But to attain this result, once more is needed first of all unselfish and earnest cooperation. Singing for the sake of singing, that must become the motto. How about forming a new chorus? Would a move in that line win acceptance?</p>
   <p>Chicago, Nov. 28, 1905. F. D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
