<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Training School for Municipal Officers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A TRAINING SCHOOL FOR MUNICIPAL OFFICERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>New schools are being opened every year for a variety of purposes, but so far nobody has had sufficient initiative to establish the kind of school which, in our opinion, is most urgently needed, namely, a training school for municipal officers.</p>
   <p>Judge Gaynor of New York has complained that it is so difficult to find competent men to head the various city bureaus, and if this is true, what about the difficulties in picking competent and honest mayors, members of city councils and of important commissions?</p>
   <p>Really able men are rather scarce, and one can hardly expect a successful businessman to give up a profitable private business for an opportunity to serve the public. Such service is too often rewarded with indifference, <pb facs="5423404_2_0082.jpg" n="2"/>mean criticism, and even persecution. The voters need training as well as the candidates. Only when we start electing officials on the basis of real administrative ability and high purpose, may we expect to solve our intricate municipal problems. Many voters are still influenced by prejudices which have nothing to do with good municipal government.</p>
   <p>There is great need of a practical training school for officials where they may learn how the affairs of a city should be administered. The voters also are in need of enlightenment which will enable them to see through the fog created by self-seeking politicians, and to understand and make up their minds independently about the important issues.</p>
   <p>Such a school might accomplish much. Under our present system the average voter does not take much interest in municipal government except just before an election, if then. At such a time he is subjected to high-pressure campaigning, and the information given him on administrative questions is superficial and often misleading.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
