<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-05-05">May 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Bank Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-05-05">May 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">BANK ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May 1 marked the fifteenth anniversary of the founding of the Union Bank of Chicago--the Swedish Bank, as it is also called. The management observed the anniversary by giving a banquet in the Colonial Room of the Edgewater Beach Hotel, and among the guests were the directors and personnel of the institution as well as stockholders and friends. It was altogether a stylish affair with excellent food and entertainment; it was midnight before the party broke up.</p>
   <p>On this anniversary the bank's directors can look back on fifteen successful years. When the institution opened its doors on May 1, 1905, the bank's capitalization was $200,000 with reserves of $25,000. These figures have now been increased to $500,000 and $100,000 respectively.</p>
   <p>The directors are all able and experienced businessmen, and only three years after the opening of the bank it became necessary to look about for larger <pb facs="5423404_2_0914.jpg" n="2"/>quarters. The bank was moved to 115 North Dearborn Street, and after some time it moved again, this time to 25 North Dearborn Street. The building in which the bank was located was named the Union Bank Building. In 1915 the structure was remodeled and modernized, and the bank's offices are now as well appointed and convenient as those of any other bank in the city.</p>
   <p>The Union Bank's president is Mr. Charles E. Schlytern. Gustaf Hallbom and N. M. Hokanson are vice-presidents; the treasurer is John Gulliksen. The other officers are also well-known Scandinavians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
