<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-02-14">Feb. 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Legalized Slavery</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-02-14">Feb. 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">LEGALIZED SLAVERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Speak as loudly as you will of the slavery of old, praise President Lincoln for his noble attitude in regard to the slavery question, thank God on your bare knees that the negro is no longer a mere article of commerce; but while thus rejoicing, do not overlook the fact that legalized slavery is gaining territory with terrific speed and force in our own time. You may notice the expressions of this slavery, as they are manifest from day to day; you may hear the cries for relief from the thousands who are aching under slavery's burdens; but most likely you are content to leave to the world of tomorrow the task of removing this burden, inherent in a system which you lack the courage to tackle.</p>
   <p>Of the slaves of our time and in our city, we shall today speak of our firemen. Several times, already, we have called attention to their long <pb facs="5423404_2_0119.jpg" n="2"/>working day, and the need of a shorter work day for them. Some members of the city council took up the firemen's demands, and the council voted relief. But the mayor vetoed the bill passed by the council. Once more was the matter taken up by the council, and hope was expressed that this time enough votes would be found in favor of the bill, to override the mayor's veto. It was a false hope, however, and the members of the fire department must, in the future as in the past, remain on duty twenty-four hours a day; in the future as in the past, they must sleep, half dressed, in the fire station so as to be ready and on hand when alarm is given.</p>
   <p>These slaves, through their representatives, applied for a twelve hour working day, and called attention to the advantages to be gained in this connection. They showed (and every thinking individual must admit the truth of it) that it is impossible for a man to fight with full force the destructive <pb facs="5423404_2_0120.jpg" n="3"/>fires, when he is worn from toil, and has not had enough sleep and rest to recuperate. But their arguments pounded fruitlessly against the rock of economy. Every appeal for a reasonable workingday was met with the phrase, "there is not enough money in the city treasury." Poor, poor Chicago! The aldermen of the city are paid $1500 per year for one evening's meeting each week; but to the most courageous and fearless sons of the city, whose lives may be in danger many times a day, the city cannot afford to pay wages amounting to about $1000 per year for twelve hours of strenuous work per day; it is required that they work twenty hours per day for their little pay. The city can afford to pay its mayor $10,000 per year and $3,600 to his private secretary. The fire chief is paid $6000 per year, and some of the bridge tenders $3400 per year. But the members of the city's fire brigade must be satisfied with $500 per year, based on a ten hours working day. And as reason for this shameful slavery of the firemen, we hear the <pb facs="5423404_2_0121.jpg" n="4"/>statement, the city is too poor to do better. The mayor and his followers in the city council should blush with shame over their hypocracy and their arrogance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
