<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Hurrah for Kansas and the Supreme Court</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">HURRAH FOR KANSAS AND THE SUPREME COURT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A legislature of Kansas, awake to the demands of our age, decided to introduce the eight-hour working day on all construction jobs and other undertakings under control of the State. The law immediately went into effect.</p>
   <p>Quite naturally, the law became a thorn in the sides of those who contracted to do work of some kind or other for the State or for municipalities within the State, and who did not pay much attention in doing the work contracted for, to the number of hours their laborers had to toil. One of these contractors flouted the will of the legislature by compelling his workers to work ten hours a day on a street construction job in Kansas City. He had decided to "run his own business," as the saying goes. He was summoned before a court, was found guilty, and sentenced. He appealed to the Supreme Court of the State, and lost.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0435.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He then appealed to the United States Supreme Court, seeking to show that the law enacted in Kansas was contrary to the Constitution of our country.</p>
   <p>A few days ago the Supreme Court rendered its decision, clearly showing that the legislature in Kansas had full right to enact the law in question. He contractor in the case, the Court stated, was fully aware when undertaking to fulfill the contract that the same authority which entrusted him with the work also thereby specified that the workers must not be held to their duties more than eight hours per day.</p>
   <p>This decision by the courts is a victory for the workers -- a victory which was won in the first instance twelve years ago, when the Kansas legislature acted, but which might easily have been transformed into a defeat. The power of the Supreme Court, as we know, is greater than that of the legislatures of the individual States, as well as that of the United States Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
