<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-09">Feb. 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Children and the Factory</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-09">Feb. 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN AND THE FACTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"What is more important," asks the well-known reformer, Miss Jane Addams, "to be able to get a dress cheaply or to have the children of a community well brought up and trained?" And Miss Addams adds: "Thousands of little children are now slaving in sweatshops and factories in order that we may live inexpensively. Do we have the right to accept their sacrifice?"</p>
   <p>We who, thoughtless of the consequences, accept the sacrifices of these small children by using the products manufactured in plants where the little ones are working, are receiving poor aid in the true sense of that term.</p>
   <p>The factory in which the work can be done by children will soon discharge all the workers who become of age and who, in view of their greater ability to produce, ask for higher wages. In the long run, of course, children are <pb facs="5423404_2_0425.jpg" n="2"/>not able to stand up under the work demanded of them; they are taken ill and are discharged; and other children are hired to take their places. What becomes of these victims of industry? You may find them in their bleak homes, where once upon a time they were like rays of light; or you will find them in the poorhouse.</p>
   <p>What was the pay received by these children? A pittance -- enough to prevent death, too little to live on. An industry exploiting the little children is a parasite on the social body, a cancer upon a vital organ.</p>
   <p>Manufacturers take advantage of the fact that at present, with machines making the skilled mechanic superfluous, a child is able to produce as much as ten men could produce at earlier periods. The temptation to earn money, even at the expense of the children and of generations to come, becomes too strong, and they place children in places where grown men are needed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0426.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hundreds of children who ought to be at school are working in the stock-yards in Chicago. The employer rarely takes the trouble to look at the permit which the child presents in applying for a job, and on which is stated the age of the child. All their thoughts are concentrated on this one thing: to earn money; and to them it means nothing whether the age of the child be sixteen years or merely ten years. Due to this criminal indifference, the number of illiterate children in Illinois has increased considerably during the last few years.</p>
   <p>The six leading manufacturing States have in all 20,775 children between the ages of ten and twelve years that are thus misplaced. In Massachusetts there are nine thousand children employed in the factories; in New York there are sixteen thousand children thus employed; in Illinois there are twenty thousand; in Pennsylvania there are thirty-five thousand children under twelve years employed in factories.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0427.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the southern States conditions are still worse. In some of the textile mills in these southern States, girls are found working who are less than five years old. About thirty per cent of the inmates of poorhouses in the South started working as children between the ages of five and twelve years, and their physical powers were shattered even before they were fully grown.</p>
   <p>With conditions such as are here set forth, there are good reasons for asking oneself as well as others: "What is to become of the coming generation? What excuse can we give to the unborn generation for having turned our children into slaves?"</p>
   <p>What blacker sin is there than this: to keep the small, undeveloped children away from their playthings and their pleasures; to deprive them of hope in the future; to prevent the development of the children's minds and bodies; slowly to torture them to death at some bench or machine in a factory?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
