<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-16">Aug. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery</title><title level="a" type="sub">Axel Edwin Swenson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-16">Aug. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Axel Edwin Swenson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today we wish to present a man who is a direct descendant of the old Vikings. He hails from Bohuslan, a province richer in prehistoric finds, inscriptions, sagas, and other records from the Viking age, than any other part of Sweden.</p>
   <p>It is known that a nobleman from this district became the Earl of the Orkney Islands, and we mention the fact because these islands take on a special significance later in this narrative.</p>
   <p>Axel Edwin Swenson was born in Hjertuh Parish, Bohuslan, September 6, 1865. His father was a well-to-do ship captain, who sailed on the Swedish lakes and to distant lands. In 1870 his ship went under in a storm, and he, as well as the entire crew, lost their lives. He left a widow, Karolina Elisabet, a <pb facs="5423404_2_1034.jpg" n="2"/>daughter, Maria, and two boys, Charles and Axel. The two boys had planned to follow the sea like their father, but at their mother's insistence they gave up this idea.</p>
   <p>Their uncle, Bernhard Swenson, sailed on the Great Lakes, and made his home in Chicago. This was probably the chief reason why the boys decided to go to America. Charles arrived in this city in 1879 and Axel in 1891. Their sister, Maria, arrived later and married a prominent South Side contractor. Finally, the mother, wishing to spend her declining years with her children, risked the long voyage and came over to make her home with her son, Axel.</p>
   <p>Axel, like his brother, became a construction carpenter here, and when he was nineteen years old they went into partnership and established themselves as building contractors. They had inherited a substantial amount of money <pb facs="5423404_2_1035.jpg" n="3"/>from their father which enabled them to finance such an undertaking. But even though they were born, so to speak, with a silver spoon in their mouths, it required sound judgment, and a thorough knowledge of the construction business to operate successfully. And the Swenson brothers had what it took. Good business sense was particularly necessary for them since they constructed buildings for themselves, and sold the buildings as soon as they were completed.</p>
   <p>During our interview with Axel Swenson, we asked him how many apartment buildings they had erected, but he simply could not say offhand.</p>
   <p>The partnership was dissolved in 1893 by friendly agreement, and they began to operate separately. Axel lived for some time in Evanston, where he built a large apartment building. He owns another building at Sheridan Road and Lafayette Place, and is at present building a residence for himself on Glengyle Place.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1036.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In 1893 he married Miss Christina Stewart Nicholson from the Orkney Islands, Scotland. She came here with her parents, who are now prospering on a farm in Iowa. They have three children and worship in the North Shore Congregational Church.</p>
   <p>Axel Swenson is a pleasant and intelligent person, with a variety of interests, and there is nothing boisterous about him. He is a faithful friend, and his business ability speaks for itself.</p>
   <p>Even though he came here at a tender age, he has not forgotten his mother tongue, and is proud of being a Swede.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
