<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Home Building Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0897</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0897.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH HOME BUILDING ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In celebrating the twenty-fifth anniversary of its founding, the Swedish Home Building Association held a great banquet last Thursday in the Swedish Club. Some 150 people attended, and good fellowship and high spirits were much in evidence during the entire evening.</p>
   <p>At the table, the newly elected president, August Hindeberg, delivered a short welcoming speech, and introduced John G. Carson who acted as master of ceremonies.</p>
   <p>The main speaker of the evening was Attorney Alfred A. Norton, who served as secretary of the Association for a number of years, and at the present time acts as its legal advisor. Mr. Norton reviewed the history of the organization during the past twenty-five years, and said tribute to the men who have been in charge of its affairs during that time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0898.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Swedish Home Building Association was founded in 1896, and obtained its charter on November 10 of that year. Originally there were ten shareholders, each of whom invested one thousand dollars in the undertaking, except for one of them who doubled this sum. Changes of management have then place during the years, but some of the incorporators are still active in the affairs of the Association. Attorney Norton became its legal adviser in 1919. The membership has increased steadily, indication that the organization enjoys the confidence of our people. The capital at its disposal, as of December 31, 1920, amounted to $201,703.56, as compared with <gap unit="char" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.17 in 1910. During the last six months there has been an increase of <gap unit="char" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>The Association pays five per cent interest on the invested capital, and members may withdraw their money any time they wish to do so. At intervals, extra dividends are distributed among shareholders. The funds of the Association are safely invested, and only in one single case has it become necessary to institute foreclosure proceedings. Mr. Norton ended his speech by thanking all those who have supported the Association and have contributed to its success so far.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0899.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He expressed the home that it may continue to prosper.</p>
   <p>Following this speech, Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Whitlock, state inspector of loan associations, and his assistant, Mr. Nowalski, were introduced. Both made brief and flattering speeches, in which they expressed their satisfaction with the manner in which this association has been operated.</p>
   <p>Between speeches, the quests were entertained by the Chicago Premier Quartet, headed by <gap unit="char" extent="3" reason="illegible"/>. Anthony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
