<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-12-13">Dec. 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Singers and Musicians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-12-13">Dec. 13, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN SINGERS AND MUSICIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The picture which adorns the top of this column is that of Gustaf Alfred Carlson, a Vemlander who during the last sixteen years has been living in Chicago. He has been very active in promoting Swedish song and music, but he is of the type that does not like the limelight. However, you cannot stop free men from talking, and it has been common knowledge for a long time that the bearer of this name is an exceptionally talented musician. As we present today the singer, director, and musician, Gus. A. Carlson, we are sure that both the name and the features are familiar to our readers. In spite of his somewhat reserved nature, he has not been able to avoid being mentioned in the daily press from time to time, and today we will reveal the high points of his career.</p>
   <p>He was born in Locknevid parish, Kalmar, Sweden, February 22, 1871, and what makes him particularly interesting is the fact that he is what <pb facs="5423404_2_1284.jpg" n="2"/>might be called a "selfmade" musician, having received formal training only for a rather short time under the orchestra director, Adolf Edgren.</p>
   <p>As a youngster he moved about quite a bit in Sweden and finally decided, in 1888, to go to America. Chicago was his goal, and, being a piano maker by trade, he obtained employment with the Newman Bros. Company, piano manufacturers, and he is still with this firm.</p>
   <p>At about this time, his interest in, and talent for, music began to make itself felt, and he began first to practice on the violin; later on he devoted much time to brass instruments, particularly the cornet with which he became very proficient. Gradually a group of young men desirous of becoming real musicians gathered about him, and he decided to do something about it. Thus the I.O.V. Military Band and Orchestra became organized and soon made a name for itself. Carlson was its leader <pb facs="5423404_2_1285.jpg" n="3"/>from the beginning and continued as such for many years. Later he had to give up the job due to other more important engagements.</p>
   <p>Another well-known organization owes its existence to Mr. Carlson's initiative. In 1896 he formed the singing club Orpheus, and was its director for six years, during which time it won a secure place in the hearts of song lovers, and became recognized as one of the finest Swedish-American singing clubs.</p>
   <p>For some time Mr. Carlson has directed the Norwegian Singing Society. This is the oldest Scandinavian society of its kind in Chicago. Thirty years ago it had a membership of more than one hundred. He also directs the North Star, another singing society, and has recently organized The Scandinavian Quartette Club which is said to have among its members some extraordinary voices, and we are likely to hear much about it in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1286.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A gentleman all through, Mr. Carlson is endowed by nature with many fine qualities, but as we have already said he prefers to hide his light under a basket, but this does not in the least detract from the high esteem in which he is held by those who know him.</p>
   <p>Since 1900 he has been happily married to the former Tillie Selander, and they live with their one child at 1527 Belmont Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
