<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-18">Jan. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Swedish-American State Official</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Fine Public Servant</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-18">Jan. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A SWEDISH-AMERICAN STATE OFFICIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Fine Public Servant</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, two columns - third of a page, profile of John Kjellander.]</p>
   <p>Among the many public officials in Chicago hardly anyone has demonstrated greater ability and fitness for office than our well-known countryman, City Sealer John Kjellander, whose job it is to check up on all weighing and measuring devices used in trade to make sure that the public gets as much as it is paying for.</p>
   <p>There are public officials, even in this city, who deliberately neglect to enforce certain laws and regulations, and who are inclined to handle law-breakers with silk gloves, but Kjellander is not one of them. It is up to him to bring to justice those who use false weights and measures in their business, and he is doing a good job. He has declared war to the finish on <pb facs="5423404_2_0079.jpg" n="2"/>individuals, firms, and corporations that are short-weighting the public, and those of small means, who can least afford to be cheated, have particular reason to be thankful for his unceasing vigilance.</p>
   <p>Some time ago Kjellander went after the city's large bakeries, which were selling underweight bread. It was found that their one-pound loaves did not weigh sixteen ounces at all, but were from two to four ounces short. The bakers insisted that if the loaves were to weigh a full pound it would become necessary to raise the price from five cents to seven cents. During the ensuing controversy Kjellander pointed out that bread is much cheaper in England than in the United States, in spite of the fact that the former country imports much of its wheat from America. This observation was widely quoted in Chicago's newspapers, and commented upon in the British press. It even played an important role in the recent election campaign, being used by the radicals to show that living costs are lower in the free-trade country of England than in tariff-protected America. Kjellander's fame has thus reached <pb facs="5423404_2_0080.jpg" n="3"/>the British Empire, and we should not be surprised if it goes even further.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
