<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-09">Aug. 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery</title><title level="a" type="sub">Charles Bostrom</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-09">Aug. 9, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Charles Bostrom</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Boda parish in Vermland is situated about half way between Karlstad and Arvika; the railroad to the Norwegian border passes through it, and Boda is well known by Norwegians as well as by Swedes. It is the center of Vermland's furniture industry, and at least three-fourths of its population is engaged in manufacturing this commodity.</p>
   <p>Charles Bostrom was born on Draga farm in Boda, December 27, 1872. He attended the public school until he was twelve years old, when he began to help his father on the farm. When he was fifteen his father died, and a year later young Bostrom went to work at Valberg's lumber mill and carpenter shop, where he became a full-fledged carpenter. He then returned to Boda and started a small furniture factory of his own, and when he sold his first winter's production at Karlstad he realized a net profit of one hundred sixty five kroner, which was the first real <pb facs="5423404_2_1079.jpg" n="2"/>money he had ever earned.</p>
   <p>He worked for some time in Karlstad, but in 1892 the craving for bigger things got the best of him, and he sailed for America. He went first to Ishpeming, Michigan, where he worked as a bricklayer's helper and as a carpenter. In 1893 the World's Fair fever struck him, as it did many other people, and he came to Chicago. After having worked here for some time as a construction carpenter, he and Erik Nordwall became partners and established a contracting business of their own. They were lucky from the start and their business prospered. In 1896 they discontinued the partnership by friendly agreement, and Bostrom took his brother, Bengt J. Bostrom, and the brothers Magnus and Nels Olson into the firm. The name of the firm then became Bostrom and Olson Brothers. They engaged both in the general contracting business and in buying and improving vacant property. The business was successful.</p>
   <p>In 1900 Nels Bostrom withdrew from the firm, the name of which then <pb facs="5423404_2_1080.jpg" n="3"/>became Bostrom and Olson with offices at 1988 N. Clark Street. The business has been growing steadily, and last year the firm erected sixty buildings. This is a considerable volume, and sufficient proof that Bostrom and Olson enjoyed a fine reputation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bostrom has also found time for study. He holds a diploma from the engineering and architectural departments of the Y.M.C.A. College. He has also taken correspondence courses in architectural drawing and mechanical engineering offered by the International Correspondence School of Scranton, Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>In 1901 he married Miss Emma Carlson from Orebro, and they have one daughter, Ruth, age three. Their home is at 1046 Addison Street.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bostrom is a member of the Building Contractors' Council and the Carpenters' and Builders' Association. He also belongs to the Oconto Club, <pb facs="5423404_2_1081.jpg" n="4"/>and, as a true Swede, to the Swedish National League.</p>
   <p>He is a quiet, unassuming gentleman, with plenty of the will power and energy inborn in a man from Vermland, and he can point to achievements unusual for Swedish-Americans of his young age.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
