<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-06-02">June 2, 1908</date><title level="a">John Ericson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-06-02">June 2, 1908</date><title level="a">JOHN ERICSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>City engineer John Ericson was nearly lost to his adopted country last week. A yes from him and he would be packing his belongings for a long trip to Stockholm to give his services to Stockholm's city government. John Ericson with two S's is well known and John Ericson with one S is on the way to be likewise. Both are products of Sweden and America. John Ericson was one of the few considered in Sweden to head Stockholm's engineering works. It is a custom, when positions of this nature are concerned, that candidates apply for them, the best qualified candidate being selected. This time, however, an exception was made in the case of Mr. Ericson. Mr. Ericson was not called to this post, but men of high standing in Stockholm's political circles sent him a telegram urging him to ask for this position. Even though Mr. Ericson did not express any <pb facs="5423404_2_0744.jpg" n="2"/>desire to get the position, he received a telegram from Gust Richert, who offered him the position at a salary of 20,000 Kroner a year. This was a direct invitation to the post and showed the high esteem in which Mr. Ericson is held in the capital of Sweden. This was tempting to Mr. Ericson, whose salary as Chicago City Engineer is $6,000 a year, much less than what he could make in private employment. As Stockholm's City Engineer he would receive 20,000 kroner and free rent, with heat and light. Twenty thousand kroner in Sweden has a purchasing power equivalent to $12,000, twice the amount he now receives. Nevertheless Mr. Ericson sent the following telegram as final. "I have decided to stay in America." Why? No doubt the reason why he refused is the fact that after twenty-eight years under this form of democratic government he feels that he cannot work in harmony <pb facs="5423404_2_0745.jpg" n="3"/>with a number of overseers, or agree with them on the difficult problem between capital and labor. Stockholm, therefore, finds that Mr. Ericson will not be its City Engineer. It would be wise for Chicago to be on the lookout, for Mr. Ericson may be offered this position by other cities larger than Chicago.</p>
   <p>The telegram to Mr. Rickert was followed by a letter, which reads: "Your recent telegram offering me the position of Chief Building Engineer was received when I was on a visit to New York. I understand the high honor which came to me when I was thought of as an applicant for this responsible position. After a week's consideration I made my decision. "I cannot here give you all the reasons why I sent you the telegram 'I have decided to stay in America'.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0746.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"May it suffice for me to say that during my visit to Washington and New York, I learned that I have innumerable friends across the still waters of the Atlantic ocean. In Chicago I am honored and satisfied. I love my work and have planned construction work amounting to ten million dollars which is not fully completed, but hope to have it completed or nearly so. My wife and daughter were born here. I love this country and this city with all my soul, and the long debate with myself resulted in my remaining here. Sincere thanks to you for your friendly thought of me and full appreciation of this honor you wished me to accept. Yours with deepest appreciation. John Ericson."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
