<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-04-26">Apr. 26, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery: Anders Edward Norman</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Algot E. Strand</title> [Half-tone, 2 by 3 inches, portrait of Norman]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-04-26">Apr. 26, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY: ANDERS EDWARD NORMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Algot E. Strand</title> [Half-tone, 2 by 3 inches, portrait of Norman]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Out in the healthful and speedily growing suburb of Summerdale, situated directly north of the older suburb, Ravenswood, a number of our diligent and prudent compatriots have settled. As to church membership, the great majority of them probably are Lutherans, although a few Methodists and Mission Friends are scattered in between. Until recently, the Lutheran congregation in the neighborhood had led a some what stifled existence in a small, insignificant frame church as a meeting hall. Last year, however, a young, energetic minister by the name of Johnston came, and infused such life into the "dead bones" that it became quite the fashion to belong to his church. The church is now crowded at every service, and the Sunday school is frequented by nearly two hundred children, although one hardly heard the Sunday school mentioned a couple of years ago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1100.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In consequence of the speedy growth in church membership during a brief period of time, the necessity arose of taking steps for a new church building. The new church is to be erected this coming summer, and is to cost $25,000. The undertaking has stirred up so much interest that $4,000 was subscribed at a simple meeting. The members carry subscription lists with them, and we know of Americans who have subscribed $500 each. It appears, therefore, that the church may be built, ready for use, with but a very slight burden of debt.</p>
   <p>An invitation was given to architects to compete for plans to the church, and several of them sent in sketches. Thus, the large firm of H. C. Hallberg submitted two, and one was tendered by the official architect of the Augustana Synod, at Rock Island. This latter architect was specially recommended, being a friend of the minister of the church. But neither high reputation nor friendship won the competition. One of the members of the church submitted a sketch, which was found so far superior to those of the other competitors, both as to <pb facs="5423404_2_1101.jpg" n="3"/>the plan and the decorative features of the exterior that the first two architects simply did not "have any show," as the saying goes. The man who presented this superior plan, and who will be given a chance to execute drawings in detail for the church and supervise its construction is pictured below.</p>
   <p>His name is Anders Edward Norman. He was born on March 12, 1860, in the beautiful town of Holbacken, Vermland, Sweden, where his father, Jonas Norman, was a forester. Already at an early age Anders Edward gave evidence of aptitude for mechanical work, and when sixteen years of age, he entered as an apprentice the Finshyttan's Mechanical Shop to train for pattern maker.</p>
   <p>In the year 1880, the young pattern maker immigrated to America....and decided to make a name for himself here. He had met Miss Wrika Olson from Dalsland, whom he married on June 10, 1882. He obtained a position as foreman in a <pb facs="5423404_2_1102.jpg" n="4"/>cabinetmaker's shop in Ishpeming, Michigan, where he remained for three years. During three successive years, 1884-1887, he won the first prize at the annual industrial exposition for Marquette County. The last of his prize exhibition pieces, which was a wood carving, "Adam and Eve", evoked general admiration for the excellency of its execution.</p>
   <p>During the same period, he was Michigan's champion skater. There were plans to match him with the Norwegian skater, Paulson, but the artist in him won over the sportsman, and after having received first prize for distance skating, a 14 inch high silver bowl, he closed his sports career.</p>
   <p>In 1887, Norman moved to Chicago, starting his own business as architect and builder. Success crowned his efforts from the start; frequently did he do business for over $100,000 per year. A badly chosen place for a large woodwork plant, which he had built, ruined him financially, however. Known to be honest and able, he soon obtained credit for needed material, enabling him to <pb facs="5423404_2_1103.jpg" n="5"/>start anew.</p>
   <p>Last year Mr. Norman sold his house in Summerdale and moved to....Rogers Park. He became an architect for the large real estate firm, Weber &amp; Craute....Annually, this firm builds hundreds of houses to sell, making it practical to employ an architect to do work exclusively for the firm.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Norman is not simply an architect and builder; he is also of artistic and mechanical talent. His artistic nature finds expression in wood carving. The carvings, which he has made, are so exquisitely done that a description cannot do justice to their beauty. The first piece he designated "Adam and Eve", and those who have seen it cannot find words to express their admiration for the ability of Mr. Norman to represent in wood the lines and muscles of the human body true to life as in this piece.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1104.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The second piece is a spider's web, also in wood. Only by seeing this piece is it possible to realize its excellency. The web is as fine as if it were made of hair, and the spider, as well as the imprisoned fly, look so natural that they seem to be alive....For this work, Mr. Norman was awarded a medal at the exposition in California.</p>
   <p>The third carving by Mr. Norman was called by a newspaper "The Eighth Wonder of the World".....It was carved for the exhibition at the World Exposition in Chicago in 1893, and it represents the landing of Columbus in America. In a solid piece of wood, twelve inches high and fourteen inches wide, the artist has made a bowl shaped cut, and in it is seen Columbus, with flag in hand, ready to set foot upon American soil. His companions and a boat are seen in the background....The carving was exhibited in the Swedish pavilion at the World's Fair....</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1105.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The "Landing of Columbus"....was also viewed during the World's Fair by the Spanish princess, Eulalia, and was greatly admired by her.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Norman has decided to leave art to itself and concentrate on architecture ....Hardly was it known that his proposals for a plan for the Ebenezer church in Summerdale had been accepted before he received orders for plans and drawings for a new Swedish Lutheran Church in Cairo, Illinois. We predict that after the first of these churches has been made to stand forth in its full glory this Fall, orders for drawings for churches and elegant residences will be showered upon Mr. Norman. We heartily congratulate him for the gains that will be his.</p>
   <p>In his home life, Mr. Norman is a pleasant and courteous man, only too modest, we think. Frequently, however, the bragging and noisy people are not the ones who contribute most, but rather the quiet, modest ones.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
