<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10,1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10,1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.10.... The results of the Chicago election are printed in a proper place in the newspaper. To reflect upon it would be to repeat what has been said before about the present administration. It could well be worse, but hardly better than it has been; especially now since those concerned have interpreted the result as a vote of confidence in themselves. How far this confidence is evidenced for the Democratic administration, in reality is seen most clearly thru the aldermen's election return. Twenty-two Republicans were elected against thirteen Democrats and a couple of Independents. The great majority of the Republican candidates were approved and supported by the non-partisan political organization, "The Municipal Voters League." This organization exists for the purpose of reducing corruption. The Republicans have the majority. It is a satisfaction to know this.</p>
   <p>Worthy of further notice is the fact that more than one-fourth of those having <pb facs="5423404_2_0138.jpg" n="2"/>the right to vote "stayed home" on election day. The reasons were probably based upon fear of ridicule, as well as differences of opinion relative to mayoralty candidates and the organizations supporting these men. Oddly enough many believed that they were working against the machine by playing into the hands of Harrisons big "boss," Bob Burke, whose nicely instituted organization works quietly but is known to rule both the city and its mayor. When such a gentleman has put his approving" C.K." on the election results it is, of course, correct for every good subject to go along contented and not to mutter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
