<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-06-14">June 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Reform Is Needed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-06-14">June 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A REFORM IS NEEDED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Congress has decided that wealthy individuals with high annual incomes are to pay proportionately higher taxes than persons with low incomes. This will make for a more equitable distribution of the tax burden. It is only proper that the rich be made to pay the greater share. But, strange to say, the rich do not seem to think so, and, in order to avoid taxation, they invest large amounts of money in tax-exempt securities. This practice draws much capital from industry and business, and tends to lengthen periods of business depression and unemployment.</p>
   <p>President Harding realizes the dangers inherent in this kind of legal tax evasion, and has proposed that Congress adopt an amendment to the Constitution prohibiting the issuance of tax-exempt securities. But Congress does not seem inclined to take such a step, and the reason is that our lawmakers know only <pb facs="5423404_2_0331.jpg" n="2"/>too well that the political leaders in the various states, and particularly in the big cities, would resent any limitation upon their right to issue tax-exempt bonds, behind which it is so easy to hide the waste of public money.</p>
   <p>The question is very complicated and unpleasant to handle. And hence it is evaded, although it is evident that only the rich benefit from the situation. They have the right to withdraw their money from the market, put it in tax-free securities, and live in extravagance on the interest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
