<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-08-29">Aug. 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Something Must Be Done</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-08-29">Aug. 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SOMETHING MUST BE DONE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The law passed by Congress for the prupose of preventing child labor in factories and shops was declared unconstitutional by the United States Supreme Court on May 15, 1922, and it will be remembered that this ruling caused considerable consternation throughout the country. But the highest court of the land had spoken, and that seemed to settle the matter, at least for the time being.</p>
   <p>However, the issue will not stay buried. The Children's Bureau of the Department of Labor, under the direction of Grace Abbott, has collected data which show, much better than words could do, that there is urgent need for such a law. Since that fateful ruling by the Supreme Court, the <pb facs="5423404_2_0317.jpg" n="2"/>number of children employed in industry has increased considerably. In the state of Kentucky, a total increase of fifty-seven per cent has taken place, and in the city of Waterbury the increase amounts to eight hundred per cent.</p>
   <p>Supported by these figures, Grace Abbott has now appealed to the proper authorities that the Constitution be amended in such a way that it will become possible for Congress to protect children against exploitation by unscrupulous factory and shop owners. One of the large American dailies has declared editorially that if the children of poor families cannot be properly protected by any other means, such an amendment is in order. But we know from past experience that the amendment procedure takes a long time. The same newspaper suggests, therefore, another plan, which may seem rather drastic, but which, nevertheless, is well worthy of serious consideration. The paper simply asks, "Why not adopt a constitutional amendment which will divest the Supreme Court of the authority to declare null and void a law which has been duly passed by Congress?"</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0318.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The suggestion merits serious consideration, particularly in connection with such legislation as the child labor law. Congress wishes to protect the exploited children, and so does the great majority of Americans. Does not the will of the people mean anything? Laws are supposedly made for the benefit of the people, but sometimes it looks as if the relationship were reversed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
