<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Banker in New Post</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Gustaf Hallbom]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0869</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0869.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN BANKER IN NEW POST</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, picture of Gustaf Hallbom]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It quite often happens that people who in their business or professional life have earned the respect and good will of their fellow men enjoy their greatest popularity as a result of their activities in entirely different fields. This may be said of Gustaf Hallbom, the Swedish-American banker who is well known, not only in Chicago, but throughout the entire country. For in addition to being an able banker, Mr. Hallbom is known among Chicago Swedes as an ardent lover of Swedish song and as a "good fellow" in the best sense of that term.</p>
   <p>It is fitting at this time to recite some of the events in Mr. Hallbom's carcer, for he is now resigning his position as vice-president of the Union Bank of Chicago in order to take over the even more responsible post of president of the Builders and Merchants State Bank, a newly established <pb facs="5423404_2_0870.jpg" n="2"/>Swedish institution which will be located at Clark Street and Foster Avenue in a building which is to be erected during the summer.</p>
   <p>Hallbom has been a North Sider for more than forty years, for when he came to Chicago in 1879 he headed straight for Belmont Avenue and Clark Street.</p>
   <p>His first position here was with the newspaper Hemlandet, and he has ever since retained a certain affection for the men of the press. For the last thirty years, he has been engaged in the banking business, first in the State Bank of Chicago, and later in the Union Bank. He is, undoubtedly, the most widely known Swedish banker in the city.</p>
   <p>However, as indicated above, it is as a lover and promoter of Swedish song that he has really won the hearts of his countrymen here. He has a powerful and melodious tenor voice. Soon after his arrival here he became an active <pb facs="5423404_2_0871.jpg" n="3"/>member of a choir. As one of the leading members of the Swedish Glee Club, he was instrumental in the organization of the Swedish Singers League. He was also a member of the committee in charge of the great song festival at the Columbian Exposition, when Swedish song won its greatest victory on American soil. He was among the promoters of the trip to Sweden made by the Swedish Singers League in 1897.</p>
   <p>In addition to his activities as banker and singer, Mr. Hallbom is a highly valued member of several Swedish organizations and societies here. He is a charter member of the Swedish Club, and is on the Board of Directors of the Swedish Home for the Aged.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hallbom's many friends in and outside of Chicago feel that his long experience as a banker and his excellent personal qualities make him well qualified to head this new Swedish-American enterprise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
