<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Assistance to Farmers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-12-14">Dec. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ASSISTANCE TO FARMERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reduced buying power of the farmers will gradually affect the general price level. The sudden drop in the market value of farm products, amounting to billions of dollars, has discouraged the producers, and no price reduction of machinery, tools, and other manufactured goods that the farmers need, can make up for the losses which they have already suffered.</p>
   <p>We should do everything in our power to come to their aid. It is in the interest of the entire nation that every intelligent proposal be carefully studied. Adequate credit facilities which are economically sound must be extended to the farmers. A system must be evolved whereby these producers are enabled to procure sufficient capital to operate their farms efficiently, and sell their products throughout the year at prices which assure them a <pb facs="5423404_2_0569.jpg" n="2"/>reasonable return on their labor and capital investment. This should be possible if our economic system is sound.</p>
   <p>Words to this effect were spoken by Secretary of Agriculture Wallace at the stock show which took place recently in Chicago, and it is encouraging for farmers and stock breeders to hear such statements from an official who represents the Government, and who already has done so much to make operating capital available for producers, within the limits of sound financial practice. His efforts in behalf of agriculture have been untiring.</p>
   <p>Improvement of sales' methods as well as of methods of distribution is of the greatest importance for both producers and consumers, and the Department of Agriculture is prepared to aid in the introduction of reforms which promise desirable results.</p>
   <p>While Wallace probably does not consider it advisable to discard entirely the present system, he is for abolishing those middlemen whose services <pb facs="5423404_2_0570.jpg" n="3"/>are of no economic value; this is also the attitude of the majority of the producers. Such services constitute an economic waste, no matter who performs them, and the sooner they are done away with, the better for all concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
