<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-30">Nov. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-30">Nov. 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was about sixty years ago that the women's club movement had its inception in this country, though the great federation was not formed until 1889. Later came the various state organizations, of which the first was established in the state of Maine in 1892. The Ohio organization was formed two years later. The federated clubs now have a total membership of about a quarter of a million, and it is estimated that some seventy thousand women belong to independent organizations, outside of the federations.</p>
   <p>If these clubs were merely of a social nature, or were formed for the purpose of promoting only selfish purposes, they would not have survived these threescore difficult years. Such undertakings seldom last long unless they are motivated by unselfishness and high ideals, and it has repeatedly been <pb facs="5423404_2_0507.jpg" n="2"/>demonstrated that these women's organizations are based on high motives and a desire for service. They have been behind most of the social reforms that have been effected during the last generation, and are aiding in the fulfilment of many now pending. Other problems that may become acute five or ten years from now are already under discussion in many women's clubs.</p>
   <p>Not so many years ago it was the fashion to make fun of these organizations, and many professional comedians actually specialized in this type of humor. That time has passed, and there is now every reason to take these activities among women seriously. They rank among the most significant developments in modern times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
