<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-11-29">Nov. 29, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Singers and Musicians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-11-29">Nov. 29, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN SINGERS AND MUSICIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The man from the North is deservedly known for his knightly courtesy and consideration toward the weaker sex, and we felt deeply the seriousness of the situation when we for the first time interviewed a lady singer for this column.</p>
   <p>Many Chicago Swedes know the artist in question, for she makes her home in Chicago and the name Margareta Dahlstrom appears frequently on concert programs here. For more than a decade the bearer of this name has worked here, won recognition as a singer, and become popular both with the public and with her professional colleagues.</p>
   <p>Margareta Dahlstrom was born to Swedish parents in Port Henry, New York, March 9, 1873. She lived in that city until she was twenty years old, when she moved to Chicago. Here she began to study singing under Professor John R. Ortengren at the Chicago Musical College, which is <pb facs="5423404_2_1288.jpg" n="2"/>recognized as one of the world's finest music schools. At the same time she studied harmony and composition under Dr. Louis Falk, and also the Italian language, proficiency in which is so necessary for singers, under Signor Enrico Alfiero.</p>
   <p>After five years of study she received a diploma as a teacher, and graduated a year later, in 1899, from Chicago Musical College. That finished her formal schooling, and she established herself as a singing teacher. As she became better and better known, she began to receive engagements for public appearances, and performed at numerous American as well as Swedish-American concerts; in addition she became more permanently attached to a number of organizations. Among those were the North Chicago Hebrew Congregation Temple where she now has been a soloist for seven years. For a period of time she also sang in the Union Park Church and in the Sixth Presbyterian Church.</p>
   <p>Besides having a large number of private pupils, she also holds a position <pb facs="5423404_2_1289.jpg" n="3"/>as a teacher at Baldtka Musical College.</p>
   <p>Miss Dahlstrom may well be counted among those who have already made their mark. Her beautiful contralto voice and her fine personal qualities have won her numerous admirers and friends among her public, pupils, and colleagues.</p>
   <p>We congratulate her and wish her continued success!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
