<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Legislation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR LEGISLATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>America's workers are surprised and disappointed because President Taft did not voice any concern for them in his message to the Sixty-first Congress, and are asking themselves if he has already forgotten whose votes put him in the White House. They are hoping that he will deal with their problems in a special message, but are, in all probability, due for another disappointment. However, the laboring man does not readily give up, and he is accustomed to fight hard for every inch of gain as far as progressive labor legislation is concerned, even though such legislation is admittedly beneficial, not only to his own class but to the entire nation.</p>
   <p>The workers of Illinois have for many years attempted to put through a so-called "liability law," and strong pressure is being applied during the present session of the legislature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0380.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here are some clauses that should be included in this law: The abolishment of the so-called "fellow servant rule." It should be left to the discretion of the jury to decide what constitutes negligence; to what extent the victim of an accident was at fault; and whether or not he exposed himself to unnecessary risks.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this law should be to provide protection for the worker, and place upon the employer the responsibility of taking certain measures to prevent accidents, and protect the health of his employees. A law of this kind has been the object of controversy for a considerable length of time, and in spite of repeated defeats its supporters are keeping right on fighting, not only in Illinois, but in several other states.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
