<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1928-11-22">November 22, 1928</date><title level="a">Eventually - Why Not Now?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1928-11-22">November 22, 1928</date><title level="a">EVENTUALLY - WHY NOT NOW?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great World War cost the United States one hundred billion dollars, according to a statement the other day by President Coolidge. This information was primarily intended for our friends in Europe, who still maintain that we profited by the war and who now have designs for the reaping of additional harvests.</p>
   <p>The plan, as evolved by them, is to merge into one gigantic loan all the war reparations owed to the various warring nations by Germany and on which that country was to make annual instalment payments. This huge new loan is now graciously being offered America by the victorious allied powers.</p>
   <p>The most remarkable part of this plan, which by most Americans has been branded as an unreasonable and impudent act, in reality is not altogether infeasible. It would not be a bad thing for our internationally inclined bankers, who naturally would reap millions of dollars in commissions on a deal of this kind. Already their mouths are watering, we are sure.</p>
   <p>After all we are not in the least surprised to hear this news. It has often been said that America would have to pay for the World War. Perhaps this is just, inasmuch as we had no business to be in it. At any rate we hope that this will serve as a lesson - until the next time. Since we have so much money, perhaps it would not be entirely out of place to spend a few hundred million dollars for our own defense. Preparedness is a safe investment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
