<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The State Legislature</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE STATE LEGISLATURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6.... The state legislature at Springfield intends to adjourn the first of May. However, on its roster at the present moment, it has for consideration a matter of great importance. The congressional redistricting of the state is being debated. But the consideration of the matter has progressed slowly to date, although we are assured that the final vote will be cast today, Wednesday. The measure would have been decided long ago, however, if our Chicago Representatives had not opposed the measure and allowed personal motivations and ambitions to enter into the matter. We wish to state that this is further disagreeable to think about since we know that the Republican legislators have agreed.</p>
   <p>Another weighty matter, which is unfinished legislatively speaking is the question of a change in the constitution. This change has to do with administrative reforms and includes the city of Chicago. Sherman's <pb facs="5423404_2_0458.jpg" n="2"/>motion for a revision of the constitution has not been completed. The Civic Federation of Chicago has sent in proposals for changes, these concern: 1. Centralization of the Town-Administrations, 2. Enlargement of Community Loan Privileges, as well as 3. necessary reforms within the lower courts, (justice shops). Special proposals regarding these points will eventually come to pass.</p>
   <p>Sherman's motion appears to have been stranded because of the indifference of the Representatives from the country districts regardless of Chicago's screaming need. The Civic Federation would not disregard the old custom of not amending more than one article in the constitution each legislative session, though this in all probability will finally be declared legal. A method of overcoming this dilemma would be to avoid the paragraph against "special legislation." This would enable the legislature to have a free hand when the facts are presented concerning the needs of the larger cities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0459.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Time is short, as we have said, and one can hardly expect any resolution worthy of mention now. But if it is to be at all, it must be done soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
