<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-07-27">July 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Promotion of World Peace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-07-27">July 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROMOTION OF WORLD PEACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Butler of Columbia University, a very active friend of peace, recently concluded one of his speeches with a Latin saying which, freely translated, means that if you want peace, you should prepare for peace. The more one thinks about it, the more one becomes convinced of the profound truth of this maxim.</p>
   <p>We are often told that in time of peace it is wise to be prepared for war. But we are inclined to believe that the dark clouds of war on the world horizon would brighten considerably if nations would spend only half as much for the maintenance of peace as they do for war preparations. If England and Germany, for instance, would make a sincere attempt at rapprochement, and declare their willingness to make sacrifices in order to adjust their disagreements and promote mutual interests, it might come to pass that the building of more and bigger and better <pb facs="5423404_2_0269.jpg" n="2"/>dreadnaughts would become unnecessary.</p>
   <p>It is doubtful whether the United States is doing all that the nation is capable of doing to bring about world peace. We are in a favorable position. Without becoming embroiled in their quarrels we can point out to the other nations of the world the folly of war and the desirability of peace. But we cannot convincingly propound the blessings of peace, and at the same time work overtime constructing battleships and other instruments of destruction. For it is getting so that when one power launches a man-of-war the others feel it necessary to build two, regardless of how big a navy they already have.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
