<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-30">Aug. 30, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery Charles F. Ogren</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-08-30">Aug. 30, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY CHARLES F. OGREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Years ago, Swedish-Americans used to complain because the thirst-quenching nonalcoholic beverages which they became accustomed to in the old country could not be obtained here. For regardless of what kind of upbringing he may have had, a Swede's stomach is so constituted that he cannot enjoy drinking ice water or coffee with his meals. Both these beverages have a harmful effect on the digestive process and should not be taken at mealtime.</p>
   <p>[Charles Fredrik] Ogren noticed these complaints, and began to manufacture and sell Swedish soft drinks, but it soon became clear that neither teetotalers nor those that worship Bacchus cared much for them, and Ogren lost money on the undertaking. His first factory was located at Division and Wood Streets and was established in 1884.</p>
   <p>However, he did not become too discouraged, but decided that if the customers <pb facs="5423404_2_1071.jpg" n="2"/>did not like the soft drinks he would give them something stronger, but still nonalcoholic.</p>
   <p>When Ogren decides to do something, action follows immediately. He bought a number of building lots on Shober Street, the name of which was later changed to North Irving Avenue, and built quite a large factory, which during the years, has expanded steadily until it now is the largest Swedish-owned establishment for the manufacture of soft drinks and nonalcoholic malt drinks in this country.</p>
   <p>Needless to say, only the finest raw materials are good enough for Ogren; he uses no substitute ingredients, and his products are beneficial to health and well-being.</p>
   <p>In that section of the plant called The Liquid Food and Tonic Department, "Ogren's Pepsinated Hopcream," "Malt Cream," "Dr. Agnew's Hop Tonic," "Honey Beer," "Ogren's Gothenburg Porter" and "Ogren's Stout and Beef Tonic" are made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1072.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These products ought to be placed on the counter of every drugstore, so that the public might learn about their health-giving qualities. For ages, doctors have known that beverages prepared from pure malt and hops are excellent for building up the system.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ogren also manufactures a variety of ordinary soft drinks, also of fine quality. As to the popularity of his products, it is sufficient to mention that they are the only ones used at the Swedish National League's picnics and similar occasions.</p>
   <p>Charles Fredrik Ogren was born in Dalsland, Sweden, on November 24, 1847; his parents were farmers. He came to America in 1881, and first went to Michigan, but soon moved to Chicago. Here he worked for some time as a carpenter foreman, and little by little began to take small building contracts on his own account. As already mentioned, he began manufacturing soft drinks in 1884. The firm's name is now Chas. F. Ogren and Company, and its plant is located at 625-629 North Irving Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1073.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He married Christina Nilson, his splendid wife, in 1872, before he left Sweden, and the union has been blessed with six children, of whom five are now living. The three boys are all employed in their father's business.</p>
   <p>As an example of Ogren's remarkable energy and industry, it may be noted that last year he completed a full course as a brewing master at the American Brewing Academy and received his diploma. Such a course requires considerable study and application, for a brewing master must understand thoroughly the chemical processes involved in brewing and many other technical problems. But it was comparatively easy for Ogren, thanks to his previous practical experience, which dates back to his youth in Sweden.</p>
   <p>Being a born hustler and almost always busy, Mr. Ogren has not had much time for the social side of life, but he does enjoy his membership in the Odd Fellow Order and the Swedish Glee Club. Best of all, he likes to have his friends come to his home, which is noted for its informal and genuine hospitality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
