<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-07-26">July 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Farmer Has Changed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-07-26">July 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE FARMER HAS CHANGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When rural mail service was first introduced it was considered merely an experiment, but now some three billion postal items are distributed annually in the country districts. Forty-one thousand rural mail carriers are engaged in this service, and its cost to the Government amounts to thirty-six million dollars annually. The rural mail service was a great boon to our farm population, and was later followed by the telephone and various new types of transportation services. The farmer thus became less isolated; in fact his entire existence underwent a revolutionary change in the course of only a few years.</p>
   <p>The time has passed when his only source of news was the small-town weekly, and when he has had to drive a long distance to get his mail and do his shopping. Now he has a telephone in his house, his mail is delivered on <pb facs="5423404_2_0589.jpg" n="2"/>schedule, and he subscribes to a metropolitan daily newspaper. He ships his products by train, and it is easy for him and is family to seek the pleasures and entertainment offered by the nearest town.</p>
   <p>This change is most noticeable to those who remember the old order. And what an improvement it is!</p>
   <p>Only a few years ago, when a farmer appeared on a city street he was conspicuous by his clothing, behaviour and language, and anybody could tell that he was from the country. But today, a farmer in the city on business, cannot readily be distinguished from the ordinary city-dweller, lawyer, doctor,businessman, clerk or mechanic. He is predominantly a businessman, and enjoys the good things of life to an extent which was impossible when he was isolated on the farm, often miles from his nearest neighbor.</p>
   <p>The city man and the man who tills the land have been brought closer together. The latter has learned that the other can be a fine fellow and the former has <pb facs="5423404_2_0590.jpg" n="3"/>come to respect the term "farmer" and understand what it really stands for. Both parties realize that they supplement and need each other, and that it is to their mutual interest to meet each other half-way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
