<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-15">Sept. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Physician of Swedish Ancestry</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. August Anderson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-15">Sept. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Physician of Swedish Ancestry</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. August Anderson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As reported last week, Dr. August Anderson, lieutenant in the medical corps, has just returned home, after three weeks' service on the gunboat "Wilmette". This ship is attached to the school of navigation at the Great Lakes Naval Station, and is used as a training ship for the naval reserves.</p>
   <p>Dr. Anderson saw service aboard many of the navy's ships during the war, and remained in active service until 1919. At the present time he belongs to the naval medical reserve corps. He is in private practice, and maintains offices in the Calo Building, 5412 North Clark Street.</p>
   <p>Dr. Anderson was born in Chicago, April 22, 1881, and was educated in the public schools of this city in preparation for his professional career. At the out-break <pb facs="5423404_2_0704.jpg" n="2"/>of the Spanish-American War he enlisted as a private in Company E of the First Illinois Infantry Regiment, and took part in the Santiago campaign.</p>
   <p>After the war we find Anderson in the Government's railroad mail service, where he remained until 1910, when he resigned in order to take up the study of medicine. In 1914 he graduated from the Hahnemann Medical College in Chicago. After graduation he did special work in the Chicago Union Hospital in order to improve his knowledge of his chosen profession.</p>
   <p>At the outbreak of the World War, he placed himself and his medical ability at the disposal of the Government, and he was appointed a lieutenant in the naval medical corps.</p>
   <p>In his private practice Dr. Anderson specializes in diseases of the chest. He is on the clinical as well as on the teaching staff of the Chicago Polyclinic Medical Center, and is chiefly occupied with tubercular cases. It is of interest to note that during the summer of 1916 Dr. Anderson served as physician at</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0705.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Daily News Sanitarium in Lincoln Park.</p>
   <p>Dr. Anderson is actively interested in American Legion work, and belongs to Navy Post No. 372. He is a member of the Evangelical Immaculata Lutheran Church, and lives at 6610 Newgard Avenue, Rogers Park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
