<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1908-02-01">Feb. 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Lingon Berries to United States from Sweden</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0981</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0981.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1908-02-01">Feb. 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">LINGON BERRIES TO UNITED STATES FROM SWEDEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lingon Company in Sweden is planning to open a branch office in America. S. J. Swensson, the president and founder of the company was received by King Gustav in Stockholm recently. The king was very much interested in the business of the company; he told Mr. Swensson, in fact, the king's father was a big stockholder in the company and King Gustav intend to take over his father's stocks there. Then Mr. Swensson told the king about the company's plans to extend its business to America. Sugar being much cheaper in the United States than in Sweden, it would therefore, be good business to export the raw material from Sweden to America, and to make the berries ready here for sale.</p>
   <p>The king asked Mr. Swensson to forward a royal thanks to the Swedes in America for their hospitality to his son, Prince Wilhelm, when he was visiting America last year. It is Mr. Swensson's intention to visit <pb facs="5423404_2_0982.jpg" n="2"/>New York, Worchester, Boston, Chicago, St. Louis and Minneapolis, and probably other cities in the far west. He has the hope that the "red gold" from the Swedish Forests soon will be known and appreciated in America, because "there isn't a finer and fresher fruit of its kind," he said to a newspaper man, who interviewed him in Stockholm, shortly after his visit to the king.</p>
   <p>(Swedish Lingonberries are similar to the American cranberries. The translators note.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
