<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-30">Oct. 30, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A Straightforward Speech</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-10-30">Oct. 30, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A STRAIGHTFORWARD SPEECH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A noteworthy address was delivered by Alexander Legge, chairman of the Federal Farm Commission, before the great industrial congress which was held last week here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In discussing the present plight of our agriculture, Mr. Legge stated that it is not at all surprising that the farm population is more inclined than other groups to embrace doctrines which, in capitalistic circles, are termed radical. And he further declared that, if the farmers do not soon receive the assistance to which they are entitled, they will take another step to the left and become really radical.</p>
   <p>The congress in question had been called jointly by the University of Chicago, the Institute of American Meat Packers, and a score of business <pb facs="5423404_2_0534.jpg" n="2"/>organizations, for the purpose of bringing together the leaders of American business and industry.</p>
   <p>Legge spoke at the banquet which was given last Wednesday night in the Palmer House, and his words attracted more attention than anything else that was said during the entire meet, notwithstanding the fact that a number of our industrial and financial bigwigs also had their say at the congress. The banquet was attended by more than nine hundred prominent businessmen and manufacturers.</p>
   <p>As an introduction, Legge reminded his audience of the reprimand which the Farm Commission is said to have received from certain senators in Washington, and which he himself seemed to take lightly. But he then went on to say that it should not cause any surprise to see the farmers join the radical bloc, and that effectial assistance is the only measure which can prevent such a step. If nothing is done, we may expect to witness the appearance of a much more extreme radicalism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0535.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The speaker pointed out the most evident causes of the distressing situation in which our farmers now find themselves. While the authorities have been busy encouraging other industries, agriculture has been forgotten. That this is so is clearly demonstrated by statistical tables. They show that, out of seventeen billion dollars which have been appropriated, donated, and spent for the promotion of trade and industry, and for the benefit of industrial workers during the last few years, agriculture has received one billion dollars. If a farmer wants to benefit from such expenditures he had better move to the city.</p>
   <p>Another reason for agriculture's present predicament, according to Legge, is the farmer's highly developed individualism, too highly developed for his own good. He fails to see that the salvation of himself and his group lies in co-operation. While other workers and producers have formed strong organizations, by means of which they have managed to improve their status, the farmers have been operating separately, and therefore been unable to determine the prices of their own products.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0536.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Legge gave a few concrete examples of what co-operation can do for the farmers. In St. Paul, for instance, the retail price of milk is two cents lower per quart than it is in Chicago, but nevertheless,farmers in the St. Paul district get more for their milk than do farmers who depend on the Chicago market.</p>
   <p>The gist of the address was that a more intimate co-operation among the farmers themselves, and also between agriculture and other industries is highly desirable. The speaker declared that the bill which is now pending in Congress calls for no privileges for the farmer which are not already enjoyed by other industries and industrial workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
