<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-10-25">October 25, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">A Paradise Close to Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1177</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1177.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-10-25">October 25, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">A PARADISE CLOSE TO CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL. The Swedish Tribune, Chicago, reprints an editorial from the Chicago Evening Journal concerning Mr. P.S. Peterson's Nursery at Rosehill. </p>
   <p>The author of this article took recently a trip north and came to a real paradise in the heart of Jefferson Township - Mr. P.S. Peterson's Nursery at Rosehill, which grand place is located not fully eight miles from the city. Lincoln Avenue goes through this glorious nursery and is a short distance from Mr. Peterson's magnificient home.</p>
   <p>The nursery consists of 365 acres and its owner has with care and intelligence taken care of its expansion during a quarter of a century.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1178.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The property, surrounded by tall trees and beautified with grass lawns, flower-beds and bushes, is an ideal of comfort, as well as a charming country home.</p>
   <p>Many of the large shade trees have been moved from other places to Rosehill by Mr. Peterson himself, and he is as attached to each one of them as if they were his own children.</p>
   <p>The oldest and tallest of all the trees is a stately elm. "This" - said Mr. Peterson, pointing with pride at the tree - "is George Washington, and this," pointing at another large elm, "is Abraham Lincoln, and this is General Sherman and there is General Grant."</p>
   <p>Mr. Peterson has millions of trees on his farm and he knows each type by sight. Most of these trees of all dimensions and types are planted in long rows and assume the appearance of large armies, regiments, brigades, and divisions. There are elms, maples, birches, ash, lark, chesnut, mulberry, and wild cherry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1179.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In other words, every conceivable type of tree that can be grown in this latitude is ready to be re-planted. Many of them are imported from Europe and other parts of the world. Flowers, many of rare and exotic beauty, are found in abundance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peterson has one of the largest and finest collections of trees, bushes, and flowers in the entire West, as well as a pleasant home.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peterson keeps more than twenty-five horses, and has one of the finest stables in the State of Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
