<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-24">Aug. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Justice for Workers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-08-24">Aug. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">JUSTICE FOR WORKERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is customary among corporations and individual employers to discharge faithful elderly workers on the grounds that they are old and worn out, and that the business is in need of younger blood. It is only natural that this practice produces bitter feelings among its victims.</p>
   <p>As a rule, no provisions are made, in the form of pensions or other security, which would enable these unfortunate people to face their declining years with courage and hope, and without fear of complete destitution. On the contrary, it is often said of such and such an old discharged employee that "he received fair wages, but did not save anything, and it is, therefore, his own fault if he now has nothing to fall back on".</p>
   <p>The situation is too serious to be dismissed with such a hard-boiled statement. It offers no solution, and is just as unsatisfactory as if an employer were <pb facs="5423404_2_0363.jpg" n="2"/>to say of a worker who had been crippled for life in an accident on the job, "It is too bad, but the accident was not caused by any negligence on my part". In the case of the old worker, he has given the employer a lifetime of work, and the disabled worker may have given one or more of his limbs or have suffered some other incapacitating injury. Their employers certainly owe them something more than their bare wages. After they have used, and benefited from, their productive capacity, they have no right to throw them aside as one throws away a worn out pair of shoes. Both the injured worker and the one dismissed on account of age are entitled to security.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
