<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-03-20">Mar. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Uneven Distribution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-03-20">Mar. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">UNEVEN DISTRIBUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This country is so rich that everybody could live in comfort, and nobody would have to go through life in poverty if our wealth were more evenly distributed. But, unfortunately, it is in the hands of a select few. The Federal Trade Commission has just released statistics which show that no less than fifty-nine per cent of all the wealth in the country is owned by one per cent of the population, and thirteen per cent of our total population owns ninety per cent of the wealth, leaving one tenth of it for the remaining eighty-seven per cent of the people.</p>
   <p>These eighty-seven per cent comprise the workers and the great middle class. The latter consists of farmers, skilled workers, owners of small businesses, professional people, teachers, professors, etc. These people lead in the <pb facs="5423404_2_0303.jpg" n="2"/>intellectual and cultural field, and make up the nucleus of our national stock. They represent all branches of our political, social, and religious activities. But they receive only a small part of the nation's riches, which, after all, is the fruit of their labors.</p>
   <p>What is left when the few excessively wealthy people have taken theirs is just enough to provide a bare living for all the rest, a large number of whom live in actual want. America is the richest country in the world, and if our wealth were more evenly distributed, prosperity and well-being could be enjoyed by everybody.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
