<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-13">Nov. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Equal Taxation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(For Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter, by Plebs)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-11-13">Nov. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">EQUAL TAXATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(FOR SVENSKA TRIBUNEN-NYHETER, by PLEBS)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The smaller fellow should not carry the heavy end of the burden, and neither should the poor man pay more taxes than his wealthy fellow-citizen. This seems so self-evident that there is hardly room for argument. Nevertheless, the laws here in our free America are so formulated as to bring about precisely this condition in regard to taxation. We pay all our taxes to the Federal Government in the form of import duties. Thus, if I buy a dollar's worth of sugar, I pay forty cents to the government and actually receive sixty cents' worth of sugar. That is if the sugar is imported from a foreign country; in the case of domestically produced sugar, I pay the forty cents to the sugar trust, and the government does not benefit from the transaction.</p>
   <p>So it is with most of our necessities. Of all those commodities which we consume to any large extent, coffee is the only one on which we do not pay import duty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0394.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A worker earning five hundred dollars a year may pay as much as fifty dollars out of this income in taxes to the government, while a multimillionaire earning five million dollars a year cannot possibly pay proportionately as much in import duty, inasmuch as he cannot consume one thousand times as much as the worker in question; if he did, his tax would be half a million dollars.</p>
   <p>It is also a well-known fact that large estates are not being assessed, in proportion, as highly as the small ones. Therefore, the people of small means are required to contribute from five to ten times as much toward the support of their government as the rich ones. This is the actual situation even though many do not realize it.</p>
   <p>Of course, it is unjust, but how may a more just condition be brought about? Easier said than done! The Federal Government must have revenue in order to carry on its functions, and up to now import duties have been its only <pb facs="5423404_2_0395.jpg" n="3"/>source of such revenue. But it certainly ought to be possible to work out a more just system of taxation than the one which is now in force. There is no sense in forcing the poor man to pay twice as much tax, in proportion, as the rich one, not to mention paying actually many times as much, as under present conditions.</p>
   <p>From time to time I have commented on the labor question, and it seems to me that it would be very much in order for the country's workers to take up the fight for a revamping of our tax system.</p>
   <p>I understand that the Swedish government also collects import duties, but not to such an extent as is done here. Income below a certain limit is tax exempt. In this country the introduction of a tax on income would undoubtedly be a step in the right direction. Under such a provision, the man with a five-hundred-dollar income would pay a certain percentage of it in taxes, and the millionaire would pay the same percentage out of his five-million-dollar income, and even if the worker's five hundred dollars should be exempt from taxation, no great injustice would be done. Chances are <pb facs="5423404_2_0396.jpg" n="4"/>that the latter would have a greater number of future citizens to support than the rich man. Even at that, the advantage would be on the side of the millionaire, for one thousand such workers might bring up two thousand future citizens, which would be impossible for any single person to do, even if his income alone were larger than theirs combined. And certainly, the bringing up of the country's children is by far the most indispensable contribution to its future well-being.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, I admit that it is no easy task to rectify this existing injustice. My chief purpose is to call attention to the problem, and it is to be hoped that a solution will be found in the not too distant future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
