<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-09-21">Sept. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Notable Swedish Businessman of Chicago</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Carl Max Hedman]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0925</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0925.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-09-21">Sept. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Notable Swedish Businessman of Chicago</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Carl Max Hedman]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many successful Swedish businessmen in Chicago, and today we give you one of them--the well-known manufacturer Carl Max Hedman, president of the Hedman Manufacturing Company.</p>
   <p>He was born November 18, 1862 in Nederkalix, Sweden, where his father was a customs officer. After having attended all the schools available in that town, young Max went to Stockholm, where he learned the instrument maker's trade.</p>
   <p>In 1884 he left the Swedish capital, and went to Copenhagen, Denmark, where he was employed by the Great Nordic Telegraph Company. He also worked with Professor Jorgensen, who taught him how to make special instruments used for astronomical observations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0926.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But even though Max is not such a big fellow himself, he felt that Copenhagen was too small for him, so he decided to go to America. He came directly to Chicago, arriving with two empty hands which were, however, eminently suited for instrument making. He also brought with him a goodly supply of high spirits, a fine singing voice, and a good head, and with this equipment he began his career in America. His first job was with the Knapp Electric Company. Later on he worked for the Western Electric Company, and still later he became a foreman with the American Electric Company.</p>
   <p>During this time he made many friends, thanks to his sunny disposition and excellent voice. He was in demand everywhere. He became a member of the Swedish Glee Club, the leading Swedish singing society at that time, and he was also much in demand for lovers' roles in the then existing Swedish Theater Company. Many of us remember him as "Eric" in "The Varmlanders" and as "Passepartout" in "Around the World in Eighty Days;" his portrayal of many other characters also lingers in our memories. He was considered the best Swedish amateur actor in Chicago at that time. The theater company <pb facs="5423404_2_0927.jpg" n="3"/>traveled about the country a good deal, and Hedman always went along on these jaunts. He thus acquired a large circle of friends and admirers outside of the city. Wherever he went everybody liked "Little Maxie," the pet name by which he is still known among his friends. </p>
   <p>In 1889 Hedman went to work for the Stromberg Carlson Telephone Company, of this city, in its experimental laboratory, and won one promotion after the other, until he, in 1902, became general superintendent of the entire plant. That same year he left the firm, and together with a Norwegian, Johnson, established the Johnson &amp; Hedman Manufacturing Company, which specialized in dental instruments. They designed many new instruments, and the undertaking was a success from the beginning. In 1913 the firm was dissolved. Hedman bought out his partner, and began to manufacture a check protecting device, the "F &amp; E Check Writer," which is now being sold all over the civilized world. In the same year he organized a new company, for the purpose of going into mass production of the article,with himself as president, and his son, Herbert R. Hedman, a graudate of the engineering school of the <pb facs="5423404_2_0928.jpg" n="4"/>University of Illinois, as secretary. The factory, an up-to-date and quite large plant, is located at 227 West Erie Street, and business is good, thank you.</p>
   <p>Hedman married Ragnhild Forsmark of Stockholm in 1886, and the family lives at 1330 Winnemac Avenue. Besides the son, Herbert, mentioned above, there is also a girl, Grace.</p>
   <p>Hedman is a Free mason, and also a member of the Swedish Engineering Society and the Chicago Association of Commerce. He himself thinks that he is getting old now, but nobody agrees with him on that. He still has that sunny disposition, which is just as contagious as ever, and his stimulating company is still sought by young and old alike. We suspect that he has discovered that much talked-of fountain of youth. Of course, like anybody else, he has known sorrow and discouragement, but these he has taken in his stride.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0929.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In 1897 he was among the Swedish-American singers who visited Sweden, and in 1912 he again visited the homeland with his family, at the same time taking in the Olympic games.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
