<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-01">Sept. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-01">Sept. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Nebraska Farmers' Union, the great association of farmers has just been incorporated under the laws of the state. The organization is said to have forty thousand shareholders, and to be made up of fifteen hundred local associations. It owns three hundred grain silos, fifty merchandising establishments, three creameries, and two flour mills.</p>
   <p>In the bylaws of the organization, provisions are made for paying a dividend of eight per cent of the annual profit. The profit remaining is to be divided among the owners, in proportion to their interest in the undertaking.</p>
   <p>This great farmers' union is based on the principle of co-operation, and if it is given the right kind of leadership, it should be successful. The main idea is through co-operation the farmers will be able to enjoy the fruits of their <pb facs="5423404_2_0580.jpg" n="2"/>own toil, and, also, to protect their common interests.</p>
   <p>The secondary, but also, very important consideration is that through such an organization, the farmer may eliminate the many middlemen who are the chief cause of the often unreasonably high prices which the consumer must pay for farm products.</p>
   <p>An ideal situation would exist if the producer and the consumer could deal directly with each other. Such a condition is not easily obtained, particularly in the large cities, but it is a goal toward which we should work. In most cases the middleman is a parasite, who is trying to live off of others, without making any productive contribution towards the well-being of the community. Such individuals should not be allowed to live by their wits, but should be forced to go to work.</p>
   <p>In order to lower the present high cost of living, it is necessary that we first <pb facs="5423404_2_0581.jpg" n="3"/>remove these parasites from the social body.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
