<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-23">Oct. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Workers and Postal Savings Banks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-10-23">Oct. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS AND POSTAL SAVINGS BANKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of all civilized countries the United States is the only one which does not have postal savings banks. It is not hard to find the reason for this. It is the influence of the financial kings on our government and Congress that has hindered the establishment of such banks.</p>
   <p>The working class, especially, should put forth every effort to force the Federal Government to establish such banks without undue delay. They should also strongly advocate changes in laws regarding other savings banks so that the depositors would be adequately protected. The Stensland Bank is the latest and best example of a bank with no protection for the laborer's savings. The failure of this bank caused more deaths from shock, and suicides than has ever happened before in a bank crash.</p>
   <p>Often the factory worker cannot invest his savings in real estate. The <pb facs="5423404_2_0398.jpg" n="2"/>factory may be shut down unexpectedly and the savings are as lost as though they were lost in a bank failure. If the worker has his own home, the employer can (and often has) take advantage of this by closing down, making it necessary for the laborer to go elsewhere to earn his living, and then the worker will find no one who is in a position to buy the house or the equity in it.</p>
   <p>If the worker has his savings deposited with the government the money is safe; no matter where he is forced to move, he has the right to withdraw his money as he may need it. If there is an argument regarding rate of wages he can move wherever he pleases, and he does not lose one cent.</p>
   <p>Insurance companies have also done their utmost to oppose the establishment of the postal savings banks. Their pet argument was to suggest the advantages of endowment policies. The recent insurance scandals have shown where a poor man's money goes.</p>
   <p>The postal savings bank will be a real help to the really poor man, as it <pb facs="5423404_2_0399.jpg" n="3"/>permits him to open an account to which he may add deposits as small as ten cents and up at a time. The pennies make the dollar and in time the total amount saved is often somewhat surprising.</p>
   <p>The French postal savings banks are shown by statistics to be the greatest help that the poor workers have had the good fortune to obtain.</p>
   <p>My opinion is that the establishment of postal savings banks in the United States will be impossible unless the matter becomes a political issue. The strongest argument in favor of the banks will be the fight put up against them by our big bankers and other money magnates.</p>
   <p>The farmers, united with the populists, made a determined effort to bring about the reorganization of our banking system but the Bank Syndicate was too strong.</p>
   <p>The present prosperity may make many think that the postal savings bank is <pb facs="5423404_2_0400.jpg" n="4"/>unnecessary and useless but history repeats itself; when a depression occurs again, the millions lost by the working class will be many, which they can ill afford to lose, while if the money were in the hands of our government not a cent of loss would be sustained by the poor man. Further discussion on this subject will appear in a future issue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
