<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-06-01">June 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">For Prospective Farmers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-06-01">June 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">FOR PROSPECTIVE FARMERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very interesting and instructive pamphlet entitled Where Shall I Go? has recently been published by Henning Landahl of Little Falls, Minnesota, who will mail it free of charge to anybody who writes and asks for it.</p>
   <p>The pamphlet discusses farm conditions not only in Minnesota but in other parts of America as well, and should be of value to anyone who is planning to go in for farming. It is clear that the author knows what he is writing about.</p>
   <p>In the final chapter he gives some advice which we quote:</p>
   <p>"While I am on the subject of virgin land I will take the opportunity to say to those of my countrymen who are planning to purchase such land: Preserve your ready cash! If you are young and have nobody but yourself to take care of, it would be wise for you to buy virgin land, or land which has been only partially improved. It is not necessary that there be buildings on it. Put money into it gradually, and keep in mind the time when you may no longer be single; <pb facs="5423404_2_0611.jpg" n="2"/>then you and your wife together can plan permanent buildings.</p>
   <p>"If you already have a family--in the country, the larger it is the better--and only a few hundred dollars in cash, do not buy a farm which is already well cultivated and which has new, good buildings on it. You will only get yourself into debt and have a hard time getting out of it. Build yourself whatever may be needed or,even better, repair the old buildings if there are any. Do most of the work yourself, even though this may call for hardships and sacrifices. Particularly in central Minnesota, building materials are reasonably priced, and you should add to your buildings little by little. In most cases neighbors will be glad to help you, and sooner or later you will have an opportunity to reciprocate. Remember that it is important for your future to keep the debt burden and interest charges down. When I drive through one of these state's many Swedish settlements,I often see standing next to the new,modern barn, the primitive hut, now used for a sheep shed, which the farmer built for himself in the early days of the farm. My advice to the young man who is planning to start in today is that he do likewise."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
