<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-12-07">Dec. 7, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Right Road</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-12-07">Dec. 7, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE RIGHT ROAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From Ottawa, the capital of Canada, comes a report that a member of the Parliament has introduced a resolution urging that the Government start negotiations with the American Government for the purpose of concluding a reciprocal trade treaty between the two countries. He pointed out that in these critical times friendly co-operation between neighbor nations is more necessary than ever before, and declared that a treaty based on the principle of reciprocity would greatly benefit both nations.</p>
   <p>We agree with the Canadian statesman, and we are convinced that the sooner the proposed negotiations get under way the better for us as well as for our neighbors to the north. Economists all over the world agree that the high tariff walls which many nations have erected, presumably for their own protection, are among the main reasons why the present economic crisis has <pb facs="5423404_2_0466.jpg" n="2"/>become so severe and so long lasting. Many people place the blame on America, and we are not without guilt. The tariff law which the Republicans managed to push through the Congress undoubtedly caused many other nations to erect similar trade barriers. Such barriers must be lowered and international trade facilitated before the current depression can be lifted and normal times return.</p>
   <p>The Democratic party, which formerly advocated free trade, is now in power. Its attitude toward free trade has changed considerably of late but even so, its traders are not committed to the high tariff system and should be open-minded enough to listen to the voice from Ottawa. It is certain that much would be won by a reciprocity treaty between Canada and the United States. During Theodore Roosevelt's administration we had such treaties with several countries, and then we had good times in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
