<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-20">Oct. 20, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery: Anton Wilhelm Johanson</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Algot E. Strand</title> [Half-tone, 11/2 by 2 inches, profile of Johanson]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-20">Oct. 20, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY: ANTON WILHELM JOHANSON</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Algot E. Strand</title> [Half-tone, 11/2 by 2 inches, profile of Johanson]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anton Wilhelm Johanson was born in....Stockholm County, Sweden, on March 5, 1861. When he completed the course of study of the grammar school in the district in which he was born, he was apprenticed to the noted watchmaker, Mr. F. W. Tornberg, Stockholm. In the latter's shop watches were actually made, so that the boy Johanson had an excellent opportunity to learn the trade. During his period of apprenticeship, Johanson also attended the vocational school. This served him in good stead in his future work.</p>
   <p>After having finished his apprenticeship, Johanson, who at this time had become of age, immigrated to America in May, 1882. He obtained a position <pb facs="5423404_2_1123.jpg" n="2"/>with a Swedish watchmaker in Jersey City, New Jersey. A few months later, he left for Chicago and obtained a position with the firm of C. D. Peacock, where he remained for a year and a half. He was then offered a position as foreman at a watch factory in Baraboo, Wisconsin.....In 1891 he became a partner in the wholesale jewelry firm of M. S. Fleishman and Company.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Johanson started a jewelry business at 270 [No.] Wells Street in the year 1895, several of his friends thought that the location was not very suitable for that kind of business. But in addition to being a man of virtually inexhaustible energy, Mr. Johanson also possesses...great perseverance and singleness of purpose. He has always dealt with his customers in an honest and friendly manner, convinced that conducting his business in this way, it would not matter so much where his business was located. Anyone who visits his elegant place of business will admit that he was right.</p>
   <p>Although Mr. Johanson is widely known among the public and especially among <pb facs="5423404_2_1124.jpg" n="3"/>the Swedes in Chicago, he is, perhaps, even better known among watchmakers in all parts of the United States and in Europe. The reason for this is to be found in the fact that Mr. Johanson has invented and marketed a considerable variety of watchmakers' tools. A list of these tools would fill a small catalogue.</p>
   <p>In his store is still to be seen the model constructed by Mr. Johanson for a tower which he suggested for the World's Fair in Chicago, and which was to have exceeded all other buildings in height. It would have cost three million dollars. The tower was not erected, however, but Mr. Johanson received much praise from the directors of the exhibition, both for the great idea and for the beautiful model.</p>
   <p>In 1892 Mr. Johanson was elected judge of the Horological Society, a position which he still holds. He is the only Swede who has ever held a post of this <pb facs="5423404_2_1125.jpg" n="4"/>nature. The task of the judge is to render a decision regarding [the merit of] watchmakers' work which has been submitted and to grant diplomas [certificates of merit].</p>
   <p>In his social life as well as in his business life Mr. Johanson is a cheerful and pleasant person, whose acquaintance one is happy to make.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
