<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-16">Feb. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[Accidents on the Erie Railroad]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-02-16">Feb. 16, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[ACCIDENTS ON THE ERIE RAILROAD]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The blame for the many railroad accidents in this country is generally placed on the railroad companies; the companies have only one thought in mind: to earn money. What do the railroad companies care if some thousands of people are being knocked down, crippled, or killed at crossings and in collisions? The railroads throw the blame for these accidents upon the men employed by the roads. Thus they claim that this or that engineer was not careful enough, that he was driving at too great a speed. But nothing is said about the fact that if the engineer had slowed down and had not arrived at his destination at the appointed hour, he might have been discharged.</p>
   <p>The traffic manager of the Erie railroad, however, has surprised the American people by the assertion that "the greatest cause of all the irregularities which have recently occasioned complaints against the railroad is the lack of properly trained and capable workers," and he adds that he would like to hire a thousand men competent to do the work assigned them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0645.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is possible that the railroad in question has men in its employ who are not well-qualified for their work, but if so, the blame is with the railroad. The men who built the railroads and the locomotives certainly must know how to keep both the roadbed and the rolling stock in proper repair. Nine tenths of all railroad accidents could undoubtedly be avoided if the railroads could be prevailed upon to give their engineers, their conductors, and their switchmen a somewhat shorter working day.</p>
   <p>It may happen, of course, that an engineer, a conductor, or a station inspector may be unforgivably remiss in his duties, and is therefore responsible for a railroad collision, but this remissness could hardly be occasioned by lack of training on the part of the employee in question.</p>
   <p>It may be that there are machinists in our country that are better trained <pb facs="5423404_2_0646.jpg" n="3"/>than those who serve as engineers on the railroad, although we doubt it; but the engineers in service cannot be held responsible for the railroad's failure to hire these superior men. Here again, the blame must be placed upon the railroad management, which has not taken sufficient care in its selection of workers. We dare say that the traffic manager of the Erie railroad would not need to go about--lantern in hand--looking for capable and trained workers, if only he would turn to the large machine shops in his own state of Pennsylvania, where so many thousands of faithful and capable Swedes are employed. There he would have no difficulty in engaging the one thousand competent men of whom he claims his railroad is in need. If he would then arrange to pay decent wages and, in addition, reduce working hours so that the men would not become weary and drowsy--as a result of prolonged sleeplessness and nervous strain--and therefore remiss in the performance of their work, he would then find that the number of accidents on the Erie railroad would be considerably reduced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
