<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-07-19">July 19, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Farming Versus American</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-07-19">July 19, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH FARMING VERSUS AMERICAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Tribune, Chicago, reprints a very interesting editorial, taken from Skaraborgs Lans Hush,Tidning,Sweden. The author of this article writes:</p>
   <p>An American who understands American farming has written an interesting article comparing American and Swedish farming methods.</p>
   <p>The Swede is not as practical as the American. The former works harder, but the latter produces more because he estimates with greater caution the careful use of his own time as well as that of his workers. He uses and tries to get the most modern farm implements and inventions at all times. New inventions are readily accepted by the American farmer regardless of the size or amount of his farming interests. On the other hand, while in Sweden, education is a means of determining agrarian class or rank, this is hardly true or characteristic of American farm society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The educated Swedish farmer is far in advance of his American brother theoretically, but the latter is a better business man and knows how to conserve his time and use it more profitably. The American farmer is both wise and industrious. If the less fortunate cannot afford to own farm machines, he rents them. All his tools, even the simplest ones, are up to date. He does not eat too much. The Swedish farmers and their hired workers eat five meals a day in some parts of Sweden, and during harvest time six. The American eats only three times a day, and does not taste brandy when he is working. He is not lazy, even though left without an overseer; and he is always respected. Lazy workers in Sweden are often industrious workers when they come to America; and their social status is better, too. On the other hand, the educated Swedish farmer has a kind, democratic attitude toward the working class, or more definitely those whom he employs.</p>
   <p>Nationalistic rivalry is becoming more and more intense and apparent, but it cannot be led exclusively by the educated class; the masses must participate, and that nation, where the people are most prepared to participate <pb facs="5423404_2_0620.jpg" n="3"/>for the common good, will advance more rapidly. The Swedes and other European countries are too clannish, and that prevents both material and intellectual prosperity. The American soon, however, evidences a decided desire for acquisition of education and refinements of living and manner. It is not the material standing of the American worker that prevents Socialism from getting a foothold in America, but it is his improved social condition, which acts as a preventive. If the difference in rank had been less in Europe; if the worker there had been socially thrown together with the educated classes, and thus had become more informed, the social movements now endangering many lands, would not be prevalent. It is a mistake to think that the American worker is more restricted than the European. The American master gives short and precise orders, and fires at once lazy and disobedient servants. Carelessness is unknown in America, and has added towards creating a better working class.</p>
   <p>The wife of the American farmer is busier and more industrious than one imagines.. She does not, however, work as hard as her European sisters of the same class. She does not care for the cattle, nor carry firewood, coal and water. She is a model of a real mistress. The practical arrangements in kitchen and pantry and the time-saving machines which lighten her work are unknown in the homes of the Swedish workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0621.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The American is not only practical in making arrangements in his house; and in the treatment of his servants, and in caring for his farm business; but also in the choice of plants he intends to cultivate. Swamps and water-covered areas, which in Sweden are looked upon as worthless for cultivation, are sowed, in Massachusetts and New Jersey, with cranberries, which gives ten times as large profit as some grown on the best of soil.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that in Sweden the great abundance of berries and berry crops, such as cranberries, loganberries, blue-berries, raspberries, and many others - are not made to contribute to her marketable goods because it would undoubtedly amount to several millions annually.</p>
   <p>The cooperation between the American farmers and merchants - two classes, whose interests are usually very selfish in motivation in our country -has been good and has had the best of results. The American merchant notifies the farmer what products are most in demand on the market, and how they should be handled and packed for export. These merchants understand thoroughly that they can import merchandise only, if their customers, make way for the farmer's products on the world's market. There are many companies and societies in America where scientific men, merchants, and farmers, work and cooperate together in unity and with success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0622.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Our farm societies," says the author in conclusion of his editorial, "should, as a result, give us better farm products. America can teach us much concerning the way of 'self-help,' which makes the people strong and independent."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
