<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-11-16">Nov. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Svithiod Singing Club Passes Half Century Mark</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-11-16">Nov. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">SVITHIOD SINGING CLUB PASSES HALF CENTURY MARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Svithiod Singing Club observed the fiftieth anniversary of its founding last Saturday night with a festive banquet in the clubhouse on Wrightwood Avenue.</p>
   <p>The club was founded in 1882, and of the fifteen charter members two are still living. They are Axel Back and Axel Blomfeldt. Its original name was the Svithiod Choir, but in 1893 the organization was incorporated under the name of the Svithiod Singing Club.</p>
   <p>During the first years of its existence the choir was partly supported by the Svithiod order, but this support was withdrawn in 1891, and since then the singers have been standing on their own feet.</p>
   <p>At the time the Choir was incorporated John L. Swenson became its director <pb facs="5423404_2_1557.jpg" n="2"/>and it reached its peak under his leadership. On January 11, 1896, it competed in an international singing contest in the Auditorium. The group was awarded first prize, a silver trophy with the inscription "Champion Singers of Chicago." In 1906, Swenson was succeeded by John R. Ortengren, and among the later directors may be mentioned N. B. Emanuel, John S. Meck, Joel Mossberg, Edgar Nelson, and Gustaf Carlson.</p>
   <p>The banquet was a spirited affair with much singing, speech making, and good fellowship. Dancing continued well into the small hours of the morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
