<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-08">Sept. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Businessman Active in Swedish Societies</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Ernst Lindskog].

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0904</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0904.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-09-08">Sept. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Businessman Active in Swedish Societies</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Ernst Lindskog].
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a previous issue of this newspaper we reported that Ernst Lindskog, insurance man and real-estate broker, had become the head of the savings department of the Union Bank.</p>
   <p>Although still a young man and a comparative newcomer to Chicago, Mr. Lindskog has been here long enough to impress everyone who knows him with his insight and judgment in business matters, and his great capacity for work. What he has already accomplished is a good indication of what may be expected of him in the future. This is the reason why we selected him as the subject of the week's "In the Foreground" article. <!-- 5423404_2_0903 omitted, duplicate of 5423404_2_0904 --></p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0905.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lindskog was born April 20, 1885, in the city of Ystad in southern Skane, where his mother still lives. In 1902, at the age of 17, he decided, as so many young Swedes have done, to try his luck in the New World. He went first to the state of Iowa, but three years later we find him in Chicago, and this city has been his home ever since.</p>
   <p>Lindskog is particularly well known in the Swedish districts of Lake View, Edgewater, and Summerdale, where most of his business in insurance and real estate has been developed.</p>
   <p>He is a member of Brage Lodge of the Independent Order of Vikings, Ring Lodge of the Independent Order of Svithiod, and the Orpheus Club. He joined Brage Lodge in 1906, and is now regarded as its leader. Few, if any of Brage's thirteen hundred members are better known by name or by appearance than Lindskog. For the last seven years he has served as financial secretary of the Lodge, and he is also on the Executive Committee of the Order.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0906.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>While a member of the singing society, Orpheus Club, Lindskog served for many years as financial secretary of the western division of the Swedish Singers' League of America.</p>
   <p>In 1909 Lindskog married Elin Person, who was also born in Ystad. The union has been blessed with two children, both girls. The family lives at 5309 North Paulina Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
