<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-25">July 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Bellman Concert at Riverview Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-07-25">July 25, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">BELLMAN CONCERT AT RIVERVIEW PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nearly ten thousand people attended the concert given on Sunday in Riverview Park in honor of the great conductor, Carl Michael Bellman.</p>
   <p>Once more the various singing societies presented us with a unique play and a rare musical enjoyment. Great enthusiasm, conviction, and sincerity were evidenced in the singing. The repertoire offered caught the interest; it held a far more powerful immediate appeal than the music in which foreign competitors seem to find such great pleasure.</p>
   <p>The greater part of the numbers sung lie very close to the popular inspiration; <pb facs="5423404_2_1704.jpg" n="2"/>they possess all the immediacy and fragrance of the latter, and it causes no surprise to find that several among them, for example, several of Bellman's songs, become almost as popular as if they had sprung from the people. These compositions present us with a true picture of the nature and musical soul of the Swedish people, and this fact is probably in part the reason for the very unusual attention with which the crowd followed the concert. Bellman chants especially were sung with idyllic sentiment.</p>
   <p>The Grand Chorus gave a magnificent example of highly developed musical art. It is almost impossible to sing with greater unity, correctness, and precision, and at the same time, with greater sincerity, freshness, and courage. No <pb facs="5423404_2_1705.jpg" n="3"/>unnecessary nuances or vocal effects were necessary. A splendid measured power, not excluding the softer strains, but free from sentimentality; manly, honest, and simple; songs sung in a way to awaken enthusiasm, and move to tears. The singers are amateurs who sing because they love singing, not professionals looking for applause; but these amateurs sing as well as if they were professionals.</p>
   <p>The applause which burst forth even after the first number continued throughout the concert, and resulted in a number of encores, first "Hor oss Svea,".... and in closing, "America."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
