<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-26">Nov. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Artists Hold Annual Exhibit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-26">Nov. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH ARTISTS HOLD ANNUAL EXHIBIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Artists' Society opened its annual art show last Saturday night in the Edgewater Beach Hotel. The program included speeches, music, and song. Many people attended the opening, and there was a general agreement that this year's exhibit offers much interest, and compares favorably with those of previous years.</p>
   <p>The president of the Society, Einar Soderwall, introduced the Swedish vice-consul, G. Bernhard Anderson, who delivered a brief address in which he dwelt upon the role of art in society, and then declared the exhibit opened. A number of popular Swedish performers entertained the audience with songs and music. Later in the evening Congressman Carl R. Chindblom arrived, and delivered a speech in which he complimented the Swedish-American artists on their accomplishments.</p>
   <p>The exhibit comprises more than ninety numbers, of which about twenty are <pb facs="5423404_2_1349.jpg" n="2"/>sculptures. There are only a few portraits, and among them we noted particularly "My Father," by Akina A. Hallbom, and "Mr. W," by Axel Linus, the latter pictures the work of none other than the well-known artist, Axel Westerlind, who is also taking part in this exhibit.</p>
   <p>Landscapes are in the majority, and among the painters in this group we noted G. Ahlman, Thomas Hall, Charles J. Bergstrom, Asgurd and Elizabeth Goranson, A. Hessel, Helga Hessel, Alfred Jansson, Webster Kullberg, Ellen Larson, Axel Linus, Martin Lundgren, Carl Olson, Signe Palmblad, Florence M. Ruden, and Carl Wallin.</p>
   <p>Ahlman is represented by a painting with the Indiana dunes as its motif, and it is excellent. Asgurd Goranson's "In the Woods" is also outstanding. Signe Palmblad exhibits two charming Swedish landscapes. Wallin's three canvases are <pb facs="5423404_2_1350.jpg" n="3"/>characterized by artistic imagination, and they attract much attention, as his work always does.</p>
   <p>Einar Soderwall and Frithiof N. Spolander exhibit three marine paintings each, and Mary C. Peterson is represented by two still life canvases. Her separate exhibit in the Illinois Women's Athletic Club, which we reviewed last week, is still open.</p>
   <p>Six sculptors are taking part in the exhibit. They are Peter Anderson and Frank Gustafson, who are represented by six pieces each, and Hallsthammar, Herman Cederblad, Dr. Axel W. Akesson, and Rudy Renzius. Peter Anderson is a newcomer to this annual show and seems to possess considerable talent. In our opinion Gustafson's bust of Hjalmar Nilsson and his "Billy" are the best pieces in this group.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1351.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We wish to confess that this review is based on the hurried observations which we made on the opening night, when the large crowd and the various features of the program made it difficult to concentrate on the work. The review is, therefore, not all that it should be.</p>
   <p>The exhibit closes November 30.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
