<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-12-11">Dec. 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">An Interview with a Leading Swedish Importer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0983</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0983.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-12-11">Dec. 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTERVIEW WITH A LEADING SWEDISH IMPORTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ambition and love of hard work are qualities certainly not lacking in our well-known countryman Mr. Axel Johanson, who came to Chicago nineteen years ago and soon became recognized as a leader within the Swedish-American business world. More than ten years ago he established the Swedish Produce Company, which firm is now well known all over America. His greatest ambition has been to introduce and develop a market for Swedish products here in his adopted land, and many Swedish manufacturers and merchants have, through him, found a profitable outlet in this country.</p>
   <p>Last summer Mr. Johanson sold the Swedish Produce Company and, accompanied by his family, took a trip to Europe for the chief purpose of visiting Sweden, where he was born, in the province of Smaland, on Christmas eve, 1867.</p>
   <p>As already mentioned, Mr. Johanson's business is to sell Swedish products <pb facs="5423404_2_0984.jpg" n="2"/>here, particularly such as have not heretofore been imported, and during his recent trip he naturally took the opportunity to establish connections with various Swedish firms, which he now represents and whose products he is placing on the American market. Among the better known houses whose representative he is are the Drags Company of Norrkoping, which makes woolens of unexcelled quality; Klara, stearin candle manufacturing company, of Stockholm; and Carlsten's Porter Brewery, also of Stockholm. He will also handle the genuine Eskilstuna steel products. This trade-mark has been shamefully misused by foreign manufacturers, who have applied it to goods manufactured outside of Eskilstuna, and it is going to be too bad from now on for those that Mr. Johanson catches practicing that kind of piracy.</p>
   <p>We venture to prophesy that the future will see more Swedish merchandise in America, thanks to Axel Johanson's able leadership. More power to him!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
