<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-17">Nov. 17, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">"The Life of the Warrior Is So Glorious"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-11-17">Nov. 17, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">"THE LIFE OF THE WARRIOR IS SO GLORIOUS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One may yet hear someone singing that old ditty about the glorious life of the soldier, about the honor of dying in battle for one's country, and one's people, etc., but if one reads the news coming from the more militaristic countries, one may get a glimpse of the true nature of this glorious life. Germany beholds its best sons mistreated and sometimes killed by Army officers. In Sweden, we see the bloom of the population going westward to America in order to escape this glorious life.</p>
   <p>In the United States, military life seems to be embraced with a kind of love which is akin to disdain. The adventurous young man, to whom the blue uniform and the brass buttons appeal, may enlist in a moment of intoxication; he swears to the colors and receives his uniform. Then he awakens from his dreams of military bliss, and the bare facts are facing him. His fine blue jacket is <pb facs="5423404_2_0278.jpg" n="2"/>a prison coat; his spurs are the blacks of the chain gang; his whole uniform is an oppressive yoke. Beware, boys of the shining misery!</p>
   <p>The Army report of the United States of October 15, 1903 reveals that of America's standing Army of 58,000 men, 29,279 applied for discharge, or else deserted; 5,034 soldiers, or one in every ten has deserted. When one considers the punishment awaiting the deserter, if and when he is caught by the authorities, then one realizes that the life of a soldier must be something of a Hell, since he is willing to take the chance of years in prison rather than remain in the Army.</p>
   <p>Beware of the shining misery, boys!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
