<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-21">Apr. 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Workers Are Slighted by Some Judges</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-21">Apr. 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">WORKERS ARE SLIGHTED BY SOME JUDGES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From our earliest childhood, we have been told that "work enables the worker." In Sweden, some facts do not always seem to justify the saying, and many have been inclined to discern a greater gulf between employer and employed in Sweden than in America.</p>
   <p>On coming to this country, many of us imagined that no gulf existed between the workers and their employers here; that the class difference was practically non-existent, and equality was the word; no master, no servant.</p>
   <p>Many are yet holding to this opinion, and perhaps he is the happier who can keep this belief.</p>
   <p>Now and again, however, even he who has been most strongly immured in the belief <pb facs="5423404_2_0130.jpg" n="2"/>that equality is the watchword in America, is pulled forcibly out of his happy dream and made to face stark reality. In the latter part of the past week, labor and the laborers were dealt a blow in the face by one of the judges in Chicago--a blow which, in time, we hope will rebound with doubled force upon the man who dealt it.</p>
   <p>Judge Neely, of the Chicago courts, is the man who showed his "respect" for the workers by declaring that a certain branch of labor is not respectable. A man, who is a driver for a laundry in the city, was before the court accused of having stolen a coat. The accused pleaded guilty. On being informed that the accused was employed by a laundry, the Judge insulted not only the man before the court, but all those who are employed in similar work. Addressing the accused man, Judge Neely said: "No wonder, then that you are a thief.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0131.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Any man who goes about gathering dirty articles of wearing apparel belonging to other people may be expected to steal; it is natural for him to do so. Why don't you get a respectable job? If you find some other kind of a job, I shall acquit you."</p>
   <p>A more despicable attack, a more shameful insult against a class of wage earners has probably never been made by a judge. Judge Neely is evidently incompetent. He finds that one out of a thousand, perhaps, has gone wrong, and so he undertakes to accuse every laundry driver of being a thief, and stamps the laundry driver's job as non-respectable. He even goes so far in his hatred of the laundry workers that he declares himself willing to break his judge's oath, and acquit the thief if the latter promises to seek a different kind of a job.</p>
   <p>The work of the laundry driver is as honorable as that of the judge, and equally <pb facs="5423404_2_0132.jpg" n="4"/>necessary as that of the latter, but not quite as degrading, morally. Judge Neely's clothing, too, need to be laundered, and even though he, himself, might undertake to wash his dirty linen between sessions in court, this would by no means give him the right to insult those whose work is to launder the clothing of others.</p>
   <p>In his declaration to the defendant laundry driver, Judge Neely has also declared that he is not an impartial judge, but he has proven himself an enemy of an honest occupation. He has declared himself a person unworthy to pass judgment on the acts of others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
