<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-04-27">Apr. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Mrs. Palmblad's Exhibit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-04-27">Apr. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MRS. PALMBLAD'S EXHIBIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of Signe Palmblad's separate exhibit in Bryden's Galleries, 318 South Michigan Avenue, was attended by a large number of art patrons, most of whom were native Americans.</p>
   <p>The exhibit hall was decorated in Swedish colors and two girls in Swedish national costumes served refreshments. The promising young soprano, Theresia Lind, also dressed in a becoming national costume, rendered a number of songs which seemed to make a big hit with the audience. It is quite possible that Miss Lind's appearance on this occasion may lead to more important engagements. There were people in the audience who are influential in American art circles and they were very favorably impressed by the young singer's performance.</p>
   <p>The exhibit consists of oil paintings and a number of illustrations of <pb facs="5423404_2_1333.jpg" n="2"/>national costumes from various provinces of Sweden. The noted sculptor, Carl Hallsthammar, helped to arrange it, and it has received much favorable comment.</p>
   <p>The president of the Illinois Society of Fine Arts welcomed the visitors in a brief speech, and characterized the exhibit as unique and very interesting. Mrs. A. J. Pohlman, vice-president of the Illinois Federation of Women's Clubs, and Mrs Ivon Wakeman, president of the North End Austin Women's Club also spoke and complimented Mrs. Palmblad on her work. They pointed out that her artistic accomplishments are so much more remarkable since she did not begin to paint until she was forty-nine years old.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
