<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-27">Oct. 27, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Portrait Gallery Iii.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gustaf Lindell by Algot E. Strand [Half--tone, 11/2"x 2"]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-10-27">Oct. 27, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN PORTRAIT GALLERY III.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Gustaf Lindell by Algot E. Strand [Half--tone, 11/2"x 2"]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gustaf Lindell was born in beautiful Vermland, Sweden, November 9, 1864....His parents, Lars and Maria Larson, were farmers.</p>
   <p>While in grammar school, the boy showed considerable promise, and after having finished, he was permitted by his father to attend the continuation school in the district. There he also won high praise from his teachers.</p>
   <p>In April, 1887, Mr. Lindell caught the American fever...and in May of the same year he arrived in Chicago, where he obtained a job as carpenter. In February, 1890, he obtained a contract to build a house...and since <pb facs="5423404_2_1120.jpg" n="2"/>then he has erected hundreds of buildings, some of them dwellings, some of them buildings for other purposes.....</p>
   <p>The following are a few of the buildings which Mr. Lindell has erected: For the University of Chicago Settlement at Gross and Ashland Avenues, a gymnasium for the Morgan Park Academy; a club house for Edgewater Saddle samp; Cycle Club; club house for Exmore Golf Club, Highland Park... Mr. Lindell, as a builder, has won the confidence of the trustees of the Lehman's estate. At present, he is busy erecting Hotel Granada for this estate, at Ohio and Rush Streets.</p>
   <p>In 1897, Mr. Lindell married Miss Maria Olson.... They have a daughter, three years old.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lindell has been recording secretary for the society Iduna, and is a member of the Carpenter Builders' Association.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1121.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Upon meeting Mr. Lindell, one realizes that he is in possession of a considerable amount of concentrated force, mental and physical. But he is no boaster. He has won friends everywhere by his jovial ways and his honesty of character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
