<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-10-04">Oct. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Popular Will and Direct Primaries</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-10-04">Oct. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE POPULAR WILL AND DIRECT PRIMARIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In political circles it is conceded that the sentiment in favor of direct primary elections is gaining momentum, and many observers predict that within a comparatively short time legislation providing for such primaries will be in force throughout the country. It is significant that opponents of this highly desirable reform do not now come out openly against it, but are working under cover trying to bemuddle the issue, and preparing so many loopholes that the primary law, when it is enacted, will be ineffective.</p>
   <p>Before the election one did not hear much of the "insurgents" in Michigan. They did not have such energetic and outstanding leaders as had Indiana, Iowa, Wisconsin, Kansas, and California, but when the votes were counted it appeared that they had taken the state. This result was undoubtedly due to the direct <pb facs="5423404_2_0472.jpg" n="2"/>primary elections. If the voters had not had this opportunity to express their will, Senator Burrow, the standpatter, would have been re-elected, and the state would now also have a governor which it did not want. This is a fine demonstration of the beneficial effects of primary elections.</p>
   <p>The opponents of the direct primary and of initiative and referendum are missing the mark when they talk about preserving our "historical and constitutional representative system of government," and such popular phrases should not be permitted to unduly impress anybody. What those people really want is to preserve a form of government which is not representative. If they are so strongly committed to representative government why are they afraid of letting the people express its will directly?</p>
   <p>When ex-President Roosevelt declared that the Constitution should be interpreted in the light of present-day conditions and needs, his conservative critics raised a howl as if he had desecrated something holy for which our ancestors gave their blood. The fact is that only a small minority had anything to do with <pb facs="5423404_2_0473.jpg" n="3"/>the formulation of the Constitution, and an even smaller number entertained any enthusiasm about it. When it was adopted there were about one-third as many voters in the entire country as there now are in the city of Chicago. In every state the privilege of voting was limited to those who owned property, and in 1879 the number of qualified voters in this country amounted to 120,000. It is quite likely that if a popular franchise had been in operation at that time the Constitution would have been voted down. It took a vigorous campaign, which lasted for one whole year, to get it ratified by the state of New York, and then with a majority of only two votes. It finally became the basic law of the country by the decision of fewer voters than there now are in three or four wards in any of our large cities. The Constitution is in many respects a great document, but when one considers the circumstances surrounding its creation there is nothing holy about it.</p>
   <p>The people speak through the direct primary elections, and the true friend of the people is not afraid of a procedure which facilitates the expression of the popular will.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
