<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-05">Apr. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Forty-Hour Work Week</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-05">Apr. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A FORTY-HOUR WORK WEEK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Henry Ford is undoubtedly one of the most dangerous opponents of the exploitation system, and when one reads the publications which favor this system one can readily see that he is as much liked among the general run of big industrialists as a white crow in a flock of black crows. Ford, who has more ready cash at his disposal than any other person in the world, not only advocates the abolishment of the present monetary system, but is also trying to make life more pleasant and more worth living for his workers by paying them more than he really has to.</p>
   <p>About a week ago, his son, Edsel Ford, who is now the president of the Ford Motor Company, announced that a forty-hour work week is to be the standard in all <pb facs="5423404_2_0335.jpg" n="2"/>the company's plants, and that, as a result of this innovation, it will become necessary to hire an additional three thousand men. The new schedule affects some fifty thousand workers, none of whom receives less than six dollars a day. But the three thousand unemployed who will now go to work will start in at five dollars per day.</p>
   <p>Spokesmen for the company point out that this change is in line with the managements' desire to make it possible for the workers to spend more time at home with their families, and to provide for them an opportunity for more rest and recreation, in addition to more steady employment. The fact that the company will now be able to employ three thousand more men is, of course, another important consideration.</p>
   <p>Henry Ford believes that every man needs more than one day a week for rest and recreation, and he understands how important it is for the worker to <pb facs="5423404_2_0336.jpg" n="3"/>lead a happy home life, and to spend the time when he is off from work in a pleasant manner. He believes he should spend as much time as possible with his family and in working around the home, and also that there should be time for reading and self-education. He realizes that ideal conditions are still far off, but considers it quite likely that the administrative departments may soon be able to introduce the forty-hour week, so that the white-collar workers may also enjoy two days off each week.</p>
   <p>Nobody should think that this is done as an act of charity. Mr. Ford himself will certainly not be the loser. The workers are paid only for the time they put in on the job, and those to be added to the payroll will start in at a lower pay. The most important feature is the acceptance, in principle, of the forty-hour work week by the Ford Company, while industry in general is fighting stubbornly to preserve the antiquated forty-eight hour week. By his stand on this question, Mr. Ford has widened and deepened the chasm which for a long time has separated him from his fellows in big business and industry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
