<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-04-14">Apr. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">In the Foreground</title><title level="a" type="sub">One of Chicago's Swedish Dentists</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. Nils Tuveson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0708</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0708.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-04-14">Apr. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE FOREGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">One of Chicago's Swedish Dentists</title> [Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, full-face picture of Dr. Nils Tuveson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The subject of this week's foreground article is a man who has shown that he possesses more than usual ambition, energy, and ability, and who may well be held up as an example for young Swedes who come to America with empty hands and a strong desire to make good.</p>
   <p>An immigrant who manages to gain the required command of the language, take up the study of dentistry, and graduate from an American dental school, all within the space of five years, must have something. And Dr. Nils Tuveson evidently had it.</p>
   <p>Dr. Tuveson was born in Helsingborg, Sweden, April 10, 1885. His father was <pb facs="5423404_2_0709.jpg" n="2"/>Ola Tuveson, a businessman. In 1906 young Tuveson embarked for America and came to Chicago. He had no definite plans for the future at that time, but he certainly did not want to go idle. He soon found a fairly well-paying job. Gradually the idea took hold of him that it would be a fine thing for him to become a dentist. No sooner had he reached the decision than he set out to realize his ambition, and within a short time we find him a student in the School of Dentistry of Northwestern University. The years passed, and in 1911 Tuveson graduated. After having worked for some time as an assistant instructor at the University, he opened his own office at 5333 North Clark Street, and has now built up an extensive practice.</p>
   <p>Dr. Tuveson is a member of the National Dental Society, the Illinois State Dental Society, and the Chicago Dental Society. He also belongs to the Swedish Club as well as several other Swedish and American organizations.</p>
   <p>In 1914 he made a trip to Sweden, and he tells us that he is now planning another visit to the old country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
