<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-12-10">Dec. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Song Concert by Madame Norelli</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-12-10">Dec. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SONG CONCERT BY MADAME NORELLI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day for the Concert of the Swedish Singers Society in the Chicago Auditorium draws near. Only three days remain before it will take place. Sunday is the day. The large choir is ready for its presentation, and Prof. Ortengren promises that it will be proud of itself. The drawing power at this concert will be Madame Jennie Norelli, the celebrated singer, who is on the way to win world renown. She is not only known in the United States and Sweden, but also in England and France, where she has made a name for herself as a singer of renown. She has been accorded worthy praise by England's Press, particularly on one occasion when she played the role of "Gilda" in "Rigoletto" for Madame Melba, who was ill. She played this <pb facs="5423404_2_1680.jpg" n="2"/>difficult part in such a splendid way as to win the acclaim of the audience. London had not heard anyone other than Madame Melba sing this part up to that time, and it was, therefore, real bravery on the part of our compatriot that with only a few hours rehearsal, she played this difficult role. But luck was with the brave, and it won here. She received praise, even though the odds were against her. Now she will sing for the Chicago Swedish critics next Sunday. She will surely sing her way into their hearts, and perhaps more able to do so than those who do not hail from the same country from which she comes.</p>
   <p>Madame Norelli, or Norelius, her Swedish name, was born in Norrland, Sweden. She studied first under Ivar Hallstrom, at the Royal Swedish Academy of Music in Stockholm, and afterward with that master, Dene Sedie, in Paris. She also <pb facs="5423404_2_1681.jpg" n="3"/>studied in Milan, Berlin, and London. Her debut was made in the Play "Taken Away," from the Royal Opera in Stockholm.</p>
   <p>She was for a time "Prima Donna" with the Metropolitan Opera Company and shared the honors with Madame Sembrich, Caruso, Plancon, and Reczke.</p>
   <p>The concert at the Auditorium promises to be unusually good, and the proceeds will go toward helping defray expenses of the trip the Elite Choir is to make to Sweden in 1910.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
