<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-12-09">Dec. 9, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Artists Open Exhibit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-12-09">Dec. 9, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH ARTISTS OPEN EXHIBIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The art society, Swedish Artists, which has now been in existence for five years, opened its fourth annual exhibit last Saturday in the Edgewater Beach Hotel A large number of people were present, and the society's president, Gotthilf Ahlman, was in charge of the opening program.</p>
   <p>The exhibit comprises eighty-three numbers and is well arranged. The society has taken the occasion to honor the memory of one of its members who passed away during the past year, the noted landscape painter, Alfred Jansson. Seven of his canvases have been placed apart and are grouped around a portrait of the artist which was painted years ago by Arvid Nyholm. It is worth noting that two of Jansson's paintings have already been sold.</p>
   <p>Thirty-four artists are taking part in the show. The majority are old timers but there are also a few new names.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are not many portraits, but a few of them deserve more detailed comment than can be given here. We noted particularly Frank Carlson's "Industrious," a portrait of a young girl occupied with embroidering. The delicate face and striking light effects are remarkable, and the work reminds us of Arvid Nyholm's art. Carlson also exhibits a summer landscape with motif from "Ostergotland, Sweden, also a noteworthy painting. Mary C. Peterson exhibits two portraits of which "Jessolyn M" is the better.Carl Olsen's portrait of the sculptor Hallsthammar is very good.</p>
   <p>Gotthilf Ahlman, president of the society, is represented by two oil paintings and one aquarelle, and Thomas Hall also exhibits both oil paintings and aquarelles. His "North Shore" is done in ultra modern style, and is different from anything that we have previously seen by this artist. Signe Palmblad exhibits three oil paintings and Martin Lundgren has two.</p>
   <p>In the group of etchings we noted the works of Anne Anderson, Hugo Westerberg, and P. Anderson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1339.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The sculpture group is not large, containing only twelve numbers, but they attract much attention and deserve it. P. Anderson's "The Death of Socrates" is a plaque in wood and a very fine piece of work, but the lighting arrangement in the room fails to do it justice.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately time and space do not permit us to review this exhibit as it should be done. We suggest that our readers go and see it for themselves. It closes next Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
