<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-01-12">Jan. 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Are the Churches Immune to Fire?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-01-12">Jan. 12, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">ARE THE CHURCHES IMMUNE TO FIRE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the terrible theater fire in Chicago, Mayor Harrison has ordered the closing of all the theaters in Chicago, as well as the large and small auditoriums and dance halls, pending a thorough investigation of their fitness as public assembly halls. It seems probable that this investigation will lead to the permanent closing of most of the dance halls. Some of the theaters may suffer the same fate.</p>
   <p>The investigation has even been extended to include the hotels and also those many business places which are called department stores. But the investigation does not include all public buildings; the churches have been exempted. It would seem as though the officials in our city believed that God would hold His protective hand especially over those wooden and brick buildings on the roof or facade of which a cross is placed. Or do the authorities believe that the pain is less intense when people are suffocated, or trampled upon, or burned to death in a <pb facs="5423404_2_0658.jpg" n="2"/>church than [when they suffer the same fate] in a theater? Most churches in Chicago are worse <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> than the theaters. Fow of the former have more than one exit, and the windows either are usually placed too high to be reached from the floor or else are made of glass of much strength that a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>  be needed to break them. Those of our fellow citizens who visit our churches are not calmer or more <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the face of danger than those who attend the theaters--rather the opposite [is true]. If a fire <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to break out in a church, it is quite certain that the children of God would <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> just as <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> down the feebler ones in their <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> be in would be in case a theater were to catch fire, exposing the children of this world to danger and death.</p>
   <p>Why are not the churches also being closed until the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> has taken place? <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> very <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that our board of alderman <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> be fearful of a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> increase in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in Chicago if the churches were to be closed for two weeks or for as long a period as the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> would require.</p>
   <p>The <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> criticism of our mayor and board of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for laxity in the inspection of the destroyed theater as well as other places of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> came from <pb facs="5423404_2_0659.jpg" n="3"/>the pulpits. From those places, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of wrath were loosed, and lightning bolts of censure were <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> at the mayor and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> board. From the pulpits, the officials were condemned before the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>Many of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> were standing in crowded buildings that are worse firetraps than the Iroquois Theater and are less fireproof than most of the dance halls--yet there they stood, hurling their bolts of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> at the heads of the city officials.</p>
   <p>Let us suppose that the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and other objects used in decorating the Christmas tree at some Sunday <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Testival were to catch fire..a match has been dropped on the floor <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> being stepped on. Then the judge in the pulpit would grow silent, the prayers on the lips of the faithful would cease,..and the fear of death would take hold [of everyone], <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and commonsense action, and awakening the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> brutality in the breasts of the stronger ones. And the next day, the he<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> would carry the story of the terrible <pb facs="5423404_2_0660.jpg" n="4"/><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in which people were <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the fire at the----church.</p>
   <p>The churches have <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the theaters do not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> they <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> not pay taxes. For this reason, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the city <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> far <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> justified in closing the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> than in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, if the city government has reason to believe that the churches are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
