<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-12-18">Dec. 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Leon Lundmark Reaps New Laurels</title><title level="a" type="sub">Known as Lake Superior's Painter</title> [Half-tone, one column, fifth of a page, picture of Leon Lundmark.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_1363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_1363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-12-18">Dec. 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">LEON LUNDMARK REAPS NEW LAURELS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Known as Lake Superior's Painter</title> [Half-tone, one column, fifth of a page, picture of Leon Lundmark.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As our readers already know, the marine painter Leon Lundmark was awarded first prize in the oil painting group at the recent Scandinavian art exhibit in the Illinois Women's Athletic Club. This was by no means the first time Lundmark has won such distinction. His artistic standing has been well established for many years now, and his canvases may be found in art museums, in private collections, and also adorning the walls of learned institutions, both in this country and in Europe. Wherever he takes part in an exhibit his works always are among those which attract most attention.</p>
   <p>He takes most of his motifs from the North Sea, the Atlantic between Maine and New York, and from the Great Lakes, but, above all, from Lake Superior, whose varying moods he knows as nobody else, and which he can reproduce on the canvas in a masterly manner. That may be the main reason why he enjoys special popularity <pb facs="5423404_2_1364.jpg" n="2"/>in the state of Michigan. How much they think of him there was demonstrated recently, when the city of Marquette observed the fiftieth anniversary of the founding of the Peter White Library. On that occasion a special Lundmark exhibit containing some sixty of his paintings was arranged, and the artist himself was invited as guest of honor at the festivities.</p>
   <p>Besides being a painter, Lundmark is also a lecturer and a teacher of art. As late as last Sunday he lectured in the Allen Art Gallery, 645 North Michigan Avenue, on the topic "Art in America".</p>
   <p>He was married several years ago, and his home and studio are at 1031 East 45th Street, where he does much of his work. He also conducts an art school there, where gifted pupils are given free instruction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
