<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-12">Sept. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Farmers Could Help Themselves</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_2_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_2_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-12">Sept. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE FARMERS COULD HELP THEMSELVES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An association of farmers in Wisconsin recently adopted a resolution in which every farmer was urged not to sell any of his products unless he received a fair price for them. This same organization has also made up a list of prices for a variety of farm products, prices that it considers will give the farmer a fair compensation for his toil.</p>
   <p>During the next session of Congress, the Government will be called upon to take effective measures for the improvement of farm conditions, and definite plans have already been made by the spokesmen for those who till the soil.</p>
   <p>However, the farmers would be wise not to place too much faith in campaign promises, regardless of the sincerity of those who make them. The Government has many irons in the fire, and it will not be easy to put over <pb facs="5423404_2_0550.jpg" n="2"/>legislation which will materially benefit our agricultural population, no matter how urgent the need for such legislation may be.</p>
   <p>That farmers' association in Wisconsin may be on the right track. The farmers should take matters into their own hands. They have the same right as the manufacturers to determine the prices of their own products. But they have always been and still are handicapped by their lack of unity and organization. On the day when farmers fully realize the value of unity and cooperation, they themselves will be able to bring about better conditions without waiting for legislation to do it for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
