<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-31">Oct. 31, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Chicagoan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0925</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0925.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-31">Oct. 31, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How surprised the reader of this will be when from the start we inform him that we will write about "guns," "dupes," hangmen," and the song of a priest's wife, "The Priest's Wife in the Loom," and that his business is to find the connection between them.</p>
   <p>At least we will try our level best to present to the reader this jumble from the life of the Greeks of Chicago as it comes to this scribe's observation. We will try to picture the development of the peculiar, though not flattering, character of the Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>And although we offer our opinion or explanation as to the evolution of these exceptional conceptions of the Chicago Greeks, we will present <pb facs="5422062_1_0926.jpg" n="2"/>them as they come to our observation, and let the reader form his own opinion as to how these peculiarities have developed in the mentality of the Chicago Greek as a result of cause and effect or the influence of the environment. These characteristics of the Chicago Greek are entirely peculiar and local, perfectly natural to them, and not at all flattering or decorative.</p>
   <p>You may form your own conclusion from the incidents to be reported forthwith.</p>
   <p>Here is Mr. Panagiotes Eliopoulos, a peddler selling such various articles of men's furnishings as ties, shirts, collars, etc., who is always in need of customers and should cultivate the sympathy and good will of his customers.</p>
   <p>In spite of this, when one of his customers bought three neckties and <pb facs="5422062_1_0927.jpg" n="3"/>paid him, this self-made Chicagoan said to the bystanders in the presence of the customer, "Here is another sucker." And he said it shamelessly, without any remorse, with irony, not a bit concerned that his remark was an insult to his benefactor or that it showed ingratitude to the man who had given him a chance to make a profit.</p>
   <p>What is the cause that makes this man develop this mental attitude? Why did he show so bluntly that he has no sense of gratitude or any other high feelings? Why insult the very man who wanted to help him, the very man who thought that a peddler is entitled, as others, to a profit? Is it right to reward his good intention by making him the victim of such undeserved insult?</p>
   <p>Not only that, but this peddler accepted a penny offered to him by some bystander who wanted to see how low his dignity would go. The peddler showed, that for a penny profit, he didn't have any dignity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0928.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>How could this be explained unless we ascribe it to a lack of good example and an ignorance of high ideals?</p>
   <p>Of this or similar types of mentality many can be observed among the Chicago Greeks. What is the reason?</p>
   <p>Here is another. Mr. Evangelos Koskinas is the owner or works, -we don't know which,-in a fruit store at Cicero Avenue and Harrison Street, where thisscribe went to mail the Proodos to a subscriber and sell it to some others.</p>
   <p>By coincidence the newsboy selling the Greek newspapers arrived and asked Koskinas if he wanted a paper. He inquired what paper the boy was selling and when the boy said "Greek papers," how do you think he replied? You just make your own conclusion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0929.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"So, you sell Greek papers, eh! I don't want any. If you had Turkish papers, I would buy."</p>
   <p>The scribe asked him if he was a Greek or a Turk, and when he said that he was a Greek, he was asked if he was able to read the Turkish papers he wanted to buy. He answered in the negative, and the scribe told him that he ought to be machine-gunned in his own store, to be among the dead Greeks who wanted to read Turkish. Of course a business talk with an individual of this type is out of the question, especially if it is about newspapers.</p>
   <p>What do you think about this man? Was he so terrified by the Greek journalists and the Greek newspapers that he preferred Turkish papers that he could not read, because he is an Arcadian? What do you think is the matter with a man who shows so crass indifference to dignity propriety, and hospitality, just for the pittance of five pennies?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0930.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>What is the reason?</p>
   <p>Here is another. An elderly man, whom we liked to meet and whose name we refrain from publishing out of respect for his age, was bitterly expressing his contempt for some unworthy individuals only because they did not have any money or care to make it. In his opinion they ought to be hanged.</p>
   <p>Asked if he would hang them, he replied in the affirmative.</p>
   <p>"Then my friend, he was told, "you are the person to be an executioner and your place is in the Brutzi" [small island outside of the Nauplium, where the executioner is kept].</p>
   <p>Can you imagine an old man of over fifty having so much disregard for human beings? To judge by his age and appearance, one would have thought he had experience enough not to have developed into a misanthrope.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0931.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Has the bitterness of life made this old man a storehouse of every inhuman and hateful sentiment?</p>
   <p>What causes the low mentality of some Chicago Greeks, who from the standpoint of environment and the opportunities offered them here ought to be much better?</p>
   <p>Haven't they had better examples of dignity and goodness to make them better?</p>
   <p>Disregarding for the present the errors of religious leaders, we point to the foolish example of the editor of the Greek Star of Chicago, who corrupted his readers commercially and now protests because they sing at the meetings the song of the "Papathias."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
