<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Demand for Labor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEMAND FOR LABOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Star takes this opportunity to inform the Greeks of Chicago that it has been sent a letter and a pamphlet from the United States Bureau of Information, which is connected with the United States Immigration Bureau. The aforesaid bureaus inform us that there is a pressing demand for laborers in the United States, especially in industry. Recently, a group of specialists from Washington, D. C. made a study to determine whether there were sufficient labor resources in this country to satisfy the needs of industry. They were of the opinion that the lack of industrial manpower was felt very keenly in all types of industry. At the same time, a huge wave of immigration was flooding the United States labor markets.</p>
   <p>Mr. Powderly, who conducted this extensive survey, announces that there is a serious shortage of laborers in all types of factories, in spite of the fact that daily wages range from three to three and one-half dollars. This information has been obtained from the manufacturers themselves. In other fields where labor is employed, including agriculture, Mr. Powderly based his <pb facs="5422062_1_1464.jpg" n="2"/>figures on rough estimates and comparisons.</p>
   <p>There prevails the opinion that this shortage of labor must be made known by circulars and pamphlets to all immigration and steamship agencies. Notices will soon be sent everywhere within as well as outside the United States, printed in the principal foreign languages spoken by our immigrants. In this way, the newly arrived immigrant will know where to apply for work.</p>
   <p>However, we fear that this action will be of no avail, because the immigrant, upon arriving in the United States, goes directly to friends or relatives, who live in widely scattered parts of the country. This is only natural, since the immigrant is instructed in advance to proceed to his relatives, who will advise and help him secure some sort of employment. It is also expected that Greek immigrants, for instance, will tend to gather in large cities in Chicago, for example--where large Greek groups are concentrated and where added protection and mutual support can be easily found. There are many who read the circulars and announcements of the Department of Labor and the <pb facs="5422062_1_1465.jpg" n="3"/>Immigration Bureau, but not much attention is paid to them.</p>
   <p>The work that has already been started, however, is proceeding in the right direction. The labor resources, the manpower of this country must be evenly distributed throughout the United States. However, the great industrial centers must attract the necessary number of workers for their efficient operation. There is sufficient assurance that a great number of immigrants can find good jobs in inland cities, that opportunities are not restricted to New York and other port cities.</p>
   <p>The workers must be properly guided and advised in regard to opportunities for employment. In the final analysis, however, it must be remembered that the laborer has a free will and is independent to act or think any way he sees fit.</p>
   <p>The Greek laborers of Chicago must know that there are many opportunities for work which are waiting to be profitably exploited. Our workers will use their <pb facs="5422062_1_1466.jpg" n="4"/>best judgment in accepting work and in assisting the Greek immigrant to find suitable work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
