<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-06-09">June 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Association of the Greek Community of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-06-09">June 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE ASSOCIATION OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6- We hereby notify all members of the Association of the Greek Community of Chicago that the board of election supervisors of the Socrates Greek School, which was elected in accordance with resolution 224, passed by the general assembly on April 29, 1923, and resolution 225, of the executive committee of the community and also in accordance with the revised constitution of the Socrates Greek School, has met and passed the resolutions hereto appended:</p>
   <p>"1. All petitions of candidates for offices in the Socrates Greek School must be filed not later than June 17, 1923.</p>
   <p>"2. All petitions of candidates must be sent to the offices of the Association of the Greek Community of Chicago, 1101 South Peoria Street, or to the office of the chairman of the board of supervisors, 604 Blue Island Avenue, and they may be sent by mail or handed to a member of the board of supervisors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"3. Those who file petitions as candidates must comply with the following regulations:</p>
   <p>"(a) Only male persons who have been registered for six months as members of the Association of the Greek Community of Chicago, and who have paid their subscriptions to date, shall have the privilege of voting or of being elected as officers.</p>
   <p>"(b) All candidates for membership on the committee must be twenty-one years old and must submit their petitions in writing to the board of supervisors.</p>
   <p>"(c) Three members of the community may submit a petition of candidacy for a fourth member.</p>
   <p>(d) The officials of the community are ineligible for office in the School, and the officials of the School are ineligible for office in the Association of the Greek Community."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0401.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The date and the place of election and the names of the candidates will be published in newspapers fifteen days prior to the election and posted on our church bulletin-boards.</p>
   <p>The Board of Supervisors: N. Kokkines, president, H. Soteras, secretary, D.N. Kollias, I. Tsoulos, K. Karydes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
