<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date><title level="a">Traditions.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0867</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0867.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date><title level="a">Traditions.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. Every country has its own habits customs, and traditions, that is how it distinguishes itself from other countries. The forefathers of each race dedicated a certain day of the year for the commemoration of the cause of each important tradition, and we repeat that, from generation to generation. But let us not forget that the traditions and customs were intended to be celebrated locally and not internationally. Let us remember the old saying, "when you are in Rome, do as the Romans do", a popular dictum that is accepted by all civilized nations. Therefore, the Greeks in America, if they want to be in harmony with the rest of the civilized nations. Therefore, the Greeks in America, if they want to be in harmony with the rest on this civilized nations, on this matter, must not celebrate their traditional habits and customs in this country with the same indulgence that they do in Greece.</p>
   <p>In Greece and other countries, where the National religion is Greek Orthedoxy, the ecclesiastical custom is to hold the divine services of the Sepulcher in the hours of early morning. A certain part of this time is taken up with a public procession, the carrying of the symbolical Sepulcher of the Savior around the streets in pomp and solemnity. This is usually well done and is a <pb facs="5422062_1_0868.jpg" n="2"/>custom that is accepted and appreciated by the whole of the homogeneous populace. But in heteriogeneous America this must not be done.</p>
   <p>People of other nationalities want to get their sleep, so they can go to work in the morning. They do not want to be disturbed by this Greek religious procession and the Byzantine music that accompanies it.</p>
   <p>When this method of celebration was established by the father of our Church, it was not conceived or pre-conceived that Columbus would discover America, and that the Greeks would emigrate by the hundreds of thousands to America and hold their religious services in a territory where all are not Roman.</p>
   <p>Why do the Greeks of America insist, and persist, in keeping up their traditional service, while Greeks in England, France, Italy, Germany, Austria, etc., refrain from disturbing people during the early hours of their sleep, with that which is typically Greek and not universal?</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America must be thankful and proud of their foster Mother, <pb facs="5422062_1_0869.jpg" n="3"/>America, whose freedom and liberty we enjoy, but we must not abuse that privilege. These words of counsel are not intended as a criticism or as a reproach regarding the managers and the fathers of our churches, but are intended for the benefit of our race. I'm certain that the heads of the Greek Orthodox Church would abbreviate this pompous service, as they did abbreviate, curtailed and eventually abolished the traditional habit of our priests; the wearing of long robes, long beards, and long hair. I'm certain Christ himself would not be in accord with pompous and showy celebrations, but on the contrary, he would have favored solenm, quiet, and peaceful, divine services.</p>
   <p>Let us hope for the best. Let us hope the Greek churches and the Greeks of America will realize that they are not on Greek soil but on American soil. The ancient Greeks used to say that, "Even Gods obey the law". The unwritten law of our beloved America should not be disturbed.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
