<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-05-25">May 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Unite! Unite!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-05-25">May 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">UNITE! UNITE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unity! It is a symbol in which every Greek, whether in Greece or anywhere else, should believe because it is sacred and because it proffers salvation.</p>
   <p>Unity between the American people and our own Greek people of Chicago in thought and action is the surest guarantee for security and progress through mutual understanding and co-operation.</p>
   <p>Just as Prometheus, the Titan, was chained on a rock of Mount Caucasus, and there talked to the chorus of Oceanides about the benefactions he conferred on mankind (for before he brought and gave fire to man, men were carnivorous beasts, who, while they had eyes, could not see, and, though they had ears, could not hear and lived as ants in subterranean holes and caves); just as <pb facs="5422062_1_1126.jpg" n="2"/>Hellas, (Trans. note:- Poetic for Greece) whose vision carries far beyond the shaggy rock of the Acropolis, proclaims before all nations that she has been for three thousand years now the wakeful sentinel of Europe, her wise instructor and pedagogue and the luminous intellectual torch from which the world has received light throughout the ages, so does that fair goddess, Unity, fly in the universe proclaiming: "I gave you all strength, beauty, motion, and action; next to God, without me, nothing could move, nothing could shine in this world."</p>
   <p>Yes, unity was the main factor that accounted for the greatness and grandeur of ancient imperial Rome. It was through unity that she gained undisputed dominance over all the world and over all peoples. On the other hand, disunion and disorganization caused the downfall of her great empire.</p>
   <p>North America was the continent to which no attention was paid by the peoples of Europe when it lived in separate states, but today all the peoples of the earth look up to the United States of America with respect since The Star-Spangled Banner announced that the several states have been united. We, the <pb facs="5422062_1_1127.jpg" n="3"/>Greeks of Chicago, were never given serious consideration by the American people and their leaders, until, during the Liberty Loan campaign, we decided to work as a unit, to unite our efforts, and ever since, so much has been written highly praising and eulogizing our people.</p>
   <p>But just as the great unions of peoples create power and strength, a living example of which are Great Britain, Italy, and Germany, so, too, does the union of individuals and capital produce material, moral, and especially business strength and faith.</p>
   <p>To comprehend the power and beauty of unity, lift your eyes upon the universe and examine the planetary system and the stars and you will see that any separate or individual celestial body examined by itself makes no impression, while the whole, the entire system is wonderful.</p>
   <p>Examine the systems of associations and trusts today and you shall see that <pb facs="5422062_1_1128.jpg" n="4"/>by uniting and combining their capital resources, they have dominated and controlled business and business activities.</p>
   <p>Judging from these few examples, we are convinced that if we are to become significant factors, both as individuals and as businessmen, in society and in the United States in which we have built our homes and established ourselves, we must unite and organize companies and associations in order to present ourselves as calculable forces, which are not to be lightly disregarded. But, if we are to accomplish this, we must prepare ourselves for such a union; this preparation can be effected if we will understand and believe in the necessity of uniting as our only salvation in every respect.</p>
   <p>This newspaper offers the first idea by proposing the establishment of a business club or a chamber of commerce in which we may meet, exchange opinions, and discuss ways and means whereby we shall be able to solve our problems and regulate our affairs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1129.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The organization of such a business club will cleanse us socially and, consequently, unite us. Thereafter it will be used as the chief unifying force for our association and fraternization with the Americans. Thus, by uniting and coming in intimate contact with the Americans we will ensure our prosperity and progress, the very things in which we are vitally interested.</p>
   <p>Those who espouse this idea of organizing such a union are requested to clip the form which appears below and which is addressed to the Saloniki; let them sign and send it to us in order that we may call them together to co-operate and confer on the matter.</p>
   <p>[Trans. note:- The form directly under the editorial follows.]</p>
   <p>Reply Form</p>
   <p>To the Editor of The Saloniki</p>
   <p>748 Blue Island Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1130.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>I, the undersigned, state that I am in accord with the idea of organizing a business club and I am willing to work as much as I can for the realization of this idea.</p>
   <p>Name.....</p>
   <p>Address.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
