<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-11-10">Nov. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Business and the Greek</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-11-10">Nov. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BUSINESS AND THE GREEK</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A world study of business enterprise cannot help but reveal a great many worthy businessmen of Greek birth. However, a closer scrutiny will show that the Greeks do not attain the heights reached by other races in the financial world such as the Jewish, American, etc.</p>
   <p>It is peculiar that although the Greek, as a simple merchant, presents and possesses many good qualities, he fails to make a marked impression upon the commercial world. The exceptions to this statement have been the individuals who were brought up in this country and therefore are more accustomed to their ways of doing business and to their manner of living.</p>
   <p>Examining the Greek as a commercial unit, we find him to be brave and daring in his business enterprises. The strange thing is that despite this characteristic of courage, with which he is so richly endowed, the Greek does not <pb facs="5422062_1_1387.jpg" n="2"/>often ascend the ladder of success. He does not become a great merchant like others of different nationalities.</p>
   <p>This state of affairs leads us to ask, "What can be the cause of this peculiar situation, where a group is composed of successful business individuals, and yet as a group remains a nonentity in the business world?"</p>
   <p>We volunteer two reasons for this condition. One is the lack of business training and understanding; and the other is the egoistic, individualistic, non-co-operative characteristics of our race. These faults prevent any form of co-operative thought or action. Since co-operation and union are the foundations of success for any group engaged in any activity, the lack of power and success of Greek business men as a nationality, becomes easily understood. An American once said, "In unity there is strength"; our lack of unity explains our lack of strength.</p>
   <p>If the Greek could only comprehend the potential power within himself, and make use of it in the commercial world, his future would be entirely <pb facs="5422062_1_1388.jpg" n="3"/>different. If the Greek race wishes to progress and hold a high position in the business world, unification must take place. A union of interests must be formed following the usual ways of American business co-operation. Without such unity nothing can be accomplished. But unity alone is not enough. In this community of interests a friendly spirit must prevail; trust and truthfulness must be dominating factors, and co-operation must exist if the union is to be successful.</p>
   <p>Here exactly is the weak spot in the armor of modern Greek Achilles; for if he understands the meaning of co-operation and trust, he certainly gives no evidence of it; he is therefore in the position we find him in today.</p>
   <p>In order to prove our point, we shall use the confectionery business as an example. The Greeks in America hold the reins of the candy and confectionery business in their hands. Despite this, most of them have made little or no money. Seventy-five per cent of them not only work themselves to death, but are at the mercy of the least breath of financial upset. These men go to <pb facs="5422062_1_1389.jpg" n="4"/>strange towns and cities and open places of business; nevertheless the profits do not go to them, but into the pockets of the wholesale merchants.</p>
   <p>If the Greeks in this line of business were united, they could buy their supplies in large quantities, or else form their own wholesale houses; this would enable them to save the middleman's profit, and to buy their commodities cheaper. Let the Greeks swallow their false pride and egoism, and the world will be amazed at their progress. There are other fields in which the Greeks could have a monopoly if they united, such as restaurants, hat and shoe establishments, and.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
