<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-01-12">Jan. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Brilliant Success of the Greek-American Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-01-12">Jan. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">BRILLIANT SUCCESS OF THE GREEK-AMERICAN MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a Greek poet would have been able to describe graphically the panorama of the first Greek-American meeting, which took place last week at Hull House, and which marks the beginning of closer co-operation between Greeks and Americans.</p>
   <p>Not being a contemporary Homer, the Star will not attempt to apotheosize the spirit of the meeting, leaving the "impossible to describe," the eulogy, and the deification to Chicago sister dailies, which were all represented at the meeting, and which with unanimous voice and in colorful language informed the public of this first meeting of the two races, of its astounding success, and of the sincere enthusiasm of Greeks and Americans alike.</p>
   <p>The Parthenon of Hull House, bedecked with two huge flags, American and Greek, and surrounded by the labarums of all the Greek societies in Chicago, was transformed into matchless beauty by expensive flowers, plants, and hanging baskets, which had been donated by the Greek florists of Chicago. The ceiling, <pb facs="5422062_1_1321.jpg" n="2"/>the walls, and every available inch of space in the hall were embellished by a profusion of flowers and plants of various kinds. Myriads of Fantastic polychromatic lights reflected the scintillating panorama, which tantalized mind and senses. Rhythm, beauty, and harmony prevailed everywhere.</p>
   <p>Eight o'clock was the time set for the opening of the program, but the hall at six o'clock was already packed, and the doors were closed. When the Mayor and his wife came at 9:00 P.M., it was necessary to telephone inside the hall to open the gates for the distinguished visitors.</p>
   <p>In spite of the jam and the disappointment of people unable to enter, perfect order prevailed inside and outside the building.</p>
   <p>At 8:10 P.M. everybody stood up as if by magic, for the orchestra began to play the American National anthem, which was followed by the Greek National hymn. Hand-clapping and loud cheers filled the hall for three minutes.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1322.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dead silence ensued when Miss Jane Addams rose. In well-chosen words she opened the session and delivered the introductory address, explaining the object of the meeting, and then presented the Reverend L. Pegeas, chairman of the organization committee.</p>
   <p>The Greek archimandrite, tall, handsome (they all are), exceptionally dignified and gifted with a mellifluous voice, delivered a significant address urging the Greeks to accept and adopt American idealism, which according to his conception is the highest in the world. Thunderous applause filled the hall again. A sister daily said next day: "The thunder of the heavens has less effect on the human ear than the thunder produced by the hand-clapping at the Greek-American meeting." A melody from "Aida" followed to soothe the ear-drums.</p>
   <p>Miss Addams next introduced Judge Edward Brown, who for half an hour, with the polished rhetoric characteristic of the jurist, connected the brilliancy of ancient Greece with the enormous progress of the Greeks of Chicago, who, in a short period of time and in spite of many disadvantages, have risen and progressed with Chicago. This time "The Waves of Danube", played by the <pb facs="5422062_1_1323.jpg" n="4"/>orchestra, relieved the deafening applause for Judge Brown.</p>
   <p>But fate decreed that the many blue-blooded American ladies present, who in spite of the thunderous applause were very much pleased with the enthusiastic Greeks, should not long enjoy this respite, for the soothing melody of the orchestra was overwhelmed by a fresh outbreak of cheers when the news spread that the Mayor of Chicago was standing outside waiting to be admitted. As the Mayor and his wife took their seats on the platform, Mr. E. Karavelis, floor manager, in a resonant voice announced: "In honor of the Mayor of Chicago, who has honored this meeting with his presence, I request everybody to rise and cheer for the Honorable Edward Dunne." The audience responded to the request, and the enthusiastic applause, as reporters described it, "appeared to be the end of the world."</p>
   <p>Dr. Paul Shorey, Professor of Greek Literature at the University of Chicago, was the next speaker, and for an hour and ten minutes he kept the audience agog with his quiet reasoning, enumerating the achievements of the Greeks in Chicago and their effect upon the city and the country. The erudite Professor, <pb facs="5422062_1_1324.jpg" n="5"/>who was interrupted by applause no less than thirty-two times, in calculated yet fascinating phrases told the assemblage the story of Greek progress, beginning with the immigrant Greek of yesterday.</p>
   <p>Although the Mayor was not on the program as a speaker, he nevertheless made a polished and humorous ten-minute address, eulogizing the Greek element of the city's population. He terminated his speech with these words: "Whenever I hear the Greek language spoken on the streets of Chicago, though it is all Greek to me, it arouses in me a feeling of friendliness and admiration for the Greek race." Selections from "Rigoletto" were then played by the orchestra, and Miss Addams introduced Mr. N. Karalopoulos, who delivered in English a profound address, which the Inter-Ocean published in full.</p>
   <p>Other speakers were Andrew J. Vlachos, Dr. Gregory Papaeliou, and Dr. N. Salopoulos, Greek consul general in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Comments on the Greek-American meeting were published by the Tribune, the Chronicle, the Inter-Ocean, the Record-Herald, the Daily News, the Examiner, <pb facs="5422062_1_1325.jpg" n="6"/>These newspapers carried long articles about the Greek-American meeting and its success and about the Greeks of Chicago in general.</p>
   <p>The brilliant success of the meeting is attributed to the organized efforts of the committee, which left nothing unprepared. The meeting was attended by many society women, by representatives of the bench, by captains of industry, by bankers, by persons of wealth, by educators, and by the entire press. The Greeks, although they had no such dignitaries as the Americans in attendance, nevertheless presented the best that they had: doctors, lawyers, prominent persons of the Greek community, businessmen, publishers of Greek newspapers, representatives of the church, many well-to-do Greeks, and the Chicago Greek consul general.</p>
   <p>A bevy of American and Greek beauties, followed by a score of boys laden with <pb facs="5422062_1_1326.jpg" n="7"/>baskets of flowers, left no lapel without a rose or a carnation, and no American or Greek lady went home without an armful of choice flowers. The reception committee left nothing to chance in its efforts to accommodate and please the invited guests. Blue-blooded American ladies beamed with joy at the courteous treatment and the hospitality extended to them by the obliging Greeks. All in all, everybody was pleased and looked forward to a repetition of the event.</p>
   <p>Credit and honor are due to Miss Jane Addams for being the initiator of the affair, which has had a far-reaching effect. The Star is grateful to her.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
