<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-08-10">Aug. 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Countess Sophia De Rilly and the Chicago Greeks.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-08-10">Aug. 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">COUNTESS SOPHIA DE RILLY AND THE CHICAGO GREEKS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.--It is really amusing to what lengths of misconstruction some newspapers go in order to concoct news of the affairs of Greeks. Here is what a Chicago newspaper has said regarding the Greek lady, Countess Sophia De Rilly, when she was entertained by fellow-Greeks while in Chicago:</p>
   <p>"Chicago Greeks hope that Countess De Rilly will not marry an American if she chooses a husband. A numerous committee appeared before the noble lady and emphatically expressed the disapproval of the Greeks of Chicago of her marrying an American. Since she is the Queen of Greece's lady-in-waiting and the daughter of a prime minister, it is her duty to marry a Greek if she decides to get married."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1302.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What a fantastic and preposterous idea! What a gross misstatement! The Chicago publication which printed this midsummer night's dream must be in want of spicy news; so we advise the writer to leave the Countess's name and marriage-making committees out of its columns and go direct to the Greek Colony of Chicago, to report the real things that happen there which will satisfy its craving for something new.</p>
   <p>The activities of Greeks provide an inexhaustible supply of strange events for newsmongers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
