<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Youth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK YOUTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How many Greek children are there in the United States at the present time? Perhaps this question could be answered more easily if our priests kept birth and baptism records in some semblance of order. Roughly, we estimate that there are 300,000 Greeks in America, and about 15,000 of them are children.</p>
   <p>It is highly improbable that more than 2000 of these children attended Greek schools or classes. Most of these children attend the American public schools, even in districts where Greek schools are located. This is due, very often, to the poor organization and facilities of the [Greek] school. Sometimes it is the parents who are responsible for the low attendance of the school in their locality, because they do not take proper interest in their childrens' education.</p>
   <p>As yet, there is no real understanding of the position of the Greek school and its influence on the future of the Greeks in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0464.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have built impressive churches and have created highly complex social organizations; but we have completely overlooked, or deliberately ignored, our Greek schools. Of course, we do not belittle the efforts made in New York, Chicago or Lowell or....But even in those cities the schools are run so badly and the teachers are of such low calibre, that the schools are not very highly regarded by the parents in the community.</p>
   <p>Our first duty is toward our youth and their education; that is, if we want our language and religion to survive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
