<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-30">Aug. 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">All Must Bow to the Will of the Majority</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-30">Aug. 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ALL MUST BOW TO THE WILL OF THE MAJORITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nearly all America has read of the truimphant victory of Upton Sinclair in the primary elections of the state of California. Although he is a self-admitted Socialist, he was fanatically supported by the Democratic voters. We can easily imagine what his opponents had to say about him and his Socialistic precepts. The Regular Democratic party presented him as a menace to society and as a bomb-hurling Bolshevist. Nevertheless, Sinclair emerged the victor, and many believe that he will be elected governor in November.</p>
   <p>This support of Sinclair as a nominee for governor of a large state is a sign of the political change that is going on in this country. It reveals that new ideological trends are influencing the American people, trends that are <pb facs="5422062_1_1488.jpg" n="2"/>even more radical than any that have been introduced by President Roosevelt. If there is any doubt that the American people are accepting the changes made by the President, it can be easily dispelled by an examination of the situation in California. Not only did the voters choose the candidate who offered them radical and basic changes--changes even more extreme than Roosevelt's; but they also overwhelmingly voted for an out-and-out Socialist.</p>
   <p>In America, where it is very hard to inaugurate radical changes in ideas, the man who believed in the downfall of capitalism and in public ownership, was preferred by the majority of the voters in his state. Even now, when he knows that according to the rules of politics he should be very tactful and conservative in his speeches, Sinclair boldly asserts that capitalism is no longer of service to society, and should, therefore, be replaced. We cannot foretell the nature of the opposition which the Republican party will present to Sinclair. But we are sure that all the conservative factors in the Democratic party will help the Republicans fight him, tooth and nail. They will, no doubt, brand him a traitor, a communist, an ally of Hitler and Mussolini, and in short, an <pb facs="5422062_1_1489.jpg" n="3"/>undesirable person.</p>
   <p>It is very probable that the President will maintain a neutral stand as regards the coming California election, because he will not want to be identified with Upton Sinclair's platform. One of its most radical planks is the meeting of California's need by Federal loan grants to factories and manufacturers. Such an outright Socialistic plan cannot be supported by the President; however, he does not seem very anxious to see his political opponents emerge victorious. If he gives even the slightest encouragement to Sinclair, the conservative groups will label him a Socialist. In other words, the President finds himself between two evils, and close observers of the political campaign will watch his actions with great interest.</p>
   <p>Upon first thought, the victory of Sinclair at the primary election may not be considered a very good indication of the political ideals of this country. However, persons who study social trends proclaim it to be the beginning of the death- <pb facs="5422062_1_1490.jpg" n="4"/>struggle between capitalism and the liberal forces; and these observers are neither Socialists nor supporters of Roosevelt. America has begun to be aware of the deficiencies which mar her social order. No longer are they considered the problems of social workers. Man's responsibility for his brother is no longer something read about in the Bible. People are starting to look at their social structure with critical eyes. Perhaps the struggle will take many years, and assume various forms; but in the end the wishes of the majority will be carried out. The opposition of petty selfish interests will not be sufficient to stem the tide.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
