<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-07-03">July 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks and Marriage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-07-03">July 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS AND MARRIAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- Most of the Greeks in America will not get married! This is an unwritten law that has reduced the number of eligible girls to nothing.</p>
   <p>The first immigrants from Greece to America were all very young. They worked hard to make fortunes in order to send money to Greece, often to pay off accumulated debts. Many of them married off four or five sisters with handsome dowries. With great pride they performed all filial duties. They no longer have serious financial obligations in the old country. Their parents are dead and their brothers and sisters are now living their own lives. Today these grown-up boys, who are now men, have money and time to think about themselves and their future. They seriously contemplate marriage now that they are beginning to lose their youth. Their chances are fading fast and with these chances all their youthful dreams and hopes have faded, nor will they return.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0708.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Yes, John, I must get married soon. It is about time. Thank you for speaking of your younger sister. She is an exceptional girl, but I, if it is possible, am going to marry one who has been born in Greece. We will get along better together.</p>
   <p>"The Greek girls born in America are more intelligent and more beautiful, but they want too much. Whether he has the money or not, a man must buy her a grand piano. This is a promise before her consent to the marriage. For every dance or holiday party, he must close his store, buy her a new dress, and stay up all hours of the night to please her.</p>
   <p>"I want a woman who will be my housekeeper, to keep everything in order, raise my children properly, and ask for little in return. I want to be king in my house."</p>
   <p>They overlook one fact in their analysis of a perfect wife. The modern girls don't want them! They are too old. The young Greek girls want to marry young men born in America even if they possess nothing but <pb facs="5422062_1_0709.jpg" n="3"/>youth. As a result many eligible bachelors, not so young, and many Greek girls born here, not finding their Prince Charming, will remain single.</p>
   <p>Isn't it better, then, for a Greek-American girl to marry an older man with suitable means than to wait for a good-looking young man with little, if any, money? Girls really aren't spendthrifts. It is only that they are modern, and want to look their best. Nowadays, the Greek girls of America are better housekeepers than those in Greece. They are more scientific, save themselves and at the same time take better care of their homes.</p>
   <p>Take heed, and marry as soon as you can.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
