<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date><title level="a">What an American Thinks of the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J.M. Rife Iv. the Greeks and their Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date><title level="a">WHAT AN AMERICAN THINKS OF THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J.M. Rife IV. The Greeks and their Children</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most important work which the human being accomplishes is the rearing of children. There are no more serious human problems than those confronted by parents. The ever changing problems of parenthood are difficult enough in one's native environment, but when a family takes up its residence in a foreign country, the difficulties are doubled. Greek parents ask what I think is best in the education of their children. I try to imagine what my wife and I should do with our children were we living in a foreign country, but it is exceedingly difficult to say.</p>
   <p>Children seem instinctively to respect the environment outside the home more than the home influences. American missionaries in China find their children prefer to speak Chinese as long as they are in China. When the <pb facs="5422062_1_0799.jpg" n="2"/>family returns on furlough the children rapidly transfer their preference to English. Of course the American missionary is determined his children shall learn English, and with similar feelings, the Greek parent in America feels it would be an irreparable loss, if his children failed to preserve the speech of Hellas. What attitude shall the Greek parent take on the language question?</p>
   <p>The American naturally feels that, of all people, the Greeks are justified in preserving their language in a foreign environment, because of its vital connection with the past glories of the nation. I cannot help sharing this feeling, yet we must raise the question: Is it best for the children to urge, or even force them to learn Greek? Their welfare must be the prime consideration. Will they be better off if they learned Greek? Several considerations present themselves in answer to this question.</p>
   <p>In the first place, I believe it is a sound instinct which prompts the child to adapt himself to language and customs of the land in which he lives. For his own good, the Greek child in America must learn English <pb facs="5422062_1_0800.jpg" n="3"/>as perfectly as possible, whether he learns any Greek or not. The Greek children are all doing this, so we need not urge the inevitable.</p>
   <p>I cannot feel, however, that it is an equally sound instinct which leads children to despise the traditions of their elders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
