<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-01-13">Jan. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">United and Ununited</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-01-13">Jan. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED AND UNUNITED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>United and ununited are two words whose meanings are entirely opposite, just as the results of interpreting these words are opposite. While one word represents harmonious workings of a group toward a certain goal, the other stands for dissension and individual selfishness. Unity and lack of unity are so prevalent in our cosmic structure and in our natural surroundings that it is difficult for us to recognize them. It is like a star which has brightness and strength in its own self, but which can never equal the power of the entire heavenly universe [sic].</p>
   <p>Each man has in himself the power to accomplish much, but how much more can he accomplish when working in harmony with his fellow men? This is the theory upon which most governments are founded. The French proverb says, "L'union fait la force" (unity creates strength). Let us Greeks <pb facs="5422062_1_1142.jpg" n="2"/>examine this statement, and see if it clarifies our national duty any better than it has been done before.</p>
   <p>Should we become exponents of unity and lovers of co-operation, or should we continue to fight for individualism and our own selfish interests as is unfortunately characteristic of everything we have done so far? What would be our country's destiny, if we were to accept the former and were forever to banish the latter--which, like a cancer, is eating away our nation's heart? We will try to answer this question in order that all might see that our country's progress and liberation is dependent upon whether or not we unite.</p>
   <p>If we wish to become powerful enough to demand and obtain the things that we as a nation desire, then we must blindly follow the path of unity. We can then go before the other nations of the world as a single, unified country, and demand those things which are in all justice ours. The united voices of over sixteen million people cannot be easily ignored.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Singly, we would be vainly calling for help in the wilderness--a condition that would bring much joy to our enemies, sorrow and shame to our friends, and profound melancholy in the breasts of the lovers of the former splendid country of Greece.</p>
   <p>If we remain as we are now--divided--the nation will be assimilated by its neighbors; and in the course of time will be completely obliterated. Therefore, a great need exists that we cast aside hatred and selfishness and become co-operative. If we do not do so, we will soon mourn the passing of a nation that died simply because it had not the courage to live.</p>
   <p>The choice between unity and lack of unity will determine the future of our fatherland. Unification despite all sacrifice is the desire and cry of Saloniki.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
