<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-01-25">Jan. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Our Thoughts Turn to the Dodecanese</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-01-25">Jan. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">OUR THOUGHTS TURN TO THE DODECANESE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first armed conflict to arise from the suppression of the people of the Dodecanese Islands came a few days ago at Kalymnos. The people of this Island universally disapproved the action of the Bishop, who obeyed the orders of the Italian rulers. This acceptance of Italian authority by the Bishop caused the churches of the Dodecanese to be cut off from the Greek Ecumenical Patriarchy. So great was the people's wrath that they threw the Bishop out of their church.</p>
   <p>These events were considered revolutionary in spirit by the Italian tyrants. Consequently a body of marines was dispatched to restore order and to suppress further activities on the part of the protestants. This was accomplished by the simple expedient of firing upon unarmed groups of men and women. Many were killed and many more were wounded.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1473.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ugly words and phrases which can best describe some races and some people are usually omitted from the printed page; but there are certain instances when the most amiable persons can be turned into raging beasts. Such is the psychological effect of this brutal massacre of unarmed people on every Hellene who has heard about it. The many similar events in these Islands have filled every Greek heart with righteous, furious, despair and anger. It is possible that the Greek Government will not even register a public complaint. What would be the use?</p>
   <p>As for us in America--since the day that the women and children were murdered by the command of that mad idiot, Benito Mussolini, our hearts have been filled with rage against him. We shall always consider him an enemy of Freece, despite the many visits exchanged between him and Venizelos, Tsaldaris, and Kondilis. As an enemy of Greece and as a potential threat to the peace and safety of the world we shall always describe him in the foulest terms. One thing we are certain of is that <pb facs="5422062_1_1474.jpg" n="3"/>Mussolini, like his friend Adolph, is a perfect model for a strait jacket.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
