<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-09-15">Sept. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Finest Greek School in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-09-15">Sept. 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE FINEST GREEK SCHOOL IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday at two o'clock in the afternoon, the Socrates School--repeatedly described as the finest Greek school in the United States--held exercises celebrating its anniversary. [Translator's note: Which anniversary is not specified.]</p>
   <p>The classrooms and the assembly hall of the school were profusely decorated with beautiful fresh flowers. These flowers had been donated to the school by two of our progressive citizens and friends of education, Mr. Venizelos and Mr. Papantony. In addition to their generous contribution of flowers, they undertook the actual decoration of the school.</p>
   <p>Around one-thirty, the leading members of the Greek community began to make their appearance. The consul, the boards of directors of all the Greek churches, <pb facs="5422062_1_0432.jpg" n="2"/>newspaper men, priests, professional men, and many others, honored the school by their presence. By two o'clock, the hall was packed to the point of suffocation.</p>
   <p>The Reverends L. Pygeas and C. Hadzidimitriou jointly pronounced the benediction. This was followed by a speech by Reverend Pygeas, who is chairman of the school committee. His address was excellently worded, and was heartily applauded by the audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. N. Salopoulos, Consul General of Greece, then arose and pointed out various needs of the school, and the benefit derived by the community from the existence of such a fine institution. He said that the community was itself benefited when it improved the condition of the Greek school.....</p>
   <p>Mrs. C. Kantzou, teacher and principal of the school, addressed the audience, and as usual made a fine impression.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0433.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A collection was taken up, which netted $405. Saloniki expresses its joy at this fine support accorded the Greek school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
