<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Barbarous Custom</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A BARBAROUS CUSTOM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We Greeks have very many striking and beautiful customs which are very old, and which are part of our traditional religious and social heritage. However, we have a few customs that are as ugly and repulsive as they are antiquated.</p>
   <p>These must be corrected if we are to avoid the ridicule and the derogatory remarks of our American friends who often witness many of our ceremonies and social affairs.</p>
   <p>To-day, we propose to smear the foreheads of our celebrated violinists and other players of Greek musical instruments in our typical and unique Greek orchestras. We, hereby, wish to urge the Greek people to stop the ugly and disgusting habit of rewarding the orchestra players by wetting one-dollar or five-dollar bills with their tongues and then sticking them on the musicians' foreheads. Members of Greek bands have made of this custom a system of scientific exploitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0766.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are many relatives and friends of the players who start sticking bills on the foreheads of the latter for the purpose of forcing the dancers to imitate them. This is considered a neat way of making the dancers and the celebrating crowd empty the contents of their purses into the brass tubes in order to show the other people that they have plenty of money and that they are well pleased with the screeching, nerve-wracking tunes of the sweating players.</p>
   <p>As if these disgusting demonstrations were not enough, we have, at the end, the violinist and the drummer or banjo player quarreling with one another for the money that has been thrown all around them. In this way, the wedding celebration becomes a most revolting comedy.</p>
   <p>While many Americans, who are curious to see a Greek wedding, admire its beauty and the elaborate ceremony, something of this sort--the ugly practice of sticking dollars on the music players' foreheads during the reception and wedding celebration--causes the most painful impression. There is no doubt that they become thoroughly disgusted with the sight.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0767.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is not asking too much when we plead with our people to abandon this barbarous and uncivilized custom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
