<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">In Defense of the Greek Name. What the Press Says</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">Feb. 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENSE OF THE GREEK NAME. WHAT THE PRESS SAYS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. -- There is a growing tendency to look askance at certain European races of the south, who now constitute the greater part of the million immigrants who arrive in our ports every year.</p>
   <p>As a rule these people work for lower wages than Americans are willing to accept. They are less particular as to the kind of work which they do. They do not lend themselves readily to labor agitation. They stick to their jobs, making the best of what is often a pretty bad bargain, and taking care of themselves without depending upon organizations of any kind.</p>
   <p>This spirit of unfriendliness toward a race of which the only offense is that its members work too willingly or too cheaply is so remarkable that the time has come, we believe, to seek to check it. In view of the fact that these races are now being discussed not a little in connection with the Balkan Wars, their case may properly be regarded as one which warrants examination from a new angle.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1169.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Of the several nationalities in question the Greeks appear most prominently, since they belong to a race which dates back to ancient civilization, and their life and their activities in America are somewhat better organized and more conspicuous than that of their former neighbors in Europe. They have many newspapers in the United States and many churches and social organizations. They appear to be more numerous in many of our cities than other southern European races.</p>
   <p>The charge has recently been made that they were false friends of the Bulgarians toward the close of the Balkan War. But this is a charge that may be explained, we believe, on the ground that the Greeks are a people of different temperament and different standards than the Bulgarians, whose Tartar origin explains a fierceness which is foreign to the Greek character.</p>
   <p>From the standpoint of the American people, our Greek citizens are worthy of higher esteem than that which they have sometimes enjoyed. A race which will turn back to its native shores by thousands when war is declared surely possesses a spirit which Americans can appreciate and applaud.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1170.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fact that thousands of Greeks are performing lowly tasks in the United States means only that they are handicapped by lack of comprehension of the language, of the customs, and of many of the tasks to be done in their new environment. They have qualities which will overcome this handicap within the space of a generation; courage, energy, and a fine eagerness to learn, to be friendly, to be worthy. Such a race ought not to be made sullen and resentful by unfriendliness.</p>
   <p>If America has ceased to be wholly American, it is not because Greeks and others have come to our shores in great numbers, but because too many Americans themselves have fallen away from the old, sound standards of tolerance, equality, and good will toward all their fellow men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
