<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-04-08">April 8, 1911</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Unjustified Attack.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-04-08">April 8, 1911</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">UNJUSTIFIED ATTACK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday morning at 4 A. M. a group of garbage carriers attacked and shot a Greek employed in the same line of business by Mr. K. Geortsos.</p>
   <p>The attacked Greek testified, to authorities, that the attackers must have been Irish as he judged from their accent. But he was in doubt that he could recognize them.</p>
   <p>The trouble started when Mr. Geortsos contracted over one hundred Greek restaurants to carry their garbage for one dollar per month. His clientele increased and so did his garbage wagons. The Irish garbage carriers very much resented the new competitor, Mr. Geortsos, and the attack against him followed. "Get out of the garbage business or we will kill all of you Greeks," said the Irish garbage carriers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It really is a disgrace to civilization to compete in business by attempting to commit murders. The Greek in any line of business does not compete with a gun, but with legitimate business methods. The Greek is not a coward to attack his competitors in the dark from behind with a gun. That is cowardly.</p>
   <p>The Greek when he is defeated in business by his competitor does not shoot them in the back on some dark night, but he folds up his tent and goes to learn about better methods of competition in business.</p>
   <p>Personal precautions are taken by the Greek garbage carriers, who are determined to put a stop to intimidations and attempted murder.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1198.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They say we are law-abiding citizens trying to make our bread and butter honestly and with plenty of labor. We will beat cowards to the draw if another dastardly occasion arises. The law of the land will justify our action which is based on self defense.</p>
   <p>The editor predicts that there will not be any further outbreaks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
