<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Journal</title>,
<date when="1921-10-27">Oct. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Leaders See Venizelos Private Conferences Held by Ex-Premier Shuns Public Speeches Extends Stay Will Attend Church Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Journal</title>,
<date when="1921-10-27">Oct. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK LEADERS SEE VENIZELOS PRIVATE CONFERENCES HELD BY EX-PREMIER SHUNS PUBLIC SPEECHES EXTENDS STAY WILL ATTEND CHURCH SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greek-Chicago continued to pay homage today to Eleutherios Venizelos, the former premier whose powerful influence swayed that country to the ranks of the allied nations during the world war.</p>
   <p>Delegations from every local Greek society and from near-by cities filed in seemingly never-ending procession in and out of the statesman's suite at the Blackstone Hotel.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1086.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fourteen leading Greek-Americans, headed by Attorney Paul Demos, composed the first group to be received. They officially welcomed him to Chicago and urged him to reconsider his decision to accept no formal invitations while here.</p>
   <p>He declined to be their guest at any reception. But the great statesman expressed a desire to attend the services of St. Constantine's Greek Orthodox Church, Sixty-first and Michigan Avenue, next Sunday morning, providing there be no celebration.</p>
   <p>"I will be glad to see any countrymen in church," he said. "I will consent to attend services at St. Constantine's Church next Sunday if there is order and no manifestation of any kind. If all is quiet when I arrive there I will enter. If it is not, I will go on and worship in some other way.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1087.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I am not on exhibition," he continued. "I am no Charlie Chaplin. I cannot go anywhere unless I talk. And at present my mouth is closed and my lips are sealed. I refrain from talking. I fear that if I do the present regime in Greece will act contrary to my advice, and that would be against the interests of my country."</p>
   <p>Special services will be held in his honor. Archbishop Meletios, metropolitan of Athens, who accompanied the ex-premier and his wife on their trip from New York, will preside. The three Greek orthodox priests in Chicago will assist.</p>
   <p>The Cretan delegation was next received. Venizelos, who is himself a native of the romantic Isle of Crete, greeted them as brothers. Representatives of the Greek Liberal Democratic League followed. The Greek Students' Association, composed of students from colleges abroad and here, the National Espirotic society, and special delegations from Gary, <pb facs="5422062_1_1088.jpg" n="4"/>Hammond, South Bend, Fort Wayne, Indiana Harbor and East Chicago, each took their turn in the diplomat's drawing room.</p>
   <p>Costas Regis, president of the Greek community and the Greek Liberal league, headed a large representation from Milwaukee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
