<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Labor Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE LABOR QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago, a railroad company took one hundred Greek laborers from Chicago after the latter had paid the usual fee to the labor agents. The next day, they were on their way to the location of the work, which was near Omaha, Nebraska.</p>
   <p>After having worked only two days, the poor Greek laborers received an order to the effect that they must quit their work and depart from there. Anyone can imagine the agonizing moments that our unfortunate countrymen experienced, when they found themselves in the prairies of an uninhabited region without friends or money. For a whole day and night they had nothing to eat, and they were forced to sleep in the open fields.</p>
   <p>On the next day, they became so desperate that they began destroying and tearing apart the railroad line. Men from the company summoned the police, who arrested the Greek workers and put them in prison without giving them a chance to explain why they were forced to begin damaging the property of the railroad <pb facs="5422062_1_1458.jpg" n="2"/>company.</p>
   <p>The judge who handled the case a little later not only found the workers free of any guilt but also forced the company to provide them with free railroad fare back to Chicago. On their return here they told us the long story of their adventure and hardships.</p>
   <p>The hiring agent, either a Bulgarian or a Macedonian, defrauded fifty Greco-Macedonians a few days ago by collecting ten dollars from each of them for his commission. He promised them that he would find suitable work for them at the new railroad station of the Consolidated Railroads of Chicago. No one knows, however, when construction work at the new station will begin.</p>
   <p>Another hiring agent, an Italian, swindled a hundred Greek and Italian laborers. By making false promises, he was given five or ten dollars in advance by each worker. He did not provide any work, so he was arrested and freed on two-thousand-dollar bail.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1459.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Chicago today, we have 120,000 unemployed, among whom many hundreds--I should say, thousands--are Greeks. There are many industrious and ambitious young men who would be glad to do any kind of work in restaurants or candy stores for small wages.</p>
   <p>In the advertising section of Saloniki many hundreds of advertisements are inserted free of charge for poor young men who are seeking work.....When a business man advertises for employees, he is swamped with hundreds of applicants.</p>
   <p>A bright young worker was telling us, with pain in his heart and with great disappointment, that more than a thousand young Polish women are working in the numerous Greek restaurants. If the Greek restaurant owners would hire young Greek men as waiters, cashiers, dishwashers, extra help, etc., more than a thousand Greeks could secure excellent jobs for themselves. This would repay the managers and proprietors many times, and they would be doing a great service and favor to deserving men of our nationality. As we have written before, many Greek restaurant owners were sued and fined by the Bureau of Public Morals for employing young Polish girls as waitresses.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1460.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We mention these facts in order to prove that the proper organization and consolidation of our Greek community and business interests could effectively do something to protect and support our Greek laboring class. Furthermore, a way could be found to provide useful, profitable, and morale-building work for many hundreds of our own countrymen. We cannot fail to notice that most members of our laboring class are suffering many indescribable hardships and are already feeling the pangs of hunger. There must be some way these people can be helped by our businessmen.</p>
   <p>The consolidation of the Greek community of Chicago is not a fanciful idea nor is it an impractical platonic theory. The unification of all the Greeks of Chicago under the leadership of the Greek Orthodox church organization will give rise to the creation of a great national Greek family with our religion and country as the binding and conserving forces. Within this great powerful family, the weak, the poor, the sick, and those who deserve any kind of help, will find shelter, protection,relief, material and moral support, and loving kindness.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1461.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This is what the Greek Orthodox community and organization should be. This is Christian brotherhood in action. This is patriotic support to our own people who live in a foreign land. And this is what Saloniki is fighting for. The program for the unification of the Greek people of Chicago is broad; it has many noble and indispensable objectives.</p>
   <p>Today's editorial dealing with the vital problem of the needs of our laboring class, which is composed of thousands of Greek workers, deserves the serious and immediate consideration of all. Surely, never can a good man be more thrilled to his very soul and profoundly pleased than when he is able to help and support a fellow countryman or a fellow human being.</p>
   <p>By the consolidation of our entire community, all our social needs will be satisfied; the labor question will be effectively solved, so that there will be no poverty-stricken, demoralized, and suffering Greeks. Our present condition of indigence, despair, and misery must be corrected at all cost.</p>
   <p>Our churches must become the centers of relief and mutual aid. Our priests <pb facs="5422062_1_1462.jpg" n="6"/>and the officials of our churches can do much toward helping our own unemployed and unfortunates. They can recommend our Greek laborers to our prosperous businessmen by advising them to prefer and hire Greek labor in their businesses.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, in the future, a united Greek community will be able to protect our laborers from thieving labor racketeers as well as from the evils of exploitation.</p>
   <p>In exposing the sad state of our laboring class, Saloniki is ready and willing to do its part to alleviate suffering by contributing to the improvement of the workers status. This newspaper welcomes any "work wanted" advertisements by Greek workers who are seeking a job but cannot afford to pay. May we appeal to our businessmen to co-operate by preferring, at all times, our poor countrymen whenever they have to hire any kind of labor?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
