<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>
      <date when="1932-01-01">Jan. 1, 1932</date>
      <title level="a">There is One Good Omen</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>
     <date when="1932-01-01">Jan. 1, 1932</date>
     <title level="a">THERE IS ONE GOOD OMEN</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the first of the year is not any different from any other days, we have some to believe that on this day a new year begins which all of us hasten to welcome and celebrate as the best omen of happiness and properity. We offer one another hearty wishes that the new year become like a spring giving every good thing in life.</p>
   <p>In this beautiful custom we would not fall short, ourselves, in spite of the fact that the new year's foreleadings are not so happy and prosperous as long as we continue in such a severe economic crisis.</p>
   <p>Addressing outselves to Greeks, we have reasons to believe that, no matter how depressing conditions are, the Greek-Americans will face the crisis with their usual fortitude show in critically hard times. Because this is the characteristic of our race---to show an indomitable endurance and to successfully overcome the obstacles with courage and perseverance. We must not have the least doubt that the Greeks of America will show up these qualities in the difficult times now confronting us.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0951.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true and indisputable, that the Greeks have suffered great disasters, and that every Greek is engaged, today, in a desperate struggle for existence in this country. THeir property has been almost eliminated; their business is in danger of being destroyed; but it is equally true that they are facing all these difficulties with a courage, and an inward conviction, that tells them they will come out victorious.</p>
   <p>The present crisis is undoubtedly unique in the history of humanity and there is no way of comparing it with previous economic crisis. It is for this reason that no man can foresee its course.</p>
   <p>There is one thing certain and indisputable, namely, that the situation has gotten out of control of the ones in power. That things have taken a direction towards happiness and prosperity and he who would last to the end shall be saved.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0952.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is for this reason we commit ourselves with conviction in regards to the Greeks, that they will come out victorious because they, in particular, possess characteristic qualities of patience, persistence, perseverance, which, in difficult times, they know how to utilize, and just for that, we not only wish but steadfastly believe that the New Year will prove a happy one for them.</p>
   <p>S. P. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
