<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-01-19">Jan. 19, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigrant of Yesterday</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Factor Today Greek-American Meeting and its Object (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-01-19">Jan. 19, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRANT OF YESTERDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Factor Today Greek-American Meeting and Its Object (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The object of the first formal public meeting between Americans and the Greek community was twofold. On the one hand it was to have the character and the status of the Greeks in Chicago advantageously set forth before the public and so to confute prejudice against them as "immigrants." On the other hand the object was to challenge the Greeks themselves to put forth their best efforts to win and deserve the esteem of Americans.</p>
   <p>The Greeks have special problems to meet in adjusting themselves to a new western country, entirely and altogether different from their own. These problems were not specifically dealt with at the first meeting. Its purpose was to bring the two races together in a spirit of cordiality, fellow- <pb facs="5422062_1_1317.jpg" n="2"/>ship, and understanding. Of course this is the beginning of a new era for the Greek colony of Chicago, and the success of the meeting should give the Greeks energy and confidence to meet these problems.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the most important general consideration impressed on the meeting was the thought that the Greek community of Chicago represents traditions and capabilities which should properly become a valuable constituent element in the cultural life of the city. Greeks the world over have that they are a progressive race possessing many valuable qualities foreign to other races. And the Greeks of America, imbued with Americanism, will eventually shine like stars. This may sound illogical to the uninformed, but to real, honest-to-toodness Americans it is a hard fact. Their minds and their hearts, being truly American, are open and receptive to the knowledge and understanding required to appreciate the latent potentialities of the Greek race.</p>
   <p>A dozen or so years ago there was but a handful of Greeks here in Chicago, and for the sake of distinction they were "immigrants," but today they number about ten thousand, and the unpleasant word, "immigrant" is becoming less properly applicable. The thought of the masses is beginning to change in favor of the Greeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1318.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those so-called immigrants of yesterday, illumined with just a spark of American greatness, began to rise, and the more the light of Americanism is thrown upon them, the quicker they reach the top. The uninitiated Greeks of yesterday are rapidly absorbing the fruit trade, the flower business, the restaurants, and the confectioneries not only here in Chicago but also in other big cities of the country. Their enterprise and their thrift are astonishing. The Greek community of Chicago, with its churches and its societies, has kept a vigilant eye on needy members of the colony and so efficiently have these agencies functioned that no Greek has become a public charge. The obedience of Greek to the law of the land is a great credit to them. And all these qualities are characteristic of what we call a good citizen.</p>
   <p>The immigrant of yesterday has now mingled and rubbed elbows with those Americans who stand highest in Chicago society and business. One lady among those born to the purpose who attended the meeting said: "Oh my, the Greeks are a proud race, and I can see that the Greeks of Chicago are not lacking in pride." Indeed not. They are not lacking in pride, and sometimes they appear to be oversupplied with it. Of course pride is not entirely a detrimental quality, and the pride of Greeks is founded not along on the ancient glories of their race but also on its inherent greatness.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1319.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Greek-American meeting, which was the first of its kind in the history of Chicago, may be accepted as a pledge of new efforts by the Greek community to become a distinctively valuable element in the life of the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
