<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-21">Sept. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">How Civilization Is Sacrificed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-21">Sept. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">HOW CIVILIZATION IS SACRIFICED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the beginning of the twentieth century, when the entire civilized world was at peace, the peoples of the earth began to discard the methods and habits of the past and to seek a better and more progressive way of thought and action. This desire for improvement and progress which began to grow in the hearts of men was based upon certain facts which were recognized by all.</p>
   <p>During the entire nineteenth century--and especially in the latter portion-growing changes in the general mode of living were of such a nature that the evils of society were rapidly being uncovered and terminated. That was, of course, what happened to any social evil as soon as it became a matter of public knowledge. During this period, for the first time in the world's history, slavery was abolished. With few exceptions divine right was no longer accorded to royalty, and became intolerable even to the commonest man. Education <pb facs="5422062_1_1519.jpg" n="2"/>was beginning to be available to all who desired it. There was even compulsory education for children. Truly a new world was being created and in it a new civilization was making its appearance.</p>
   <p>The changes witnessed by those living in this period were countless. Inventions tumbled over each other, science and the professions made great strides in research and methods. Natural phenomena were explained, and unseen forces measured. Sociologists began to prepare the groundwork for the new society which they had long dreamed of.</p>
   <p>The rich and poor continued to exist; but the restrictions of the past, which had forced each one to stay within the class into which he was born, were gone. Social barriers were removed, and opportunity awaited all individuals, regardless of their birth or the size of their pocketbooks. Freedom was extended to thought and religious beliefs..... This situation prevailed and was inherited by the twentieth century. It existed until the fateful day when war in Europe was declared. That is how long the spirit of progress, peace, achievement, <pb facs="5422062_1_1520.jpg" n="3"/>and social equality endured.</p>
   <p>The great catastrophe of war brought the world to a new detour. Of course, inventions did not cease to make their appearance, and neither did individuals lose their social rights. The manner of life itself did not change. It was the spirit of public thought that changed. The ego of the individual was drowned in the anachronistic spirit of nationalism, which resulted in the curtailment of certain individual rights. Good examples of what we mean can be found in Russia, Italy, Germany, Jugoslavia, and, in lesser degree, in the other nations of the world.</p>
   <p>In Europe, again today, it is just fear and not lack of desire, that prevents the declaration of another war. In fact, it is publicly stated that war is impending. In the East, the Kingdom of the Rising Sun teaches its people that it is the will of God that the earth be ruled by the Japanese. The Germans and Italians are sure they are the ones best suited to rule a subjugated world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1521.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In Europe, each inch of earth is drenched with human blood. And yet, new pacts, new alliances, and new treaties are still being made, the only fruit of which will be war and more war... Individual rights, which were not abolished even in the Middle Ages, are today suppressed to an unbelievable degree. An inhabitant of one nation is not welcomed in another. The spirit of patriotism and nationalism has been inflamed to an intolerable degree.</p>
   <p>The tolerance and humaneness of the few will not be able to stop humanity from plunging itself into a horrible war the purpose of which will be to defend its various nationalisms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
