<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-27">July 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">President Roosevelt Heralds New Era</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-27">July 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT HERALDS NEW ERA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If ever a nation has found itself in a difficult situation during the last three years that nation has been the United States of America. Despite its position as a highly prosperous and contented nation, over night it became desperately and hopelessly a victim of the world-wide depression. The people of America exhibited exemplary patience and suffered in silence in order to give the Government a chance to get the country out of the doldrums. Finally, hunger and bread lines harassed the patience of the people, and they decided to do something themselves. The customary procedure was followed. The Americans use their vote as a weapon to gain their ends. Therefore, when the presidential election was held, the party that had been in power for the twelve years was ousted, and the candidate of the Democratic party, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, was elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The new President faced a terrifying situation. The economic system of the nation was practically ruined, and, on all sides, murmurings could be heard against the do-nothing attitude of the Government. The country, at its wit's end, began to discuss the merits of Communism, which at least does guarantee food, shelter, and work to those who are deserving. At the time of Roosevelt's election matters had reached a dangerous and crucial stage. The farmers from all sections of the country had practically revolted--in fact, the spirit of universal revolt was rampant. The nation was faced with the fact that if the present system of government was incapable of correcting the economic situation, a new system would be found.</p>
   <p>Just at this opportune moment Roosevelt was given the reins of government. He was fully prepared to face the situation. He represented a new type of president--a type which had long been absent from the American scene. It was apparent from his speech and his actions that the President was in complete understanding of the nation's ills, and that he had in mind the remedies that would relieve the acute suffering and unrest which prevailed throughout the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1529.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What has occurred in Washington since his election is known to all of us. His ideas are vital and if actually put into practice they cannot help but put life into America. Of course, some of his ideas are Socialistic in nature, and this will be used against him by his greatest enemies, the capitalistic class.</p>
   <p>In regards to the proposed plans of the President resembling socialism, the truth is that his program is entirely experimental. His program is not attempting to find a method of abolishing individual enterprise and wealth, but a means of enlarging the economic scope of the average citizen. The plans of the President may result in a social order called "national socialism"; but it will not be the kind of socialism advocated by the leaders of the socialist movement. That which the President feels is basically wrong with the country is the unequal distribution of its wealth. Only a more equal distribution can help the great mass of humanity, and the President hopes to introduce this fairer system.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1530.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>main effort of our modern society is directed toward ways and means of creating new machinery to lessen man's burden.</p>
   <p>President Roosevelt intends to find new ways and means of providing the American people with a guarantee of security and economic stability. This effort is being watched by the entire world with unconcealed interest: for the majority of people feel that all the President's acts are motivated by his sincere humanitarian ideology.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
