<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-05-08">May 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Inferiority Complex</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-05-08">May 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">INFERIORITY COMPLEX</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the next column we reproduce a picture of the procession of the ceremony of the burial of Christ, which the Tribune of Chicago published last Saturday with a description of our night litany.</p>
   <p>It is known to all with what interest Americans watch such festivals, and how much reverence they show for the religious ceremonies of the various peoples that have immigrated to this country. Concerning the procession of the ceremony of the burial of Christ many eagerly attend the spectacle and carry away splendid impressions.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, we Greeks, contrary to the impressions and feelings of Americans, abolish whatever we hold beautiful in Greek life because we fear that it may create an unpleasant impression, and we are ashamed of our Greek traditions, traits, and customs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0857.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Those of our countrymen who think this prove their petty character and servility, qualities which are due, assuredly, to lack of culture and national dignity. In other words, they suffer with inferiorty complex, and they mean to impose their inferior character upon others who desire to preserve their mores and do not feel that their religion and nationality are of a lower category.</p>
   <p>Up to a short while ago all the churches in Chicago were holding the procession of the ceremony of the burial of Christ on the night of the Good Friday. Lately, unfortunately, by the urging and exhortation of the diocese, they are beginning to abolish the custom because we are ashamed to keep up any longer our traditional ceremonies, and we are afraid to appear before the eyes of others as Greeks. For the same reason we are beginning to abolish the "stefana" (bridal wreaths) from our marriage ceremony and to find substitutes for the Greek language in our sacred mysteries and liturgies, for we think that in this manner we shall present a pleasant appearance to strangers!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0858.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, if, instead of abolishing our beautiful ceremonies and traditions, we tried to present them in a more serious manner, we should gain the esteem and respect of strangers, and they would hold us in much higher consideration as Greeks conscious of our descent than they do when we are ashamed to appear as such.</p>
   <p>Leaving these to one side, we appeal to those who are conscious of their Hellenism and desirous of keeping it up, to organize as much as possible in the most dignified and imposing manner the night litany of the ceremony of the burial of Christ, and to let them be sure that such ceremonies arouse respect and esteem rather than scorn as those about the diocese think who are pursuing systematically their efforts to apolish this Greek custom and even the formalities of our church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
