<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-03-05">Mar. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Are We Sincere?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-03-05">Mar. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ARE WE SINCERE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, the new President of the United States, Mr. William H. Taft, was officially inaugurated as chief executive of this great country. After the noisy campaign of last November was over and the Congress of the United States resumed its legislative work, the people of the United States forgot the heated arguments and the verbal battles because they have accepted the new administration and have now buried the hatchet. They are now co-operating with one another and are devoting all their time to peaceful and constructive daily pursuits.</p>
   <p>The Republicans have won, but the Democrats bear no grudge against their opponents. All differences are now composed. Members of both parties are Americans and what matters most is America, its welfare, and its future.</p>
   <p>Can we Greeks claim that we act similarly after our elections are over? Do we accept and congratulate the victors with all sincerity? Most of us in many cases <pb facs="5422062_1_1211.jpg" n="2"/>have not proven that we are big-hearted enough to graciously accept the dictates of the majority; we continue to hate; it is with some difficulty that we again become friends with our opponents.</p>
   <p>Let us profit from the fine spirit which prevails in all American political and social institutions. Let us see whether we too can put the country and the general interest above party and partisan loyalty.</p>
   <p>Such attitudes are the mark of a great people; such a spirit makes for true patriotism and true national greatness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
