<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-23">Nov. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Recognition of Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-23">Nov. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">RECOGNITION OF RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the President of the United States has formally invited Soviet Russia to send a representative to America, the complete recognition of Russia is practically accomplished. Only a few details of secondary importance are still unsettled. The countries seem to be in complete harmony.</p>
   <p>The conservative factions in America can talk and argue all they wish against the President's action. America was obliged to recognize the U. S. S. R. because Russia's present form of government has endured now for sixteen years. It makes no difference if the Russian people are experimenting with communism. In so far as the status of their country is concerned, the Soviet Republic has the same right to recognition as any other government in the world. The social order and ideologies are not the same in any two nations of the world.</p>
   <p>The administrations of Harding, Coolidge, and Hoover had no serious justification <pb facs="5422062_1_1516.jpg" n="2"/>for their refusal to recognize Russia, and neither were they forbidden to do so by international law. They followed the policy that was prescribed by the most conservative and selfish groups in America--which, curiously enough, were, in the majority of cases, the monied groups.</p>
   <p>Fortunately such policies and such groups are no longer acceptable to the political ideals of the American people, and will never be again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
