<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-08-06">Aug. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Double Baptism in the Stevens Hotel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-08-06">Aug. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">DOUBLE BAPTISM IN THE STEVENS HOTEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2- On last Sunday two prominent families of our community, those of Messrs. Xenophon Alafouzos and Antonios Benetas, celebrated magnificently the baptism of their daughters at the Stevens Hotel in the Presence of a select company of Greeks and Americans.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Antonios Benetas stood as godmother to Mr. and Mrs. Alafouzos's daughter. She named the child Thalia. The well-known importer, Mr. Wicholas Deligiannis, godfather of Mr. and Mrs. Benetas's daughter, gave her the names of Themis and Hea.</p>
   <p>After the ceremony all the guests sat down to a lavish supper in the dining-room of the Stevens Hotel. Among the guests were Mr. and Mrs. H. Bemetrios, Mr. and Mrs. Kicholas Deligiannis, Mr. and Mrs. Sarenzen, Mr. Green, Mr. Pulakis, Mr. Weikelt, Mrs. Karali, Mr. Sarensen, Mr. Dr. Green, Mr. Poulahis, Dr. Gavaris, Attorney Gavaris, Mr. and Mrs. Pangiotis Lambros and their daughter, and Dr. and Mrs. Papatheodorou.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0865.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Palaiologos Mammonas presided at the supper. The guests rose to drink a toast to the happiness of the newly-baptized children and their parents. Messrs. Alafouzos and Benetas replied with expressions of thanks to their guests.</p>
   <p>After the supper the company danced to the music of Mr. Alafouzos's orchestra and extended individually to their hosts their hearty congratulations.</p>
   <p>S. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
