<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-12-05">Dec. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">School Benefit Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-12-05">Dec. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL BENEFIT DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dance given by the Evangelismos Church of Chicago in behalf of its Greek school was a tremendous success. It was held last Saturday night in Turner Hall. The Hall was filled with hundreds of patriotic Greeks who realized the importance of making the affair a financial success.</p>
   <p>The sum raised by the dance amounted to four hundred dollars. The dance was held under the sponsor-ship of the Greek Bowling Club, which is composed of the following members: John Adinamis, George Maniates....</p>
   <p>Due to the sincere efforts of the gentlemen on the dance committee and to the whole-hearted support of the Greek community, the fund for the North Side Greek School is rapidly growing. Before long, Chicago will have three Greek parish schools in which to educate the children in their own language, customs, and religion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first Chicago Greek school was opened six years ago, and is now governed by the board of trustees of the Holy Trinity Church. It has an attendance of one hundred and fifty children of the West Side. At least eight hundred pupils have graduated from this school since it opened.</p>
   <p>The second school was opened by the St. Constantine Church on the South Side. It has an enrollment of over sixty children at present. It is evident that the North Side is badly in need of a Greek school to accomodate the children of that section. That is why strenuous efforts are being made to open a school in the Evangelismos parish.</p>
   <p>It would be a serious omission if we did not mention the name of Mr. Karambelas. He has been a pioneer in the Greek school movement, both here and in New York City. He addressed the group and was listened to attentively by all those present.</p>
   <p>We congratulate all who supported the worthy affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
