<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Journal</title>,
<date when="1918-04-26">Apr. 26, 1918</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, p. 88, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St., Chicago, Ill. Foreign-Born Residents and Liberty Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Journal</title>,
<date when="1918-04-26">Apr. 26, 1918</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, p. 88, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St., Chicago, Ill. FOREIGN-BORN RESIDENTS AND LIBERTY BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The foreign-born residents of Chicago have done well in subscribing to the third Liberty Loan and will do better before the campaign is ended. But they have not all done equally well. It is impossible to give figures as to proportionate subscriptions of many of the most zealous groups of alien-born people because in the census returns Bohemia, Poland, Lithuania, the southern Slavs, and many others are not recognized as nations.</p>
   <p>But the following table of nationalities which can be identified both in the census figures and in the Loan returns is well worth noting.</p>
   <p>Number by Nationality of Foreign-Born in Chicago Amount of Loan Taken</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Germans</cell>
     <cell>182,281</cell>
     <cell>$2,106,750</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Italians</cell>
     <cell>45,169</cell>
     <cell>1,280,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Greeks</cell>
     <cell>6,564</cell>
     <cell>1,100,000</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>In other words the Germans of Chicago, up to the date when the above figures <pb facs="5422062_1_1132.jpg" n="2"/>were compiled, had subscribed $11.57 per capita for Liberty bonds, the Italians $28.44 and the Greeks $167.83.</p>
   <p>There are one or two perfectly valid reasons why the Greeks should lead in any such per capita test. Adult males are found in the Greek colony in larger proportion than in any other group of foreign-born residents among us, and their commercial genius is as remarkable as their patriotism, their fighting capacity, and their fondness for education. These are the qualities which have enabled their race not merely to survive centuries of subjection to Turkish tyranny but even to be through all that period, as they are still, the intellectual and financial leaders of the Balkans.</p>
   <p>Even so, their record in buying Liberty bonds is superb.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
