<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Dance Given by the Socrates Greek School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANCE GIVEN BY THE SOCRATES GREEK SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3- Last Sunday the dance of the Socrates Greek School was conducted in the Ashland Auditorium with perfect orderliness and decorum.</p>
   <p>At 7 p. m. the guests began to arrive and by 9 o'clock both halls were filled with dancing couples.</p>
   <p>The teachers of the school were busy selling flowers; other members of the committee sold tickets of admission and took care of the bar and the buffet.</p>
   <p>In the largest room the couples danced European dances, while those in the smaller room danced Greek dances to the music of old fashioned Greek instruments.</p>
   <p>The majority of those in attendance were from the West Side; very few appeared from the North and South Sides. A dance like this, the purpose of which was to keep one of the largest and most perfect Greek schools in America, should have been attended by Greeks from all sections of the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The shop-keepers and other residents of the West Side should be thanked for their bountiful contributions of lambs, cheese, bread and pastries for the dance.</p>
   <p>The executive committee was constantly in motion and was really exhausted with its activities. Thanks are due also to the Greek orchestra which played free of charge for the sake of the school.</p>
   <p>The number of guests was estimated at three thousand, and the proceeds were very satisfactory and helpful to the school.</p>
   <p>The Greeks are noted for their lavish expenditure at social affairs and for their generosity, a national chacteristic.</p>
   <p>Saloniki, the defender of everything Greek, congratulates all and invites our compatriots to assist the School, which is the connecting link between us and the coming generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
