<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-25">Apr. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Academic Freedom and Freedom of the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-25">Apr. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ACADEMIC FREEDOM AND FREEDOM OF THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Freedom of speech has its drawbacks. A dumbell who happens to be teaching in a university classroom can say things which are just as silly and disturbing--even as dangerously near the seditious--as a dumbell in any other place. If the parents of university students do not happen to agree with some professor's line of talk, they can send their offspring to the class of another professor. If they do not relish the atmosphere of the university itself, they can send them to another. Professors without pupils and universities without teachers will soon join the bread line.</p>
   <p>We can find no fault with the action taken by Charles Walgreen in withdrawing his niece from the University of Chicago and notifying President Hutchins why. Mr. Walgreen is "unwilling" to have her "absorb the insidious communistic instruction to which she is exposed". He cannot understand why the University should "permit, even to a limited degree, seditious propaganda under the name <pb facs="5422062_1_0044.jpg" n="2"/>of "academic freedom".</p>
   <p>The young lady will go elsewhere to study, and the authorities know the reason why. We trust, however, that Mr. Walgreen will not join the group of university and school-baiters led by the Hearst newspapers and the Chicago Tribune which deny to educators the freedom of speech which they so jealously demand for themselves.</p>
   <p>There is much confused thinking in this time of change. Doubtless many teachers....are as confused as are newspaper editors, legislators, and businessmen. But the fact of change cannot be ignored. It should be studied and understood. Where should it be studied....if not under competent teachers with open minds, in a university?</p>
   <p>Change denotes progress, and no board of trustees of any university, and no school system with which we are acquainted, is competent to a greater extent than its teaching staff to turn the stop and go signals of progress along the ways of <pb facs="5422062_1_0045.jpg" n="3"/>political, economic, social, and industrial thought. It is man's nature to progress. There can be no progress without education. There can be no real education without the discovery of truth. And truth cannot be discovered without freedom of speech. If freedom of speech is suppressed education is smothered, and the world stands still. Civilization is the result of challenge and response. If a people "can't take it," if a nation will not look facts in the face, it begins to live in the past. Nations, as well as individuals, who are content to live in the past cannot expect much in the future.</p>
   <p>If free speech is taken from teachers, they become slaves to the thought of the past. Their pupils, in turn, take on the yoke of the same slavery. Repression and prohibition are twin handmaidens of ignorance and folly. Academic freedom has its glaring faults. Freedom of the press has just as serious faults. But we must endure both for the sake of our future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
