<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1934-09-01">Sept. 1, 1934</date><title level="a">The Crisis of Capital.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (c)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1934-09-01">Sept. 1, 1934</date><title level="a">The Crisis of Capital.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many believe that the present crisis is one of the many that have come and will go as did the ones in the past and that, gradually, things will resume their normal course. Few, however, know that the crisis we are experiencing for almost three years in America is a singular one, and that no companion can be drawn to those previous, as the causes of this crisis are wholly due to improved machinery, different methods of production, the reduction in the number of workers, and to overproduction.</p>
   <p>But the reduction in the number of workers, and overproduction, have as a direct consequence caused the reduction of profits and frequent losses.</p>
   <p>Capital, therefore, the value of which consists in creating profits, cannot possibly fulfill its mission, because no matter in what enterprise it be invested, cannot find a market due to prevailing unemployment. Even if unemployment is to be fought by a reduction in the hours of work, so that production will find a market capital again cannot create profits, because profits will be distributed by the workers among themselves, who, by working a few hours, would be paid in accordance to an integral rate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1486.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Consequently, in the first case as well as in the second, there is no more profit for capital, and just for that reason, capital today remains dormant. The present crisis, consequently, is a crisis of capital, which, by reason of new conditions, cannot perform the function which up to now it has fulfilled and continue to be used as the motive of production, generally, and distribution of produce.</p>
   <p>As a result, the great question arises: In so far as capital is unable to motivate industry and distribution, must we all stop doing anything about the matter and suffer death by starvation? The answer, of course, is not difficult, because all of us want to live, and if capital cannot serve us any longer, we must find other means and ways, wherewith, to distribute production and create new jobs.</p>
   <p>In so far as we have all the means of production in land, innumerable factories, workers working and are able to produce all we need, it would be the greatest folly to suffer, and not hasten to substitute in place of capital some system that will carry on for the benefit of all concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
