<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-05-29">May 29, 1928</date><title level="a">Mothers' Society Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-05-29">May 29, 1928</date><title level="a">MOTHERS' SOCIETY MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Today we will continue the publication of the minutes of the "Mother's Society" of the Greek School, Socrates, which will show how and what the mothers think of the scandal that has come up. It will show, how indignant the mothers are against the parasites of journalism and their libelers, who undertook professionally to defame the Greek school, appearing as its defenders allegedly, while in reality being double-dealers and slanderers.</p>
   <p>The voice of the mothers is the right judgement in this regrettable case, because the mothers are deeply concerned and feel the necessity, more than anyone else, of morality in the school. They are in a position to know things and persons better than anyone else.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Mouzakiotis, with profound emotion and with tears rolling down her cheeks, protested against the calumny and slander published against the teachers, G. Drosos and N. Lambrinides. She considered these slanders as against all the mothers and daughters who have attended and graduated from that school.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>She stated that Mr. Drosos was engaged as a private teacher for her children for a long time at her home. If he was late after the various school ceremonies and play presentations, he would often escort her daughters home in an automobile, and present them safely to their parents. They never had any grievance against him. The children loved and respected those teachers and had full confidence in them. Mrs. Mouzakiotis expressed her children's indignation for the slanders against the teachers and declared that men of such character and culture as Messrs Drosos and Lambrinides, could not possibly commit such malignant acts as the ones of which they are accused.</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. Tsipianitis expressed her satisfaction for the conscientious work of the teachers and their honest character. Mrs. T. Tsimboukas declared that her children, although of advanced age, have such a respect for their former teachers that whenever they meet them they stand at attention and salute them.</p>
   <p>Mrs. P. Kouri stated that her daughters felt very sorry for the slanders against their teachers whom they love and respect as much as their own fathers, and that she herself has no complaint whatsoever against them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0366.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. G. Samprakos opened an attack against the Executive Board of the Brotherhood for not having this meeting called sooner, so as to enable them to express their confidence and respect for the unjustly accused teachers and, as a mother of four children, expresses her full confidence in the teachers under whose tuition more than one thousand girls have graduated, without a single complaint being made.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Helene E. Nikolopoulos has stated that her daughter, a graduate of the school, had expressed her grief in not having higher grades so as to continue her courses. She succeeded, passing into high school from the sixth grade, in six months time.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Panagopoulos declares that she is very satisfied with the teachers and that she found Mr. Drosos to be very strict in his supervision of the conduct and attendance of the boys and girls.</p>
   <p>Mrs. P. Papaspyrou and Mrs. K. Hanea have expressed themselves to the same effect with the latter making the statement that she knew both teachers from Birmingham, Alabama.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0367.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Then Mrs. Helene Sakelariou and Mrs. Koralia Niakaris followed, the former with an indignant condemnation of the slanderers calumnies, with the assertion that, due to her profession, she visits most of the Greek families, and in ten years time never heard a complaint against the teachers, Drosos and Lamprinides.</p>
   <p>Many mothers (whose names follow-Translator) and others have expressed themselves likewise, with full confidence in the teachers. The President of the society asked if there were anyone who had a complaint against the teachers. All in unison cried, "No."</p>
   <p>Finally, after condemning aloud those who had dragged down the good name of the school and the morality of their daughters, the mothers asked for a resolution which was voted unanimously, whereby they went on record as upholding the teachers, Messrs G. Drosos and N. Lambrinides, with full confidence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
