<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-02">Feb. , 1927</date><title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-02">Feb. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, 1927</date><title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of establishing in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> fcollege according to the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>rican system, as been enthusiastically from the contributions secured, so far the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> which amount to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. We have, no doubt, that the Greeks of America also will hear the suggestion with <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> enthusiasm and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>liberally support it.</p>
   <p>Athens was lacking <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> an institution, despite the fact that it is the capitol of the nation, and is considered to be the center of Greek letters. The Greek colleges do not import enough knowlded <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to their graduates because their <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ain object is to prepare students for the University where they are taught a speech of profession.</p>
   <p>For those, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who do not desire to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> profession there was no higher school of an enc<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>clopedic education. Forthis reason, it was about time to establish such college of higher encyclopedic education.</p>
   <p>Up to a few wears ago the diploma of a College was a token of wide knowldge, and the diploma of a University was the crown of knowlege. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, however, <pb facs="5422062_1_0148.jpg" n="2"/>the Greek college education is not enough to reader a person educated, and the American system of colleges is indispensable for the completion of the encyclopedic education. From this point of view the inecessity of such an institution of higher learning Athens was indispensable.</p>
   <p>In addition, the teaching of the Greeks according to the American system in Athens, bring the two countries closer together. This must greatly stimulate the interest of the Greeks of America, who living for so many years were within America environment, ought to be interested for the development of American methods in Greece and, in fact, of everything beautiful that this country possesses.</p>
   <p>The new Greek generation in America, in particular, who have had the opportunity to attend courses in, and graduate from, the American colleges will especially be pleased to hear of a collegiate institution in Athens and, with great enthusiasm, will also promote the completion of the job.</p>
   <p>It should be the specific purpose of the Greeks in America to bring the two countries closer together, because such a contact would be beneficial to them both.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
