<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-09-01">Sept. 1, 1929</date><title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1007</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1007.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-09-01">Sept. 1<gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, 1929</date><title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the Greek, eating is an important event which takes place, usually, twice a day. Food is not only a necessity of life; it is a joy. A good cook, in the eyes of the Greeks, is superior to a doctor or an astronomer. The discovery of a star isn't important because thousands of other stars have been discovered. A doctor is concerned with curing sick people but a cook must feed healthy people and keep them that way.</p>
   <p>A Greek eats well, and takes two hours to do it. He will sit at the table with great solemnity, even if he partakes solely of bread and cheese. Food invites conversation. At the table, whether it is a simple affair or <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> there will be discussed a thousand subjects, serious, practical or flippant. An American will hasten to work with the last bite still in his mouth. A Greek has practically digested his food before rising from the table. Half of his life is spent at the table, in eating and conversing. "What are we going to eat today" and what shall we buy for tomorrow" are every-day phrases in Greek households.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1008.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to live! Everything else is secondary. In order to live well, he must eat and drink well. <gap unit="words" extent="3" reason="illegible"/> life. This is probably hereditary because <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> told, ate and drank plentifully.</p>
   <p>Americans <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> work--<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> the riches around us are the result of work. The Greeks are wiser than the Americans. Men who work hard lose the significance of their achievements. When you balance good-living and production, you will see that good-living is easier to achieve and more satisfactory. A friend once remarked to me, "You don't realize how I've learned to love Life."</p>
   <p>He forgot to mention that life as he saw it meant food and drink and plenty of both.</p>
   <p>You may work hard all your life and gather around your costly and rare objects, amusements, cherished possessions, but you will never enjoy them. You are too busy working.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1009.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Greek lives by eating and conversing. He converses most of the day, works a little, eats and drinks well and sleeps contentedly the whole night through.</p>
   <p>The laziest Greek is wiser than the hard-working American. His philosophy is, "Once I will live, thrice I will love and once I will die."</p>
   <p>
    <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>
   </p>
   <p>September, 1929</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
