<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Vournas, George C., <title level="a">"The Second Objective"</title> <title>Ahepa Magazine</title>, Washington, D.C.,
<date when="1932-12">Dec. 1932</date>, pp. 6-7.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0942</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0942.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Vournas, George C., <title level="a">"The Second Objective"</title> <title>The Ahepa Magazine</title>, Washington, D.C.,
<date when="1932-12">Dec. 1932</date>, pp. 6-7.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year 1933 will mark the completion of the tenth year since the founding of the Ahepa and generally speaking, the first third of a century from the commencement of the great influx of Greek immigrants to the United States. Whether we arrived in the United States by force of circumstances or as a result of economic pressure, the relentless task of earning a livelihood confronted us all. Today some of us feel that we can give a creditable account of our accomplishments in the economic field in America and some of us do not. One thing is certain--that the number of those who could point with pride to their successes is much lesser today than it was four years ago.</p>
   <p>Whether success crowned our efforts or not, it is safe to assume that by now both as Ahepans and as a part of the immigrant family in the United States, we have had ample time to adapt ourselves to our new environment, politically, socially, and economically. We have come to view America as our home and to be concerned with the affairs of our adopted country, <pb facs="5422062_1_0943.jpg" n="2"/>while in the earlier years our eyes were fixed toward the shores of our birthplace for any and all things that affected our lives. While the spiritual bonds uniting us to our Fatherland are dutifully maintained and we hope they will forever continue, our immediate concern is our home, our family, our welfare and that means the United States of America. That this fact is accepted by all persons and classes of our people today may be cited as an eloquent example of the beneficial import of the Ahepa and the successful culmination of the first part of its program and objective.</p>
   <p>The Americanization--political assimilation--of all persons of Greek descent in the United States having been practically completed, the time appears to be at hand to devote increasing attention to the second, but equally important task of our organization, to wit, "to promote throughout the world, and especially in the United States of America, a better and more comprehensive understanding of the Hellenic people and nation, and to revive, cultivate, enrich andmarshal into active service for humanity, the noblest attributes and highest ideals of true Hellenism."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0944.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We all have heard much about Hellenic "ideals and customs." We hear the swan song at every turn. No one, however, has taken or takes the trouble to reduce the often confusing generalities to specific principles and formulas and point the way to their practical application.When American-born children of Greek parentage ask questions regarding the "ideals and customs" of the land of their fathers, they seldom receive the same answer from two persons. Each individual gives his own version and idea depending on the locality of birth in Greece. In most cases, what goes under the label of Hellenic "ideals and customs" is closely related to what Spencer called "The Dead Hand"..the great mass of errors, myths prejudices that came down to us from the Dark Ages. Do we, as a class, possess any virtue or quality worthy of presentation? It is my sincere opinion that we do. I am also of the opinion, however, that a lot of debunking has to be done to what we call Greek "ideals and customs" before such ideals and customs can be useful to America and a twentieth century civilization.</p>
   <p>What can we do during the year 1933? We can set ourselves to the task of revaluation--determine in the light of knowledge and experience so far <pb facs="5422062_1_0945.jpg" n="4"/>gained, what to keep and preserve and what to forever drop and forget--retaining the Hellenic Formulas of the enlightened period of Greece and not of the Dark Ages. Ways and means must also be devised to harmonize the social and cultural views of those who were born here, with the end in view of creating a common objective. It goes without saying that undertakings of great magnitude such as this require the sincere cooperation and contributions of all thinkers, whether members of the Ahepa or not. Effective application of principles, however, can be carried out only by a disciplined organization. To this end, the best if not the one and only organization, blending the old and the new is the Order of Ahepa with its junior subdivision, the "Sons of Pericles."</p>
   <p>This organization constitutes not only the last hope for united effort but also the best available medium to carry out successfully what above has been referred to as the second objective. Enlightened self-interest dictates that we stand united and apply ourselves to the task with unfailing enthusiasm and determination. The undertaking is colossal.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0946.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The only way that we can preserve for our posterity the valuable right to point to Hellenic immigrant contributions to Americancivilization, however, is to come to grips with the problem. the problem. The time is here--now. The Ahepa cannot evade the responsibility.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
