<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1904-10-21">Oct. 21, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Public Schools Are the Bulwark of the Nation Schools Independent of the Church Are the Best</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1904-10-21">Oct. 21, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS ARE THE BULWARK OF THE NATION SCHOOLS INDEPENDENT OF THE CHURCH ARE THE BEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- With our Greek schools in America springing up like mushrooms beside Greek churches, the Greeks of Chicago and elsewhere are warned to bear in mind the futile efforts of the Church in the past to dominate public instruction. History tells us that the Church for many centuries took to itself the role of guardian of the entire education of youth. In Spain, Italy, Austria, Greece, and the other countries where the Church exercised such influence, and its superstitions flourished unchecked, the result was an increase in those dubious theories which are the precursors of sciolism. This happened simply because the complete education of youth was left in the hands of the Church, or rather the Church succeeded in dominating the education of youth.</p>
   <p>Under so superstitious an education ignorance, antagonism to science, and intolerable nonsense reached such heights that history records no other characteristic products of this theocratic education than religious dogmas, letters of blood, and the resigned submission of the populace.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0171.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The real educational system, under which the human mind expands cosmologically, and by which false theories and superstitions are routed, is to be found here in America. And we Greeks of America, for our own interest, the interest of coming generations, the interest of our adopted country, and the interest of the Church itself must accept this great American educational system, which is free from any ecclesaistical domination. Church is an imperative necessity for a nation, but School is the nation's whole life, and public schools, which are free from theocracy, are the real bulwarks of the country. Let us profit by the pitfalls into which others have fallen and maintain freedom of education if we wish to produce good, useful, broad-minded citizens whose knowledge and enlightenment will promote and protect the welfare of the Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
