<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-25">Apr. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Imitation</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-25">Apr. 25, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">IMITATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hitler, the imitation dictator of Germany, has lately begun to forget some of his former beliefs and policies. At first, he violently persecuted the Jews and ran them out of Germany. Those who did not run fast enough were murdered and their fortunes confiscated. Among the exiled was Einstein. Hitler forgot, however, that people like this great genius do not have their fortunes in their homes, but in their minds. Only death can rob Einstein!</p>
   <p>Recently, newspapers state, Hitler has refrained from violent persecution. Perhaps he finally realized the foolishness of such procedure. I cannot determine the cause of his sudden doubtful leniency. But I can say for certain that when Hitler ordered the persecution of the Jews, he proved himself to be a humskull--ignorant of history and of the psychology of the Jewish race. Is it the first time this race has suffered persecution? Of course not. All over Europe the Jews have been the victims of taunts and exile since 70 A. D. <pb facs="5422062_1_0908.jpg" n="2"/>And yet, they survive as a race, having lost neither their religion, their customs, nor their language.</p>
   <p>This imitation dictator is wasting his time and effort. He foolishly believes he is the discoverer of high explosives.</p>
   <p>Such and worse persecutions have been endured by the Jews since the time of Titus. The persecution they suffered under Titus was not only terrifying in its brutality; there was even something of grandeur in it. Nevertheless, the continuance of the race uninterruptedly, went on, and today the Jews say, what Seneca once said of them that the entire world is their birthplace. The truth of the statement is obvious to all. One cannot help but recall the description of what happened after Titus conquered the Jews and destroyed Jerusalem. As Christ had predicted: "They shall not leave stone upon stone".....</p>
   <p>What remains of that great triumphal display proclaiming victory in what <pb facs="5422062_1_0909.jpg" n="3"/>now is modern Rome? The ruins of the Roman Forum and the Tullianum, which testify to the success of Titus and the strangulation of Giyora [leader of the Jews]. But the race is still strong and powerful. It outlived Titus, as it will, no doubt, outlive Hitler.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
