<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1921-12-11">Dec. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Few Comments</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-12-11">Dec. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A FEW COMMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Saloniki,</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>It was with a great deal of pleasure that I read the article by Dr. Papatheodorou, in a previous issue. The article mentioned, was in answer to an article entitled "They Sometimes Come Back," that was written by Mr. K. Roberts and published in the Saturday Evening Post, September 10, 1921. I would like to take this opportunity to commend Mr. Papatheodorou on his patriotic feelings and his defense of his nationality....from the article of Roberts, a wrong impression of our people and country will be given....In regard to our great national cultural heritage, Mr. Roberts finds it difficult to believe we are the same group of people, <pb facs="5422062_1_1080.jpg" n="2"/>when he sees our present political and moral decline.</p>
   <p>Why is he, as a third party, blamed for writing what he sees and knows to be true? The existing conditions force other people to become severe critics of our country. For example: Aesop was born and raised in Greece. His inspiration for his instructive fables came from Greece, and yet the present inhabitants of Greece are not taught and are not familiar with Aesop's Fables.</p>
   <p>And, if we do accept the statement of Mr. Papatheodorou, that, Mr. Roberts underestimated and abused the present day Greeks, we must produce evidence of modern Greek contribution to science and to the betterment of mankind.</p>
   <p>And one desires to ask, "In the name of all that is holy and truthful, can <pb facs="5422062_1_1081.jpg" n="3"/>our nation, over a period of one hundred years, claim any way in which it has gained the respect and admiration of the civilized world? In business, in science, or in social advancement?</p>
   <p>Not only is it impossible to make any such claims, but even the present improvements in education and progress made by Venizelos were brought to an end.</p>
   <p>Signed,</p>
   <p>A Son of Greece</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
