<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-25">May 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Waiters' Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-25">May 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK WAITERS' UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Waiters' Union has sent the following letter for publication in the Saloniki:</p>
   <p>"On April 26, 1917, the Secretary of State of Illinois recognized the Greek Waiters' Union as an organization composed of the workers employed in restaurants, confectionary stores, and confectionary factories through out Chicago and surrounding territory.</p>
   <p>"The offices of the Union are located in the Cunard Building, 140 North Dearborn Street. The officers are John P. Sotiras, president; George Berry, secretary and treasurer; and George B. Pike, vice-president.</p>
   <p>The aims of the Union are to establish a twelve-hour working day and a six-day week. The employers of union members must be made to comply with these demands.</p>
   <p>The Union now has a membership of over two hundred."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1419.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We hope for the complete success of this union as it will aid most of the Greek workingmen. But we sincerely beseech the Union to see that all actions taken by its members shall be in a friendly spirit only. Conferences between employees and employers should be peaceful and pertaining to the point in question, for they must remember that these employers have worked hard to gain what they possess. The desire for social benefit and brotherly love should govern the future actions of both the Union and the capitalist groups.</p>
   <p>Upon this basis the Saloniki will gladly offer its services as an organ of the Union. We hope for a peaceful and friendly understanding between all concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
