<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Mixed Marriage (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MIXED MARRIAGE (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Marriage is considered to be one of the most important social problems. A common expression avers that a man is born, married, and dead only once. This editorial is written especially for those Greeks who marry not only once, but two and three times. We desire to publicly chastise the men who give the American people the impression that Greeks do not respect any but Greek women.....</p>
   <p>The theories of some low-minded men about the conduct and customs of either the Greek or American woman are fantastic. The truth of the matter is, that such low types of individuals cannot live a happy married life with any woman, regardless of her nationality.</p>
   <p>A woman always adjusts her life and her actions to suit the desires of the man she marries. She does this regardless of her nationality or her customs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0730.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since there is no race of Amazons alive, today, who would seek to dominate and rule their males, no just cause exists for the complaints and excuses of some Greek men.</p>
   <p>Due to an acute shortage of Greek women in America a few years ago, many Greek men married American girls whom they loved and respected. Any one who criticises them for marrying these women is a cad and a no-good.</p>
   <p>Examining this matter from the religious standpoint, we find that the marriage must be performed in the Orthodox Church if the children are to inherit any property in Greece.</p>
   <p>This does not impress us as being important enough to serve as a barrier to a mixed marriage. The important aspect is the social one. The men and women who desire to marry should submit to physical examinations in order to prove their fitness. In other words we believe in refined, desirable marriages of decent people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0731.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that adventurous-minded Greek men had other ideas on this subject. They were even foolish enough to make them known to the American people. They thought that marriage was not a serious matter to the American women; so they proceeded to get married to Polish or German women. Then when they tired of married life, these cads took their hats and left their homes and their wives, and went blithely on their way. This has occurred so many times that we do not believe that any American woman will ever marry a Greek man. We are all being judged by the actions of a few.</p>
   <p>A good woman, regardless whether she is a Greek or an American, is worthy of respect and consideration. We Greeks must realize this and change our tactics. If we do not we are sure to be ostracized by the American communities. We do not want such a stigma attached to the Greek name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
