<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-11">Dec. 11, 1929</date><title level="a">What American Thinks of the Greeks</title> By. J.M. Rife  
    <title level="a" type="sub">V. Getting an American Name</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0990</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0990.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-11">Dec. 11, 1929</date><title level="a">WHAT AMERICAN THINKS OF THE GREEKS</title> By. J.M. Rife  
    <title level="a" type="sub">V. Getting an American Name</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This may seem a trivial matter, but it is none the less aggravating to me. My complaint is that Greeks with perfectly good, and even noble sounding names usually adopt some cheap nickname to be known by in America. What makes the process particularly disgusting is that they usually get the wrong nickname. What American, unless he has made a special study of Greek immigrants, would ever dream that Tom, Bill, Gus, and Pete were baptized Athanasios, Basilios, Konstantinos, and Panagiotis.</p>
   <p>Are Americans to blame for originating these absurdities? Did they first apply them to the immigrant in ignorance of Greek and in disdain of foreigners? Or did such crude devices begin with the Greeks in their <pb facs="5422062_1_0991.jpg" n="2"/>ignorance of English, not knowing that Athanasius, Basil, and Constantine are perfectly good and respectable English names Not only good and respectable, but with a touch of dignity besides? Of course Panagiotis is a problem. I suppose the French "Toussaint" would be the best substitute in English. The English language has, from the time of the Norman conquest, been so strongly Gallicized that almost anything French will go in English. "Pete," of course, has nothing to do with Panagiotis, it is the nickname for Peter (Petros). Likewise, Will is for William, Gus for Gustavus, and Tom for Thomas. If your Greek name is Gouilielmos, Goustabos or Thomas, than call yourself Will, Gus, or Tom, but nor otherwise.</p>
   <p>I met a Greek one day who was naturalized with the ridiculous name "Bill Mike." It was a pity. A could not know how cheap and crude it sounded to English ears and the careless, disdainful naturalization officers had not had the common decency to suggest any more appropriate rendering of the euphonious Basilios Michael. What was the last outrage I heard perpetrated? The helpless infant's baptismal name was Eustathius, but the <pb facs="5422062_1_0992.jpg" n="3"/>proud papa told me, unless I am mistaken, that his name is "Charlie." Knowing that Karolos is no regular name, I said, "For goodness sake, "Pete!' What good Greek name are you desecrating now by trying to nick-name it 'Charlie?'"</p>
   <p>The American would normally expect Greeks to have respectable, even dignified names. I hope the Greeks will stop disappointing us in this respect. English has equivalents for most Greek names and I believe the rest can be found in French. The Greeks owe it to their own self-respect to show some slight measure of taste and discriminating in such an intimate matter is the adjustment of their names of English.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
