<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-01-16">January 16, 1926</date><title level="a">Formation of a Greek Labor Educational Society in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-01-16">January 16, 1926</date><title level="a">Formation of A Greek Labor Educational Society in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, January 10, 1926, one hundred Greeks congregated at the Hull House, Halsted and Polk Streets and formed the above mentioned organization.</p>
   <p>Its aim is, to elevate the ethical and intellectual standards of its members. It intends to install a library in a capacious hall, for reading purposes; it will give lectures of sociology and science. It will organize musical and dramatic classes, and in general, will guard the intellectual and cultural aspects of Greek workers in our community.</p>
   <p>The new society invites all the Greek ladies and gentlemen of the City, to become members, so that with the assistance of all, the aim of the society will be achieved. Our Greek working class is behind the times and very much lacking in the understanding of prevalent standards. The society urgently invites the educators and the intellectuals amongst the Greeks, to become members, so their lectures and enlightment will raise the standards of our workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The society further asserts, that the Greekmerchants of Chicago are commendable for their commercial and business success, but it regrets their negligence towards the Greek working class.</p>
   <p>The Greek worker, without using a subterfuge is not up to the prevalent intellectual standard of America, and it is our duty for the benefit of all to elevate him up to that standard.</p>
   <p>For further information and details apply either in person or by mail to Mr. Constantine Chrysafidis, secretary, 610 South Halsted Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
