<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-05-02">May 2, 1931</date><title level="a">Impoliteness Rewarded</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-05-02">May 2, 1931</date><title level="a">IMPOLITENESS REWARDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- Panagiotis K.--, a restaurateur, is one of the few Greek Restaurant Keepers, who does not know what politeness is. This unsuccessful "hash-slinger" is short in body and barrel-like but very swift of movement when it comes to collecting money from his patrons. When a customer asks for a second piece of butter, he is absolutely immovable.</p>
   <p>Last Tuesday afternoon, the restaurateur was sulky and depressed, due to the fact that his till was not loaded up with the almighty quarters and dimes. A cake salesman walked in to collect the price of a cake he had left in the morning. One eighth of the cake was unsold and the barrel-like "Pork Roast," Panagiotis K., ordered the cake salesman to take it back. The trained cake salesman complied with the request of the restaurant keeper, took it back, and asked fifty cents for the portion that was sold. The proprietor with incivility threw twenty-five cents on the cigar case and commanded the poor salesman to leave.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1378.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The cakeman, in vain, endeavored to explain the injustice done to him but the Greek, with a cigar butt in his mouth, which he had picked up from under the counter, refused to acknowledge the pleading of the cake man. The latter, after exhausting every means of salesmanship, patience and politeness, threw the returned cake straight at the bovine head of the Greek. The aim was good and the lemon cream cake made an appropriate decoration on the face of the obstinate Panagiotis K.--</p>
   <p>The fundamental principles of success in business are honesty, integrity, politeness, service and quality. The unfortunate Greek, has no such words in his vocabulary as yet.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
