<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title><date when="1935-09-19">Sept. 19, 1935</date>,

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title><date when="1935-09-19">Sept. 19, 1935</date>,
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>a cultural and socially desirable one. It takes him far from those influences which are so bad for his mind and morals.</p>
   <p>There are various ways in which Greek youth can acquire a good education. The best and most productive one of which we know is attendance at a daily Greek school or at daily Greek classes. When children receive Greek instruction from an early age they retain their Greek heritage for the rest of their lives. The afternoon schools do their best to influence the youngsters in this direction, but the daily schools, such as Socrates, are the most effective. Their success is due to the fact that they get the children before they attend American public schools and begin to think knowledge of the Greek language unnecessary. After entering the public school they learn to think in English and quickly forget how to speak their own language. Moreover, afternoon classes are very tiring for children who have already spent a day in school. The pupils in these classes may benefit by learning Greek, but their health constantly suffers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0222.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If our children are to learn Greek letters at the expense of their health by becoming nervous, run-down, and tired, it is better that they do not learn them. We cannot benefit from a young generation of ailing people, no matter how much Greek they know or, how much they love things Greek. An inspection of the children attending afternoon schools reveals the fact that most of them are tired, pale, hungry, and listless.</p>
   <p>If the directors of the Greek afternnon schools nave not become aware of the seriousness of this situation, it is the duty of the parents to do something about it. Then, the question arises: What? The answer is comparatively simple. Through united effort they can build daily schools, such as Socrates--only better--and keep them functioning by urging the enrollment in them of all Greek children.</p>
   <p>No one must be allowed to believe that children will be retarded by attending Greek schools. On the contrary, records reveal that they usually have better work and study habits than children from other grammar schools.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
