<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-04">Sept. 4, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">How to Organize Our Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-04">Sept. 4, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">HOW TO ORGANIZE OUR SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is not the first time that we are compelled to say that The Greek State has abandoned the Hellenism of America to its fate. We are afraid we must emphasize this many times before the Greek government takes cognizance of the fact. We make again the accusation against the government that it has cruelly abandoned the 500,000 Greeks of America to their fate. The occasion of our stressing this today is the opening of the schools in which the Greek children of America will be taught the Greek language and the history of the land of their fathers.</p>
   <p>In saying that the Greek government has abandoned the Greek people of America we do not mean to say that the people need any material aid, or support from the Greek State. What we mean as the lack of aid, in nurturing the ideals of Hellenism in America, aid in the establishment and continuance of Greek schools; aid in the efforts of the Greek people here to preserve their national identity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0360.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such an endeavor is worthy of support because its arm is the furthering of the national interests, and the accomplishment of this aim lies beyond the power of the Greeks in America, unaided.</p>
   <p>We avail ourselves of the occasion of the opening of the schools, because in the schools, for the maintenance of which, so many efforts and sacrifices have been made by the Greek communities of America, lie all hopes for the keeping alive the new generation The Greek language and the traditions of the Greek race.</p>
   <p>But how is it possible for the Greek communities, despite all their efforts, to be transformed into boards of education, or Superintendents of schools, to know the ability of the teachers to be able to arrange the school programs and teaching material, factors upon which the successful functioning of the school depends?</p>
   <p>It is to be questioned whether there is even suitable teaching; personnel! But even if there is, how can this personnel function without adequate supervision?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0361.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It must be understood, that by schools we do not mean merely buildings furniture equipment or even the teachers and the pupils considered number of pupils, nor that of teachers separately.</p>
   <p>The principle thing is organization combined with intelligent supervision. It is labor in vain to erect magnificent school buildings, furnish them, assign teachers to them and encourage parents to send their children to these schools when we know that these schools lack proper organization and proper supervision.</p>
   <p>Since those whose duty it is to support the institutions morally are indifferent to the perpetuation of the ideals of Hellenism, much of the purpose of Greek schools is lost.</p>
   <p>The communities and churches are struggling desperately for the preservation of the schools, and their efforts were worthy of all praise. The task, lies beyond their power.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0362.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When the state does not choose representatives worthy of their mission, but sends officials who are not in touch with the Greek people here at all how is it possible for such a state to be informed of the needs of the people and to be able to render them its moral aid and support.</p>
   <p>When the State has severed the Ecclesiastical bonds with the Greeks of America without justifiable cause; when the State tends to keep these Greeks divided to the detriment of the national interests, how is it possible for Hellenism to preserve its national entity? How can it organize and manage its schools?</p>
   <p>On account of this, it is imperative to that these matters be placed before the Greek government directly, by the Greek people themselves since the state's representatives, unfortunately hold themselves aloof from the people and do not sense this great need.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
