<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-01-07">Jan. 7, 1932</date><title level="a">Greek Women in Business</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0815</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0815.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-01-07">Jan. 7, 1932</date><title level="a">GREEK WOMEN IN BUSINESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- A new year is beginning and the economic condition is bringing in a new order in Greek households. Many have marvelled at the Greeks who have been able to keep their daughters and wives out of the commercial field.</p>
   <p>The war was a turning point in the lives and affairs of the feminine world. Still wives and daughters of Greek born American citizens remained at home. They learned housekeeping and were content to stay at home or visit with friends during the day. Married women who worked were shunned. Their children were going wild and their housekeeping was a sight to see, it was said. If a young Greek girl worked, she was thought to be spoiled and could not get married as easily as one who stayed at home all day. Stern fathers and mothers would not think of letting a girl go out alone.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0816.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nowadays our Greek fathers see many advantages in letting their daughters go to work. In the first place, the extra income, no matter how small, is always gladly welcomed. In case the father of a family dies and there is no son to carry on, business experience will prevent the girls and the widow from being entirely dependent. Women are learning the value of money and the importance of being able to meet and judge people. They are being broadened mentally.</p>
   <p>No one, man or woman, should be ashamed to work. In times of need, work is one's salvation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
