<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-11-27">Nov. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Social Problems</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Reverend Hadzidimitriou Discusses Marriage and the Family Group</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-11-27">Nov. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL PROBLEMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Reverend Hadzidimitriou Discusses Marriage and the Family Group</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I desire to take this opportunity to publicly congratulate the editor of the Saloniki. He serves the community well by presenting articles on subjects of great social importance. These articles are arousing public discussion and reaction, and are, therefore, very beneficial.</p>
   <p>We have other journalists and other newspapers in Chicago, but they carefully refrain from writing anything to stir thoughts and comments of the people. Perhaps they are afraid to throw a few rays of light into the darkness, because their own sins and deficiencies might be brought to light. The Saloniki is striving very hard to improve the social and living conditions of the Greeks in Chicago, and in all of America, and for that reason is worthy of the highest praise.</p>
   <p>And finally, I come to the topic under discussion--marriage. I do not enter <pb facs="5422062_1_0733.jpg" n="2"/>the arena just to exhibit my great mental abilities; but because, as a servant of the Church, I am concerned with the solution of this matter.</p>
   <p>In order to speak intelligently on any subject, it is necessary to be familiar with it in all of its aspects. No man can be a good judge of a matter where he is only partially acquainted with the matter. Another man might consider himself an equally good judge, but he may be familiar with the same subject from the directly opposite standpoint. Neither one is completely right or completely wrong; for each is right within his own limited vision but both may be wrong when the matter is considered from all angles.</p>
   <p>The Church has always tried to seek the entire truth, and I would like to expound its beliefs and teachings concerning marriage and children.</p>
   <p>The Church considers the marriage ceremony to be a sacred ritual, and it also feels that each individual is free to enter or stay out of marriage.</p>
   <p>The Church respects the liberty and rights of all individuals and does not <pb facs="5422062_1_0734.jpg" n="3"/>forbid or command anyone to marry. Each person is free to marry or to remain single. These conditions impose certain responsibilities that must be recognized by all. A man is free to remain unmarried but that does not mean that he is free to live a dissolute life; or in any way to demoralize or harm the characters of others....</p>
   <p>A man that choses to remain unwedded should also remain in an innocent state. Many times he will be able to use all his suppressed energies to help make a success of his career; and he may even become a benefactor of humanity.</p>
   <p>A man is also given the right to take a woman unto himself; not in order to satisfy his carnal passions, but to have a companion and a helper in his daily existence.</p>
   <p>He who prefers marriage must be honorable in his actions, and true and faithful to his chosen mate at all times. He must provide proper care for his mate and for any children that are born. He must make any sacrifices that may be required of him in order to provide and maintain a good home for his family, and he must also see to it that they are provided with the necessities of life.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0735.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Church believes that marriage is for the purpose of bearing children, and not for the satiation of physical emotions. Children compensate parents for the sacrifices they made, and they inspire the parents with ambition and zeal. Numerous and worthless offspring, of course, is not what the Church desires. It believes in moderate-sized families, so that the children can be properly brought up.</p>
   <p>But a new stream of thought and ideology has influenced the minds of the people, especially in America. Up to this time, the Church--in order to protect the marriage ceremony--granted divorce only to those who were wedded to a partner unable to reproduce or bear children. Divorce could be gotten only from incompetent, syphilitic, tubercular or barren mates.</p>
   <p>Now people say that it is foolish to be governed by the rules of the Church; because the rules date from the time of the middle ages, and are out of step with these modern times.</p>
   <p>A new theory is blinding the people. "What do we want children for?" cry the <pb facs="5422062_1_0736.jpg" n="5"/>married couples of today. They also say: "How can we support them and give them good educations in these hard times?"</p>
   <p>But these people refuse to take into consideration a very simple illustration; namely, "if many work--so many eat, and many eat--so many work". The fewer the number of people, the less results will be obtained. The greater number of people will result in greater gain.</p>
   <p>Saloniki, Dec. 4, 1915.</p>
   <p>Although responsibilities and needs increase directly proportionate to the number of children, there are more to share the burdens of these responsibilities.</p>
   <p>There are some who say that the civilized lands will become overpopulated. That is quite doubtful but let us, for the sake of argument, agree that the earth will become crowded. Very well! But have all parts of the world been civilized? How can we be afraid of overcrowding the earth when there are still large tracts that are virgin territory? Is it possible to believe that these <pb facs="5422062_1_0737.jpg" n="6"/>will also become overpopulated?</p>
   <p>Can anyone convince himself that the egoism, the sins, [I believe he is modestly referring to birth-control], and the faults of man will permit him to multiply until the earth is crowded to the point of suffocation? And will it be possible for humans to exist without having wars, murders, suicides, and other life-destroying actions?</p>
   <p>Are we to take the word of individuals who do not believe in an immortal life, and who dare to doubt the decrees and existence of a Supreme Being?</p>
   <p>Let us cease to worry, and debate on this subject. We are not capable of governing the universe; therefore let us abide by the commands of the Creator of this universe. Let us not doubt the wisdom of one who can see where we cannot.....</p>
   <p>Mr. C. S. says that plutocrats encourage large families; as do also the tyrants and clergymen. Did he ever consider that plutocrats and tyrants are a result <pb facs="5422062_1_0738.jpg" n="7"/>of natural human failings? Many of them were born into poor and large families; and many came from small families. Why, should the size of the family be blamed for the selfish motives of one member of it? Would we not all be plutocrats if we were given the opportunity? Of course we would! Tyrants and plutocrats are the results of strong, egoistic tendencies in mens' characters. They are not the results of either large or small family groups.</p>
   <p>Or does Mr. C. S. think that plutocrats and tyrants would cease to exist if there were fewer people on the face of the earth? Or, perhaps, he thinks that everyone could then be a plutocrat, and, therefore, no one would ever suffer deprivations?</p>
   <p>I am surprised that Mr. C. S. referred to the clergy last; usually they are the first to be used as targets by the intelligentsia of all the ages.</p>
   <p>The clergy will never benefit from a constantly increasing population. Their duties will be increased, but in no way will they gain materially; for most <pb facs="5422062_1_0739.jpg" n="8"/>people feel that a priest should donate his time and his services. If the population is greatly reduced then the number of clerics will also be reduced, but they will never cease to exist as some individuals predict hopefully.</p>
   <p>Cities have existed without forts; but, no race has ever existed that did not have a firm belief in some kind of God or religion. The outstanding example is the Christian religion. If every individual was a true Christian, with a pure and innocent soul, there would be no social problems to be solved. Everyone would be happy and contented, and the ones that condemn and criticise the clergy today would be their most ardent defenders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
