<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">The Festival of the Greek School Solon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">THE FESTIVAL OF THE GREEK SCHOOL SOLON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the school festival of the Greek-American Educational school, Solon, under the auspices of the Church of Annunciation (Evangelismos), took place. This school was built on the North Side of our city in an ideal spot and is the last word in the art of building. It cost $200,000, and has been completed only a year. It is affiliated with the Church of the Annunciation and the parish of St. James. Just as the Church of Annunciation, whose priest is Rev. Nikitas Kesses, so does the school, Solon, with its church, St. James, whose priest is Rev. D. Sakellarios, truly deserve the respect of Chicagoland, for this fine showing which is due entirely to the indefatigable work of the members of the Church and the Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>This scholastic holiday of the Greek pupils of Solon school started at 4:00 o'clock and ended about 7:30. With only a year's establishment, there are enrolled 100 pupils in the school, who, directed by their teacher, Mrs. Basiliki Xrisostenou, presented their various poems, recitations, songs, plays, dialogues, etc. with such success that the audience applauded them again and again to show their pleasure and surprise.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0342.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The best part of the program was when Mr. George Kampas and his orchestra played four well chosen musical selections. His pupils, all Greek boys, truly astonished their listeners by their progress with the violin.</p>
   <p>Later, the principal of the school, Mrs. Xrisostenou, explained the purpose school festival. She spoke of the purpose of the school and the education parents owe to their children. She finished by thanking the Board of Directors and the members of both churches, as well as the Greek Ladies Educational Society taking active part in the building and maintaining of the wonderful school building. She thanked, in particular, Miss Isminin G. Papageorge, for accompanying the songs of the students on the piano; Mr. Spiros Bekatoron, who taught the songs; the Rev. Nikitas Kesses, and Mr. Monembasites (Manos) vice-president of the Church, whose diligent efforts did much towards making the event a success; and Miss Benetia Tomaras, teacher, whose intelligence and patience contributed much to the education of the children of Solon school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
