<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. C. Mammon</title>, 208 S. La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1914-04-14">April 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">(Letter sent by the Achaian League to Associated Press)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. C. Mammon</title>, 208 S. La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1914-04-14">April 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">(Letter sent by the Achaian League to Associated Press)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Associated Press:</p>
   <p>We have been witnessing a spectacular and circus-like advertising campaign concerning the announced incognito visit to the United States of Queen Eleonora, the Queen of Bulgars, and it is apparent that no trick or device has been overlooked to give the widest publicity to Queen Eleonora as if she was about to go on the stage or to take the platform on the Chautauqua circuit.</p>
   <p>If we are not mistaken the Queen's novelty-like undertaking has the same object in view as that of the late campaign of defamation given against the Hellenes.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1160.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Reports and cablegrams are coming in, in rapid succession from headquarters and enterprising press agents to effect that the Hellenes of the United States are in a resentful mood over the coming of Eleonora and these reports would have the world think that the Hellenes are fearful, as if Eleanora  <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> triumphantly marching against Marathon or Salamis or <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> destruction to all things Hellenic.</p>
   <p>We wish to emphasize that the Hellenes have no ill-feeling towards Queen Eleanora or her subjects, and we regret that such reports should be circulated, reflecting as they do, on the Hellenes. We, however, hope that Queen Eleanora will confine her activities to studying the conditions in this country and to praising her own subjects, without gratuitously assailing the character of the Hellenes and the Hellenic Army as was lately done by advertised advocates of the Bulgar cause.</p>
   <p>As for the Hellenes of the United States we beg to state that they will join with the other Americans in making Queen Eleonora's visit to the United States at pleasant personally and as successful financially as anyone could desire and in saying this we feel that we express the sentiments of all the Hellenes of the United States.</p>
   <p>The Achaian League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
