<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-18">Aug. 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Italo- before the Court</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-18">Aug. 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">ITALO-<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> BEFORE THE COURT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2--Last Thursday an Italian named Tony Arante and Bovannes, a Greek, appeared before the bar of justice charged with disorderly conduct and disturbing the peace. The evidence showed that the Italian provoked and started the fight, and the Greek victoriously finished it. Consequently the Greek was discharged, for the court said that "he had every right to defend himself."</p>
   <p>These two foreigners, who thus far have failed to Americanize their manners and use their fists in manly combat, have fruit stands opposite each other at 75 and 74 South Halsted Street. Naturally they are competitors and antagonists. The Greek, since he was able to buy at lower prices than the Italian could find, was selling his fruit for half what his competitor charged and consequently froze out the Italian. When the Italian's fruit began to decay for lack of customers, he got rid of some of it by throwing it at the Greek across the street. The Greek resented this and informed the scion of the Romans that if the assault was repeated, of course he would be compelled to use the Mosaic law and retaliate. The swarthy mountaineer <pb facs="5422062_1_1332.jpg" n="2"/>of Calabria, who was adept at throwing stones to kill birds for a meal, welcomed the Greek's challenge, depending on his dexterity at throwing and anticipating with pleasure the revenge which he would exact from the Greek, for the latter would be compelled to throw good fresh fruit.</p>
   <p>The battle began. The fresh, solid fruit in the hands of the descendant of ancient discus-throwers brought victory and also the police of the riot squad, responding to frenzied calls that a Greek was murdering a poor innocent Italian whose head and face were unrecognizable with bruises and the juice which spurted from the Greek's solid fruit. Bad business indeed--very bad. We are living in a great metropolis where a pitched battle of that kind gives credit neither to the Greek fruit merchant nor to the Greek community. Adjacent property and business, as well as the safety of pedestrians, are jeopardized by battles like this. The Greek, in spite of his right to defend himself (as the court decided), in spite of his victory over the challenger, and in spite of what others of his kind may say to justify his action, gets no credit from us, who are interested not in the outcome of the fruit-battle but in upholding the good name of Greeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
