<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-15">June 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Education as a Weapon in Life</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-15">June 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION AS A WEAPON IN LIFE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who read the American newspapers often see articles about the group of professors and professional men who have been chosen by the President as his advisors. Many believe, and rightly so, that the upturn of business is due to the insight and direction of men of high intellectual training. They well understand the national situation and know how to better it.</p>
   <p>We are one of those who believe that only through the education and the refining of the individual will the Golden Age ever be reborn. That is why we view the brilliant attainments of the Greek boys and girls in the American high schools and colleges with such tremendous pride and joy. The majority of Greek parents have had no opportunity to go to school themselves, and so they feel the lack of an education in this modern scientific world. They have determined to send their children to school even if it means many sacrifices and hardships on their own part.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0069.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let no one imagine that a little learning is enough. No one can ever learn too much. In fact, a little learning is worse than none at all. Only an extensive education is of large benefit--especially in times like these, when the demands made upon life are so overwhelming.....The educated men are the ones who will always be in a position to look ahead, because they know what has happened in the past.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
