<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-07-11">July 11, 1931</date><title level="a">Defenders of Greek Idealism</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Attorney Andrew Vlachos.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-07-11">July 11, 1931</date><title level="a">DEFENDERS OF GREEK IDEALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Attorney Andrew Vlachos.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Among the great Greek intellectuals, who are upholding Greek idealism in this country, Andrew Vlachos, Assistant States Attorney of Cook County, is a leader.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos, in a recent speech urging the new generation to add to their studies the Greek language said,</p>
   <p>"The treasuring up in the mind, of the world's best thoughts and feelings, has been a never failing source of happiness to many. And the best thoughts of the world are to be found in the minds of the Greeks."</p>
   <p>But some will say, "I will get my knowledge of Greek literature from translations." Many of the translations are good but, after all, they are not the real thing, only chromes of the real picture. Niagara may be seen in pictures or photographs and described in books, but these are not equal to the effect of few moments observation of the magnificent Falls.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0089.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Greek literature is a marvelous and wonderful field of human experience which helps us deal with human nature, today. Euripides says that, "Experience teaches us all that we know; but reading is a short cut to experience." Science helps us get a living; psychologic studies like Greek, teach us how to live.</p>
   <p>Further, those who wish the best foundation for culture or for any active career, today, should not omit Greek. Those who do not study it may reach a certain degree of excellence in their career, but not the highest.</p>
   <p>The Greek language is unsurpassed in precision, exactness, diversity and beauty of expression. Greek is the most beautiful instrument of speech that man has ever possessed.</p>
   <p>The fact that you are born and raised in this country is not a detriment and an impediment in acquiring a knowledge of the Greek language and Greek idealism. On the contrary, your American education is a great factor in <pb facs="5422062_1_0090.jpg" n="3"/>helping you to master the mother language of literature. We are looking upon you, the new generation, not only to study and learn Greek literature, but to surpass us and become torch-bearers in guiding the world to the colossal treasure of the Greek language.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
