<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-22">Mar. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Effect of Environment on Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0779</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0779.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-22">Mar. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE EFFECT OF ENVIRONMENT ON CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What makes a man that which he is--his environment or his inheritance? This is one of the most serious problems confronting sociologists and psychologists today, since they desire to improve the world, and so are trying to discover the causes of man's actions. If we take a small child and place it in an ideal environment, will it grow up having a fine character and healthy spirit, or will it be guided by its inherited traits, and live in antithesis to his environment?</p>
   <p>In scientific language, an ideal environment does not mean wealth or influential parents, nor does it mean easy living. The good environment is one in which a child can grow naturally and have, as an example, the conduct of two good parents. Their language manners, actions, and thought expressions will greatly influence the child, who is continually watchful of his elders.....In such an atmosphere, how is it possible for children <pb facs="5422062_1_0780.jpg" n="2"/>not to acquire consideration, gentleness, honor,and high ideals along with their school training? How can children use coarse language to one another when they never hear their parents use such?</p>
   <p>A good environment is most essential for our children today. Too often the home environment has to contend with the outer influences to which children are necessarily exposed. There are many evil influences against which children can be fortified if their parents are cognizant of this fact. Once the characters of these young ones become properly developed, there will be less to fear. The effect of training is hard to eradicate from the mind. So we must make sure our children are properly and continually taught to do what is best for them and the society in which they live.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
