<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-03-18">Mar. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-03-18">Mar. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Turks conquered Greece, they took certain steps to prevent the people from remembering their language and their customs, in order that Greek children might be reared as Turks. The first action taken was the closing of all Greek schools.</p>
   <p>Greek children thereafter attended secret night schools underground. They trembled with fear as they went to hidden mountain passes to receive a little bit of education from the few monks and teachers who remained alive. Hidden away in these rude caves and buildings, they learned Greek and history and received religious instruction.</p>
   <p>As these little Greek children walked long distances to school through the darkness of night, they sang a little song, which will never be forgotten..... [Translator's note: This song is loved by all Greeks. It is an appeal to the <pb facs="5422062_1_0444.jpg" n="2"/>moon to shine brightly and light the path for the children going to school.]</p>
   <p>In such manner were the Greek language and religion kept alive; and so was the freedom of Hellas finally regained.</p>
   <p>All this, however, is what we call ancient history. What are we doing today?</p>
   <p>Not because of the Turks but for a reason quite opposite we must address our entire attention to the problem of education. How are we to educate and train our children, born in this liberal land, in our language and religion?</p>
   <p>This is not the first time that we have asked this question of the Greeks in America. And it will not be the last time, unless real action is taken.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, our efforts to systematize and unite the Greek churches have <pb facs="5422062_1_0445.jpg" n="3"/>failed. This failure is due to the indifference of the community, and this may be charged to the influence of various Greek papers, of which the chief purpose is to create dissension among the Greek people. They devote much space to articles causing hatred and feuds among churches and among certain groups because they feel that it promotes their personal interests to do so. They do not devote a single column to anything that will help unify and strengthen the Greeks in America.....</p>
   <p>We have appealed through our columns to the three Greek churches of Chicago to unite. The basic purpose of this unity is to build enough Greek schools to let the thousand Greek children now being educated in American schools receive instruction in their religion and in their language.....</p>
   <p>Fortunately our appeal has done some good. The councils of the three church parishes have appointed a central committee. This committee has <pb facs="5422062_1_0446.jpg" n="4"/>established a fund for the benefit of needy families, and fifty families have received financial help this year. When this fund has been increased, more families will be aided throughout the city.</p>
   <p>We are glad to see that our repeated efforts have at least accomplished some results. But this is not enough!</p>
   <p>We need schools for more than a thousand Greek children!</p>
   <p>We need boarding schools for another thousand who live near Chicago but are not near any Greek school. Their patriotic parents would be very willing to pay tuition for their children to a well-regulated school of high standards.</p>
   <p>A few years ago, the parishes united long enough to purchase a large piece of land in a central location. Six years ago the building on this land was occupied by a Greek school. Two hundred pupils are enrolled in the school at present,....but the building is not a desirable one nor adequate to the <pb facs="5422062_1_0447.jpg" n="5"/>needs of a school.</p>
   <p>It is not properly equipped; it has not desks and seats enough to accommodate the pupils. The teaching facilities are so poor that of 450 children who enrolled at the beginning of the semester, only 175 remained. The others were transferred to the American schools, where at least there is room to sit comfortably.</p>
   <p>Holy Trinity Church gives $250 a month towards the maintenance of the school, but this sum is insufficient. The parents are supposed to give only one dollar a month. It is a small sum, but it is a sufficient excuse for sending the children to the American schools.....</p>
   <p>Our ever helpful and progressive consul, Mr. Nick Salopoulos, with the aid of the Reverend Leon Pygeas and Mr. B. Georgakopoulos, G. Sellas, J. Agriostathi, and B. Doukas, has endeavored to raise this amount of $250 <pb facs="5422062_1_0448.jpg" n="6"/>to $700 a month.....They took up a collection among themselves and raised $500, which is in the custody of Mr. Sellas, who acts as treasurer.</p>
   <p>This committee intends to work hard and to raise sufficient funds to enlarge the school and buy proper equipment. They intend to collect enough money to make the school adequate for five hundred pupils in September.</p>
   <p>These facts are staring Chicago Greeks in the face. A thousand Greeks are needed who will give three cents a day or a dollar a month to the school fund.</p>
   <p>That is all that is needed!</p>
   <p>Saloniki has never before started a campaign to raise money; but it is starting one right now!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0449.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>We will give sixty dollars a year--five dollars a month, or seventeen cents a day--to this fund.</p>
   <p>In order to set a good example, we have already mailed a check to Mr. Sellas. And we hope that within one month we can publish the names of a thousand Greeks who will give three pennies a day to help the thousand children of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The money may be sent to Mr. Sellas or directly to the office of Saloniki. We will publish the names of all contributors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
