<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-11-01">Nov. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Gambling and the Coffeehouse</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-11-01">Nov. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">GAMBLING AND THE COFFEEHOUSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the winter season is approaching, the gambling epidemic is taking its toll, if one may judge from the police reports.</p>
   <p>Around the gambling tables of our Greek neighborhoods you will find scores of our people in smoky, stuffy, filthy rooms, swearing, gesticulating violently, and with the most disgusting expressions on their faces. These men are spending and gambling away their savings and hard-earned money by associating with confidence men and professional gamblers, whose job it is to fleece their victims after encouraging them and giving them some hope of winning.</p>
   <p>Is it not utterly foolish to entrust your luck to the turn of the cards? No cardplayer is ever satisfied. In these gambling hideouts you will hear the wretched losers swearing at God and all the saints.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0649.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are not opposed to the Greek coffeehouses as such, for they are good business enterprises and social centers when they are properly operated and patronized by good people. Many circumstances have contributed to the establishment and development of the institution of the coffeehouse among the Greeks. Many friends have the opportunity to meet in the coffeehouse, and engage in interesting conversation about business, politics, or anything else. In this case, the coffeehouse is not in danger of becoming a gambling place; it is simply a pleasant meeting spot. The open-air orators find an opportunity to "address" the crowd around the coffeehouse tables in the summer time.</p>
   <p>Gambling is the coffeehouse's black spot. There are very few coffeehouses which have not been raided, and whose owners and patrons have not been taken to the police station on a gambling charge. We do not know whether this condition should be attributed to the coffeehouse owners or to the gambling instinct of the patrons. Not infrequently, after the police have cleaned out the gambling nests, the arrested gamblers continue their disrupted game in the prison cell.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0650.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus, we have two problems before us: the coffeehouse and the gambling joint. We will touch upon these two subjects again when we take up the labor question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
