<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-12-11">Dec. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Religion and the Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-12-11">Dec. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">RELIGION AND THE SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have stated, a short time ago, that the Greek children being educated in the American public schools are entirely without religious teaching, while the American children are regularly given Bible lessons in their churches and synogogues.</p>
   <p>This is of no small consequence to the Greek race in America. The result will be a generation of men and women who have no religious faith or training.</p>
   <p>In this case it is very simple to determine the guilt of those who permit such a condition to exist. No one is responsible for such a condition except the Greek Orthodox Church and the Greek communities. If they allow these conditions to continue, due to their indifference, they are going to lose the entire <pb facs="5422062_1_0453.jpg" n="2"/>new generations of Greek-Americans.</p>
   <p>The Catholic Church, famous for the administration of its schools and churches, is a good example to our negligent church. The Catholic church spends hundreds of thousands of dollars every year for the founding and maintenance of their schools, in which thousands of children are enrolled each year. These children are of various nationalities, such as, Irish, German, French, Spanish, Italian, etc., and they are given complete training in the dogma and creed of the Catholic church.</p>
   <p>Just imagine, thousands of children being sent to parochial schools, instead of public schools, in order that they might be kept in the church.</p>
   <p>The Archbishop of the Catholic Churches of Chicago, George Mundelein, gave the following statement to the press recently: "The Catholic Church is growing all the time. Our school system establishes a firm basis for our religion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0454.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There are between 180,000 and 200,000 children in our parochial schools in Brooklyn alone. When these children have finished their education they will know the standards of their religion; they will be familiar with its history; and will understand its sprit. That is why the Catholic religion is strong."</p>
   <p>We agree with the most Reverend Archbishop. The basis and foundation of a church is the school and only the school. We, however, as Greeks and as Orthodox church members, have a two-fold obligation to create and maintain parochial schools. First, to preserve our orthodox religion; and second, for the preservation of our language and customs.</p>
   <p>If the American Catholics do so much for the continuation of the Catholic religion alone, we Greeks must do twice as much as they. Yet, we have done nothing at all so far.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0455.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A tremendous campaign in behalf of our Greek schools must be undertaken. Since it will take some time to change the existing conditions, the clergy must, in the meanwhile,prove their worth and their patriotism by teaching Sunday school classes in their parishes.</p>
   <p>We wait, anxiously, to discover the first Greek priest who will undertake the religious training of the Greek children. Who will be the cleric who will raise the flag of progress and patriotism by giving his time and his efforts for this cause?</p>
   <p>Reorganization and harmony are essential. Too long have our churches been the arenas of selfishness jealousy, and egoistic enterprise.</p>
   <p>Down with the accursed factions seeking only their own interests! Rid the sacred places of all evil-doers who do not respect the sanctity of the church.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0456.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Let the priests cast off their cloaks of indifference, and become aware of the danger that threatens the survival of their church!</p>
   <p>It is not enough that they baptize, marry and bury the members of their congregations; they must work systematically, and be responsible to their Divine Ruler for their actions.</p>
   <p>The undertaking of a drive for a school and a Sunday school must begin at once.</p>
   <p>Study the words of the Catholic Archbishop and aid the clergy in this serious and far-reaching matter. If each man does his duty the dream will soon become a reality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
