<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-09-05">Sept. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Our Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-09-05">Sept. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The readers of the Greek Press follow the activity of the parochial schools, concerning which much is said around graduation and entrance times. In about ten days a large number of children will enroll in the Greek parochial schools of Chicago, to begin another semester. Most of them enroll, not so much from a personal desire for instruction in a Greek school, but to satisfy the demands of their elders. They attend because we, who preach and believe in Creek culture, language, and ethics, demand it of them.</p>
   <p>Maintenance of these afternnon and evening Greek classes satisfies our ego, but does it create anything stable and fruitful. Such a procedure cannot, of itself, develop Greek consciousness in our youth. Our present methods are based upon no fundamental pattern and encompass nothing definite. Naturally, haphazard efforts will lead to haphazard results.</p>
   <p>More than a thousand children attend Greek schools every semester, paying more than <pb facs="5422062_1_0224.jpg" n="2"/>a thousand dollars a month tuition. They are then privileged to be under the supervision of persons having no special qualifications for teaching. Then, the rest of us sit back and fondly imagine a future Creek community which shall be filled with young men and women speaking and writing perfect Greek and adhering to old customs and ethics. Let us face the truth. We are only hiding from ourselves facts that are self-evident. Creek youth cannot possibly remain true to its heritage if we do not give it every encouragement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
