<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-11">Aug. 11, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Language and the Duty of the Community</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-08-11">Aug. 11, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK LANGUAGE AND THE DUTY OF THE COMMUNITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek language has always been considered and is still considered by all civilized people the rich and inexhaustible source from which the phrases have been drawn to express the loftiest ideas, the moral concepts which are the foundation and the strength of religion and of the state. Cicero, the great Roman orator, returning to Rome from Athens, where he had assiduously studied the Greek language, said, "If gods converse, undoubtedly they express their ideas in Greek."</p>
   <p>The great men of the world have loved the Greek tongue, and the study of Greek was considered the means of developing noble characters and lovers of honor. It was also considered a force to meld the mind and a creator of nobility of soul. Nations and individuals imbued with the divine ideas expressed in Greek literature always became leaders and expounders of civilized thought and philanthropic sentiments.</p>
   <p>Is the Greek community of Chicago showing any inclination toward the study <pb facs="5422062_1_0519.jpg" n="2"/>of the Greek language? Are Greek-American boys and girls going to be deprived of the opportunity to study the Greek tongue, through which Christianity became known, in which the gods and the poets sang, and by which enlightenment and nobility of soul were spread over the world? Greeks in Chicago as religious devotees have established up to this time three churches, but no steps have been taken to establish a Greek school for our young. Are we going to do the thing of first importance last?</p>
   <p>It is now high time to consider the establishment of a Greek school if we want our boys and girls to feel proud of their progenitors as we ourselves are proud of their achievements. The Greek-American youth with his racial and religious traditions and with his American education crowned with his knowledge of the Greek language will be a model citizen of this great Republic.</p>
   <p>Let us have Greek schools as quickly as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
