<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek-American News</title>,
<date when="1937-03-15">March 15, 1937</date><title level="a">Historical Development of the Greek Chamber of Commerce of Greater Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek-American News</title>,
<date when="1937-03-15">March 15, 1937</date><title level="a">HISTORICAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE GREEK CHAMBER OF COMMERCE OF GREATER CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Chamber of Commerce of Greater Chicago which was recently organized is the result of twenty or more years of work by the Greek Community. The necessity for such an organization was recognized and, heretofore, two or more attempts had been made to form such an organization. These attempts, however, did not materialize but remained undeveloped.</p>
   <p>To prove that this idea is not new in the Greek Community of Chicago, that it was an idea fostered a decade or more ago, I shall quote from an article written by Peter G. Shepis in the American Hellenic World, on July 4, 1925. This article is captioned, "Let us not be reluctant in organizing commercially before we reach the Danger Line." Mr. Shepis commences his article written twelve years ago as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1441.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Articles have been repeatedly written by pioneers, and men of letters advocating the formation of business organizations without producing results.</p>
   <p>What we need to do is to commence some real work which will result in the formation of indispensable organizations."</p>
   <p>In explaining the benefits of such organizations, men must remove the handicaps, social economic and political, that limit the development of their fellowmen; and in proportion as men accomplish the task the individual will be assisted and solve his business problems. Business organization, then, is the modern interpretation of the new economic philosophy, which can be achieved only by such a movement which will do away with the individual egoism, selfishness, jealousy, and the lack of realization of the benefits to be derived by such organizations.</p>
   <p>Thus wrote Peter G. Shepis twelve years ago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1442.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He pleaded with the Greeks to organize commercially, to form a Chamber of Commerce. Now that the foundations of such an organization have been laid, it is the duty of every Greek business man to join forces with this organization, which will in turn greatly benefit him and his business.</p>
   <p>Chris D. Toulon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
