<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-17">Aug. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Moratorium</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-17">Aug. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">MORATORIUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That poverty breeds discontent is an adage as true as it is old: as true as the light, and as ancient as the pyramids of Hespos. And yet, in certain things--in the family circle, for instance--discontent and arguing should not overstep the bounds of logic and human endurance.</p>
   <p>Four days ago, I happened to hear a Greek woman complain of her husband, with whom she has passed many happy, secure years of married life. Her complaints were entirely illogical and uncalled for. This wife and mother said: "I have done everything for him (her husband). I have sacrificed my youth, my freedom, and the best years of my life for him. I worked very hard to keep my home and my children above reproach. And now that we are in financial difficulties, he cannot provide me with even a few of the comforts of life."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0690.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>God bless her! What never ceases to surprise me is the fact that nine women out of every ten make the same complaint and present the same case history. Why? Because women are under the impression that men are their eternal debtors merely because they have given themselves in marriage. They think that anything they do in married life should be regarded as a sacrifice. Yet, a woman does no favor to a man when she marries him. In fact, any argument offered by the women can be used just as readily by the men.</p>
   <p>It is the women who have created and fought for the preservation of the marriage convention. They are pushed into marriage by their normal and natural instincts and desires. The woman seeks the man just as much as the man seeks the woman. This has been true in the past, it is still true today, and, I am quite sure, it will continue to be true in the future.</p>
   <p>My dear lady, you complain of the loss of your freedom. Hasn't your <pb facs="5422062_1_0691.jpg" n="3"/>husband cause to make the same complaint? It is just as difficult for a man to choose a mate, to entrust his future life and happiness to her, and to make her the mother of his children, as it is for a woman to place her life and future happiness in the hands of a man.</p>
   <p>The dreams and hopes of young girls are no more beautiful or more deeply cherished than are the secret ambitions and dreams of young men. Men are just as romantic as women. They, too, are hurt when their illusions and ideals are destroyed by some individual or by some circumstance.</p>
   <p>Aside from all this, experience proves that nine tenths of the time a girl is pretty sure of the kind of man she is marrying. A man, on the other hand, has only an outer shell to judge from, because a woman is not a creature of even and quiet temperament. She is like Pandora's box.</p>
   <p>My dear lady, you have worked hard for your husband, your children, and your home. We acknowledge that. But hasn't your husband worked just as <pb facs="5422062_1_0692.jpg" n="4"/>hard for you? Why do you value your own labor so highly and his so lightly? Even if you had not married, wouldn't you have done some kind of work during the course of your life? Then why portray yourself as a martyr with a crown of thorns on your noble brow? You say you have given the best years of your life? Please forgive me for disagreeing with you. The years and your youth have merely passed. You haven't given your youth to your husband anymore than he has given his to you. The years have simply flown by in obedience to the laws of nature.</p>
   <p>No one is to blame if we lose our youth. Look at the matter logically, madam, and you will see your error. A husband does not owe his wife more than a wife owes her husband. It is true that a woman can make a man deeply indebted to her, but that can be done only by exhibiting exceptional traits of character. Therefore, all you married men and women should declare a moratorium on your debts to each other and start with a clean slate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
