<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Year Book of St. Constantine Church and Korais School.</title> 1936, P. 131.
<title level="a">The Daughters of Penelope "Hellas"-</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>YEAR BOOK OF ST. CONSTANTINE CHURCH AND KORAIS SCHOOL.</title> 1936, P. 131.
<title level="a">The Daughters of Penelope "Hellas"-</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is true that the multiplicity of Greek Societies in Chicago cannot be found in any other city of the United States. Indeed it is noteworthy, that the Greeks of Chicago are distinguished for their desire to organize, and their determination to unite the Greek elements, although under different aspects, under our roof, named Greek Unity. The plethora of Greek societies is attributed to that.</p>
   <p>The Cloister, of the Daughters of Penelope, "Hellas" made its manifestation two years ago, with the avowed purpose of uniting all the Greek ladies under our organization and under one guidance.</p>
   <p>The activities of this society are directed towards our Greek Schools in all communities in the City of Chicago. The proceeds, of the numerous dance banquets, given by the society, are destributed to every school, according to its needs. Thus, we add one more ring to the chain of Greek Societies making the chain stronger and stronger for the unity of the Greeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On or about April 17, 1934, the brilliant active and energetic youth, Mr. M. Mamalakis, organizer of "Ahepa" and the "Cretans", and formed The Cloister, of The Daughters of Penelope, "Hellas "</p>
   <p>The desire of all the ladies to be united and the convincing fundamental principles defined by Mr. Mamalakis, were quickly molded into the present society. Officers of the society were, Maria Pofanti, president; Mrs. B. Mantas, vice President; Mrs. Athena Peta, treasurer; Mrs. Maria Spannon, secretary; Miss Angelika Andritsopoulos, executive secretive. Board of Directors were: Mrs. Varouni, Mrs. Massahos, Mrs. Karambi, Mrs. Andrew and Mrs. Maniati.</p>
   <p>The unity of the Greek ladies, is acclaimed by all the Greeks of Chicago as a new era of Greek progressiveness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
