<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Coffee Shops</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-08-08">Aug. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COFFEE SHOPS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are not going to discuss those few Greek cafes that have brought unfavorable criticism upon the Greek community of Chicago. Certain cafes have become gambling centers instead of social centers. We are sworn foes of this type of coffee shop or cafe, and will do everything in our power to have them closed.</p>
   <p>Just because a few cafes have become gambling houses is no indication that all the cafes are undesirable and should be closed. The cafes are important to the very existence of the average Greek man. They are places where he can debate and converse on each and every possible subject.</p>
   <p>The Greek Kafenion or cafe is analogous to an American club. It would be very unjust if the government were to impose a tax upon the cafes, since the clubs are not restricted and are even given special privileges. If a five hundred dollar tax is imposed upon each Greek cafe, they will all be forced to close their doors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1393.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This tax has been suggested by one of the members of the Chicago City Council.</p>
   <p>Such a course will lead to many evils. The coffee shops will be replaced by illegal gambling houses and by even worse places. Anyone who is going to take a stand on this matter, must take certain things into consideration. It is not only that eighty or a hundred men will be forced into bankruptcy and ruin; the matter is far more comprehensive than that. Thousands of Greek men find companionship and enlightenment in these cafes. Intelligent conversations are heard on all sides, which at least, cause individuals to think seriously. There, old acquaintances are renewed, and experiences exchanged. In many cases, it is the first place to which an unemployed man will go in his search for a job.</p>
   <p>A Greek immigrant finds haven in the cafe. He goes there to seek information about his friends and relatives. Sometimes he learns his first English sentences from some kindly customer in the cafe. Such a man would be lost if he were to lose the help of the cafe. He would fall prey to racketeers and cheats, and would probably end in jail or die of loneliness and fear.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1394.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If you ask any man where he went when he first arrived in Chicago, nine cases out of ten he will name a Greek cafe, and he will bestow a blessing upon the patriotic proprietor.</p>
   <p>The undesirable cafes are very few. Must the whole group be penalized and abolished for the sake of a few?</p>
   <p>Another aspect of the problem is this: if the Greek cafes are closed, the Greek communities will dissolve. If there are Greek communities on Halsted Street or on Grand Avenue, it is because of the existence of the cafes. In the evening, all the workingmen stroll over to the cafe to talk, and they do not even have to spend a penny of their hard-earned money. If the cafes are closed, these communities will disperse and be lost within other groups.</p>
   <p>The closed cafes will cause the taverns and the liquor stores to be crowded to overflowing, and the Greeks who are not yet known to be drunkards--because only coffee is sold in the cafes--will acquire the habit of drinking strong liquor. Let the gambling houses be closed--but not the Kafenia!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1395.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our mayor Mr. Harrison, condemns the cafes as centers of ill repute which add to the demoralization of minors. However, they must recognize the great difference between the two types of Greek cafes. We agree that the places which contribute to juvenile delinquency should be closed. But there are very few of them.....</p>
   <p>The Saloniki asks all respectable cafe owners to unite and sign a petition to be presented to the City Council. They must protest against this unfair discrimination.....The whole Greek community must protest against the proposed fine. We can and must restore dignity and respect to the Greek name.....</p>
   <p>If we allow this matter to drift, the shame will be ours. The American people will receive the impression that every Greek who has ever spent an hour in a cafe is a gambler, or a no-good. We must explain the true purpose of the Kafenion to the American public. We are sure that a different attitude will be taken when the true facts are known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
