<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Greek School of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK SCHOOL OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[A picture of the architectural plans of the School for the West Side Greek community of Chicago is included].</p>
   <p>The Saloniki takes national and patriotic pride in having this opportunity to print the diagram of the School, which is to be built on the large piece of property belonging to the West Side church. There are at least five hundred Greek children in the immediate vicinity. This number in the future will pursue their studies in the Greek American School.</p>
   <p>A long list of previous articles have described at length the benefits to be gained by the unification of the church parishes of Chicago; and now we see this is about to be accomplished.</p>
   <p>This building of a new Greek school is a progressive step toward fulfilling <pb facs="5422062_1_0458.jpg" n="2"/>the dream of the three parishes. This building will have room for a high school with dormitories and lunchrooms large enough to accomodate over five hundred young people.</p>
   <p>The beginning has been made. The Board of Trustees of the Holy Trinity Church, under the leadership of the well known Mr. B. Georgakopoulos, is to call a general meeting for next Sunday at three o'clock. It will be held at Horran Hall on the corner of Halsted and Harrison Streets, for the purpose of making further plans for the school.</p>
   <p>This achievement will benefit each and every Greek in Chicago; not only those living now, but those of future generations.</p>
   <p>We applaud the entire community, and extend our best wishes for the quick completion of the new school building.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
