<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1921-03-12">March 12, 1921</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1921-03-12">March 12, 1921</date>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. James V. Clarke, Managing Editor</p>
   <p>The Presbyterian Advance</p>
   <p>Presbyterian Building</p>
   <p>150 North Avenue</p>
   <p>Nashville, Tennessee</p>
   <p>My dear Mr. Clarke:</p>
   <p>Having before me your letter dated February 26, 1931, which asked that I "read this article very carefully and with a disposition to agree when facts are stated and to take issue only where there is divergency from the facts," I have very carefully read the article "Shall the Liquor Traffic Control" by Norman B. Barr, D.D., in the February 5, 1931, issue of the Presbyterian Advance.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0614.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ours is a government of majorites -- that is as it should be; majority does not mean 51% of all the people but rather 51% of those who exercise their right of suffrage -- actually a government by minority.</p>
   <p>That war hysteria had much to do with the 18th Amendment and its adoption permits of no argument.</p>
   <p>One of the chief, if not the leading, arguments and pleas, advanced by the Drys was "Conserve grain and malt now used for intoxicants and help win the war." This slogan was effective and those keeping the home fires burning voted to amend the Constitution, while the four and a half million men under arms here or "Conquering Germany" were deprived of the opportunity to vote or express their view to legislators on this question.</p>
   <p>A free and open discussion of the benefits and demerits of this Amendment, the Jones 5 and 10 Law and the Volstead Act having shown the "Saviors of <pb facs="5422062_1_0615.jpg" n="3"/>Democracy" the facts, not previously laid bare, they have joined with the minority of 1917-18-19, and those of Dry opinion of that day who have seen the error of their ways and demanded a resubmission of the whole question to all the people for a decision.</p>
   <p>Being a government of majorities, why should any one quarrel with that principle? The Declaration of Independence enunciates it and the Constitution authorizes it.</p>
   <p>It is not my intention to discuss the merits or demerits of the 18th Amendment in this letter, but I merely touched upon it to indicate to you that I have read the article with a great deal of care, and while it for the most part deals with generalities, it is specific in one instance, and that is in gratuitously libeling millions of ex-service-men, tens of thousands of whom are in harmony with the 18th Amendment and the enforcement acts.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0616.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>With reference to the former soldier, sailor or marine the article charges: (a) "War sets society back very apparently at least for one generation and less evidently unto the fourth generation;" (b) "The boys we sent to Europe to conquer Germany came back conquered by all Europe"; (c) "While many individual boys went away and came back clean of the liquor habit, the great majority came back with the taste for liquor strong in their physical systems with a mental bias for alcoholic beverages, etc."; (d) "The American Legion twelve years after the war's end cannot hold its conventions without the wildest abandon to liquor and all that goes with it"; (e) "Of all the causes for the breakdown of the Dry sentiment which prevailed before the war the influence of the returning soldiers is most potent"; and (f) "The soldiers, millions of them, returning to their communities all over the land, corrupted not only the youth of the country to whom they returned, and who idolized the soldiers, but the adults also, the parents as well as older brothers and sisters and friends and acquaintances."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0617.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In that sequence answers will be made herein. When in agreement, free admission of that fact will be made, and only when there is a divergency will issue be taken.</p>
   <p>(a) That "War sets society back very apparently at least for one generation and less evidently unto the fourth generation" cannot be taken to mean only those who shoulder arms. Any such change certainly effects the entire population of all the nations at war, hence it should not be assumed that the soldiers are responsible for the "setback of society." After all, the soldiers did not plan the war. All they did was to fight in it, and apparently they did a pretty good job.</p>
   <p>(b) That "the boys we sent to Europe to conquer Germany came back conquered by all of Europe", is not a correct statement, but a nasty libel, utterly without foundation. The further charge --</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0618.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>(c) "While many individual boys went away and came back clean of the liquor habit, the great majority came back with the taste of liquor strong in their physical systems with a mental bias for alcoholic beverages," etc., is so sweeping that it necessarily must fall by its own weight. Such charges caused the indictment and conviction of one Lorenz, publisher of the Illinois Staats Zeitung in Chicago some years ago. Perhaps some one will again take up the cause of the ex-service men and force Dr. Barr to prove his words and justification for their utterance.</p>
   <p>(d) "The American Legion twelve years after the war's end cannot hold its conventions without the wildest abandon to liquor and all that goes with it", is another statement grossly exaggerated, for at all American Legion conventions the delegates have business of vital importance to their sick and disabled to transact and their record shows that such business has at all times been transacted in a very efficient manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0619.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>If the delegates were under the influence of liquor as the article would have us believe, they could not accomplish so much good for the disabled and for the nation at large. I have attended many of these conventions, departmental and national, and I, too, have seen men stagger on the streets, but never have I seen anyone even slightly intoxicated in the convention or committee meetings. In many instances those intoxicated are ex-service men, but a great majority of those who are inebriated were never in service. The mayor or police of any convention city hall will testify to that.</p>
   <p>I do not know just what information Dr. Barr has as to what "they (the soldiers) did when off duty in Paris or some other European city" but for his information, the beverages drank by ex-soldiers while in Europe were not Bourbon, Rye, Brandy or Scotch, but on the contrary, were light wines and cordials.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0620.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>I wonder how frequently Dr. Barr has seen intoxicated Frenchmen staggering along Paris boulevards. Not often, I'll venture, if at all.</p>
   <p>(e) "Of all the causes for the breakdown of the dry sentiment which prevailed before the War the influence of the returning soldiers is most potent", is another gross misstatement. There was very little sentiment for prohibition before the war as evidenced by the inability of the prohibitionists to pass a law outlawing intoxicants before the war, although they surely tried hard enough to do so.</p>
   <p>The article, in addition, is contradictory. In one part is the charge that the breakdown of the dry sentiment is attributable to the Legion, while in another part it is charged that "Foreign influence is protecting the liquor interests" where protection is needed, presumably among enforcement officials. Again the wet city daily is responsible for the breakdown and finally Big Business is blamed for it. That "there seems to be no single cause for anything in the world," is a truism with which <pb facs="5422062_1_0621.jpg" n="9"/>all must agree, and the most logical statement of Dr. Barr, "In any event the returning power of the Wets cannot be explained by any one cause, much less by the influence of the returning soldiers", is just a phrase, meaningless but pretty. That statement "The returning soldier is wedded to booze" certainly cannot come from the mind of a spiritual guide who was in possession of all his faculties.</p>
   <p>(f) "The soldiers, millions of them returning to their communities all over the land, corrupted not only the youth of the country to whom they returned, and who idolized the soldiers, but the adults also, the parents as well as older brothers and sisters and friends and acquaintances."</p>
   <p>Where, oh where, is the consistency in the charge that "returning soldiers" were responsible for the craze for liquor, when at another part of the article it is stated that in the city of Chicago "at the opening of the <pb facs="5422062_1_0622.jpg" n="10"/>Board of Trade Building, one of the largest and most reputable of the stock and bond houses is reported to have furnished the best of liquors in abundance to all customers and friends."</p>
   <p>What part could The American Legion or soldiers, out of work, broke, and many of its members, homeless, have played in that instance? Again, how utterly ridiculous is the charge that the millions of returning soldiers have affected the drinking of liquor "in our large cities where the population is largely of foreign birth?" If that statement is true, certainly the foreign born population is not made up of nor influenced by them. The falsity and the absurdity of that statement is very easily demonstrated when it is considered that the foreign born population is not given to the drinking of whiskey.</p>
   <p>The Germans are fond of beer, the French, Italians and Greeks indulge in light wines, as do the Poles and Slavs. None of these groups are whiskey <pb facs="5422062_1_0623.jpg" n="11"/>drinkers, and it is whiskey, moonshine, alky, etc., that is charged with the failure of the 18th Amendment -- not wines and beers.</p>
   <p>I am not attempting to defend whiskey drinking, nor wine and beer drinking by foreign populations. I am only interested in the charges made against the "returning soldiers". Any self-respecting, red-blcoded American citizen will resent the charge that "The soldiers, millions of them, returning to their communities all over the land, corrupted not only the youth of the country to whom they returned, and who idolized the soldiers, but the adults also, the parents as well as older brothers and sisters and friends and acquaintances." That statement is untrue, unfair and libelous. It certainly has no place in a Christian paper. It does not add to its prestige, nor is it becoming of a paper intended to advance a spirit of tolerance and brotherly love. To say the least, the article is most uncharitable, and above all things, it does not partake of Christ and his teachings.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0624.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>I believe that this letter voices the opinions and views of most of the ex-service men, those of prohibition tendency as well as those who are more moist in their desires and if it has in even a small degree tended to eradicate from your mind any falsity of their position or action, then the time spent in composing it and other letters in this series, as well as in reading your letters and the article itself, has not been wasted.</p>
   <p>It is hoped that such comment or action as is consistent will be taken by you or the Advance to place before your readers the true position of the service men and the Legion with reference to prohibition and its alleged evils by violations.</p>
   <p>Yours very cordially,</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis,</p>
   <p>Chairman</p>
   <p>Americanism Committee Cook County Council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
