<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">School Benefit Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0570</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0570.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL BENEFIT DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dance given by the West Side Church in behalf of its Greek school, was marked by dignity and the fine behaviour of the participants. The orchestra, under the baton of Mr. Nick Varzos, pleased the dancers and made their feet feel light. Many couples danced to the strains of American music. One couple, Mr. Dandelis and Miss Skordilis, received much attention because of their graceful dancing. At eleven o'clock the Greek dancing began.</p>
   <p>The sum of eighty dollars was collected during the dances. [It is a custom to throw money into the center of the ring of dancers, especially when a good dancer is leading the circle]. A small girl arose at the beginning of the dance and recited a little poem,which in text asked the audience to be generous because the school in which she studies Greek needs the money.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0571.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What we noticed and worried about was that the number of people present at the dance, was sadly out of proportion to the size of the Greek population of Chicago. The purpose of this dance alone should have attracted a larger crowd. But, unfortunately, our indifference to important social matters is still a characteristic of our race. Political disagreements and differences of opinion have put us in such a psychological condition that we have become slaves to revenge, and we do not attend certain necessary and important functions in order that they might fail. Why? Because some one on the committee, perhaps, is of a different faction than ourselves.</p>
   <p>We wish to mention the names of John Agriostathis and A. Tsekouras because they succeeded in selling a few tickets by going from store to store although getting refusal after refusal.</p>
   <p>We hope that this condition and animosity will soon be replaced by a sincere desire for the community well-being.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0572.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Saloniki congratulates the interested, progress-loving individuals who attended; and expresses its shame of those who showed their indifference by staying away.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
