<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Education and the Newspapers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION AND THE NEWSPAPERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a previous issue of this paper we made the statement: "We are in need of general education." Education, is the only means by which the Greeks, even the ones living on the highest mountain of Greece, can ever hope to emerge from the terrible condition in which they live. When educated, they will be able to discern right from wrong more easily as well as those things that are or are not of advantage to them.....it is more desirable that Greece should have besides their heavenly horizon, climate, and the various beauties of nature, educated and cultured citizens, admiring the beautiful and admired for their works and lives, rather than to have monuments and statues, to the classical people, who lived before and who are heavy burdens upon the backs of the present ignorant people. These works of art are used as a weapon against the modern Greeks, by great sociologists, and <pb facs="5422062_1_0162.jpg" n="2"/>historians, because the latter compare the modern and ancient Greeks in cultural attainments. The difference between them is a reflection on present-day [Greeks]. "It stands to reason that the higher an individual or country desires to seem, so much more is demanded by the rest of the world, of this individual or country in cultural and progressive ways."</p>
   <p>It would seem preferable then, that, instead of the Greeks urging measures that are not worth-while, they should strive for the education of the masses of people in all fields; which, would result in a much better society. "It is better to have a small Greece, which, as in past ages, was a source of enlightenment and culture, rather than a large Greece which is in a deplorably dark condition."</p>
   <p>"I remember in my young days of hearing one,a politico, berating a man, who had opened a Gymnasium (High School), by saying to him, What! Mr....., <pb facs="5422062_1_0163.jpg" n="3"/>you have founded a Gymnasium in your community; you have dug our graves." This shows that education opens the eyes of the people, causing them to see things of which they had not been aware before due to ignorance.</p>
   <p>The three most useful educational branches then would be the teaching, the religious, and the journalistic fields.</p>
   <p>We will try and show the relationship of the progress of the community and its newspaper.</p>
   <p>It is a general truth that the majority of the people, form their ideas from what they read in the papers.....</p>
   <p>"A paper can create or destroy good and bad ideologies. For this reason a <pb facs="5422062_1_0164.jpg" n="4"/>paper must be of the highest integrity." And the citizens themselves must support the paper which is of value, and ignore the press when used for wrong purposes.</p>
   <p>Only when the people realize the value of education and the right kind of press, will the Greeks begin to progress."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
