<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material (Manuscript) in Possession of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 N. La Salle St. Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1922-10-26">Oct. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One Thousand Dollars Reward an Open Letter to the Gree Business Ten on Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material (Manuscript) In Possession of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 N. La Salle St. Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1922-10-26">Oct. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE THOUSAND DOLLARS REWARD AN OPEN LETTER TO THE GREE BUSINESS TEN ON CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has come to our attention that certain persons have circulated rumors among our customers and friends to the effect that we have displayed advertising cictures offensive to the Greek people.</p>
   <p>We therefore take the liberty to emhasize the fact that aside from one poster entitled "Turks Defy Britain" no other picture or pictures have ever appeared anywhers over our name, and any rumers to the contrary are malicious and without foundation, caused either by unscrupulous persons or unfair competition.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order that we may terminate such rumors forever, the Case and Martin Company, hereby, offers a reward of "One Thousand Dollars" to anybody for sufficient evidence of a picture or pictures showing views of the Turkish Army offensive to the Greek people, with the exception, of course, of the one picture referred to above, entitled "Turks Defy Britain" in which not even the word "Greek" is mentioned, and which was recalled and destroyed as soon as our attention was called to the matter.</p>
   <p>We believe in honest competition and fair play and we are determined to use every effort and legal procedure if necessary to put an end to such false representation by untruthful propagandists whom we defy to produce such a picture or pictures.</p>
   <p>In conclusion we wish to convey to you a message of admiration for Greece, the mother of Art, Liberty and Culture and in addition we want to express <pb facs="5422062_1_1060.jpg" n="3"/>our highest appreciation for the most cordial business and friendly relations that have existed for many years between the Greek people and Case and Martin Company.</p>
   <p>Cordially yours,</p>
   <p>Case &amp; Martin Company,</p>
   <p>Elmer G. Case,</p>
   <p>President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
