<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-07-22">July 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Church and the School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-07-22">July 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Church and the School</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first duty of the united parish of Chicago is to establish and support many Greek schools.</p>
   <p>The parishes of St. Constantine and Holy Trinity are both worthy of praise for their support of the only two Greek schools in Chicago. The Evangelismos Church also plans to organize a Greek school. The churches should unite and create a central school with higher grades. This school should also have a cafeteria, since most of the students will have such long distances to travel.</p>
   <p>The Greek schools in America--a land where education is free to all--find themselves in pathetic circumstances. The slightest difference of opinion, either on the part of the parents, the teachers, or the board of trustees, results in <pb facs="5422062_1_0440.jpg" n="2"/>hindering the progress of the school. We emphasize the necessity of sending our children to the Greek schools. However, many parents have no understanding of the benefits derived, and on the slightest provocation they remove their children from the school.</p>
   <p>Therefore, our priests, as spiritual leaders, must press the parents constantly in order to make them understand the necessity for Greek learning, and to make them aid the progress of the schools. One of the duties of a priest is to unite the church, the family, and the school. Not only the priests, but the professional men must also join this fight for education.</p>
   <p>There are one hundred Greek churches in America today, and only twenty-five Greek schools. And yet, in the charter of each of these churches, is a clause saying, "The purpose of this parish is to found a school and a church."</p>
   <p>Of course, when Greek immigration had just begun, there was no need for <pb facs="5422062_1_0441.jpg" n="3"/>schools because there were no families. Now, the Greek children are plentiful, and schools are a necessity.</p>
   <p>Sadly enough, we have lacked a man who would serve as a capable leader; consequently, the twenty-five schools were organized haphazardly by each church. The teachers were chosen because of their friendship with a member of the board, rather than for their abilities.</p>
   <p>This is also hindering the progress of our churches and clubs. There is a great need for a rebirth of patriotism, unity, and a spirit of unselfishness and selflessness.</p>
   <p>The schools are holy ground, just as much as a church, and whoever enters into them to do wrong is sinning against his God. Many of the Greek schools have on their teaching staff individuals who, although properly educated, are not pedagogues. These people do not know how to teach properly, and so <pb facs="5422062_1_0442.jpg" n="4"/>the time of the teacher and the pupil is wasted. Other teachers are well fitted for their jobs, but are known to have bad characters.</p>
   <p>If we wish to have respectable Greek schools in America, we must first build airy, attractive, and roomy buildings; and then we must provide a capable teaching staff. It is impossible to obtain a fine teacher when we only pay forty or fifty dollars per month. They must be paid enough in order that they might face the community with some dignity. Their positions must be secure as long as they do their work capably, and not be fired every time someone decides that they don't like the way he (the teacher) parts his hair.</p>
   <p>When the schools make these reforms and make themselves worthy of the name "School," then we are sure that all the parents will not hesitate to send their children. This matter is worthy of the attention of every individual, especially those of us living in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
