<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-31">July 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek School of Holy Trinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-31">July 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK SCHOOL OF HOLY TRINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Board of Trustees of the Holy Trinity Church held a lengthy meeting discussing the plight of the Greek school. Plans for raising funds in order to enlarge the school were postponed because a more urgent condition existed that had to be settled.</p>
   <p>This Greek school has had the misfortune to fall into the clutches of people who were in no way capable of directing a Greek school. One of these is the sister-in-law of the apostate Papadopoulos. She held the position of teacher in this school and entered into a plan with the principal, Mr. K. Georgiadou, whereby the students were given absolutely no religious background and were even forbidden to make the sign of the Cross. As is common knowledge, Mr. Lambros--taking orders from Georgiadou--kept the parishioners and the trustees fighting by printing all kinds of lies and vicious propaganda in his excuse for a newspaper.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0466.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Trustees of the Church are deserving of praise for accomplishing the cleansing of those Augean Stables--a truly herculean task. They ousted both the unprincipled principal and the teacher, whose sex is her only protection against the wrath of the parents. But, since we see that this unbeliever is still writing editorials, the Board of Trustees is urged to take the broom in their hands again. We trust they know which end of the broom will have the best influence on Mr. P. Lambros.</p>
   <p>The board also appointed Mr. J. Agriostathis accountant of the Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
