<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Optimists and Fatalists</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">OPTIMISTS AND FATALISTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the drifting and backwardness which the Greek Community of Chicago has shown lately in regard to our nationalistic and communal affairs, there are a few amongst us who call themselves optimists and contented patriots and who are unable to see beyond their noses. These individuals are able to see that our community is making marvelous progress and winning glories and praises.</p>
   <p>This is the opinion of those optimists who are content with vain hopes and who are fooling themselves in order to show the public that they have worked hard, that they have achieved great things, and that they are deserving of the official titles conferred upon them and of the responsibility which was given them as leaders of our common affairs. If some one would disagree with them and indicate their errors and deceptions, he would undoubtedly be <pb facs="5422062_1_1285.jpg" n="2"/>characterized as a fatalistic, pessimistic, and unpatriotic individual. In addition he would be accused of opposing their patriotic actions, to which some of us think that we have monopolistic rights. Do not many of us know that many such actions and thoughts are hidden under the veil of pretense and hypocrisy?</p>
   <p>We are not pessimistic about the future of the Greek Community of Chicago, for the evolution of things will surely lead us to a broader and better order; but, if this is to be achieved and if the social structure of our community is to be strong, it is absolutely necessary that our impractical dreamers, and empty-headed and inspired crack-pots keep away from the healthy elements of our society. We must clear our community of all those pseudo-patriots and hypocrites just as the farmer uproots the weeds in order that his crop may grow more easily and freely. In this way, we shall get rid of all those who have become an intolerable burden on our community and who are impeding the normal development and continued progress of our people. Those dark clouds which are weighing heavily over our heads and protecting a class <pb facs="5422062_1_1286.jpg" n="3"/>of hypocrites who are shamelessly exploiting the sacred patriotic sentiments of our people must be dispersed. These exploiters haven't the slightest idea what duty and responsibility to country imply.</p>
   <p>Discussing our affairs from a general point of view, we do not wish to underestimate even to the least the nationalistic and patriotic convictions and sentiments--if any exist--of those who shout boastfully and make all sorts of meaningless exhibitions; however, we are of the opinion that they must control themselves and instead of their deafening and disgusting noises should be content to do their duty without any foolish demonstrations in public, as did the publicans and Pharisees of the Bible. For, as things are today, our professional demagogues and rabble-rousers must remain silent while the good Greeks of our community, whose purpose it is to serve our national interests, are expecting deeds and facts which are the only indication of progress and a true spirit of patriotism.</p>
   <p>We say that it is necessary for our press and journalists to dispense with <pb facs="5422062_1_1287.jpg" n="4"/>hatred, insults, and violent attacks. Our clergy must always stand high in the esteem and respect of the people by doing credit to the sacred office for which they have been selected and ordained by God and by the Holy Greek Orthodox Church. They must preach and constantly teach by precept and example our greatest church commandment which urges all Christians "to love one another" and treat all human beings and especially our countrymen as brothers and sisters. Those of us who have been offered the exalted titles of president, vice-president, etc., of our community and organizations should be made conscious of the fact that they cannot honor themselves nor justify the titles which they have won, unless they can accomplish and create real things. Anyone that does not do so and is comforting himself merely with the notion that he is a president or some other kind of official in our public life, is nothing more than a gold and clay immage, which when allowed to fall to the ground breaks and is thus of no further use to its owner. An idle and self-complacent official will be dishonored and discredited for abusing the trust and confidence imposed on him by the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1288.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>So, we deem it necessary to put a stop to innumerable fancies and plans which are full of false motives, hypocrisy, and selfish political and personal considerations. It must be realized that our present circumstances impose upon us the stern duty to develop and guide the people of this community to their best social interests. It is absolutely imperative that we do our duty to our fatherland and to our community which has been badly disorganized and neglected. Let us remember that we can atone for our wrongdoings and previous failures with deeds and genuine accomplishments and not with exhibitions, empty titles, and vaunting rhetoric.</p>
   <p>In order to achieve the objectives which we have outlined above, all those who have not rendered any worthwhile services--all those who have been of no good use to the community--must be put aside, as those trees that do not produce any fruit are cut and thrown into the fire. Then, those who have the courage, willingness, initiative, and are willing to sacrifice self must undertake the promotion and proper administration of every phase of our community life. This must be done immediately because our people have been <pb facs="5422062_1_1289.jpg" n="6"/>losing their enthusiasm and interest in every great Greek cause and community undertaking. We can well remember the important contributions which the Greeks of Chicago made two years ago to the national Greek Navy drive to build a new Greek war fleet. Where is that enthusiasm and willingness to support a great cause today?</p>
   <p>The sober-minded members of our church and social institutions must admit that our key men in the Greek community are obstacles to the realization of the sacred objectives of our people. If our leaders have any feeling at all, they must do either one of two things: work hard and awake to the importance of their task or resign their office. This will prevent our community from going to pieces and becoming thoroughly disillusioned.</p>
   <p>If our just appeal finds no response in the ears of these men, then the Greek Community of Chicago must strike hard and courageously at every useless official and at everyone that is in any way harming the unity, progress, welfare, and morale of our people. The salaried drones and loafers, who are living at <pb facs="5422062_1_1290.jpg" n="7"/>the expense of the hard-working Greek laborer and businessman, must be kicked out. It would be better if these parasites would find something else to do instead of living off the community treasury. Furthermore, let every adventurer stop disgracing the Greek name by posing as a patriotic supporter of some idealistic but doubtful scheme. The garment of loyalty and pretended patriotism should not be used to protect and shield the rascals and vagabonds.</p>
   <p>Thus, when the dead-weights of our community are done away with and everyone shall occupy the position which he properly deserves, then we shall be able to declare that the Greek Community of Chicago is truly deserving of its high national mission.</p>
   <p>Let us start building, then, with the help of the newly established Macedonian Society which we can use as the foundation of a national Greek-American social, cultural, church, and intellectual structure and community organization in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1291.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>May we begin putting into effect all that we have suggested right away.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
