<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-06-29">June 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Athletes of Greece</title><title level="a" type="sub">Written by K. N. Karalopoulos and Published by the Daily News in Answer to the Criticism in Collier's Weekly.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-06-29">June 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE ATHLETES OF GREECE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Written by K. N. Karalopoulos and Published by The Daily News in Answer To the Criticism in Collier's Weekly.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-......."Woe to the glory that was Greece! The Greek is not an athlete anymore. He falls lamentably short of the robust, well-trained athlete of the New World".</p>
   <p>The paragraph above and a few more sarcastic phrases were printed in Collier's Weekly in regard to the defeat of the Greek participants in the Olympic games held in Greece and the victory of the Americans. Mr. Karalopoulos took exception to the sarcasm and wrote the following article, which was published by the Chicago Daily News:</p>
   <p>"That Greece and the Greeks of America were overjoyed and sincerely happy over the American victory in the Olympic games is revealed by the enthusiasm, friendliness, hospitality, and royal entertainment tendered by the Greek people not only to the victorious athletes but to all the Americans in Greece. The Greeks considered it an honor to be defeated by Americans. As for the Greeks of America, the press of the nation has published more than enough about the hearty reception and the honors which they have accorded to the victors. As for their falling short of the robust and well-trained American athlete, that is true, but the inference is wrong. Greek athletes in their present stage cannot be compared with Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1307.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The American athletes were chosen among eighty million people, the best and the most prosperous people in the world, who for a long time have enjoyed freedom of mind and freedom of body, where as the Greek athletes were chosen among two or three million people of a nation which gained its independence only seventy-five years ago. Athletes are not born to a nation; they are made by the nation. American universities and other institutions of this incomparable country have put at the disposal of athletes facilities which cannot be found any where else in the world, whereas athletes clubs in Greece, a little poverty - stricken country, are very few as yet and are supported by the paltry dues paid by members.</p>
   <p>The writer in Collier's displays gross ignorance in comparing little indigent Greece with America. Were he conscious of what America is, he would not expect the flower of America's athletes to be defeated by crippled Greece, whose wounds are still sore and bleeding. He further displays ignorance and lack of intellectual balance by his sarcastic inference that the Greeks are no longer athletes. Greece, in spite of her present condition, - and she still walks on crutches, - has the love of athletics deeply rooted in her heart; it was she who revived the Olympic games, which have now become international instead of national.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1308.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This writer in Collier's, lacking the faculty of discrimination and not fully conscious of America's incomparable advantage, indirectly underestimates the ability of the flower of America's athletes when he says that the Greek athlete falls lamentably short of the robust and well-trained athlete of the New World.</p>
   <p>Did he expect the Greek athlete to come out victorious over the American?</p>
   <p>Greece, who loves America, and the Greeks of America are more highly conscious and appreciative of what America is than some narrow-minded people and paranoiacs who in spite of their American nativity underestimate the dymanic and potential greatness of this incomparable country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
