<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-12">Sept. 12, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Athens College.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-12">Sept. 12, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE ATHENS COLLEGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The action taken by the youth societies to arrange for a grand ball for the benefits of the college to be erected in Athens is a praiseworthy one.</p>
   <p>The girls' societies, Young Ladies 'Philomusical Club of North side, Nea Genea of the South Side, Greek Youth of the West side the boys' Society Plato, also of the west side, and the Sons of Pericles, prove by the decision they have made what noble sentiments they are animated by and how much interest they have in the establishment of an American institution of learning in Greece.</p>
   <p>Athens College is an institution in which the Greeks of America should take deep interest for many reasons, two of which are most important. First, it serves American interests, and second, it serves Greek interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0142.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The serving of American interests consists in the spreading of American ideals through the educational system of America and the development of close relationships between Americans and Greeks.</p>
   <p>The serving of Greek interests is in the fact that Greece acquires a first class College in which the Greeks will benefit by the knowledge of the English language and higher encyclopaedic education, as well as Greek learning.</p>
   <p>It must be noted that the Greeks in Greece knew about American colleges long ago, for many of them have taken courses at Roberts College in Constantinople, which had a special department for Greek students in the Greek language. Because of their high opinion of this American college they sought from the Americans the establishment of a similar college in Athens, and have supported the undertaking generously.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For these reasons, the Greeks of America should support Athens College. It serves the Greek-American interests and brings closer together the Greek and American people.</p>
   <p>The young girls and boys who compose the above mentioned organizations are to be congratulated that they realize this high purpose of and desire to aid in its establishment.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that the whole Greek community which has always been prompt to further all good causes, will, in this instance, prove its readiness to support Athens College by attending the ball to be given next Monday, Sept. 17,at the Trianon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
