<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-08-26">Aug. 26, 1928</date>, p. 5
<title level="a">Chicago Greeks Jubilant Over Venizelus Election.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1024</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1024.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-08-26">Aug. 26, 1928</date>, p. 5
<title level="a">CHICAGO GREEKS JUBILANT OVER VENIZELUS ELECTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Greeks all over the city were celebrating the election of Mr. Venizelists. For some time they were divided into two political factions, Venizelists and Royalists, but judging from the gladness and joy that pervaded the Greek colony, we are able to see that the division, if still existent, is forgotten and everybody celebrated the good news.</p>
   <p>Eleutherios Venizelos despite his ill health and repeated efforts to retire from public life, apparently is still the most powerful figure in Greece. From a campaign of extreme bitterness between the Royalists and Republicans he has emerged with a victory that has given him a great following.</p>
   <p>Returning to Athens as Premier early last month, as he had done before to help his country out of difficulties, Venizelus insisted upon the dissolution of the parliament and the election of a new one on a majority vote, instead of on the old basis of proportional representation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1025.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the election, in which the principle issues were financial measures that caused the downfall of the last ministry, the most active enemies of Venizelos were the most signally defeated.</p>
   <p>The return of Venizelos to guide the destinies of his country is more than an incident in the stormy career of a man who, frequently, after the World War, was pronounced the ablest statesman in Europe. P-rticular significance is seen in the rousing support given to him by the liberal elements in opposition to the Royalist program. Venizelos, who represents the Greek desire for freedom, won 228 out of 250 seats in the parliamentary election. Royalists, who think they need a king, are wiped out.</p>
   <p>Where "The mountains look on Marathon and Marathon looks on the sea," Byron, musing there an hour alone, dreamed that Greece might still be free. Greece is free, at least free of kings and the Hohenzollern brood, and apparently will remain free for a while.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Greeks have great cause to be jubilant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
