<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Social Problems</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL PROBLEMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I feel it is my patriotic duty to express my opinion in the matter of Greek upbringing. This is directed not so much at the people who are educated and brought up in the Greek manner as at the ones who are ignorant perhaps due to lack of opportunity or because of their own desire.</p>
   <p>A completely Greek standard of morals and customs cannot be attained [here] due to different environment, different moral standards, and at times opposing ideals. But we can approach this standard if strong efforts are made for our children by two mediums--the family and the teachers.</p>
   <p>We cannot underestimate the influence of the teacher. When a child attends school for the first time, he feels that he is beginning a period of imprisonment. His understanding is not large enough to make it easy for the teacher to teach him. And so a teacher must overcome many obstacles before he can successfully lead these young minds.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0168.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Parents have even more of a responsibility towards the children than have the teachers. They are held responsible for the welfare of the children both in and out of school. They must aid the child in the selection of his friends and activities. They must be continually watchful of the child's progress and development. I again state that cooperation between teachers and parents is essential to insure a Greek upbringing to our youth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
