<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-23">Oct. 23, 1929</date><title level="a">What an American Thinks of the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Rev. J.M. Rife Ii. the Greek and His Money</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1001</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1001.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-23">Oct. 23, 1929</date><title level="a">WHAT AN AMERICAN THINKS OF THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Rev. J.M. Rife II. The Greek and His Money</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"I never say a stingy Greek". This is a remark which I have often made to other Americans and which none has disputed. I admire the Greeks for their apparent ability to adjust their expenditure to their income. There are two sides to this matter and on each side there are Americans who err badly. One should live within his income, but not too much within it. There is a small minority of people who do not spend enough. In the days of their first meager incomes, the Greeks I have known, have lived meagerly; but as their wages increased, as they went into business for themselves, and as their profits mounted, these men have willingly and generously opened their purses wider and wider, both for private and for community benefactions. In this I seem to see some of the classic "Sofrosini", variously interpreted as "wise moderation" and "sweet reasonableness."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1002.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>An American associating to any extent with Greeks is struck by the complete absence of the "Dutch treat". Some Americans prefer the "Dutch treat", others despise it, Greeks never dream of it. They are their own severest critics and one of them has suggested to me that their custom, of always allowing one man to pay the expenses of a group, is often mere ostentatiousness and unwarranted display. Nevertheless, it does show an openhandedness which is not so universal in certain other races.</p>
   <p>Americans generally regard the Greek as a good business man, that is, good in the sense that he makes a good margin of profit. It is reported to be a current saying in the Levant that, in a business deal, "One Greek is equal to two Jews and one Armenian to two Greeks." Whether this is true or not, Americans are quite ready to believe it. I have known Greeks, however, to fail in business ventures. There are some of them far better fitted to do good work for an employer than to manage a business of their own.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1003.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The worst opinion of Greeks is found among Americans who have lived in foreign countries, especially Africa. They say the Greeks in Northeast Africa will, in order to make money, stop at no debauchery of the natives. They charge them with being liquor dealers and panderers and indulging in concubinage. I am inclined to discount these reports somewhat, but their unanimity makes me fear that there is a decidedly unpleasant amount of truth in them. Possibly a less scrupulous class of Greeks engages in business or perhaps the Greek emigrant generally is too apt to adapt himself to the standards of the natives among whom he lives.</p>
   <p>There are those who say that every man has his price, i.e., in dollars. I do not believe this, and always object when such a statement is made concerning Greeks or any other race.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
