<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-22">Mar. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The School Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-22">Mar. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOL QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4 -- With the determination to accomplish that which has been left unaccomplished by its predecessors the newly-installed executive council of the Greek community has tackled the question of the Greek school. Feverish attempts are being made to close the gap which for years has been an imminent danger to Hellenism.</p>
   <p>Parents and others have been invited to communicate to the officials of our colony their ideas as to the best method of establishing Greek schools in Chicago and as to how the schools shall be supported.</p>
   <p>The offices of the community are located at 8 Dearborn Street.</p>
   <p>In previous issues the Star has dealt at great length and very explicitly with the school question, and it hopes that the time is not far away when the Greek community of Chicago will be the proud possessor of two or more Greek schools for the instruction of our American-born children.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0491.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The establishment of a Greek school in Chicago will be the beginning of a new era for the community. It will produce a new type of citizen, a citizen who will be proud of his mother country, the great United States of America, and also proud of his grandmother country, immortal Greece.</p>
   <p>A wise ancient Greek said, "The foundation of every state is the education of its youth," and another, "The fountain of wisdom flows through schools."</p>
   <p>Our future youth, possessing a foundation of Greek education and a complete American education, will be able to cope with any problem in life.</p>
   <p>If knowledge is the breath of gods, and the gods spoke the Greek language, then the Greek schools in our community, as everywhere, will be temples of the gods through which the Greek language will be immortalized.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the present administrators of the community's affairs will <pb facs="5422062_1_0492.jpg" n="3"/>direct their efforts to the initiation of useful projects indispensable to the welfare and progress of the community. The question of the Greek school is that which demands their first attention. And the establishment of Greek schools will be a racial achievement, the foundation of the progress of our community and a source of pride and credit for Greeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
