<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">Sept. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Reduction of Wages</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">Sept. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">REDUCTION OF WAGES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Steel Corporation and others have announced that beginning October 1st wages will be reduced 10 per cent. Thus the reduction of wages is put into effect after the already effected reduction in values.</p>
   <p>It is understood that this reduction of wages is only the beginning, since the workers of these corporations, although they number hundreds of thousands, do not belong to labor unions and consequently this wage-reduction will not bring united protest and resistance, nor can it be considered a violation of contract between unions and corporations.</p>
   <p>But when the reduction is extended to workers belonging to unions, then, of course, the aspect of things will be changed, and resistance to reduction of wages will find all unions united, with strikes and protests as a result, the extent of which it is difficult to foresee.</p>
   <p>To wit: the labor reaction will be added to the present crisis, and conditions surely will get worse because of measures that are taken allegedly for improvement.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1416.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The reduction of wages is a measure included in the famous program of readjustment, namely, in the adjustment of values at their proper level from the height where they were, and at which they could not be kept any longer.</p>
   <p>The principle of readjustment is that all values shall fall, and that the dollar, whose buying power has fallen about one half shall rise. Now then, when the value of various articles falls, the buying power of the dollar necessarily rises because with one dollar we can buy objects of higher value, since their value has fallen.</p>
   <p>But with the fall in value of articles and the rise of that of the dollar, the question arises: where are the dollars? Because of what use are the fall in value of articles and general low prices at the moment when people have no money to buy things with? In other words, we have come to the place where the camel is being offered for a nickel, but nobody has the nickel to buy the camel with.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1417.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But will people find work, at least, with the reduction of wages? In other words, is the problem of unemployment solved in that way? Certainly not, for the purpose of the readjustment was not that; it was only to raise the buying power of the dollar, which has fallen because the value of all things has risen, and those who have the dollars, namely, the financial capital, the cash, are pursuing the course by which the value of their capital will increase, so that they will be able to control all other capital and regulate its value.</p>
   <p>Sp. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
