<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-12-20">Dec. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Preservation of the Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-12-20">Dec. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PRESERVATION OF THE FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many people who firmly believe that the Greek-Americans of today are not what they were fifteen or twenty years ago. In other words, they mean to infer that the Hellenes of today have forgotten or ignore many things which they deemed so important when they first came to America. Many years have passed since the majority of us arrived at Ellis Island. Nevertheless, despite the beliefs of many, an examination into the lives and conduct of the Greek people will reveal that there is no basis for their accusation. The Greek people have lost nothing whatever of their cultural or religious background. They are, in fact, superior to themselves as they were when they first came to America. By this we mean that they have cultivated their language and traditions since their arrival in order that these possessions might not become obliterated. No one had any such fear in Greece, and so took many things for granted.</p>
   <p>Pessimistic observers claim that the interest which was evident in the past no longer exists. They are not examining the situation very closely or such <pb facs="5422062_1_0776.jpg" n="2"/>statements would not be made. Therefore, let us make a few honest examinations and comparisons of our own.</p>
   <p>The ratio of churchgoers among the Greeks in comparison with the whole Greek population is much higher now than it was during the Greek immigration period. Then, what can our doubters say about the social events of the Chicago Greek community of today? Can they be compared with the social activities of the past in respect to attendance, conduct, results or intrinsic worth? Our dances and other activities are purely Hellenic in character. Even the children of the new generation, in the great majority of cases, remain true to their Greek heritage. They are in evidence at all of our social gatherings. Not a few times have we proudly watched a group of American-born youngsters perform our difficult Greek dances with ease and obvious enjoyment. Perhaps some will say that they are forced to attend these gatherings by their parents, and that, therefore, their presence there is no indication of Greek attachments on their part. That point is conceded; but can anyone truthfully assert that these young people could be forced to feel the rhythm <pb facs="5422062_1_0777.jpg" n="3"/>of the Greek music? If this rhythm does not exist in the very soul of the dancer, it is an impossibility to perform some of the dances, despite much practice and training.</p>
   <p>Another reason for the maintenance of Greek customs can be found in man's habit-forming characteristics. Those things which children hear, see, and are obliged to do during the formative years of life become habits. They respond to certain influences without really intending to do so. This natural phenomenon is easily explained by sociologists and psychologists, and is consciously used to advantage in certain instances. For instance, the head of the Catholic Church requires that the church be in complete charge of the education and training of all children until they are ten years old. After this age they are permitted to attend any school they choose. The Catholic Church is certain of the importance of first impressions and their influence upon the actions of individuals all through the remainder of their lives. Our youth is in many ways more Hellenic than many of the old-time Hellenes, who, despite their numbers, did not associate with each other to any great extent.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0778.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The progress we have made as a group in America has been mainly due--if not entirely--to the existence of Greek homes and families, which were so rare twenty years ago. The Greek women who lived among us, either as wives and mothers or as sisters, are the creators of todays Greek community, which constantly is developing its social and Hellenic aspects. Now, with thousands of Greek homes in Chicago which are living centers of respectable, conscientious people, there is every reason to believe that tomorrow will be brighter and better than today for the Greeks of Chicago. Both we and our children shall cultivate with care the Hellenic heritage we are so fortunate to possess.</p>
   <p>Everyone's attention should be focused upon this cultivation during the year 1935. Especially should those individuals who have a loud voice in our community activities pay heed in this regard.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
