<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-30">Nov. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">More Greeks Enrolled at Scammon School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-30">Nov. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">MORE GREEKS ENROLLED AT SCAMMON SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A couple of weeks ago the director of Scammon School, Mr. W. R. Hornbaker, informed us that 125 Greeks have already enrolled to attend night classes, and we really were interested and pleased that the Greeks were the largest foreign group attending classes there. Now he comes with more good encouraging news that 68 more Greeks are enrolled, making the total number 193 in one school.</p>
   <p>It seems that our exhortations to learn the English language were heeded, and we certainly feel proud to know that the Greek community in Chicago has the largest per capita night school attendance.</p>
   <p>To lay any more emphasis upon the subject is unnecessary because we all know the importance of English and the benefit from knowing it. Let us all make <pb facs="5422062_1_0603.jpg" n="2"/>it a habit to attend the night schools which this great country makes available for our use and thereby better ourselves.</p>
   <p>The Star highly commends the teachers in charge of the Greeks for their enthusiastic interest in their foreign pupils, and it warmly praises the superintendent who has done everything possible for the Greeks in attendance.</p>
   <p>In an interview with Mr. Hornbaker we discovered that he is a great philhellenist and has a burning desire to visit Greece so that he may tread upon that classic soil where the greatest teachers and philosophers taught the Athenian people wisdom and enlightenment.</p>
   <p>No wonder the Greeks attending his school are treated with exceptional interest and care!</p>
   <p>In the Scammon night school, besides the English language, shorthand and <pb facs="5422062_1_0604.jpg" n="3"/>typewriting are taught, and those who wish to attend these classes will find the same facilities available and the same courtesy extended to them as in the classes in which English is taught.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
