<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-06-21">June 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Christening.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-06-21">June 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK CHRISTENING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2-Last Sunday occurred the christening of the youngest son of Mr. George Tsiagouris, a prominent real-estate broker. The godfather was Mr. Andreas Karavannes or Karzas, who named the child Homer. The priest who performed the ceremony was the Reverend Constantine Hatzidemetriou.</p>
   <p>After the rite of baptism a Homeric banquet with Homeric food was served in honor of the new Homer at the residence (in the Homeric house, we should like to say) of the parents.</p>
   <p>At this hilarious celebration a Homeric dispute arose as to the nationality of the young Homer. Mrs. Tsiagouris, a Spartan lady, who has given birth to six robust and athletic children, insisted on naming them with ancient Greek names; so they are known as Demosthenes, Aristotle, Pericles, Alexander, Socrates, and Homer.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0875.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This Spartan lady also insisted at the banquet that her children were Spartans, while her husband, Mr. Tsiagouris, as the head of the family, disputed this assertion and said that they were of the race of Mantinia, his birthplace and not Spartans.</p>
   <p>For some time there was a strain on the family tie, and when the seriousness of the argument increased, the priest and the godfather had to intervene as peacemakers.</p>
   <p>Finally this Homeric dispute was settled when the godfather said that all the children belonged to Greece, to the satisfaction of all and the peaceful continuation of the banquet.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0876.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But they had hardly had time to quiet down after this quarrel when Demosthenes, the oldest of the boys, challenged the right of his parents to dispose of his nationality so lightly, since he and his brothers were Americans! So there was another revolt in the family about the individual rights of the children, and now the priest had to interfere and quiet the youngsters with good priestly advice.</p>
   <p>To judge by the success of the banquet given in honor of the young Homer, we see another perfect Grecian family with all the racial characteristics, especially the over-independent and individualistic spirit. For this we are glad and proud, and Saloniki extends its best wishes to the Tsiagouris family for the young Homer and all the other boys.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
