<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-10-31">Oct. 31, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Hellenism of America!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0177</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0177.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-10-31">Oct. 31, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HELLENISM OF AMERICA!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are certain general topics, situations, and problems of nationalistic importance concerning which dissension should not be condoned. The much-discussed educational problem of the Greeks in America is within this classification. There is no doubt that the "Archiepiscopacy" which governs us, more or less, would be greatly delighted to take steps to insure the success of an educational program for us if no opposition on our part presented itself. The opposition is that the Hellenism of America desires to accomplish its educational aims through its own efforts.....</p>
   <p>What is a teacher? Aside from all the other definitions which are commonly accepted, we can say that the word "teacher" is bound up with the history of our people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0178.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Despite its civilization, the ancient world put education within the reach of only the very wealthy, free citizens. We can easily imagine the plight of the huge masses of slaves who lived in the enforced darkness of ignorance. This condition existed up until the birth of Christ.....</p>
   <p>He was the first to be called a "teacher," and, as such, he was introduced by his disciples. Therefore, Christianity raised the teacher to a high pedestal.</p>
   <p>The school developed from this Christian spirit, for the purpose of educating the children of the common people, thus enabling them to read for themselves the truths expressed in the Bible.</p>
   <p>The public school for the Greeks of America and for the Greeks of the enslaved <pb facs="5422062_1_0179.jpg" n="3"/>times [when under the yoke of Turkey], has always been closely allied with the church and the clergy. The school teacher has usually been the parish priest. Exceptions, of course, have existed--where a teacher was available. At the same time he [the priest in enslaved Greece] acted as a general and led his students against the Turks in guerrilla warfare. Therefore, the same baptismal font was shared by the church and the school, strongly linking these two holy symbols in the heart of every Greek. Even today we endeavor to hold our young people with the combined force of these two influences.</p>
   <p>How can we get better teachers? May we be permitted to state the opinion that the wage scale for teachers should be raised to a much higher level than it is at present. An effort must be made to attract the finest and most suitable people to this hard, thankless, poorly paid profession. How else are we going to educate our Hellenic youth in a constructive manner? This can only be accomplished through the efforts of our unrepaid heros and martyrs--our laymen teachers. They should really be revered and rewarded by all; for only <pb facs="5422062_1_0180.jpg" n="4"/>through their sacrifices can we hope to have future generations of Greek-speaking Americans.</p>
   <p>Greek parents and guardians must be made to realize this need so that they will hasten to satisfy it; for, if they do not, they will shed bitter tears in the future.....</p>
   <p>A good school requires good teachers, and they are acquired only by means of just reimbursement. Let us not begrudge a few dollars for the monthly salary of the Greek school teacher.</p>
   <p>The Hellenism of America enthusiastically works for and contributes to all kinds of unnecessary programs. It should reduce church expenses and clerical salaries, and devote more money to its educational program. I contend that the educator is the most potent force in any community. He helps individuals <pb facs="5422062_1_0181.jpg" n="5"/>to fulfill their destiny.....The Greek language is the ancestral fortune bequeathed us, and it is our duty to keep it alive and honored.</p>
   <p>This can easily be accomplished if we assume responsibility for it, instead of letting it drag itself along as well as it can, unaided. Let us give our Greek educators a chance to prove their worth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
