<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. LaSalle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-07-10">July 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">(Typewritten letter sent by the Sec'y of the Achaian League to Barrett O'hara)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. LaSalle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-07-10">July 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">(Typewritten letter sent by the Sec'y of the Achaian League to Barrett O'Hara)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>In the Chicago Tribune of today you were <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> as having said at an alleged "indignation meeting" held last night under the auspices of Lloyd Wheaton, Post of the Veterans of the Foreign Wars, "There are <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> restaurant and lunchrooms and over <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> are conducted by aliens who never have applied for citizenship. Unless the public is aroused, the American small businessman soon will be extinct."</p>
   <p>If you are not correctly quoted have the Tribune make proper correction. If you were properly quoted, permit the suggestion that you have no right</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1097.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>to create race prejudice, and that your <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> which were un-American came with poor taste from one whose own race was similarly treated by un-American bigots some few years ago. The time is within resent memory when signs reading "No Irish need apply," and when advertisements in the public press containing the same "boycott" were no uncommon sight.</p>
   <p>You were undoubtedly aware, at the time you made the remarks quoted, that about <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of the restaurauts and lunchrooms in Chicago are conducted by people of Hellenic descent. You may not know that approximately 70% of these Hellenes are naturalized citizens or applicants for citizenship, and that in the recent World War many of these Hellenes were soldiers, sailors and Marines in the American Army and Navy, and did their part in preserving the freedom and integrity of America, and in establishing the liberty of mankind throughout the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1098.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Are you advocating either as a "Major" or as a citizen that the balance of the American people now "boycott" that race and these people? Who is to know, when he enters a restaurant or lunchroom, whether or not the proprietor is a citizen or an alien? How do you propose to enforce your "boycott," excepting it be by boycotting all restaurants and lunchrooms conducted by these of Hellenic descent?</p>
   <p>You were a Major in the United States Army, and if you knew any of the privates of your battalion (if you had one) you will recall that the names of the enlisted men ran like this: <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>nolio, Kokekiski, Abrams, Fornier, Mc Pherson and so on, representing every nationality on the face of the globe. Do you consider the boycott of a race, whether Irish or Hellenic, to be either a wise or a just or American proceeding? Or was <pb facs="5422062_1_1099.jpg" n="4"/>your description merely perpetrated to win the momentary applause of a misguided few, and at the same time enable you to exploit yourself?</p>
   <p>Do you not know that antagonism begets hatred, and that instead of boycotting aliens, it would be more American and more human to show to all aliens that broad spirit of brotherhood which in turn begets love of America, her institutions and her people?</p>
   <p>The children of today's aliens will be tomorrow's Americans and it behooves all today's Americans to engender everywhere a spirit of brotherhood rather than a spirit of boycotts and bigotry.</p>
   <p>The people operating restaurants and lunch rooms and other lines of small business are honest, honorable citizens, and what they get they earn by <pb facs="5422062_1_1100.jpg" n="5"/>hard work and through <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> political draft; pay their taxes and obey the law.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, the taxes which they pay are used in paying the salaries of political office holders in maintaining the police and fire departments, the court of justice, the Army and Navy of the United States, and "boycott" is a poor return to them, citizen or alien.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
   <p>The Achaian League</p>
   <p>Anthony C. Coorlim, President</p>
   <p>George F. Mulligan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
