<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-03">July 3, 1929</date><title level="a">Exercises at the Socrates School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-03">July 3, 1929</date><title level="a">EXERCISES AT THE SOCRATES SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The oldest, largest and best of our Greek schools gave, last Thursday and Friday, its graduating exercises. In the large hall of the Socrates school were gathered 100 students representing five grades.</p>
   <p>The boys and girls were amply rewarded for their hard work and patience in arranging the program; the program was a huge success. The poems, recitations and dialogues were the very same as those we used to learn in the schools of Greece.</p>
   <p>The president of the church, Mr. N. Kokkines, the principal of the school, Archreverend Aberkios Dimakopoulos, the pupils and their parents, are all to be congratulated. The purpose of the school, which is to establish the Greek spirit in our children, is being carried out much better than we ever expected.</p>
   <p>The students of Socrates attend the all-day classes. They have all the Greek lessons besides those given by the American teachers, Miss Helen Scacciaferro and Miss Flora Pratt.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0332.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under the direction of the teacher of the school, Mr. Aristides Parisis, all the boys and girls have done their parts with unexpected dramatic ability. The audience was amazed! Credit must also be given to Mr. George Stefanakos, another teacher.</p>
   <p>The participants of the program were all awarded gifts donated by Mouzakiotis brothers.</p>
   <p>All those taking part in the programs on the 27th and 28th of June will also take part in the performance the school is planning to give on the afternoon of July 7th, at the Garrick Theater.</p>
   <p>The principal, George Loomis, Mr. Parisis, Mr. Stepanakos and the Misses Kouklaki, Kaloida, and Lappas are working diligently to prepare the pupils of the 7th and 8th grades for this performance on the 7th.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
