<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-06-21">June 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">From Mr. Ferriman's Treatise.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-06-21">June 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FROM MR. FERRIMAN'S TREATISE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8-Probably it would be useless to assert that the ancient Greek language is not dead. However, even professional men are astonished when this author tells them that a child in Cyprus pointing at a bird cries, "actos!" (eagle), the same word which the great Homer would have used; that a peasant in Attica speaking about the weather calls the clouds "nephe," just as the master of comedy, Aristophanes, did; and that when the Greek bids you sit down, he says, "Kathese", the same expression that Socrates addressed to Strepsiades. Lord Byron discovered this in 1811 when he began to learn "Romaic," as modern Greek is called, in Athens. Douglas the traveler wrote from the same place at the same time that the Greek of classical times would have less difficulty in understanding the Greek of to-day than the contemporaries of William Frazer would have in understanding their modern descendants.</p>
   <p>The historian Finley writes that there is no greater difference between the language of Homer and that of the New Testament than there is between the New Testament and a modern Greek review. He insists that the modern Greek language has preserved even the ancient accent.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0185.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To prove that the modern Greek language is a direct descendant of classical Greek--a fact well known to literary men--Professor Blackie, who insisted on the study of modern Greek, said, "this language is a simple idiomatic variety of the ancient Greek which differs no more from the language of Xenophon than the prose of Attica differs from the language of Herodotus or Theocritus.</p>
   <p>"Of all European languages Greek is the one which has lasted longest with the least changes. You may honor Thucydides, but you should be ashamed to ignore Trikoupis."</p>
   <p>Sir Richard Jump held that only the Greek language had had an uninterrupted life from prehistoric times. In reality the modern Greek language contains more archaic forms than Attic, which is called classical only by usage.</p>
   <p>The preservation of the language and its traditions has preserved Hellenism in life. This language inspired the desire for knowledge, which has always been an obsession of Greeks, and so "education became the purest and strongest instrument of their national consciousness."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
