<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-08-31">Aug. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Magnificent Celebration at the South Side Greek Orthodox Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-08-31">Aug. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MAGNIFICENT CELEBRATION AT THE SOUTH SIDE GREEK ORTHODOX CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday, during the religious holiday celebration of the Assumption and after the morning divine service, a special benediction was sung by the pastor and choir of the Saint Constantine Greek Orthodox Church on Chicago's great South Side. The occasion was the dedication and consecration of the new ground and lot, adjacent to the Church, which were purchased only recently. Our South Side Greek parish school building is to be erected on this site. Construction will begin immediately. More than three thousand people attended the dedication ceremonies.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Medill McCormick, United States Senatorial candidate from Chicago, was one of the distinguished visitors present. Our prominent attorney, Mr. Paul Demos, introduced our honored guest. In introducing Mr. McCormick to the hundreds of Greeks, Mr. Demos said:</p>
   <p>"Never before in the history of the Greek Orthodox Church in Chicago have American citizens of Greek ancestry been so greatly honored as on this occasion. We have <pb facs="5422062_1_0418.jpg" n="2"/>with us today, ladies and gentlemen, one of the most distinguished men in our national life, a man who believes in and fights for an ideal government for the benefit and welfare of all the people, regardless of race, color, faith, or nationality; a man who knows that the American citizens of Greek ancestry are all loyal and faithful to their adopted country."</p>
   <p>Then Mr. McCormick addressed the gathering: "We have not assembled here merely to dedicate this church and school to the cause of education and community welfare, but also in order to pay a deserving tribute of respect to our country and to its defenders. We are loyal and we are dedicated first and foremost to America. We are not divided in our faith. We all recognize the fatherhood of God and the brotherhood of man. Just as Lincoln said that no nation can exist half slave and half free, so we declare that no one is a loyal American whose faith in democracy is divided. Her enemies are our enemies, and her friends are our friends."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
