<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-04-26">Apr. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Death of a Great Philhellene</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-04-26">Apr. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">DEATH OF A GREAT PHILHELLENE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The head of the Classical Division of the University of Chicago, Professor Paul Shorey, died recently. Born in Davenport, Iowa in 1859, he grew up showing great aptness for foreign languages. From his early childhood he had an especial love for the Greek language, and later he devoted his life to teaching and studying it. After studying in Germany and Greece, he returned to teach in America, and was recognized as one of the greatest Greek scholars in the world. When the University of Chicago was first organized, in 1892, its president, the famous William Harper, asked Paul Shorey to accept the Greek professorship. Four years later he became head of the Classical Language Department, and retained that high position until his death.</p>
   <p>In this column, it is impossible to give many details concerning the works of this great Hellenist.....That which we Greeks are duty-bound to appreciate is that professor Shorey was not simply an academic friend of our people. He was a hyper-Greek in every sense of the word. The Greeks of Chicago <pb facs="5422062_1_0183.jpg" n="2"/>first contacted him as an ardent defender of Greek rights. He was heard from during the Cretan uprisings and during the trouble in Macedonia. In fact, his appeal for justice was made every time the interests of Greece were endangered.</p>
   <p>Despite all that this man has done for our language and our country, a monument will not be erected in his honor; nor will some fine boulevard bear his name. He has erected his own monument in the form of his notable writings and profound scholarship. His name will live forever in books of classical research and in translations of ancient Greek philosophy. Most important of all, his memory will be cherished by the entire Greek people--especially by the Greek group of Chicago--for many years to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
