<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-23">Feb. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Once Again the Greek Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">by James Brouklis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-23">Feb. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ONCE AGAIN THE GREEK SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by James Brouklis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Each time I write an article on the Greek schools, insults are heaped upon me, and I am told that I am the enemy of my fatherland, my church, my race, and all the rest of society.</p>
   <p>Of course, I thought that I was doing my duty when I uncovered the rotteness. In fact, my secret hope was that I should be proven mistaken; but it seems my exposure was justified. Our schools have reached the stage where even the most stubborn unbeliever of my words shakes his head in dismay.</p>
   <p>Let us ignore the pedagogical aspect of our schools because much has already been written on this topic. (To be sure, the voice of the critics has been "a voice crying in the wilderness".) Let us first examine the financial condition of our schools. Chaos and havoc are their main attributes. In most of them, the teachers have not been paid for many months. Now, gentlemen, just how do <pb facs="5422062_1_0239.jpg" n="2"/>you expect these people to live? Unfortunately, the age of miracles is over, and the Lord does not send down bread and fishes from Heaven. It is not necessary to quote Plato, Hugo, or Nietsche to prove the seriousness of the condition of our schools.</p>
   <p>Are the teachers the only ones who are suffering? Our children, too, share the discomforts. Most of the schools do not have enough coal to heat even one classroom, much less the whole building--and yet we send our children to such schools to learn their letters! The only thing they are likely to acquire is consumption.</p>
   <p>The evil has reached a stage where it can no longer be tolerated. If we want our schools to be social centers and exponents of our racial and social ego, we must assume definite responsibilities toward them. No school can properly function without sufficient funds. It does no good to give dances, parties, or plays in order to raise a few dollars for the <pb facs="5422062_1_0240.jpg" n="3"/>gangrenous condition present which cannot be cured with salves.</p>
   <p>Our schools need definite sums of money, to be budgeted for their various needs, if they are to serve their purpose efficiently and uninterruptedly. This money cannot be obtained from any such unstable source as benefit dances. If we earnestly desire to have schools for our children, we must all come to their support. The problem of their financial support would be solved if each one of us subscribed one dollar a month for this purpose.....Thousands of dollars are spent for foolishness--even during these times of depression. Don't we have one dollar a month for schools? If not, then why do we shout about the fatherland and the preservation of our language and customs?</p>
   <p>Money is not all that our schools lack. Personnel is most important. Ignorance and illiteracy have been the lot of our schools and churches. Let the frauds and the ignoramuses move over and make room for real leaders, for capable leaders!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
