<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date><title level="a">News from the Contributions for the American College in Athens.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date><title level="a">NEWS FROM THE CONTRIBUTIONS FOR THE AMERICAN COLLEGE IN ATHENS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P - 7. The funds committee, in Chicago, which accepts contributions for the American College in Athens, Greece, informed us that Mr. Anthony B. Benakis of Athens, son of Mr. E. A. Benakis who contributed $150,000 for the college, donated $25,000 to help complete Benakis Hall, the first unit of Athens College. Due to the fact that Greek-American contributions are rather slow, the young Benakis made the donation of $25,000 in order to complete the building which is now in use for class work and as a dormitory for a hundred of the Greek boys who are enrolled in the college.</p>
   <p>The gift of the $25,000 will apply toward the $91,000 still needed for Athens College, and which is necessary to be raised before July 1, 1929, if contributions from America are forthcoming. The Greeks of Chicago are wealthy enough to send the needed money at once. Why be slow about it? The Chicago Greeks always lead in anything. Why the delay now? Send in your share.</p>
   <p>In a recent appeal issued by Albert W. Staub, American Director of Athens <pb facs="5422062_1_0137.jpg" n="2"/>College, Mr. Staub states that "developments of Athens College during the past four years have been phenomenal. Starting with forty boys in rented quarters in the fall of 1925, the school is now occupying Benakis Hall with an enrollment of 266 students." There are special classes for boys of Greek parentage from America and all over the world who go to Athens College to learn Greek and become familiar with the country.</p>
   <p>English is the language of instruction as in the other American colleges in the Near East. Athens College aims to provide for Greek youth the highest type of American education and by this means to foster sympathetic understanding between Greece and America and to be a center of international good will.</p>
   <p>The money needed for the completion of this institution must be on hand before <pb facs="5422062_1_0138.jpg" n="3"/>July and the Chicago Greeks are requested to lead the way and raise the money. Chicago must be at the top of the honor list.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
