<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">The Platon School Holiday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">THE PLATON SCHOOL HOLIDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the church, Koimisis Tis Theotokou, with the hall overfilled, the school festival for 1928-29 was given Sunday afternoon.</p>
   <p>Two hundred and three boys and girls are enrolled in the Platon school. The principal of the school is the priest of the church, Reverend Konstantin Papanikolaou, whose helpers and co-workers are Mrs. Meropi I. Konstantinou and Mrs. Efrosinin Koraka.</p>
   <p>After the prayer, the president of the church, who has faithfully worked for the church for five years, Mr. John Koliopoulos, started the program of the day. After a short speech, he introduced the teacher of the school, Mrs. Konstantinou.</p>
   <p>She spoke very well and enthusiastically about the noble and inspiring work she is undertaking.</p>
   <p>The most sentimental and beautiful part of the program began when the Greek <pb facs="5422062_1_0345.jpg" n="2"/>children were presented to the audience. On the platform were all the little boys and girls, from whose mouths we heard recitations and dialogues, said with the same grace and liveliness that we were accustomed to hear at one time in the schools of Greece.</p>
   <p>The entire audience was truly moved when all the pupils, accompanied by four Greek boys playing violins, sang the Greek anthem.</p>
   <p>In order to give variety to our program, the president said, we are going to ask a well-known man of our community to say a few words, Mr. Paul Javaras, publisher of the weekly newspaper, the Greek Press. Mr. Javaras praised the work of the teachers, because it preserves not only Hellenism of the children of the present generation, but also of generations to come.</p>
   <p>The program continued with songs and recitations which were followed by another speaker, Mr. K. Tsarpralis, former officer of the Greek army. Mr. Tsarpralis, in a brilliant address, praised the endeavors of the Board of Directors, the priest of the church and the teachers and wished them the speedy erection of a proper building to suit their needs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0346.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The songs and pieces were resumed and lasted till 7 o'clock. Aside from the above mentioned events there were several other speakers, Mr. Spiros Kotakis, publisher of the Chicago Greek Daily; Dr. B. Lambrakis; Lawyer Petropoulos or Parry; the Rev. Papanikolaou; the treasurer of the church, Mr. Limperis, and the president, Mr. Koliopoulos, who emphasized the necessity of every one in the community to become a member of the church.</p>
   <p>Every one present celebrated a truly Greek day, filled with inspiration and faith in our nationality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
