<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Sword of Damocles</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. D. Apostol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWORD OF DAMOCLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. D. Apostol</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A friend of mine was very depressed a few days ago because his wife had just given birth to another girl baby. Naturally, he felt justified for being unhappy, and I cannot say that I really blame him. The greatest source of worry to Greek parents are the girls in the family.</p>
   <p>A boy, if he is fairly intelligent, is capable of managing his own life. He can study and progress, even if his father is a pauper. In fact, the less help a boy obtains from his father, the more chance there is for him to become a success and a fine man. That, of course, is true only if the boy has latent ability and ambition. Even if he does not possess a very fine mind, and does not qualify for any of the professions--what of it? All boys cannot become professors, doctors or lawyers. If such a boy becomes a common laborer or a mechanic the world does not feel any illeffects, nor does the sun stop shining for his mother and father. The <pb facs="5422062_1_0782.jpg" n="2"/>worst that can happen is that his misdeeds or lack of ambition may cause his parents some grief. However, such wounds heal quickly, and in time are completely forgotten.</p>
   <p>In the case of a girl, the situation is entirely different. As soon as a girl is born, the infant is a source of worry and anxiety to her father, and the cause of the tear-filled eyes of her mother. Do they not love the girl baby? Of course they do--in most instances even more than the boy baby..... That which causes the anxiety is the economic conventions with which the parents will have to contend when their daughter reaches marriageable age.</p>
   <p>As a girl child grows she becomes more and more dear to her parents and ornamental to the home. A home without a girl is not a complete home. A girl is the prettiest thing ever put on earth for man to enjoy. But although the parents may fondly watch their little girl grow into an attractive young <pb facs="5422062_1_0783.jpg" n="3"/>woman, they do so, feeling as though the sword of Damocles were suspended over their heads. As the daughter grows the sword also increases in size and threatens to fall upon their heads.</p>
   <p>To the Greeks, brains do not play a large part in the life of a girl; nor does beauty nor culture. As long as she has a dowry, the other qualities can be minimized. But to have a dowry for each daughter signifies the need of parental wealth; and show me ten Greek families which have thousands of dollars for dowries?</p>
   <p>Therefore, my sad friend was justified for being despondent over the birth of another daughter. His only consolation and hope lies in the thought that surely, by the time the child reaches adulthood we Greeks will have been taught such a hard lesson, we shall have suffered so many disappointments, that we shall have reached a state of civilization like the other races, in which the birth of a daughter causes no dismay. Then the Greeks will pray <pb facs="5422062_1_0784.jpg" n="4"/>for good and intelligent children of either sex.</p>
   <p>If anyone expresses hope for a boy it will then be merely a statement of preference; it will not voice economic fear on the part of the future. Wait, and you shall see. Customs change in accordance with changes in environment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
