<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Enroll Now in the Army of Progress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ENROLL NOW IN THE ARMY OF PROGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Young Greeks of America--who labor daily in factories, and restaurants, and idle away your evenings in poolrooms and at gaming tables of the Cafes--you are asked to enroll in an army today.</p>
   <p>You are asked to train yourselves in the use of weapons, which you will use in the lifelong battle for existence.</p>
   <p>Now is the time when the night schools open their doors. They teach all professions and trades. You young Greeks who are fortunate to live in an age of free education, do not waste these precious hours of your lives.</p>
   <p>Many of you have already graduated from high school. Perhaps more of you would be students in universities if you had not succumbed to the lure of ease and Mammon; and deafened your ears to the sweet voice urging you to continue to learn. If you lived in Greece, there would be only certain trades open to you, and, therefore, your futures would be more or less of a <pb facs="5422062_1_0601.jpg" n="2"/>static nature. Here, perhaps, you have to start in at the bottom, but there is plenty of room for you at the top.</p>
   <p>In order to succeed, you must take advantage of the educational facilities offered so lavishly and so freely in the night schools of Chicago.</p>
   <p>While making a living you can also learn English, mechanics, commerce, law, or anything else you may desire. Think of your future and make preparations for it.</p>
   <p>It is our patriotic duty to demand your enlistment in this army of progress.</p>
   <p>More information will be published concerning the great opportunities for study offered by the night schools of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
