<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">Sept. 26, 1931</date><title level="a">The Greek Schools in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Rev. Tsourounakis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-09-26">Sept. 26, 1931</date><title level="a">THE GREEK SCHOOLS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Rev. Tsourounakis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- The Greek community of Chicago, in spite of the assimilating environment, is still determined to maintain and perpetuate the Greek language and the benefits derived from the knowledge of Greek literature.</p>
   <p>Although the community is composed of people in all stations of life, who are for the time being devided politically and religiously, nevertheless, they all in unison support the Greek schools. In these schools, the new generation is taught the Greek language and the traditions of the Greek race.</p>
   <p>It would have been much better, and more appropriate if all the schools were properly built and functioned under their own roof as educational institutions. Note-worthy among Greek schools is Koraes School of St. Constantine parish which is built upon American lines, and is not only suitable for educational purposes, but also suitable for gymnastics and recreation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0278.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Due to some negligence, the majority of these schools, which prepare the new generation of the Greek race to be useful citizens of the future, are not up to date. The fault indeed does not lie with the pupils, but with us, the elders. Much money has been raised for the purpose of erecting suitable buildings, but the money always has been spent in patching up old and out of date buildings, or spent in decorating Church halls where classes are held.</p>
   <p>The Greek community of Chicago should take an example from Greek communities all over the globe and begin to build its schools according to the requirements of the present era. Greek societies and Greek merchants of our city instead of giving a few thousand dollars for the keep of the present educational system, should add an item to their budgets for new schools for Chicago, thus providing enough funds to build suitable schools for our youngsters. The present system of assisting the schools is likened to beggary. We give a pittance to a beggar to keep him from starving. We don't better his miserable condition, but we perpetuate his misery.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0279.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If we want to maintain the respect and esteem of our new generation, we must, in the immediate future, eliminate the pittance, and make it our imperative duty to provide funds for suitable buildings and to appropriate annual funds for the maintenance of the new school buildings.</p>
   <p>Home, school, and church are undivided. Home and church cannot function properly without schools. Holy, great, and admirable is the Greek Orthodox church; holy and sweet is the Greek home; but the life and perpetuation of them both, in this country, is the Greek school. Without it the Greek church and the Greek home will fall into lethargy, become stagnant, and eventually disintegrate. Thus Greek idealism will be entirely destroyed.</p>
   <p>Let us not live only in the glory of the past. We must sufficiently and properly educate our new generation, so it will be able to stand on solid Greek traditions and thwart the menacing monster of assimilation. Bear in mind what Demosthenes said to the Athenians regarding the perpetuation of virtue, glory, and the traditions of our race.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
