<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Good at Talking</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD AT TALKING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The truth of these three words was shown at the meeting on last Thursday when a number of prominent leaders in our Community met with forty other leading Greek citizens to form a large committee whose duty it would be to devise ways and means of helping our Fatherland during these critical times. Naturally, the co-operation and support of the entire Greek community of Chicago would be necessarily sought. These men are to be complimented for thinking of how they could come to the assistance of a homeland which is beset by serious internal troubles, especially by the violence following the forced resignation of the Theotokis cabinet and the threatening uprising and revolution which is being brewed by the majority of the Greek army officers. In addition, the Neo-Turk Revolution in Turkey has given rise to new persecutions of the Greek population in Turkey, Asia Minor, and Macedonia. Then, <pb facs="5422062_1_1203.jpg" n="2"/>too, the Greek Patriarch has been intimidated by the Turkish government. It is evident that we are going through very difficult times in our nation's history.</p>
   <p>The idea of appointing a committee to help Greece if need be is an excellent one. Many hundreds of us went to the meeting of the committee of which the Reverend Ambrose Mandilaris was in charge. No one is surprised, however, when we say that the meeting brought no results whatsoever. The reason? Well, when the Reverend suggested that some more members of our community be appointed to the committee a great uproar was raised. Especially did the atmosphere become charged and feelings run high when the names of certain Greeks, who were being appointed to the committee, were read. Again, the eternal and ever-present agitator and scandal hound began to accuse this one and that one. Then a group of conspiring hirelings, professional orators, and troublemakers added to the general confusion of the noisy session.</p>
   <p>It really is regrettable that ever so often we start quarreling and wrangling <pb facs="5422062_1_1204.jpg" n="3"/>with each other in order that we may satisfy our own personal and selfish purposes. Why is it that we Greeks hate one another so violently and passionately sometimes? Why these personal animosities and insults? Why do we think that we are better than anyone else?</p>
   <p>It is because we refuse to recognize anyone else as better fitted and qualified to do a certain thing that we start arguing and attacking each other with rude and strong language. We must admit that we are good talkers but it must be well-known by now that with talk alone we can get nowhere. Very often, even when matters of the greatest and most vital importance come up, we prefer to fight and show how much we can talk about nothing. Because Mr. A or Mr. B was not invited to the committee meeting they would hinder work of national importance and destroy the aims of those who wish to work for a great cause.</p>
   <p>Although the Turks are threatening to persecute and convict our brothers in Turkey, yet the rest of us are blinded by passion and personal considerations.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1205.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Although the head of our church, our Patriarch, is being bullied and intimidated by the Neo-Turks, those of us who want to help our people and leaders in distress and mortal danger live to see their work and efforts sabotaged and destroyed.</p>
   <p>We think that it is up to the simple, common folk in our Community to take the reins in their hands. If our supposedly intelligent leaders and heads of our communities and organizations can do nothing to call a decent meeting, form committees, discuss our problems quietly and in a dignified manner, and collect money for our own and our homeland's needs, then we must dismiss them and let the peace loving, progressive, and good common folk of our Community take over.</p>
   <p>The people suffer for our homeland and want to help; we cannot allow five or ten rascals and agitators to shout and talk to satisfy their own passions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1206.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Greeks of Chicago, arise! Throw out the amateur troublemakers, the agitators, and the traitors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
