<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-11-06">Nov. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek of Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-11-06">Nov. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK OF TODAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek of today should be very happy that he is living in the happy time when his country's aims have been finally realized.</p>
   <p>Many generations have gone by, and many great men have vanished with the passing centuries, who desired only to see their dreams of Greece come true.</p>
   <p>Lucky is the generation that lives to see and be witness to the liberation of its enslaved brothers.</p>
   <p>It is terrible to realize that although the Negroes in America had been freed, the Egyptian slaves had been given their freedom, and the Hindus enjoyed liberty, that, in the twentieth century, Greece--who gave culture and a love of liberty to the world--should still be in slavery.</p>
   <p>But, justice, whether national or individual, always overcomes all obstacles in the end.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1094.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The World War brought many failings of the human race to light. The Germans dreamed of conquering a world and reducing the people to slavery. They were not the only people with this megalomaniacal complex, however. It became evident in the Turks and Bulgarians, and we are sorry to admit that at one time slavery was desired by certain groups in America.</p>
   <p>It is evident that Christianity and religion have not succeeded in impressing the world with a sense of right and justice.</p>
   <p>Greece gave to the world peace, love, and justice. It is the duty of all Greeks to practice these three ideals. By doing so, they benefit not only Greece, but themselves and America. Happiness is based, not upon money, but upon those three ideals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
