<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-04">Dec. 4, 1929</date><title level="a">Talints and Money</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0994</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0994.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-04">Dec. 4, 1929</date><title level="a">TALINTS AND MONEY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever writes about Greeks in America will never fail to bring out a certain phase of Greek characteristics. Our whole life is connected with newspapers, schools, churches, and clubs. All these put on various performances which you are asked to support. Here are a few examples:</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. who passes you on the street without even a nod, calls you up one day, and the following conversation ensues.</p>
   <p>"I am sending you 20 tickets (they are only two dollars each) to build a new church."</p>
   <p>"But, Lady- -..."</p>
   <p>"Bon't mention it; it's a pleasure."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0995.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"But, lady, I don't want to sell tickets!"</p>
   <p>"What are forty dollars, sir? You can easily sell all the tickets."</p>
   <p>"But, lady, there are plenty of churches already."</p>
   <p>"I'll send all twenty tomorrow. How is your wife and baby Fine? That's good. Regards. I'll see you all at our new church."</p>
   <p>She hangs up the receiver and begins her plans to catch another victim.</p>
   <p>Next day, Mr. B. comes to your office when you're busy and tries to sell you a book he wrote, "How You Breathe Smoke-Leaden Air." The only way to get rid of him is to buy the book for a dollar.</p>
   <p>"But, mister, I don't find time to read it," you protest.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0996.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"That's funny! I find time to write it," he says.</p>
   <p>"But why don't you try to sell it to the Salvation Army, the Chiropractic School, the Ahepa or Gapa?"</p>
   <p>"I've been there," he says as he pockets your hard earned dollar.</p>
   <p>Miss C. tells you about the theatrical performance her club is putting on for some charitable or educational benefit.</p>
   <p>"But, young lady, if you please....."</p>
   <p>"What, only two?"</p>
   <p>"No! Less than one!"</p>
   <p>"But, sir this is our first chance. You wouldn't want us to be a failure at the very beginning, now, would you?"</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0997.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>She won.</p>
   <p>I hope I live to see the day when all youngsters will be educated, when all poor people are properly taken care of, when all would-be poets and authors drown. Then I shall have peace!</p>
   <p>Jay Walker.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
