<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-12-04">Dec. 4, 1930</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">The President's Message and the Economic Crisis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-12-04">Dec. 4, 1930</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">THE PRESIDENT'S MESSAGE AND THE ECONOMIC CRISIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President's message to Congress was read yesterday and by all the people today. People were anxiously awaiting this message from their President. They were eager to see what measures the government would apply to bring the country back to its normal course from the daily increasing employment and condition of economic depression.</p>
   <p>The President's message, however, had a greater value as a research study on the situation today. To those who expected to be informed about the steps to be taken by the government regarding the conditions confronting it, the speech was a great disappointment.</p>
   <p>From the message as a whole, the President's effort to encourage the people and inspire confidence was about all that could be gleaned. When the administration does not express the real facts, it is natural that no proper attention will be paid to the economic situation, even though it is unprecedented in the annals of the United States.</p>
   <p>Of course, we did not expect the President to ring the alarm bell and discourage the people; but we did expect to hear along with his excessive optimism, <pb facs="5422062_1_1450.jpg" n="2"/>what steps it will be necessary to take regarding the economic situation through which we are passing today. Regardless of how optimistic an individual may be, cold reality remains; and encouraging words and optimism may indicate merely weakness and lack of resolution to face the situation and take measures to bring about at least some little relief.</p>
   <p>The measures suggested by which some relative improvement could be effected were public works on a large scale. In this way the number of unemployed might be reduced and business might recover somewhat.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, this measure expected by all proved to be a mockery of men's hopes. The sum recommended by the President for public works, 100 or 150 millions at the most, is an amount so insignificant that it would not have the least effect on the present economic and industrial crisis.</p>
   <p>This half measure is exactly of that sort which causes deep mistrust and creates the conviction that those in the confidence of the government have no clear conception of the present situation. They expect the crisis to pass without the adoption of serious measures, believing perhaps that it is one of the usual crises and they take no proper steps to alleviate it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
