<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">April 11, 1931</date> p. 1
<title level="a">Christos Anesti</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Christ Has Risen)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">April 11, 1931</date> p. 1
<title level="a">CHRISTOS ANESTI</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Christ Has Risen)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Contrary to the majority of the people who consider Christmas as the religious day par excellence, the Greeks consider the feast of the Resurrection their most holy religious day. This phenomenon we must attribute to climatological reasons in the main.</p>
   <p>Christmas is a feast of the winter season and it is only the people of the North who, being used to cold and snow, feel within themselves the cold environment in which they find employment regarding the winter feast. Cold does not bother them Nature to them has an imposing magnificence during the winter which Christmas falls.</p>
   <p>The reverse holds true for the Greeks, for whom nature appears favors them most during the spring time, with all its grandeur and charm; with the blooming of trees; green foliage; and blue sky which all predispose the people of Greece to celebrate the feast of Resurrection with all their heart and feel its magnificence very deeply.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0844.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The "Lampri", (Easter) is the Greek feast par excellence, it is the feast that nature itself imposes upon the Greeks, because the whole of nature also celebrates and becomes rejuvenated.</p>
   <p>That Christ has risen is felt and believed by every Greek, because nature inspires and imposes it upon him. For the Greek, the words "Christos Anesti" (Christ has risen) are not just a mere exclamation or a simple greeting amongst them on Easter day. They represent an indisputable truth. Around the Greek the whole nature is reflourishing reviving resurrection at this time, thus inspiring him to such a belief. How, then, is it possible for the Greeks not to consider the feast of Resurrection as the greatest of all? To enjoy the celebration of this great feast, on "Lampri",(Easter) one must be in Greece, because only there in the Greek environment may be hope to feel as Greeks feel about it.</p>
   <p>But, even for us, the Greeks of America, who from childhood felt its imposition deeply, despite the fact that we find ourselves in a foreign environment, which cannot inspire and predispose us for such a celebration, the reminiscence, only of Greek "Lampri", (Easter) make us feel its magnificence and <pb facs="5422062_1_0845.jpg" n="3"/>celebrate it with the same enthusiasm and grandeur that it is celebrated in Greece and announce to one another the cheerful tiding "Christos Anesti" (Christ has risen).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
