<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-10-04">Oct. 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Marriage in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-10-04">Oct. 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">MARRIAGE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago have always been interested in the question of marriage. Most Greeks in Chicago and elsewhere in America go to Greece in order to get married, because there are not enough Greek girls here. Recently, the marriage question has been widely discussed, especially in Chicago. Many authorities throughout America have been trying to discover the reasons for so many divorces and for the breaking-up of thousands of families.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Ann Rogers, who is well known for her profound sociological studies, has undertaken to reveal the main reasons for the failure of so many marriages. Here are some of these reasons:</p>
   <p>1. The ease with which divorce is granted in America. In America there are 2,191 divorce courts; in Germany, there are twenty-seven; in France, seventy; in England, one. Many individuals think so casually and superficially of marriage <pb facs="5422062_1_0772.jpg" n="2"/>because they know that a divorce can be readily obtained in case of matrimonial difficulties.</p>
   <p>2. Numerous marriage bureaus and agencies have been created for the purpose of finding wives and husbands for a certain fee. A business is made out of arranging and dissolving marriages by some despicable individuals. This is being done through the medium of newspaper advertising.</p>
   <p>3. The increasing liberal tendencies of the young American women. The social environment, sports, and amusements have made our youth, our young men and our young women alike, so liberal and independent that they are being kept away from family life and marriage.</p>
   <p>And the discussion continues in the American press with the prevailing opinion that marriage in America has failed.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago have witnessed the breaking up of many American homes <pb facs="5422062_1_0773.jpg" n="3"/>and families. Divorces are a common and ordinary occurrence. The Greek must be proud of his strong, secure, and indissoluble family ties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
