<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-29">June 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">An Ignored Truth (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-29">June 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AN IGNORED TRUTH (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Restaurant and hotel men are complaining that there is no profit in beer, but that they must sell it in order to meet competition. Some of them are actually hoping that, after the repeal of the Prohibition Amendment, the sale of beer will be forced back into the saloons by high license fees. One hotel man was quoted as follows in yesterday's Evening Sun: "Americans are not a people who drink when they eat. They simply eat. They drink between meals. It is my belief that a restaurant should specialize in food, not drink."</p>
   <p>But beer is also a food. Furthermore, the last few weeks have provided visual evidence that beer is not intoxicating to normal people who drink it in moderate quantities. Of course, beer is not going to pay the expenses of a restaurant, but neither is butter, and restaurants can hardly quit serving it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is unfortunately true that Americans are not, for the most part, a people who drink when they eat. They do drink between meals....and that is a problem that must be faced if true temperance is to be attained. It is because Americans drink between meals that they become drunk. If they could be persuaded to do their drinking with their meals, instead of guzzling on empty stomachs, there would be far less drunkenness. In the first place, they would drink less. And in the second place, who wants to drink a fiery, palate-searing concoction with his dinner? Wine is the strongest beverage a civilized man cares to take at the table.</p>
   <p>Even after repeal of Prohibition, if beer and wine are available at every restaurant, the bars will be far less popular. If restaurant proprietors are unable to make the distinction between fermented and distilled liquors, how can we expect politicians to do so? Whisky is one thing, and beer another, and if we don't realize that basic fact, we shall never be able to deal intelligently with the consumption of alcoholic beverages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
