<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-09-16">Sept. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Wedding Customs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-09-16">Sept. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">WEDDING CUSTOMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All of us know what takes place at Greek weddings in Chicago. At last Sunday's wedding the priest was wearing a "shiner" on his left eye, and the head of the groom was lumpy from bruises.</p>
   <p>The result of an old Greek custom; we have to throw handfuls of hard confections as large as walnuts at the bridal pair--a barbarian custom, I declare....Is that nice?</p>
   <p>What does this custom signify? Does it signify, as we claim, good luck to the newlyweds? Does it carry our wishes to them on the occasion?</p>
   <p>If the bride and groom have to suffer because of our customs, why do we include the priests in the merry-go-round-throwing of hard candy?</p>
   <p>Is that proper and dignified especially when the solemnity of the church <pb facs="5422062_1_0769.jpg" n="2"/>and its servants is involved? All of us know that the answer is no. Why do we do it? Why do we wish the newly-weds happiness, prosperity, and the rest of the blah-blah?</p>
   <p>The custom originally was to throw rice upon the newly-weds. Why did we change from rice to hard-candy? Maybe our Greek confectioners invented the new twist, and no doubt they did. If confectionery sellers are behind this custom, it might be good and well for the candy-makers and sellers, but for goodness sake, Mr. Candy Maker and Mr. Candy Seller, make the candies smaller and softer; our priests' heads are not so hard as the heads of the grooms to withstand such heavy bombardment.....</p>
   <p>All in all, whether it is business, fun, or custom of unknown origin, let us cut it out for the benefit of all concerned, and instead of throwing candy upon the heads of the people, let us throw it into our <pb facs="5422062_1_0770.jpg" n="3"/>mouth. That may satisfy the Greek candymen and also the dentists.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of the priests (if they don(t want any more "shiners") to impose their will upon nuptial participants that this barbarian custom must be discontinued....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
