<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-16">Oct. 16, 1929</date><title level="a">What an American Thinks of the Greeks by Rev. J.M. Rife</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1004</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1004.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-16">Oct. 16, 1929</date><title level="a">WHAT AN AMERICAN THINKS OF THE GREEKS By Rev. J.M. Rife</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reverend J.M. Rife, writer of the series of articles, "What an American Thinks of the Greeks", is a well known Phil-Hellene, who has taken a special interest in the study of Greek. He is, at present, attending the University the University of Chicago where he is delving into the beauty of the Greek language and the great contributions of the classic writers. The Greek Press feels indebted to Mr. Rife for his willingness to contribute a series of articles on the subject, the first of which follows:</p>
   <p>Believing it is good for all of us occasionally to see ourselves as others see us, I have accepted the invitation of the editor to tell the Greeks, in a series of short articles, what some of us Americans think of them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1005.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The editor suggests that I make at this point, a few statements as to how much of an American I am, and what right I have to express an opinion about the Greeks. I do not like to do this, but it is, perhaps, no more than fair. I am a one hundred per cent American, all except the white sheet and mask. My ancestors came from Switzerland, Germany, Sweden, England, Scotland, Ireland and Wales, and all arrived before 1800. I have lived on the farm, in small villages, and in cities up to the size of Chicago. When I was thirteen, I borrowed a Greek grammar and learned the alphabet and a few words. I had two reasons for doing this: I planned to devote my life of natural science, and I hoped to be able, at some time, to read the New Testament in its original language. Since then I have been increasingly interested in the language, finally becoming a teacher of Greek. During my college days, I decided that the best help in learning Greek would be accuaintance with Greeks. In carrying out this idea, I have made accuaintances and friends in New York, Philadelphia, Pittsburg, Columbus, Cincinnati, Dayton, Indianapolis, St. Louis, Kansas City, Chicago, and other American cities. I have not yet had the pleasure of visiting the Greek fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1006.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Next week I plan to begin telling some of the good things, and some of the bad things in connection with the Greeks, which have impressed me, as well as other Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
