<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-03-10">Mar. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Character</title><title level="a" type="sub">by C. Salopoulos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-03-10">Mar. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK CHARACTER</title><title level="a" type="sub">by C. Salopoulos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The character of a man, is the barometer of his worth. From the moment he is born the formation of his character is guided by surrounding influences. The climate and the manner of living of his associates are very important factors in his character development.</p>
   <p>The individuals born in Greece are usually of medium height, lean,-- but inclined to put on weight after middle-age--and of olive complexion. They are industrious, and can withstand much labor and abuse. Outside of the soldiers of two or three countries, there is no army in the world whose soldiers fight so well, and at the same time live only upon bread, olives, cheese,and water. This characteristic is also true of the workingmen.</p>
   <p>The Greek as a rule is lively, mechanically minded, liberal in his views and friendly to an extreme degree. He is usally troubled with a superiority <pb facs="5422062_1_1145.jpg" n="2"/>complex which prevents him from accepting the views of any one else...He desires to become president, mayor or anything else bearing a pompous title in order to satisfy his egoism; despite the fact that he might have no qualifications for holding such a position.....</p>
   <p>He prides himself on his patriotism, and is forever raising funds or contributing to some patriotic cause. In a political argument he is very apt to lose his calmness, and throw even his patriotism--not to mention a few saints--to the devil.</p>
   <p>He is extremely hospitable, and is very sensitive concerning his honor and good name. He will turn into a raging beast if aspersions are cast upon his or his family's honor. Because of his inherent friendliness, he is often the object of duplicity--as are many other foreign people. The Greek has always hated monarchism or dictatorship; desiring and often fighting for equality and freedom. He will sacrifice all he holds dear in order to obtain justice. He desires to take <pb facs="5422062_1_1146.jpg" n="3"/>part in the affairs of his government and to have a voice in the election of its officials. He will blindly follow a worthy leader in whom he trusts. There exists an old saying "A Greek enslaved, is very good; free, he is dangerous." However, we do not venture to agree or disagree with this proverb; nor do we know if it is or is not true.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
