<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek School Again</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK SCHOOL AGAIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek school problem has again aroused great interest. But in spite of the strong desire of our countrymen to establish at least one permanent and complete Greek elementary school, we regret that no definite steps for its ultimate realization have been taken.</p>
   <p>Because of the long distances the children must travel to school in the Greek quarter, there have been many discussions and controversies regarding the question of the most suitable location for the school. And there has been no evidence of an attempt to launch a city-wide drive for necessary school funds. Nor have those of us who were nobly inspired to create an adequate school system shown sufficient initiative and courage to actually <pb facs="5422062_1_0488.jpg" n="2"/>do something about the matter. But all this can be easily done if, above all, we keep united and work harmoniously together. Otherwise, we shall forever be talking and writing without any results.</p>
   <p>The excuses that have been advanced--that no saitable site for a school building can be found, that the parents are not interested in providing Greek education for their children, and that we have no properly trained and qualified teachers--are all poor excuses and pretexts, born of mental inertia, callous indifference, and stupidity. Someone has proposed that one of the houses belonging to our church community be used for a school. Another way out of our supposed difficulties is to appoint our priests as temporary school teachers. They have the ability and the time to direct our small schools. Besides, the education of our children should be one of their fundamental duties.</p>
   <p>Under such arrangements, the doors of the school can open, and our leaders <pb facs="5422062_1_0489.jpg" n="3"/>and educators will then see how the parents will rush to send their children to a place where our religion, history, culture, and language are taught. The beginning might be difficult, but courage, strength, and determination are needed to accomplish any worth-while task. Let us remember that the beginning is half of the whole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
