<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-07-16">July 16, 1931</date><title level="a">Beyond Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0953</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0953.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-07-16">July 16, 1931</date><title level="a">BEYOND TOMORROW</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The Greek Community of Chicago has not been used to annoucements, like the following: "Archbishop Athenagoras, will speak on Heine". The Greek populace of Chicago has listened to most anything commonplace, but never to anything that savors of the higher intellect. The speech, which his Eminence is to deliver at the North Shore Chapter of the Ahepa, is attracting the attention of all lovers of the higher things of life.</p>
   <p>The self-styled Greek intelligentsia of Chicago, feeling somewhat as though M. M. Athenagoras is treading on their ground, will delve into many a volume, in the next few days, to refresh their minds about the life and works of Henrik Heine. The North Shore Chapter of the Ahepa is rendering a real service to our colony when it offers to our people such an intellectual treat, coming, as it does, from no less a person than the head of the Greek Church in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0954.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Bolsheviki leaders still persist in declaring that the capitalistic world is preparing for a gigantic war against Soviet Russia. That the capitalistic countries of the world would want to see communism exterminated goes without saying. But that in order to succeed in a sort of a holy war, is a supposition, which cannot be convincingly supported.</p>
   <p>History is replete with facts about costly mistakes that leaders of nations have made. Humanity has often and again been bled white by the blunders of its great men. It is to be hoped that no other such blunder is to be made and the crime of war thrust again upon the sons of man.</p>
   <p>With the leaders of the country enjoying their summer vacations and the populace sweltering in the slums of the cities, observers of existing conditions are becoming more pessimistic. While summer is still on the sufferings of the people are not as noticeable as they will be when bleak winter comes and the sharp boreas winds will blow through the streets of our modern cities. Thoughts of that sort are not the results of pessimistically inclined minds, but constitute an existing reality of things, for which modern society, with all its boasted advancement, cannot justify itself.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0955.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Graeco-Americanus confesses that what has transpired in Europe, the past few days, is beyond his Ken. It will be indeed too much for him to grasp the trend of events, when no less a person than our renowned secretary of the treasury declared the other day, that he has not kept up with the turn of events. And all this time we were resting at ease, believing in the omnipotence of Andrew Melon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
