<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-07-26">July 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Terror and Dictatorship</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-07-26">July 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">TERROR AND DICTATORSHIP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Serious, terrifying, and inhuman acts are taking place in Europe. Four months ago, a self-styled great man, the chancellor of Austria, Dolfuss, in the name of the law--as he understood and interpreted it--spread fear and terror throughout the nation. He ordered the massacre of thousands of his fellow citizens, simply because they did not approve of the way he was trying to govern Austria. The idea of "dictatorship" ripened with the success of Dolfuss.</p>
   <p>Within a comparatively short space of time, Europe was the scene of the crimes of another dictator, Adolph Hitler. He, too, spread tyranny, and ordered wholesale imprisonments and barbarous murders among the innocent German people. Not only did he kill strangers; some of his victims were even close friends and associates. No sooner had Europe quieted down a little after the Dolfuss uproar than it was again shaken <pb facs="5422062_1_1492.jpg" n="2"/>by the barbarity of the German tyrant. The murder of Dolfuss, by the Austrian Nazis, added to the European unrest. It is still very difficult for anyone to be assured of the future of Austria in the face of Hitler's known desire to conquer all of Europe.</p>
   <p>This terrible unrest has caused another fear to grow in the hearts of all Europeans. The fear of--war. Despite the fact that the Nazi revolt in Austria has been an open move, it is still impossible to say what the next day will bring forth. The fight between the Austrian Nazis and the Austrian Fascists is being watched by the Socialist party, which comprises forty per cent of the population. Divided as they are into three armies, the Austrian people can only be united by sheer force. In this case, one force is struggling against the other for the supremacy which will enable the winner to control the nation. Each of the two opposing forces has the support of an exterior party which is anxious to swallow Austria. Germany on one side, and Italy on the other, watch the Austrian debacle with satisfaction.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1493.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These two prominent and most powerful European dictators, Mussolini and Hitler (the men who seek to assimilate all the lesser European nations), do not understand that they are not the only ones who can control the rhythms of European politics. The ideology of Hitler is opposed by the Italian ideology. For instance, Austria at present is being fought over by the two parties; and neither tolerates the other. Not that France is uninterested in the fate of Austria; but Germany believes that the Italian threat is stronger than the French. The French policy of not permitting seizure of small countries is well known. Hitler also knows that the slightest step in that direction might bring about war. The French democracy has clearly defined its policies. Dictator-ruled Italy, however, is uneasy because her policies are not approved of--and have not been formulated by --the Italian people. They are the policies of the all-powerful Benito Mussolini.</p>
   <p>All the reassurances we get from abroad concerning the peace and policies of Europe are just smokescreens. Europe will not be peaceful many more years. These two dictators are preparing to cast Europe into the hell <pb facs="5422062_1_1494.jpg" n="4"/>and fire of war, so that their maniacal desires may be satisfied. Fortunately, there are France and England to help balance the situation.</p>
   <p>The only safe weapon against war is democracy. So it seems unavoidable for these countries, ruled by dictators, to remain peaceful long.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
