<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-14">Sept. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Slaves for Sale!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-14">Sept. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SLAVES FOR SALE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Slaves for sale were offered to the highest bidder in Detroit some days ago, and in Chicago last Sunday.</p>
   <p>We feel proud of our civilization for having emancipated the women from being considered soulless, the child from being exploited by greed, and the slave from being considered a part of the chattels of any clever individual. Nevertheless, in the year 1921, and in the wealthiest country of the world, which could maintain twice its present population in undreamed of comfort, the workers are sold at public auction! And yet nobody blushes with shame or indignation because of such an act. They are all smiling at the innovation!</p>
   <p>The auction in Chicago was held last Sunday morning in two churches, by two Priests, who offered eight unemployed slaves for sale to the highest bidder, pleading with their rich parishioners to buy them in order to enable the poor creatures to have a "bite to eat."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1454.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And then there are some ungracious and unreasonable individuals who say that man is free. And other irrationals, also, who believe that slavery of man has vanished.</p>
   <p>And there are still others who say that people govern themselves by having Democratic forms of government.</p>
   <p>The fact that Priests and Pastors, of the Christian faith, were the ones who undertook the transaction of a public auction of the slaves in the 20th Century, is of great significance and provokes sad thoughts. Why did not these Lord's servants succeed in twenty long centuries in improving humanity?</p>
   <p>Did Christian religion as a philosophic system fail? Or is priesthood a big bluff? Priesthood is mainly the cause of all the present evils of humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
