<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-08-12">August 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The American System</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-08-12">August 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN SYSTEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an editorial of a previous issue entitled "Duty and Interest", we spoke not only of proper conduct, but also pointed out the mistakes made by some of our fellow-countrymen which provoked resentment directed even against our best and most progressive citizens. We mentioned the tremendous dangers we face if this deplorable state of affairs continues. This article was so warmly received by our own people, that a great number of congratulatory letters flooded our offices.</p>
   <p>This not only establishes the truth of our opinion, but proves that our self-respecting, honorable,and chivalrous people breathed a sigh of relief that a beginning had been made in the instruction of those who having forgotten all--duties, interests, and obligations--have sought to live and work by dishonest methods. Apparently these individuals do not realize that they did not come here in order to reform or change the system,but to work and live according to the existing system. They even became so selfish and officious <pb facs="5422062_1_1062.jpg" n="2"/>as to think that for their own purposes and interests, they could overlook the interests and will of others. They disobey the laws of the country which has offered us this gracious and valued hospitality by which we have lived--which has given us our well-being--which has preserved and benefited our relatives and nation. We declared that if we desired to become worthy individuals and citizens, we must believe in and pursue the accepted social and business principles, that is truthfulness, honesty, and industry. In the absence of these prerequisites, we can never hope to attain any good in our life--even should it accidentally be won, it cannot be long-lived or permanent.</p>
   <p>Thus we have a personal interest in telling the truth to all and at all times, regardless of personal cost. For in this country, truth is worshipped as a goddess, above every other divinity. Truthfulness is the only powerful medium which will be heard, supported--[which will make possible] business relationships and win the confidence of any third party.</p>
   <p>"Who is the city's deceiver," said Demosthenes, "is it not the one who says not what he thinks?" Consequently, a city or community is deceived by the one who says the exact opposite of that which he knows or thinks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1063.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By telling the truth and working consistently according to the laws, systems, and sentiments of other people--by respecting the rights of others, we create an honorable reputation for ourselves, which is the second condition of a civilized existence. These two elements are not sufficient, however, to assure prosperity and a civilized status for the individual. A third element is required--industry. A famous ancient Greek apothegm said "With Athena's assistance, help yourself." Energy and industry are the motivating forces of all constructive work.</p>
   <p>Now then, when we fully understand these prerequisites, regardless of our mental attainments, we know that we shall not only forge ahead but, as law-abiding citizens, we will receive the appropriate support and encouragement from the American public.</p>
   <p>These remarks are understood by the honest intellectuals among our people to indicate the guiding principles of our social and business conduct in this country. It should be emphasized that for the benefit of our individual and common interests, we should force our erring countrymen to abandon their evil ways. They should be corrected and enabled to return to the right road of <pb facs="5422062_1_1064.jpg" n="4"/>decency and duty. Thus we should endeavor to be sincere, courteous and truthful in our relations with commercial [enterprises], banking institutions, landlords, and their employees or representatives. We shall always be the winner. On every occasion, we should be neat, clean, and well-dressed. We should ask honestly and sincerely for that which can justly and reasonably be given, or done.</p>
   <p>It is only through such behaviour that we can gain [respect] and live decently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
