<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Increase Your Business Knowledge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">INCREASE YOUR BUSINESS KNOWLEDGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The roar of the cannons has ceased. Military bugles and war-songs are heard no more. The young men who fought for freedom are now returning to pick up their tools. The struggle of bayonet and gun is over, but the struggle for existence did not cease, nor will it ever cease.</p>
   <p>The basic cause for most wars is business and trade. The trading spirit is what creates wealth, happiness, and benefits for every individual and country.</p>
   <p>This spirit is, I am glad to say, very much present in the Greeks. We are lacking in the ability to rise above our rivals in the business world. Just as a struggle of war is won by the highest trained men and the most wellequipped army of the modern type, so must a person struggling in the business world, have the latest knowledge of business and its methods.</p>
   <p>If we wish to benefit ourselves, we must take advantage of every opportunity to become familiar with the newest trends in the commercial world. By adhering stubbornly to our past standards, we are certain to fail and bring <pb facs="5422062_1_0166.jpg" n="2"/>destruction upon ourselves. The only thing necessary in order to learn the latest, is to possess ambition and persistence. Various night and day schools exist wherein all branches of business are taught.</p>
   <p>We ask all readers of the Saloniki, to give serious consideration to this matter, and to take advantage of these means of raising their intellectual and business standing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
