<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-06-18">June 18, 1931</date><title level="a">Beyond Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-06-18">June 18, 1931</date><title level="a">BEYOND TOMORROW</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- In making his initial appearance, as a regular columnist of the Greek Press, Graeco-Americanus--as the name itself implies--will write about persons and things, and survey the trend of events, in the spirit of a dualistic Greek and American personality--but primarily Greek. The scope of subjects that Graeco-Americanus will touch upon will be of general interest to every newspaper reader. At times they will be of local interest and quite frequently they will deal with national and international affairs.</p>
   <p>No effort will be made to write of things that will appeal to the Greek mind alone.</p>
   <p>Although at times things will be written about what a Greek shepherd boy grazing his sheep in mount Parnasus , Al Capone will not be overlooked.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0957.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Time there was--and not very far off--when writing in English for the Greeks was done with the sole object of prompting them to read English, in order that they might learn the language for utilitarian purposes alone. Things have, however, changed in the very short span of a quarter of a century. Whereas, formerly the bulk of our people were ignorant of the English tongue, the present status, if not quite reversed, is tending to that direction.</p>
   <p>All far-seeing individuals envisage the day when the Greeks of America will converse in nothing but English and will issue their newspapers in English.</p>
   <p>Though they will then be nothing but native born Americans, there will still remain a number of distinct characteristics among them to justify any tendency for retaining their distinct national characteristics.</p>
   <p>Since we are in a mood of writing about the status of Greeks in Chicago, surveying the present conditions in the business world, we are prone to express a hopeful view of the business world. As our people are mostly <pb facs="5422062_1_0958.jpg" n="3"/>engaged in the retail business they naturally suffered mostly from the existing depression. Their business astuteness, their industry and frugality will once more assert itself and soon we will see them again prospering and thriving in the business world.</p>
   <p>Just now trade has reached its lowest levels. All economic laws point to the fact that what goes down must also go back. And unless all signs of improvement fail, the country has weathered the storm and business is destined once more to keep on increasing in a slow but steady pace till the desired haven of destiny is reached.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
