<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-26">Dec. 26, 1929</date><title level="a">Hospitable Housekeepers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0819</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0819.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-26">Dec. 26, 1929</date><title level="a">HOSPITABLE HOUSEKEEPERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the Greeks, more so than other nationalistic groups, perhaps due to the many holidays, the winter season is one of association and hospitality among friends.</p>
   <p>During those days, for some reason, the housekeeper's position is one to be envied. She takes the lead in displaying her culinary skill, her "Emily Post" etiquette and her graciousness. She has the power to please her guests and hold them or to make them leave early. There are many categories in which the ideal Greek housewife may be placed. We will give two examples.</p>
   <p>As you ring the bell in the first home, you hear doors closing, and audible whispers, and admonitions. The hostess finally opens the door, greets you in correct phrases, lacking warmth, and ushers you into the house. During the entire evening, everything is under her critical eye.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0820.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>She is all nerves and if a bowl of flowers or a glass of water is moved from its place, she is "on edge." She throws warning glances at her husband when he tries to liven up the party with a few jokes. Later she will tell him how many breaches of etiquette he made according to "Emily Post." The guests leave as soon as it is possible, although the food and the service were excellent. They resolve not to go again till etiquette demands they do so.</p>
   <p>The second hostess throws the door open as the bell rings. She greets us heartily and makes us feel as if she were waiting just for our arrival. She is gay, charming, gracious. She makes everyone feel at home. Her soup may be cold and a priceless glass may be broken, but she dismisses these incidents with a gay laugh. Later there are songs, games and dances. The evening passes quickly, and the guests leave reluctantly, thanking the hostess for her lovely hospitality.</p>
   <p>Both these ladies are true Greek housewives, each being perfect in her own way. Which do you prefer?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
