<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-01">Feb. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">History Repeats Itself</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-01">Feb. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HISTORY REPEATS ITSELF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In all the history of mankind there never has existed a period in which the peoples of the earth were satisfied with their lot and did not seek to make changes. Crude as human relationships and social structures were in early times, men nevertheless made experiments to find better systems of government. For thousands of years they dreamed of a Utopia, but they did not have the power to realize their dreams, nor did they have minds sharp enough to see the advantages and the evils [of their system of society]. The great majority, who were enslaved and subservient to a powerful few, could not believe that it was possible for them to become free. The desire for liberty was not yet born in their breasts because they had inherited their chains from their fathers and took them for granted. The tragedy of this cannot be understood <pb facs="5422062_1_1500.jpg" n="2"/>by people today, no matter how vivid their imaginary conception of this slavery may be.</p>
   <p>As time passed, from the depths of ignorance and barbarism the spirit of liberty began to make itself felt. It became stronger than the desire for family and the love of country. Men began to open their eyes to the facts that the purpose of life is to attain happiness, and that they as a group could fight for the right to attain it. Many years and [even] centuries of incessant struggle and torture passed, the struggle between the poor and the slaveowners. Finally, in various places on the earth, this idea achieved form, and the first communities or societies of comparative equality and freedom made their appearance.</p>
   <p>Those were the now well-known periods in which the minds of men, freed from spiritual and physical bonds, bequeathed to the future world the lofty ideas of equality and justice. But in society, just as in all nature, nothing <pb facs="5422062_1_1501.jpg" n="3"/>remains stationary. Everything is governed by certain natural developments; so we see the sad retrogression and backsliding of the human race which took place again.</p>
   <p>After these rays of light which appeared at various intervals in ancient history ensued a period of complete darkness, and the light was hidden for many centuries. If, however, the fire of learning was put out, and man again became enslaved, the spark of freedom for the individual never was completely extinguished. Slowly but surely the idea spread among men, and only the proper moment was necessary for the fight for man's freedom to begin. The right moment finally came, and the feudal system began to crumble the onrush of the capitalistic system, which was started by the abandonment of farms and a rush to the factory in the city. The rest is familiar...The twentieth century is noted for its remarkable achievements.</p>
   <p>Again today man seeks to find a better and happier society in which to live.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1502.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But now, a new spirit pervades [men's thought], the spirit of nationalism. The nation--the new tyrant--makes its strength felt guised as a dictatorship of fascism or of proletarianism. It seeks to destroy individuality and to create masses. Evidently the world is entering a new period, the future of which cannot be predicted. The new social conceptions are the ideas of a few, and as long as the many take no steps to prevent their rulers from leading them into slavery, it is to be feared that the few are going to cause us to retrogress instead of moving toward our goal of the ideal society. At least we find this to have been true in the past; and history does repeat itself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
