<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-01-30">Jan. 30, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">High Schools Give Instruction in Greek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-01-30">Jan. 30, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">HIGH SCHOOLS GIVE INSTRUCTION IN GREEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our readers must have noticed the article in the previous issue announcing the teaching of the Greek language in the American public high schools--of course, not all high schools, but only those in which enough students request such classes. More details are to be found on another page.</p>
   <p>What interests us most at this time is that there seems to be a good possibility of the Greek language's regaining its former universal prestige among students. At the close of the French Revolution practically all of the governments of the world began to provide free public education for all children. Greek was, in most cases, a required subject. As time went by the subject became an optional one, and was no longer rigidly required of students. The twentieth century, with its mechanical and scientific thought, made it necessary that students be taught more practical subjects and fewer cultural ones. This caused the study of the Greek language to be discontinued in the schools of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, due to various influencing factors, people again have time for leisurely pursuit of the finer things in life, and as a result Greek can again become a part of the high school curriculum. Greek children, if urged by their parents, will attend these Greek classes and learn the language of their parents. This is a rare opportunity for both the parents and their offspring--a patriotic one for the former, and a cultural one for the latter. Without any excessive sacrifice on their part, our youth will be taught the language of their forefathers--the language which was spoken or understood by all the great men of history since the time of Cicero.</p>
   <p>It is up to us to bring about a Hellenic revival of art and thought in America. Only the beginning is difficult; and that is made easier by the decision of the Board of Education to allow Greek to be taught in the high schools. As soon as the first students begin their Greek classes they will realize the value and benefit, and will themselves encourage their younger friends to speak and study the beautiful language of Hellas.</p>
   <p>It is our duty now to induce as many high school students as possible to take <pb facs="5422062_1_0176.jpg" n="3"/>the classes in Greek which will begin next semester.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
