<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-13">Apr. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Statements of Some American Girls for and against the Greek as a Prospective Husband.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-13">Apr. 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">STATEMENTS OF SOME AMERICAN GIRLS FOR AND AGAINST THE GREEK AS A PROSPECTIVE HUSBAND.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 - Our social reporter after months of exhaustive maneuvering has succeeded in getting an idea of what some American girls think of Greeks as prospective husbands.</p>
   <p>Janet, who is now Mrs. P. G poulos, said before her marriage, "I would not marry a Greek for anything in the world. They are terrible." When I met her last week at the dance given for the benefit of the Greek navy, she said, "I would not change my Petros for anything. I simply cannot spare him. He is the best man in the world."</p>
   <p>Marion said, "Bess has told me all about her Greek fiancee. They intend to get married, but he is jealous as the deuce. I would not marry a Greek."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ruth: "I like Greeks very much, and I have an eye on one, but he needs lots of training. He has peculiar habits."</p>
   <p>Florence: "I have a Greek beau, and I am crazy about him, but I don't like his father. He is too strict."</p>
   <p>Leona: "Marry a Greek? I should say not: They are all rude and unpolished. Not for me!"</p>
   <p>Lois: "I have set my cap to catch him. He is the nicest and handsomest Greek that I have ever seen. He thinks that he is too smart, but I shall get him!"</p>
   <p>Sally: "I should like to marry a Greek, but gee! They get my goat with their pride. They think and act as if they were the whole cheese."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sigrid: "I come to dances and meet lots of Greeks. I don't like them; they are too fresh. One is just as bad as another, but Ill marry one if I find my type."</p>
   <p>Vivian: "I do not know. I rather like Greeks, but mother says, 'Look out for the Greeks; they are tricky!' Of course they cannot all be bad."</p>
   <p>Margaret: "I would not marry a Greek on a bet! Those that I have met are of no account. You cannot trust them."</p>
   <p>Barbara: "Mother and I like Greeks and I like my Nick very much, but my, oh, my, I cannot stand his vanity! Nick is good-looking, with brown eyes, and curly hair, but his head is empty. He thinks that every girl is in love with him. I am afraid of that."</p>
   <p>Edith: "I have one on the hook. He is the nicest Greek in Chicago, but his English is all Greek to me."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1313.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Ann: "From what I have heard and observed, the Greeks are my ideal. Katherine, my bosom friend, who is married to a Greek with a funny name, tells me that they are good people, good providers, honest, but jealous to beat the band."</p>
   <p>Elizabeth: "I would not marry a Greek. They are all dumb. I get so angry when I go to the corner candy-store for ice-cream. George, the boss, acts as if he was the mayor of Chicago. When Bill, who works there, comes to serve me, George always finds fault with him and bawls him out. George has an eye on me, but I like Bill. In short, I shall not marry George unless he changes."</p>
   <p>Julia: "I have seen enough of Greeks. They are worse than Turks. They want to have a real harem. I would not endure anything like that. They are cheaters. Why, I have just broken my engagement with John M. Sophie told me that he loves her. I do not want to see a Greek for the rest of my life. They are of no account, and they are not Christians. I am through with them!"</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1314.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Irene: "I am proud to tell the world that I am in love with my Panagiofis. I call him Pan. Though not throughly Americanized, he is the best boy in Chicago. Mother and father watched him for months before they consented to let me go with Pan. Father deals with Greeks, and he likes them, but he says, 'You have to keep your eyes wide open in dealing with Greeks; otherwise they will skin you.' My Pan is all right; the whole neighborhood likes him and patronizes him. Why, he is only a boy of twenty-four and he has a good business! Everybody speaks well of him. Some of the girls whom I know tell me that Pan is all right, but that he is just like the rest of the Greeks; a Greek has a wife in every town! I do not believe it. I love my Greek!"</p>
   <p>The statements above which express the opinions of American girls who in one way or another have come in contact with Greeks, were elicited with prodigious effort, and girls of many races were interviewed. Undoubtedly in years to come the Greek-American or American-Greek generation will comprise youth of many races.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1315.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Jealous, vain, and cheaters! These words express the charges made against the Greeks according to these statements.</p>
   <p>These faults, however, are outweighed by the numerous virtues which the Greek possesses according to the girls who have observed them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
