<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dance Given by the Plato Club of Greek Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DANCE GIVEN BY THE PLATO CLUB OF GREEK STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--The dance of the Chicago Greek students, which was given last Sunday in the aristocratic ball-room of the Sherman Hotel, was remarkably successful and was conducted with dignity and decorum.</p>
   <p>More than four hundred prominent people attended and danced to the music of an up-to-date orchestra.</p>
   <p>A splendid buffet supplied refreshments, in charge of the wife of the Reverend Father Hatzidemetrios, who like her husband, Father Constantine, and their children is always ready to offer her services for the benefit of any national or social affair.</p>
   <p>The proceeds of this dance are to be devoted to a sacred cause, the relief of the refugees from Asia Minor who are being received in Greece. For this reason the students in an interval in the dance-program exhibited motion pictures of the catastrophe in Asia Minor. The pictures aroused deep emotion, and tears fell in profusion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the pictures the president of the Club introduced Consul General Mammonas, who made a patriotic and touching address, urging the guests in the name of Christian brotherhood to perform the national and humanitarian duty of coming to the aid of Greece in its great disaster, which affects not only the refugees but the nation and its civilization as well.</p>
   <p>"I have recently been in Hammond, Indiana," said Mr. Mammonas, "to speak for this cause, and our brothers there have contributed most generously. I hope that our Chicago Greeks also, since they are more numerous and have larger business enterprises, will as always be graciously liberal with their contributions."</p>
   <p>The consul general's speech aroused genuine emotion in his listeners.</p>
   <p>A collection was taken, and a lottery was also conducted by the students.</p>
   <p>We heartily congratulate our brilliant friends the students and their executive committee in particular, wishing them progress and success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
