<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-09-27">Sept. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">[Liberty under the American Constitution]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-09-27">Sept. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">[LIBERTY UNDER THE AMERICAN CONSTITUTION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For nearly one hundred and fifty years American orators have talked in vague generalities about the virtues of the Constitution, with the comfortable assurance (equally shared by their American audiences) that the democratic system of government which it established, or something very like it, was the inevitable goal of all political development.</p>
   <p>That assurance is no longer possible today, except to the intellectual ostrich who buries his head in the sand of his national traditions, and refuses to look at what is going on around him. Democracy not only has ceased to make progress; it is rapidly losing ground in parts of the world where, only yesterday, it was regarded as reasonably secure. If the speeches which were delivered throughout the country, on Constitution Day last week, left any one impression, it was of the growing anxiety felt by men of different political affiliations <pb facs="5422062_1_1481.jpg" n="2"/>for the future of democratic government in the United States should certain policies inaugurated by the New Deal be continued and extended.</p>
   <p>Whether such anxiety is justified remains as yet a question concerning which there is much ground for argument; but this, at least, is true;--the day of the uncritical approach to the Constitution has passed. Not since the completion of the deliberations of the Constitutional Convention and the ratification of the document it had drafted by the several states, have the basic principles of our political system demanded such careful examination as they do today. The champions of democracy do their cause poor service when they ignore either the failures of democracy or the idealism that is to be found in the modern forms of dictatorship, whether communistic or Fascist.</p>
   <p>Our political system has been described by one of its greatest exponents as, "government of the people, by the people and for the people". But the modern dictators, without exception, claim to be exercising their power in the interest of the people, and can point to important achievements that support their claim.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1482.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The dictators, indeed, go farther; they contend that they govern the people even more effectively than the people could govern themselves. It is with this contention that they justify all their repressive and arbitrary methods, including the destruction of political liberty. Democracy, from their point of view, is a clumsy and inefficient instrument, which is no longer adopted to the complexities of the modern industrial state. Mussolini has remarked that the democratic system may be all right for a wealthy country like the United States, but that it is far too wasteful for a poor country like Italy.</p>
   <p>This line of argument is not new. It has long been recognized that a dictator, clothed as he is with absolute powers, is in a position to function more swiftly and more efficiently, particularly in circumstances requiring prompt action, than the administrators of a democratic government. The defects of democracy are always painfully apparent whenever an emergency arises. But in spite of these defects--and they are very real defects--the democratic system continues to be the safest form of government that has yet been devised, for it is based upon an assumption that the advocates of dictatorship persistently <pb facs="5422062_1_1483.jpg" n="4"/>ignore. That assumption, as a brilliant Englishman, J. A. Spender, recently observed, is "the fallibility of human beings (including dictators), whose plans, schemes, and methods of government need to be worked out by argument, give and take, compromise, trial and error."</p>
   <p>Suppose the Soviet plan of collectivizing the farms fails to produce enough food. What can the people do except starve, as millions starved last year?Suppose Mussolini's regimented state stifles initiative, and finally lowers the standard of living. What is the recourse except revolution? Suppose Hitler's policies destroy Germany's foreign trade and so bring economic disaster. How can these policies be changed without another blood purge?</p>
   <p>The essence of democracy--distinguishing it from all other forms of government--is, that it alone makes provision for correcting mistakes without bloodshed. The system of regular and free elections, supported by the various types of personal liberty guaranteed by the American constitution, is the only one that takes into account <pb facs="5422062_1_1484.jpg" n="5"/>the facts of human experience and the need for constantly adapting government to the changing will of the people.</p>
   <p>The sacrifice of permanent security and of the great rights of personal liberty for some temporary advantage, no matter how valuable, are too high a price to pay. In considering all plans that are proposed for fashioning this country more closely to the heart's desire, one simple question should be asked: Can those plans be carried out safely under the democratic system? If not, then in the spirit of the remarks of Mr. Spender, made while he was pointing out problems with which his country was faced we should say: "The presumption is overwhelmingly against them, unless we are willing to sacrifice free institutions, to get them adopted."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
