<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-09-13">Sept. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Strikebreakers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-09-13">Sept. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">STRIKEBREAKERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Has a workman the moral right to work how, when, and where he pleases, even to the extent of becoming a strikebreaker? The right to individual freedom of action in the greatest possible number of ways is perhaps the most precious product of our civilization. To the extent that this freedom is assured and individual initiative encouraged, social progress is stimulated. In brief, the entire advance of the masses from serfdom and feudal bondage to the sovereign citizenship of our time has been due to the increase of the liberty of the individual in matters political, religious, and economic.</p>
   <p>It must not be assumed that trade-unionists seek to curtail the absolute legal rights of men to work how, when, and where they please. Whatever unduly coercive measures irresponsible and rash men have sometimes resorted to in times of industrial trouble, trade-unions, nevertheless are prepared to grant and respect the legality of the acts of nonunionists in breaking that commandment in the labor decalogue which says: "Thou shalt not steal thy neighbor's job."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1426.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The contention of the trade-unionist himself is that he has the legal right to sell his labor when and where he pleases; for this carries with it the legal right to refuse to sell his labor except under conditions approved by him. For, if it should be assumed that the individual workman has legally no choice in the disposition of his labor, an involuntary servitude would be established. This would effectively debar the union man from refusing to work with unfair men.</p>
   <p>A man may do many harmful, unjust things and still be within the law. The "Shylock" who forecloses a mortgage or evicts a widow and orphans from their little home is within the law. The merchant who bankrupts a smaller competitor by underselling him is within the law. The trust which freezes out the smaller dealer is also within the law. Hundreds of like instances are familiar to us; all of which conclusively prove that equity and justice are by no means synonymous terms. Hence, it is apparent that an individual wage earner may be acting legally, and yet be pursuing a policy which is seriously harmful to the interests of other workmen.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1427.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>responsibility, and leave them free to put on the halo attributed to them by that emminent personage who has designated the "scab" as the best type of modern hero.</p>
   <p>But it will hardly be asserted, even by the opposition, that men are seriously lacerated in conscience by refraining from taking the jobs of men on strike. The motive which leads them to do this may come from great need, from desire for promotion, from motives of revenge, but scarcely from the promptings of conscience. The very personnel of the organized group of strikebreakers is such as to render ludicrous, even grotesque, the assertion that they are at all influenced by conscientious scruples. If they have a conscience at all that article is so diminutive as to be indiscernible to the average eye. If the principle of democracy--that is, government by the majority--is sound, if a majority of a craft decide that it is for their best interests to refuse to work under certain conditions, why does not the presumption hold good that the majority are right in this instance as in others?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1428.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The time is rapidly approaching--and has already arrived in the older trade-unions--when the fact that a workman is a nonunionist is prima facie evidence that he is also an incompetent. Nonunion labor is usually overworked and underpaid labor. The very instinct of self-preservation, therefore, justifies the union workman in condemning the strikebreaker. The strikebreaker occupies in the industrial world a position precisely analogous to that of the renegade and traitor. He represents a type of man universally condemned in any other sphere of human activity. He sells himself for less than the thirty pieces of silver; and, too often, lacks the grace which prompted Iscariot to go out and hang himself. He commits the unpardonable crime of betraying his fellows. He purloins that to which he has no claim, and is the one stumblingblock in the path of the onward advance of wageearners. The attempt to make him respectable reflects discredit upon those engaged in it.</p>
   <p>For all practical purposes in civilized lands, we may consider the Golden Rule a sufficiently accurate measurement when applied to the present day code of <pb facs="5422062_1_1429.jpg" n="5"/>ethics. If the code does not "measure up" it is not moral, no matter how legal it may be. How does the act of the strikebreaker square with the sublime injunction, "Do unto others as ye would have them do unto you"? By what torturous logic can it be asserted that the man who from selfish personal interest seeks to profit through the industrial difficulties of his fellow men, is acting in accordance with the Golden Rule?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
