<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-11-21">Nov. 21, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Our Educational Reorganization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-11-21">Nov. 21, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">OUR EDUCATIONAL REORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The fourth Ecclesiastical Congress of the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America is proceeding apace to the end of its work, and it is about to bring up for discussion the question of the reorganization of Greek-American education.</p>
   <p>Nobody will deny the importance of this question, least of all the Most Reverend Archbishop Athenagoras, our witty pastor who has proved by his splendid activities for the reorganization of our vital forces here that he is at the height of his ecclesiastical and national mission, that he is the Good Pastor whom Divine Providence has provided for us as Spiritual Father, Organizer, and Savior.</p>
   <p>The clerical and lay representatives from all parts of America have come animated by the noblest sentiments and inspired by the sacredness of this historic epoch, for the Greek people abroad will be equal to <pb facs="5422062_1_0254.jpg" n="2"/>their task. They will formulate rules for our educational program, laying for the first time sound foundations for a better educational future and assuring proper religious culture for the Greeks of the new generation.</p>
   <p>The Church was ever the natural mother and protector of the Greek people abroad, and the organization of our schools would have remained un-accomplished if it had not been for our ecclesiastical unity and the assumption of this significant task by our ecclesiastical authority.</p>
   <p>It is the opportune time now, while all the Greek population has its attention focused on the Ecclesiastical Congress, expecting with confidence its salutary decisions, to realize the necessity of entrusting the responsibility, the duty, and the right to the Archdiocese of organizing the school system from which we expect the dawn of a better morrow for our countrymen in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0255.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The waste and futility which have heretofore existed will automatically cease the moment the Archdiocese undertakes the organization of our education on proper lines.</p>
   <p>The thousands of Greek children who are not yet under the beneficial influence of education will be gathered up by Mother Church in the well-organized schools of the near future as chicks are gathered under their mother's wings and will be mentally developed and morally nurtured by national and religious education.</p>
   <p>Blessed be the day and the hour when the Ecclesiastical Congress, under the benedictions of the Mother Church and with the best wishes and expectations of the entire Hellenism of America, shall formulate the educational program of the Archdiocese and insure the preservation of our mother language, our Orthodox faith, and our national ideals and traditions for coming generations.</p>
   <p>G. Drosos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
