<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-04-20">Apr. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Then and Now</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-04-20">Apr. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THEN AND NOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is just a social comment upon a subject that is of interest to most of the Greek girls. The greater part of the material was acquired in a discussion with a brilliant friend of mine concerning Greek girls of marriageable age.</p>
   <p>"Our girls, the young girls," said my scholarly friend, "up to the present time, have been the victims of certain delusions or fantasies. They have thought of the marital state as a Nirvana. They have not doubted that great happiness would be in store for them as soon as some wealthy Greek should ask for their hand in marriage.</p>
   <p>"Who can blame them for desiring wealth? As we all know, poverty is not a very thrilling prospect. Unfortunately, however, wealthy Greeks are scarce.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They were rare objects even in most prosperous times, but now they are practically extinct. As a result of modern conditions and the depression, at least ninety per cent of the Greek girls must cut the wings of their fancies and keep them closer to the ground. Once their feet are solidly on the earth, they will learn the joy of being the proud possessor of a three-room apartment.</p>
   <p>"Of course, it is the privilege of every girl to dream about a luxurious and carefree life. But the economic situation does not encourage the realization of such dreams. The inevitable conclusion is this: Any girl desiring to marry has the right to expect but two things: first, that her husband will hold her in love and esteem; and second, that he will be capable of earning an honest living for both of them. If a man cannot earn a living, then a girl is justified when she hesitates to marry him.</p>
   <p>"However,.....any man who earns a decent living and provides a home for a wife has the right to expect certain returns from her. If a wife knows <pb facs="5422062_1_0701.jpg" n="3"/>nothing about the care and maintenance of a home, if she cannot cook, and if she is an untidy housekeeper, her husband has the right to feel that he has been imposed upon. I firmly believe that no wife has the right to use her husband's stomach as a laboratory for experimental work in order that she may learn to cook.</p>
   <p>"These are among the problems facing the young girls of today who are anxious to get married."</p>
   <p>My friend has expressed it so well that there is no need for me to add to his statements. There is just one thing I would like to say, and that is: Life, today, has become so materialistic that there is little place in it for romance. Women are as deficient in romance as men. If there are no Pygmalions to say, "Give me a cave and Galatea," so there are no Juliets to kill themselves for their Romeos.</p>
   <p>When two people enter upon a social contract which can be either Heaven or <pb facs="5422062_1_0702.jpg" n="4"/>Hell, they get from it just what they give to it. If a girl wants to get a prince of a fellow, she should strive to be worthy of such a mate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
