<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">What I Can Do</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT I CAN DO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every democracy is as good as the people in it and no better. The kingdom of Heaven itself would soon go to pieces if left in the hands of ignorant, selfish and wicked beings. Immigrants often complain that although the United States is a democracy, a land of the free and a refuge of the oppressed and ill-treated, they, nevertheless, have suffered at the hands of some people here, just as they suffered in the old country. There is a good deal of wrong done, and altogether too much law violation, resulting in unnecessary suffering. Why? Because the citizens of this country are not doing their duty towards democracy. There is too much ignorance, too much indifference, and too much pure laziness. Things will not, and cannot be made better until there is an improvement in the citizenry, especially among our Greek immigrants, here in Chicago and elsewhere.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1074.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the first place, there are too many people here from other lands who do not know English. They cannot function as citizens, because they do not know how. Too many of them do not care to take the trouble to learn how, or to make use of their opportunities to influence things for the better.</p>
   <p>It must be your wish, and the wish of every man and woman who believes in the common good, to assist those who do not know the language of the land, or how to perform their duties as citizens. You naturally ask, "What can I do?" The answer is simple: "Know these duties yourself and see to it that your nearest neighbor knows them. Unless you do this, you have no right to complain about the government."</p>
   <p>In the second place, there are people who know the language and know how to perform their duties as citizens, but dislike the work involved in performing their duties as citizens. Others do only that which will bring them some immediate advantage. They are too blind to see that failure to <pb facs="5422062_1_1075.jpg" n="3"/>fulfill their duty well is bound to cause them a great deal of trouble eventually, and that to seek merely small favors, instead of honesty and efficiency in public service, is to deprive the people of much good and much greater advantages which come from efficient and honest administration. Again you ask, perhaps: "What shall I do?" And again the answer is: "First do what is right yourself, and then influence others to do the same."</p>
   <p>Lastly, there are people who use their influence as citizens for their own personal advantage at the expense of all the people.</p>
   <p>They not only vote, but do everything in their power to make others vote for them and their friends because they are going to profit. These people very often do great harm. They are responsible in a large measure for the neglect of the public welfare and the conduct of politics as a means of helping individuals or cliques who try to grab power. If the citizens were to do their duty, it would be impossible for these people to assume power, and men would be chosen whose purpose is right and whose goal is the <pb facs="5422062_1_1076.jpg" n="4"/>public good, Your good.</p>
   <p>Are you asking again: "What can I do?" "You can use your vote against the profiteer and for the honest, public-spirited man. You can influence others around you to do the same. You can be on guard always. One alert man, who does his duty in this way is worth a hundred of the indifferent. You cannot imagine of what great value you can be to the cause of democracy by acting upon these simple suggestions.</p>
   <p>Is it worth the effort? When you consider that your happiness and that of your family and friends, and what is still more important, the safety and the preservation of democracy, depend on your doing this, it is worth your while.</p>
   <p>Do you realize that men like George Washington sacrificed their lives that democracy might live, and you and I might be free?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1077.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Do you realize that thousands have given their lives fighting for the freedom which you are now asked to preserve? Do you realize that the way shown you is the only one which leads towards better days? Do you realize how much depends upon what YOU DO? BEGIN TODAY TO LEARN TO BE AN INTELLIGENT CITIZEN; TO BE AN ACTIVE CITIZEN, AND LASTLY, TO BE A COURAGEOUS CITIZEN.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
