<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-09-25">Sept. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Greeks of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Fruit and Vegetable Business</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_1410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_1410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-09-25">Sept. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEKS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Fruit and Vegetable Business</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a previous issue of The Greek Star we wrote extensively about the business situation in Chicago and its importance to the Greek people, a large number of whom are engaged in business. We said that free enterprise and individual initiative are greatly encouraged and protected by this country. It is only natural, then, that an enterprising and commercially-minded Greek people would take advantage of the great benefits and profits that can be obtained in such a land of opportunity. A great number of Greeks are engaged in the restaurant, grocery, and fruit and vegetable businesses. Many of our people have succeeded and are doing very well, but quite a number have suffered much and have lost money for several reasons. The Greek Star has been following the progress of Greek businessmen closely, and from time to time it has observed the handicaps under which they are working and conducting their individual business affairs. Lately, we have noticed that the Greek street peddlers of fruit and vegetables have been intimidated and forced to pay small fees to some conscienceless <pb facs="5422062_1_1411.jpg" n="2"/>policemen. The poor, struggling fruit peddler in Chicago has been oppressed without any reason at all. The ignorance and passive attitude of these fruit sellers invite some shameless and dishonest law enforcement officers to obtain money by making the fraudulent accusation that they are guilty of weight shortages and the use of wrong weights. Many Greeks have become the victims of such actions.</p>
   <p>In connection with this subject, we have received a very enlightening letter from a fruit and vegetable peddler who suffered this fate. He thanks The Greek Star for showing so much interest in the matter. He also mentions that The Greek Star has protected many Greek businessmen from being cheated and deprived of their legitimate profits and business returns. Time and again this newspaper has intervened and appealed to the police and to lawyers in order to prevent the persecution of honest and law-abiding businessmen. Our correspondent informs The Greek Star as well as the public and those who are engaged in the fruit and vegetable business that an association of Greek peddlers has been organized, under the name of The Peddlers' Protective Association, to protect <pb facs="5422062_1_1412.jpg" n="3"/>their interests and thus save themselves from the intimidations of dishonest individuals. Monthly dues to the Association are twenty-five cents; membership buttons cost five cents.</p>
   <p>It is needless for us to suggest that all our people who are engaged in the fruit and vegetable business should join this Association immediately. We have only to study the various and numerous American trade unions and labor organizations to be convinced of their importance and ability to protect the interests and improve the status of small businessmen and labor. This shows that the Americans have sensed the need for unity in industry, business, and labor.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt whatsoever that the organization of trade unions in all trades where the Greeks of Chicago work will certainly contribute to their welfare. The fruit and vegetable business is an important source of income for thousands of Greek families not only in Chicago, but also throughout the United States. The newly organized Peddlers' Protective Association will do much to <pb facs="5422062_1_1413.jpg" n="4"/>improve conditions of the occupation and eliminate all abuses against it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
