<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-24">June 24, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Language Is Scorned.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-24">June 24, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK LANGUAGE IS SCORNED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.. There is in the city of Chicago a social organization composed of Greek professional men. This organization should strive toward the attainment of ideals. It should avail itself of every opportunity to promote Greek thought and to preserve Greek customs. It should serve as an example not only to the Greek community of Chicago but to the entire Hellenism of America.</p>
   <p>During the seven years of its existence not only has this society, known as the Society of Greek Professional Men, failed to make any contribution to the Greek community of Chicago; it has even abandoned the use of the Greek language.</p>
   <p>The members of this Greek organization consider it a disgrace to use the Greek language, their native tongue! This is deplorable and seems almost incredible. We may be criticized for our frankness in publishing this statement, but it is a fact that this well known group of professional men, who are patronized almost entirely by a Greek clientele, refrains in the regular meetings and in <pb facs="5422062_1_0506.jpg" n="2"/>public gatherings from using the Greek language! This is an insult not only to the language of their native land but also to the clients who daily patronize them.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately this is not the first time that a pitiful situation of this nature has arisen. We have taken the opportunity to voice our opinion about it in this column many times in the past, and our efforts have not been entirely fruitless.</p>
   <p>Motivated partly by our journalistic comments on this neglect of the Greek language, some of the members of the club resolved that since it was a group of professional men of Greek extraction, all should be able to converse in their native tongue. These volunteers made untiring and persevering efforts to teach Greek to those of their fellows who could not speak it, and all mastered the language sufficiently well to deliver addresses in Greek in public gatherings.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0507.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This was indeed an achievement! But because of their ingenuous belief that as long as the Greek language had been adopted as the official language of the organization, it was unnecessary to do more, their efforts to encourage the use of Greek ceased, and the members of the club no longer speak Greek. Thus affairs are in the same state as before; a group of Greek professional men, men of science, lawyers, physicians, and some who practice other professions, scorn their language!</p>
   <p>A pitiful situation! There is no other way to express it.</p>
   <p>An organization of professional men casts aside the language of the land from which its members came and disdains it in its regular meetings and in public gatherings!</p>
   <p>The Greek Professional Men's Club recently served its annual dinner in honor of the Greek students who are about to graduate from universities in Chicago <pb facs="5422062_1_0508.jpg" n="4"/>and its vicinity. Throughout the entire program of the banquet not a word of Greek was spoken by any member of the club, as if the Greek language had been banished, and its use had been forbidden!</p>
   <p>On this occasion Greek should have been spoken, if not because their patriotism inspired the members to use their native speech, at least out of courtesy to the Greek Archbishop who was an honored guest. The only justification which the members had for using English throughout the program was that an American professor was among the guests. An assembly of Greek professional men had to abandon the use of their language on behalf of one guest who happened to be an American!</p>
   <p>To this justification of the professional men's conduct we make this reply: Since the members felt that they had to employ the English language out of courtesy to an American professor, why did they not show equal deference to the head of the Greek Orthodox Churches in America, who also honored the members <pb facs="5422062_1_0509.jpg" n="5"/>Why should the Greeks of Chicago prefer them? The American professional men at least speak better English.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
