<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-15">Mar. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago - What We Have Done, and What We Have - What We Have Not That We Must Have</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_1_0493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-14">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-15">Mar. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO - WHAT WE HAVE DONE, AND WHAT WE HAVE - WHAT WE HAVE NOT THAT WE MUST HAVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comparing the Greek community of Chicago with other Greek communities in America, one is confronted with the indisputable fact that because of its rapid growth and its material progress the Chicago Greek community is farther along the way to becoming a great colony than any other Greek community in the United States. No other community in America can rightfully boast of so many achievements as the Chicago Greek community. Since its establishment in 1890 this colony has been climbing to greatness. Beautiful churches have been established; a $40,000 lot has been purchased for another stately temple to be built in the immediate future; many societies, organizations, and fraternities have been organized, offering valuable assistance to the growth and the prosperity of the community; many well-to-do families are permanently established here, a solid foundation for the continued existence of the community; and hundreds of thousands of dollars have <pb facs="5422062_1_0494.jpg" n="2"/>been sent to Mother Greece for public works in our native towns and for churches, belfries, and church-bells.</p>
   <p>All this is very well, and due credit and honor are accorded to the leaders and the members of the community, but the most important thing of all has not been well done; in fact, it has been almost entirely neglected and overlooked. And that thing is the establishment of good Greek schools in our community.</p>
   <p>Greek schools, which will imbue our American-born children with the idea of the greatness of the race, which will teach them the Greek language and impress upon them the Greek character and Greek virtue, have not been, up to date, at the top of the list of the achievements of the Chicago Greek community. Why this oversight? Why do we deviate from the immortalization of our language, which is universally accepted as a masterpiece of expression? Why do we wish to deprive our youngsters of the Greek virtues and of the character which has distinguished the race among the nations and has lightened the world in its darkest days?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_1_0495.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The magnificence of our churches and other buildings, already built or about to be built, the tremendous sums of money which are annually sent to erect public monuments in Greece and to our relatives there, the many organizations formed or in process of formation, and the prosperity which we have achieved by hard and unremitting labor cannot compensate for the loss in culture which our children will sustain because of our neglect to establish Greek schools in our community.</p>
   <p>The powerful influence of America and the all-devouring American environment will in one decade leave no Greek color in our children unless Greek schools are established. The influence of parents and of the Church will not be strong enough to cope with the devastating current of pan-Americanism if our children are not properly tutored in their plastic age.</p>
   <p>Here I do not wish to be misunderstood. It is not that Americanism is detrimental to us Greeks or undesirable for us, nor that we should avoid it as the foe of our race; but we must not lose our identity in the universal metamorphosis which aliens undergo in America. We should be proud of being Americans, and our pride will be redoubled if we maintain the traditions of our <pb facs="5422062_1_0496.jpg" n="4"/>ancestors, who are also the forefathers of American idealism. Americanism is the crystallized manifestation of the high thinking of ancient Greece. Whatever Athens failed to accomplish in the liberation of mankind is being accomplished to-day by the universal spirit of Americanism. So the urge for Greek schools and for Greek culture is not in conflict with the lofty idealism of this adopted country of ours.</p>
   <p>The point that we wish to make is that we should retain our individuality as Greeks in this great universal country. And for the accomplishment of this purpose the indispensable prerequisite is that our children shall know the Greek language and the brilliant past of our race and shall acquire the Greek character and the virtues of Greeks.</p>
   <p>Greek schools alone will be able to instill into the plastic minds of our youth an idea of the tremendous responsibility of a citizen to his country and to mankind in general.</p>
   <p>It is the imperative duty of our Greek Church to exert its influence upon the faithful and so to persuade them to establish adequate Greek schools in every <pb facs="5422062_1_0497.jpg" n="5"/>community in the United States. Greek culture and the Greek Church are synonymous with enlightenment, civilization, and true religion.</p>
   <p>Let us put the subject of Greek schools on the top line of our list of activities and anticipated achievements. Let us hope that the leaders of our great community will put aside factionalism and regionalism and establish Greek schools for our American-born children. To do so will entitle them to credit and honor higher and more significant than the honors which they have earned by erecting beautiful and magnificent buildings and belfries.</p>
   <p>P. S. Lambros.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
