<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian-Lutheran Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-06-12">June 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN-LUTHERAN CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Church, in convention assembled, June 6 to 13, 1918, expresses its sincere and warm loyalty to our country and the administration in this critical time of war. As true citizens of this convention, we share with undivided hearts its weal and woe. We are persuaded that those who are administering the affairs of the nation have not entered into the war through selfish motives, lust of conquest, or in order to subdue or subjugate other nations, but have done so in the name of justice and righteousness and in the interests of true democracy. For this reason, the members of our Church stand back of the national administration with hands uplifted in supplication to the Almighty that our righteous and worthy cause may be carried on to victory. And we do promise through these serious days that now confront us, not only as Christians to bring the cause of our people, the cause of the administration, the army on land and the navy at sea before Almighty God in our petitions, but also to take our full share of responsibility in all demands made by the <pb facs="5423969_5_0328.jpg" n="2"/>administration upon the citizens of this country in order that the war's aim--the liberation of the oppressed and the bringing of peace to the small as well as to the greater nations--may be secured. But, however much we are convinced that the cause for which our nation now is contending is a righteous one, yet, at the same time do we also humbly confess that, because of the sins of our nation, we deserve severe chastisement, and that it behooves us to acknowledge our shortcomings, asking God for his mercy and pardon. God grant that this fearful war may teach the people to bend the knee before Him to whom belongeth the power and the glory forever.</p>
   <p>It was also reported that the camps and cantonments had been increased. There are also more than one hundred pastors at the camps here in America. The following pastors have been sent to France: Reverends M. M. Londahl, Carl Foss, T. A. Hoff, and C. T. Jensen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
