<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1912-06-13">June 13, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The United Church Synod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1912-06-13">June 13, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED CHURCH SYNOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The work done by the Norwegian United Lutheran Church in the missionary field is quite interesting. In 1911, in the mission stations in China, 301 were baptized, 2,402 received communion, 3,575 attended sermons every Sunday, and 578 attended schools. Twelve thousand books were sold. At the Lutheran seminaries in China, sixteen Chinese students passed the examinations and are now assigned to missionary work. The United Church has appointed Marie Anderson as principal of the higher schools for women in China; she has two graduate native women as teachers, and about thirty-eight native students. A special course was given last year for Chinese workers; sixty native males attended these classes.</p>
   <p>The school for males was well attended. The school for girls, in which Miss Anna Wilhelmsen was teacher, always had a capacity enrollment. The grade school has been attended by 239 children each year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0434.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The mission hospital is one of the most modern in the missionary field. Nearly four thousand patients passed through the clinic, and 235 were inmates during the year....</p>
   <p>At a new station in Central China, $57,000 was spent on buildings...</p>
   <p>The Mission Fund has a deficit this year of $4,376.18...The American missions have shown no gains over last year; it seems that only one or two missions--the Chicago and New York missions--have made a little progress...</p>
   <p>The Town Mission, in Chicago, has a new town missionary, Reverend C. Munson, who has improved the work here a great deal. He has, for example, opened a kindergarten in Harmony Hall, the first of its kind within the United Church....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0435.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the state prison, a library has been installed, and three meetings are held each week for the Scandinavian prisoners....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
