<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The United Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Waldeland reports that the circulation of Lutheraneren [The Lutheran, published by The United Norwegian Lutheran Church of America] has increased tremendously. Last year 21,000 copies were printed, producing a net income of $2,365.51. The circulation of The United Lutheran decreased by 800; the paper suffered a financial loss of $1,335.65 for the fiscal year.</p>
   <p>The status of the Sunday papers is as follows: The Lutheran Children's Companion now has 10,500 subscribers, an increase of 900 over last year. The Lutheran Children's Paper has 19,000 subscribers, a loss of 300 for the year. The net income last year for The Lutheran Children's Paper was $384.59; for The Children's Companion, $402.33.</p>
   <p>The report on schools was given by the national director of schools, <pb facs="5423969_5_0487.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend J. A. Asgaard. Part of this report is reproduced here.</p>
   <p>Our schools have, since 1862, done a great job among the Norwegian youth. This year the total enrollment exceeded 1,800 pupils, an increase of 195 over last year.</p>
   <p>Both the Seminary and St. Olof's College are becoming more and more popular each year. It was also reported that Reverend Hegge and Professor Steenland had resigned from the board of directors. St. Olof's College teaches languages, physics, elocution, religion, etc. C. O. Solberg was appointed assistant superintendent for the coming year.</p>
   <p>The Normal School has also increased its enrollment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0488.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Concordia Academy had 315 graduating students for the year; the Waldorf Academy, 303; Augustana Academy, 250; Pleasant View Academy,116; Columbia Academy, 82; Scandinavia Academy, 53--a total of 1,219 students.</p>
   <p>The Theological Seminary has added a museum to the school, and a number of interesting exhibits were received from Reverend M. Saetelie, who is in the Asiatic missionary field.</p>
   <p>After the reorganization of Augustana College takes place, it is felt that this school will become very popular. A four-year academy course has been added; in addition, the first year of college work will be taught. In the Normal School, a five-year course has been added, and the students who complete the five-year course will receive their state certificates upon passing an examination. Other new courses include a four-year business <pb facs="5423969_5_0489.jpg" n="4"/>course; a one-year postgraduate business course; and music classes, one for voice and one for piano.</p>
   <p>Two hundred and fifty students graduated from Augustana last year--127 men and 123 women.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
