<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-07-04">July 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Luther League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-07-04">July 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LUTHER LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the biannual meeting of the Northern District of the Luther League, the following resolutions were passed:</p>
   <p>1. The Young Peoples' League, in convention assembled, June 21 to 23, hereby acknowledge that God's goodness and mercy has followed our church in all its activities in the past year, and in a large measure has blessed our work in the church. Be it therefore resolved that thanks be rendered unto God our Father.</p>
   <p>2. The young people assembled here in convention, mindful of the many benefits conferred upon each and every one by our country, and of the great dangers threatening our country and its institutions in war, would hereby give expression to their loyalty to the flag and the principle for which our country stands. God bless America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>3. Realizing that the great temperance cause is one of the greatest issues before us, and that liquor forces must be destroyed, be it hereby resolved that the young people of this district are urged and requested to use all means available in defeating the liquor traffic on election day, November 5.</p>
   <p>4. The District League requests the young people in the congregations where there are no young people's societies, to organize such societies. And all young people's societies not belonging to circuit leagues be requested to join a circuit league.</p>
   <p>5. Inasmuch as the work of our church is dependent in great measure upon our schools and school work especially at this time, be it resolved that a strenuous campaign be inaugurated to induce our young people to attend our church schools.</p>
   <p>6. Be it also resolved that the Young People's League hereby express its appreciation and thanks to the Business Men's Leagues, the Lutheran <pb facs="5423969_5_0299.jpg" n="3"/>Churches, the pastors, and the president of Luther Academy for their good will. We appreciate the generous treatment of the press toward us and the great assistance given the convention of the St. Olaf Chorus, the St. Olaf Quartet, and Professor Christianson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
