<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-04-22">Apr. 22, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Norwegian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1921-04-22">Apr. 22, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD NORWEGIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the nineties people from all over the world came to Chicago, the metropolis of the West. Many of the arrivals were Norwegians; the majority of these came at the time of the Columbian Exposition. The newcomers had different reasons for coming here. Some came just to visit; others came on business; many of them came to stay, hoping in a short time to become wealthy and return to Norway and live in comfort ever after. The great majority of this last group stayed; they found that the riches of America were not so easy to get, and were sadly disappointed.</p>
   <p>Most of the newcomers thought that they knew a lot about American politics; they too were disappointed, for they soon found that they knew very little about our politics, and they also learned that American politics was a business, and a business for the most part unclean.</p>
   <p>The old Norwegian settlers knew more about our politics than did the visitors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0891.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But our Norwegian-Americans learned about a change in Norwegian politics that was news to them. In Norway the left-wing and the right-wing parties were deadly enemies. Here in America they apparently were quite good friends, even during a "mudslinging campaign". The old colonists thought that this was also the case in Norway, but things had changed.</p>
   <p>Many of the newcomers were short of funds, and their friends here in Chicago tried to get work for them, but usually without success. What a disappointment! America, where gold is found in the gutters, where every one is rich, America the land of golden opportunity! One cannot believe anything nowadays.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
