<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-01-27">Jan. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Young People's Lutheran Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Convention at St. Paul's Norwegian Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0570</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0570.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-27">Jan. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO YOUNG PEOPLE'S LUTHERAN ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Convention at St. Paul's Norwegian Church</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Young People's Lutheran Association held its first convention last Wednesday evening at St. Paul's Norwegian Church, corner of North venue and Leavitt Street, and a great meeting it was. The church was crowded with young people, and the program was excellent. Most of the young people's societies represented had banners to mark their location. The banners were placed in front of the members of the individual societies.</p>
   <p>The program started with an organ prelude, "Hosannah", by Dubois, played by Miss Ora A. Johnson. After this the audience sang "Ye Lands, to the Lord Make Jubilant Noise", whereupon Reverend Alfred O. Johnson gave a brief speech on the topic, "Temptation of Jesus in the Wilderness".</p>
   <p>The president of the Young People's Association, Mr. G. A. Andresen, made a speech on the history, the purpose, and the future of the purpose, and the future of the Association.</p>
   <p>"Fear Not Ye, O Israel" by Dudley Buck was then sung by Miss Gertrude Olsen.</p>
   <!-- 5423969_5_0571 omitted, duplicate of 5423969_5_0572 -->
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0572.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Olsen possesses a fine, rich voice, well trained...It is to be hoped that she will remain in Chicago so that the people may have the opportunity of hearing her often.</p>
   <p>The principal speaker was Reverend G. Schuessler, minister of the English Lutheran Church of Our Redeemer. He spoke of the work of the young people in the churches, what they can accomplish, how they ought to approach their tasks, and what ought to be the motive and spirit of their work...The speech was enthusiastic and valuable in its suggestions and instructions, and it should not easily be forgotten by the many hundreds of listeners.</p>
   <p>The choir of Our Savior's Church then sang Handel's "And the Glory of the Lord Shall Be Revealed". While Miss Ora Johnson played Dudley Buck's "At Evening", a collection was taken for the benefit of the Home Finding Society after Reverend P. A. Kittilsby had called attention to the importance of that Society. [Editor's note: The purpose of the Home Finding Society is to find suitable private homes for orphans entrusted to its care.]</p>
   <p>Next came a solo by Miss Anna Christensen, of Boston, Massachusetts. Touchingly
<pb facs="5423969_5_0573.jpg" n="3"/>she sang Gounod's "Forever with the Lord". One gets the impression while listening that Miss Christensen's voice is increasing in volume and beauty each time she sings, and now as always the audience listened with rapt attention.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Young People's Lutheran Association consists of the young peoples societies of the various congregations belonging to the Norwegian Lutheran Synod. The Association was organized last spring, and its first task was to arrange for the great convention of the young people's societies in June. In this connection the Association arranged for a boat trip on Lake Michigan and a festival at Wicker Park Hall. The aim of the Association is to bring together the members of the various young people's societies in co-operative work, and to encourage the members to greater interest and activity for the advancement of the work of the churches involved. This is a beautiful task, and it is to be hoped that the interest may increase both in regard to the Association itself and the local societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
