<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-12-31">Dec. 31, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Otto C. Ericson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-12-31">Dec. 31, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">OTTO C. ERICSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Otto C. Ericson was born in Faoberg, Norway in 1852 and came to America at the age of sixteen. In spite of the many years he has been a good citizen of his adopted country he still loves and respects the land of his birth and cherishes her traditions. He is one of the many, whom Norway produced but found it impossible to return. He was forced by circumstances to leave his native country to help build and become an important part of a new Commonwealth.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ericson began his career as a carpenter apprentice. He soon demonstrated that a hammer and saw was not on his coat of arms and when he came in contact with Christian Jevne, this was turned out to be his personal "door of opportunity." Since 1870 Mr. Ericson has been an important factor in the Jevne concern. What the name Marshall-Field stood for in wholesale dry-goods, Tiffany in jewelery, Armour in meats, etc, corresponds with Ericson (and Jevne) in foods.</p>
   <p>One item that has helped build the really big concerns has been the "House Publications,' <pb facs="5423969_5_1336.jpg" n="2"/>published by the various firms. Mr. Ericson was the pioneer of this idea among wholesale grocers. This publication was entitled Bon Vivant and is today one of America's outstanding house publications. H. H. Kohlsaat, owner of an extensive chain of restaurants and bakeries became aware of Mr. Ericson's ability and offered him a partnership wherein he was to manage a considerable group of restaurants in St. Paul and Minneapolis.</p>
   <p>Ericson, however, was too valuable a man to lose so he was given a quarter interest in C. Jevne &amp; Co., whose affairs he new had managed for several years, though as a salaried employer. This event marked the beginning of a new era where the new conditions left him more free to branch out . The result was that Jevne &amp; Co. became a really large institution serving not only Chicago but the entire Midwest.</p>
   <p>An idea of the extent of this business may be reached by noting the following: The main warehouse employees no less than 125 (not including clerical help) who are busy as bees in the handling of groceries, butter, baked goods and even wines, bottled, kegged and barreled. To move all this requires forty-two horses and two gasoline trucks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1337.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In addition to the main warehouse on Kinzie Street, there are warehouses and stores on both North and South sides of Chicago serving wholesale and retail trades. With the exception of two boats the entire New York - Sumatra fleet transporting Jevne's supplies of coffee, tea, and spices are Norwegian boats. Likewise the entire office force of Jevne &amp; Co. are Norsemen, not, says Mr. Ericson, because they are Norwegian but because Norwegians have been found to be the most efficient and trustworthy employees obtainable.</p>
   <p>The country is full of men who have been successful financially though few of them have made noticeable contributions to obtain lines. Mr. Ericson is one of the few who found time for activity outside of gathering world's treasures, materially speaking. Although he was wrapped up in his business he still took a great interest in the welfare of his fellow men. He was cosmopolitan in the fullest sense of the word. His interest in humanity knew no geographical limits. His knowledge of the rest of the world was such that he would speak fluently on subjects as widely different as British politics and the natural beauty and wonders of the Rocky <pb facs="5423969_5_1338.jpg" n="4"/>Mountains. He was a man who had the courage of his convictions and was a "yes man" to no human being. His eloquence and aptitude in painting word pictures of nature in many forms and many moods was such as to hold his listeners spellbound, making them see what he saw in the most realistic beauty. A master mind in business, a child of nature. This is Otto Christian Ericson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
