<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1920-04-25">Apr. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization Fallacy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-04-25">Apr. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION FALLACY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States is suffering from one of its periodic attacks of know-nothingism. It is seriously maintained in the public prints that our recent Eastern European and particularly our Russian immigration contains enormous numbers of murderers, thieves, counterfeiters, dynamiters, arsonists, and other criminals of the most atrocious character. It is alleged that the lives and property of all of us are in imminent danger from these incredibly numerous blackguards, and that the only salvation lies in what is called the Americanization of the foreigners.</p>
   <p>Now, it is known to every respectable sociologist in America that our recent Eastern European immigrants, including the Russians, are just as peaceable and law-abiding as native Americans of native American ancestry. This is a <pb facs="5423969_5_0895.jpg" n="2"/>fact about which there is not the slightest doubt in the mind of any competently informed person. It has been repeatedly established by careful studies made by the United States Bureau of the Census, by various state boards, and by highly qualified private foundations. Furthermore, the most honest, thrifty, industrious, upright, God-fearing, and conservative portion of our foreign population is precisely that portion which has clung most stubbornly to its native ways of life and has been least influenced by American customs. Our immigrants upon changing their foreign languages, customs, beliefs, and ideals, upon becoming Americanized, deteriorate profoundly in moral character to a degree that shows itself in the criminal statistics.</p>
   <p>It is very fortunate for the moral welfare of millions of our foreign population that the present furore for Americanization is destined to fail in its object. Its failure is in its own nature. The fundamental social virtues --honesty, industry, thrift, truthfulness, and the rest--are the same for all societies on the same general level of development. They are not promoted by the custom of saluting any particular flag; neither are they advanced by the ability to read any particular constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0896.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The very complete and profound change of character implied by the phrase, "The Americanization of the Foreigner," can be wisely and safely accomplished only if spread out over at least three generations, while four or five would be better. Every year less than three generations that the progress is hastened means moral and spiritual breakdown for thousands--it means domestic tragedy and congested criminal calendars. There is only one foreigner who is really a menace to American society. He is the foreigner who is in rapid process of Americanization. The danger point is the foreign-born child, the American-born child, and the American-born child of foreign parents.</p>
   <p>The danger from these classes is real and serious, perhaps the most serious presented in the whole range of immigration questions. Here again we have very reliable statistics which leave no room for reasonable doubt. America needs protection, needs it urgently, against the foreigner of the second generation, particularly against the youthful foreigner who goes through our public school system. The father, who stubbornly refuses to learn English or <pb facs="5423969_5_0897.jpg" n="4"/>to adopt American ways, is commonly the man of admirable moral character. The son, often quite as American as young men of our old stock, is equally commonly a youth of vicious and unprincipled character.</p>
   <p>Public opinion in this matter is grieviously at fault, there is danger to American institutions, and that danger is real; but it is just the opposite of what is popularly feared. The danger lies precisely in the process of Americanization itself, particularly in the endeavor to hasten that process. If, as is commonly maintained, the present need in America is peace and safety, security and conservatism, then the Americanization of the foreigner should be slowed down in every way possible. No encouragement should at this time be offered to the foreigner to abandon his native language or religion or to change his ethical or cultural standards.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, every possible assistance should be given to leaders in maintaining and strengthening the traditional loyalties of their various groups. Our public libraries should provide themselves more liberally with books in foreign languages. Foreign-language lectures and speakers of all sorts should <pb facs="5423969_5_0898.jpg" n="5"/>be encouraged. By such means and only by such means can the spirit of unrest and disquiet be stilled, and the spirit of conservatism and contentment with the status quo be developed among our foreign population.</p>
   <p>It is a most curious popular misconception that peace and quietness and respect for law and order can be developed in the foreigner by suddenly and violently disturbing his mental life. Changing a man's language, upsetting his moral and social conventions, altering his inherited traditions of conduct, unsettling his ancestral faith--these are the very best means possible for making him a disbeliever in all established institutions, including those of the United States. Yet this is precisely what Americanization aims to do with the best intentions.</p>
   <p>Respect for government and law is not a natural instinct. It is an artificial attitude slowly built up in the individual by all sorts of direct and indirect social pressure. The breakdown of old habits of thought in any one of the <pb facs="5423969_5_0899.jpg" n="6"/>great departments of social activity very rapidly affects the other phases of conduct. The whole moral life of the individual tends to become unsettled. Nothing is held firmly except the selfish determination to obtain material wealth. Ideas and ideals which stand in the way of this are cast aside. The Americanized foreigner possesses all the native American's ruthless greed without possessing his social, ethical, religious, or political idealism. No man can learn a language perfectly who learns it deliberately, and social ideals are harder to learn than language. They can never be learned naturally and completely except when they are learned so gradually and imperceptibly that the process is unrecognized and largely unconscious. This can never be possible in the case of the foreign-born, and is only very partially attainable in the case of the children of foreign-born. Its complete realization is possible only in the case of children born and reared in an entirely American environment. That is to say it cannot be accomplished before the third generation at the earliest, and often not then.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
