<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Norwegian American Technical Journal</title>,
<date when="1928-09">Sept. 1928</date>.pp, 5-6
<title level="a">[Biography of J. H. Faleide]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Norwegian American Technical Journal</title>,
<date when="1928-09">Sept. 1928</date>.pp, 5-6
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF J. H. FALEIDE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>J. H. Faleide, vice president and chief engineer of Falwell Engineering Co., Chicago, was born in Faleide, Norway in 1881, and graduated from Bergen Technical College in 1902. He arrived in the United States in the fall of the same year. From 1902 to 1903 he worked as millwright and machinist for the American Steel and Wire Company at Waukegan, Ill. From 1903 to 1905 he worked as draftsman for the Western Electric Co., in the Tool Department. From 1905 to 1911 he was employed as a designer in the Chicago office of James Stewart and Co. This firm specializes in designing and construction of grain elevators and floar mills.</p>
   <p>In 1911 he accepted the position of chief engineer for the Buwell Engineering and Construction Company, acting in that capacity until 1916. This company also specializes in the designing and construction of grain elevators, mills, and various other kinds of industrial plants. In 1916 he became a member of the Falwell-Ahlskog Company, acting as treasurer and chief engineer. This <pb facs="5423969_5_1217.jpg" n="2"/>concern was reorganized in 1926 under the name of the Falwell Engineering Company of which Mr. Faleide is now vice-president and chief engineer. Besides the designing and construction of grain elevators, flour mills, power plants and industrial plants, this concern does general contracting for large sewers, concrete bridges, viaducts, and heavy excavation and foundation work. Mr. Faleide is a member of the Western Society of Engineers, the Illinois Structural Steel Association, and was President of the Chicago - Norwegian Technical Society in 1926 and 1927.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
