<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-09-07">Sept. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Rev. Meyer Joins Chorus]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-09-07">Sept. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[REV. MEYER JOINS CHORUS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once in a great while a representative individual turns out to be an exception.. This was demonstrated on Tuesday evening when, in spite of the attitude taken by leaders of our Norwegian Lutheran Churches in the United States towards lodges and other outside organizations, Rev. Johann Meyer, pastor of the Christ Church in Logan Square, became a member of Nordmendenes Sangforening (Norwegian Male Chorus).</p>
   <p>It will be recalled that in the Lutheran Almanac of 1912 a picture was printed which shows two trees with their respective fruits. On the "Devil's tree" (the tree of evil) the fruits bore such names as "Sons of Norway," Masons," and all other lodges; male choruses, Boy Scouts, High schools, universities, and even the time-honored G.A.R.</p>
   <p>Reverend Meyer later defended the Boy Scouts in his church paper, and now <pb facs="5423969_5_0421.jpg" n="2"/>he goes a step further and has joined one of the evil fruits, the Norwegian Male Chorus.</p>
   <p>Church conditions in Norwegian Chicago are disgusting. Our Lutheran pastors would find a good field for their labors among our Chicago lodges and societies if they would unbend just a trifle instead of isolating themselves and their congregations, while they and the members of their flocks strut around as though they, each and every one, carried in his pocket an exclusive deed to the mansions of heaven, on which to pass in preference of others.</p>
   <p>The highly honored Dr. Qualis once said in a public address: "It hurts me to note that our pastors are never to be seen at one of our gatherings, whether it be political, social, or semi-private. I deplore their superior attitude as, I know, do all my countrymen. These pastors would do well to follow the suggestion made by one of Norway's grandest old men, the late Bishop Bugge of Christiania. Bishop Bugge said: 'If our people will not <pb facs="5423969_5_0422.jpg" n="3"/>come to church, it is our duty as servants of Almighty God to bring the church to the people.'" The good Bishop it was who instituted the short divine services for those who sought recreation on skii and sleds on Sunday mornings, both at Uranienborg and Holmenkollen, Norway.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the initiative of Pastor Meyer will bear fruit and bring other pastors into our organizations; it will clear misunderstandings and be of great mutual benefit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
