<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-12-14">Dec. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Wedding</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-12-14">Dec. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER WEDDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday Canute R. Matson, superintendent of Post Office Station A, and his wife celebrated their twenty-fifty wedding anniversary at their residence, 609 Cleveland Avenue. Early in the day people began ringing the door-bell, bringing a mass of presents to the "silver-bridal" couple. The presents included articles of silver of every description, flowers, and palms. In addition, a large number of telegrams and greetings were received by the couple. Among these was one from the president of the Norwegian Old Settlers' Society, Mr. Peter M. Balken. He sent the invitation card to their wedding which he received twenty-five years ago. Mr. Balken's message and card came as a pleasant surprise and was admired both by Mr. and Mrs. Matson and the fifty guests who came in the evening to extend congratulations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Canute R. Matson was born at Voss, Norway, in 1843 and came to America with his parents in 1849....He studied at Albion Academy and later at <pb facs="5423969_5_1462.jpg" n="2"/>Milton College in Wisconsin. In 1861 he joined the army in the civil war. During the four years and four months that he followed the colors, he was promoted, step by step, so that at the time of his discharge from the army in 1865 he was a premier-lieutenant. Later on, as a member of the governor's staff and of the Grand Army of the Republic, he became a major and finally a colonel.</p>
   <p>In the fall of 1865 Mr. C. R. Matson came to Chicago. [Translator's note: Here he has been clerk in the police court; justice of the peace; coroner of Cook County; deputy sheriff; sheriff.... He is now superintendent of Post Office Station A, corner of Clark Street and North Avenue.]</p>
   <p>On December 13, 1876, he married Mrs. Isabell Richolson.... The couple have four children....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
