<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">John Wilhelm Colberg 70 Years</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1356</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1356.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN WILHELM COLBERG 70 YEARS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John W. Colberg is seventy years old today. No man has made a deeper impression on the Norwegian world of music and long in Chicago, and it is therefore, only natural that the Norwegian Singing Association is to honor him with a concert on this coming Sunday. Some of the ablest leaders in music in Chicago will be present to pay their respect to the old master. And undoubtedly, the Norwegians will show their love and regard for the old leader in music by crowding Bjorgvin Hall. The concert starts at 8 o'clock.</p>
   <p>Old Colberg, in spite of his seventy years, is a young man. He enjoys good health, and he possesses the bright, optimistic vision of youth as he ponders upon life. Even today he will, on occasion, direct the orchestra with a vigor and fire as of fifty years ago.</p>
   <p>In 1870, Mr. Colberg said farewell to Norway, and came to Chicago. Almost at once, he was appointed instructor in music at Illinois State University, and he remained there two years. In 1872, he returned to Chicago, and at <pb facs="5423969_5_1357.jpg" n="2"/>once became the leader of the Norwegian Music Society, which had been organized shortly before. Under his leadership, it developed quickly and well.</p>
   <p>Two years later, in 1874, he assumed of the Norwegians' Singing Society. This society is now probably the largest of all the Norwegian singing Societies in the U. S. A. It was organized by a for singers, who with their instructor, had left the Norwegian Turnforening and started independently.</p>
   <p>Mr. Colberg at once began the work of making the Society one of the best in the world of music in Chicago, and he has succeeded. His excellent qualities as instructor enabled him to produce something from nothing, as it were - and with astonishing speed. Howe great the progress had been during a few months was clearly manifest at the memorable concert given by male and mixed choruses. It was the first concert on a large scale among the Norwegians in Chicago, and it was held in Aurora Turner Hall. This concert, successful from every point of view, made people outside the Norwegian group take notice also, and it constituted professor Colberg's first outstanding triumph in Chicago. Put not the last by <pb facs="5423969_5_1358.jpg" n="3"/>any means. All in all, Mr. Colberg pointed the direction, and paved the way for the development in music and singing which later took place in the Norwegian group of Chicago and across the plains of the West. Altogether, he has introduced about <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Norwegian, Swedish, Danish, and German songs to the city. The intensity of this work may be understood to some degree by any singer. Mr. Colberg was also the chief director at the concert in memory of Ole Bull, on May 17, 1875.</p>
   <p>Gave Impulse to the Singing Meets.</p>
   <p>Socially also Mr. Colberg did much for the singers, for he gave the impulse to the meets, such as the first great singing meet of Scandinavian singers in Madison, Wis., and those that took place later in Minneapolis and St. Paul.</p>
   <p>In 1886 Mr. Colberg was chosen president and chief director of the Scandinavian Song Festival which was held in Chicago in under the auspices of the Norwegians' Singing Society.</p>
   <p>Then came the famous Chicago Exposition of 1895. At the Scandinavian</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1359.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Song Festival during the <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
