<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-26">Feb. 26, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Revival Meetings at Bethlehem Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-26">Feb. 26, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">REVIVAL MEETINGS AT BETHLEHEM CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Revival meetings have been conducted for sometime at Bethlehem Lutheran Church. So far the meetings have been very good, and the attendance has been fairly large. It is true, of course, that there is room for many, many more. The attendance will increase if those who are interested in the meetings will exert themselves by going about in their neighborhoods and invite people to the meetings.</p>
   <p>Last night there was a large audience of interested people. After much singing by the congregation, Reverend C. K. Solberg read Luke 16: 19-31, calling upon the Lord to bless this word, the meeting, the speakers, and the listeners. Reverend O. Shefveland then delivered a powerful, earnest, and searching sermon on the latter part of the letter to the Sardes congregation (Revelation 3: 3-5), specially emphasizing the words, "Therefore, remember what you have heard and take care to get converted!" Strongly and searchingly was this admonition from the Lord urged upon the listeners. Many were deeply touched by this serious <pb facs="5423969_5_0561.jpg" n="2"/>call from God's word.</p>
   <p>After Mr. John Rasmussen had sung "Jeg ved en vraa (I Know a Hiding Place), Reverend Ellestad spoke briefly. The congregation rose, and a few minutes were passed in prayer and testimony. Several members of the congregation participated.</p>
   <p>Reverend C. K. Solberg, who was conducting the meeting, exhorted the believers to remember also to invite neighbors and friends to the meetings and to continue to pray insistently for the presence of God's spirit at the meetings and in the congregation. Reverend Tiller led in prayer and blessed the people present in the name of the Lord.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
