<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-02-03">Feb. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Religious Honesty</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Reverend C. T. Dyrness</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-03">Feb. 3, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">RELIGIOUS HONESTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Reverend C. T. Dyrness</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the caption "Religious Honesty", Reverend Bergesen, in an article in the Skandinaven last week, had much to say against the Evangelical Free churches in general, and against myself and the Salen Evangelical Free Church in particular. At first, on reading the article, I did not feel inclined to answer at all; articles of the type mentioned do not ordinarily warrant an answer since people who are not prejudiced would be able to judge the article without comment from anybody. In the present case there might be a possibility, however, that silence on my part might be interpreted by some as an admission of the correctness of the assertions made by Reverend Bergesen. For this reason I shall make a few remarks in refutation, but only in so far as the article is aimed at me and the congregation I am serving. The rest of the article I shall not discuss.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0563.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First of all let me state that in regard to the questions Reverend Bergesen so tauntingly has been directing at me, I have asked him for the names of the persons to whom he refers in connection with his questions. Reverend Bergesen refused, however, saying: "There is no point in trying to get at these people." Quite true. But it evidently seems important to the Reverend to get at me and Salem Free Church.</p>
   <p>When you, Reverend Bergesen, publicly attack by name a person who has never had anything to do with you, then you should give the names of the witnesses you claim to have for the correctness of your assertions. When you refuse to do so, then I think it quite in order for me to refuse to answer your questions. To be frank, if your purpose had been to gain information on points of doubt, you would have found ready answers and information if you had spoken to me privately. There really was no need of dealing with these matters publicly in Skandinaven.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In regard to the congregation which I am serving, let me inform you that the name which it has chosen and borne for nearly half a generation is "Salem Evangelical Free Church". This is the name in full; under this name the Church has been incorportated under the laws of the state of Illinois. We do not call ourselves Lutheran, Reverend Bergesen. Any truthful person who knows the Salem congregation will admit that we never called ourselves Lutheran. Never did I give a member, received into the Salem congregation the understanding that the Church is a Lutheran church. Never! And this is not to be taken to mean that we have any objection to name "Luther" or "Lutheran". Many of us in Salem are, in the main, in agreement with the Lutheran doctrines, and we have never been afraid of admitting this when inquiries have been made. We hold that our right to make such an admission is as great as that of anybody else. If anybody will call this "cheating" then our answer is that as far as we know nobody ever received patent on the Lutheran faith. If we are wrong in this, perhaps someone would be so good as to correct our mistake, and we shall comply with the laws.</p>
   <p>In this connection I need to state that we of the Salem Church do not at all <pb facs="5423969_5_0565.jpg" n="4"/>approve of the manner in which Lutheranism is being practiced in most places at present. It is for this reason that we have adopted the standpoint which is ours. But, as I have said, we do not call ourselves Lutheran; this is so evident that no one can pass through the door of our Church with his eyes open without noticing the fact as stated. We are not responsible if others, intentionally or by mistake, apply to us any name or names which we, ourselves, have not adopted. Some people insist that we are Methodists. Some time ago an article was run in all the Norwegian Lutheran church papers in which we and some others were called Baptists. It is actually true that a number of the friends who have come to us from the Lutheran Free Church in Norway have told us that they are unable to see much difference between our congregation and those they came from.</p>
   <p>All right, then. We love the Lutherans, Congregationalists, Baptists, Methodists, and all the rest of God's people, and we have not found it necessary to protest when people have applied to us these various names mentioned; rather, <pb facs="5423969_5_0566.jpg" n="5"/>we have taken comfort from the old saying that "a beloved child has many names". Even when called a "sect" we consider that we belong in the successions of the apostolic congregations, for the enemies of christianity called the early Christians a "sect".</p>
   <p>We do, however, protest against the unfriendly accusation that we have been employing the Lutheran name, or any other name, with the intention to deceive.</p>
   <p>But why this lack of explicitness? Why indeed! It may be difficult to find a satisfactory answer. But, after all, it is not merely Salem and "these Free churches" who have to contend with such difficulty.</p>
   <p>In my home district in Norway, a number of years ago, there was even a Lutheran congregation of the state church which met with related circumstances. In this congregation a great revival was begun. The instrument used by God in this <pb facs="5423969_5_0567.jpg" n="6"/>movement was one of the "semi-educated laymen" who to this very day are working in the Evangelical Free Churches in America. The parish priest and his wife were God-fearing people, however, who threw themselves into the revival, heart and soul. They knelt down in prayer with those who were seeking salvation, exactly as the Free Church preacher (or sect preacher, if you prefer). They opened their homes for prayer meetings with the newly converted every Saturday evening. And, of all things, they took the "sect preacher" in,giving him the privileges of their homes.</p>
   <p>These matters were reported to the district superintendent, and he thought the matter quite out of place. "Those people are Methodists," it was said...Complaints were sent to the bishop, who in his place called the priest and his assistants to account for their behavior. It was in the balance whether the congregation was to remain under the state or become a free church. I remember the priest saying, "Rather than turn my back on the revival I shall withdraw from, the state church and organize a free church." The bishop saved <pb facs="5423969_5_0568.jpg" n="7"/>the situation, however; he decided that the congregation was Lutheran, not Methodist. But why this lack of clearness? Yes why? I, too, join in this question.</p>
   <p>Let me assure Reverend Bergesen and Reverend Solberg, however, that those who are members of the Salem Evangelical Free Church, and for that matter those who are not members but yet visit our meetings, are human beings with a general education and intelligence--men and women with common sense who know both what they want and what they are doing. In addition, they are of age so that they do not need to be told where they may go to find food for their souls and become strengthened in their faith.</p>
   <p>But now it seems in place to say that it was quite refreshing to me to notice a minister in the Norwegian Lutheran Synod suddenly develop such solicitude for a "brother minister" of the Norwegian Lutheran United Church, that he thus <pb facs="5423969_5_0569.jpg" n="8"/>steps forward in his defense. Not always was the relationship between the ministers of the Synod and the United Church thus cordial; that, to be truthful, we must admit. We are happy, however, to notice that their relationship is improving.</p>
   <p>If, now, these honored ministers would leave peaceful people in peace in the future, then their attitude of peacefulness would undoubtedly bring profit to themselves and other people, and the cause of God would profit too. If, on the other hand, they desire to go on writing the same type of articles, as far as I am concerned they will be undisturbed in their writings. I am busy with things of greater importance.</p>
   <p>The fields are golden toward harvest. Thousands of our countrymen in this city are approaching eternity without God and without hope. Is it not time, brethren, to leave the insignificant and mean behind us and strive as well as we are able to win as many as possible for Christ and Heaven, before it becomes eternally too late?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
