<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-07">Sept. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[Pastor Returns from Norway]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian Lutheran Christ Church Welcomes Reverend and Mrs. Meyer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-07">Sept. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[PASTOR RETURNS FROM NORWAY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian Lutheran Christ Church Welcomes Reverend and Mrs. Meyer</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Christ Norwegian Lutheran Church, in Logan Square, held a "welcome" social Saturday evening for the pastor of the Church, Reverend J. H. Meyer, and his wife, on the occasion of their return from a tour that carried them through Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Germany, France, and England.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar Norby welcomed the audience and introduced Mr. Louis Lawson as toastmaster. The real festivities began with the singing of a song written for the occasion by Miss Rachel Gabrielsen. The church choir sang the song of welcome with customary vigor and precision.</p>
   <p>The speech in honor of Reverend Meyer was delivered by Reverend N. J. Ellestad, who expressed his joy at seeing Reverend and Mrs. Meyer back from their tour, <pb facs="5423969_5_0533.jpg" n="2"/>and in good health.</p>
   <p>Mr. Martim Thon spoke about the work which had been accomplished within the congregation during the absence of the pastor. Mrs. Ellen Andersen sang a beautiful solo; she was accompanied at the piano by Mr. R. Gulbrandsen.</p>
   <p>Dr. Christopher expressed the thanks of the congregation to Reverend N. J. Ellestad, who had substituted during the absence of Reverend Meyer; he also presented Reverend Ellestad with a gift to show that the recognition of the minister's good work was not "confined to mere words".</p>
   <p>Mr. Oscar Norby spoke in honor of Dr. Christopher, who is one of the strongest supporters of the Church. A quartet consisting of Mrs. Ellen Andersen, Miss Rachel Gabrielsen, Messrs. Gulbrandsen and Reinertsen presented one of their numbers, after which speeches were made by Reverend F. Ring and Mr. Louis Andersen. The choir offered various numbers between the speeches.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, Reverend J. H. Meyer, thanked the congregation on behalf of <pb facs="5423969_5_0534.jpg" n="3"/>Mrs. Meyer and himself. He mentioned that he and his wife had traveled about fourteen thousand miles, and had visited Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Germany Belgium, France, and England. Although he had visited some of the most famous and greatest cathedrals in Europe, Reverend Meyer said that the Christ Church in Logan Square was still the dearest of them all to him, even though its congregation was not of the largest.</p>
   <p>The social was most successful. The decorations were executed by Mr. Oscar Norby, and Mr. W. Gulbrandsen arranged the excellent program. Mrs. Halvorsen supervised the serving of refreshments, which were greatly enjoyed by the guests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
