<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-11-26">Nov. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[An Outstanding Journalist]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-11-26">Nov. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[AN OUTSTANDING JOURNALIST]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1.col.3-4.......Anton B. Lange, editor of Scandia (Norwegian Newspaper of Chicago) passed away on Tuesday, Oct. 18th, after an illness of two months. With his passing Norwegians throughout the country lose a leading spirit, one of its most talented and least "diplomatic" journalists.</p>
   <p>Anton Lange was born in Bergen, Norway in 1857, of German parents. His father was a merchant on what is known as TYSKEBRYGGEN (German Dock).Lange Jr's training was directed toward fitting him to succeed his father in business. He was educated in the best schools in Bergen.</p>
   <p>He arrived in the U.S.A. in 1880 where for a short while he followed commercial lines, but in this there was no appeal to one of his independent, visionary nature. Merchandising was not one of the ingredients in the make up of Anton Lange. Even in his earlier school days he showed a marked tendency to ferret out and combat anything false or smacking of humbug and throughout life he was possessed with an uncontrollable desire to write and speak openly and frankly on any subject he <pb facs="5423969_5_1344.jpg" n="2"/>had in mind (hence our characterization of him as least diplomatic).</p>
   <p>He soon found an outlet for his desire for open frankness in journalism and with his entry into the realm of the Norwegian-American Press there entered into it a new spirit. The N.-A.Press which hitherto had been a more or less churchy affair, uninterestingly dry and tiresome, was awakened to the fact that the press was a power and as such should show interest in and report everything of vital importance to the community at large and to the individual.</p>
   <p>He was connected with several papers in Minnesota, among others with Nordoesten published for a short time at St.Paul, though his stay with each was short, owing to his propensity for writing the unvarnished truth. Such frank honesty did not agree with those whose publications catered to human vanities and Mr. Lange was not one to be intimidated or dictated to.</p>
   <p>In 1887 he established his own paper Scandia at Duluth, Minn. wherein he unmercifully attacked the hypocrisy and woodenness of the Norwegians in the northwest and so openly and thoroughly exposed these traits in several of Duluth's "Prominentia" that he soon was at odds with many of the pillars(?) of the community. After a few years <pb facs="5423969_5_1345.jpg" n="3"/>in Duluth he moved the paper to Chicago where his spirit of frankness and fair play won him friends from the very start.</p>
   <p>His mentality, unsurpassed and hardly equalled by that of any other Norwegian-American editor, together with his unlimited energy and industry and his willingness to fight for what he thought was right won the respect,if not the love,of the opposing press.</p>
   <p>While Anton Lange's ideals leaned slightly toward socialism he never proclaimed himself to be a "Socialist," but whimsically referred to himself as an "idealistic anarchist." His strong sense of righteousness kept him constantly alert and ready to attack anything questionable or false and his broad-minded stand against such things coming under pseudonym "Daniel Heine" were both sharp and accurate. At times he was severely criticised for the energy he put into expose's of people whom they considered unworthy of his notice.</p>
   <p>In addition to his journalistic ability he was well-known in literary and musical circles. He composed a number of beautiful poems and translated several <pb facs="5423969_5_1346.jpg" n="4"/>works of Bjornson and Ibsen. Among his literary works, widely read, are "Norge as a Republik" (Norway as a Republic) and "America and "Americans" the latter having undeniably been an inspiration to Knut Hansun when he wrote of the social life of America.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Sophie Heiberg Lange survives him. They were married in 1908. Up to that time Anton Lange had been a bachelor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
