<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1911-09-06">Sept. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Church Register</title><title level="a" type="sub">The United Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III C (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-09-06">Sept. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CHURCH REGISTER</title><title level="a" type="sub">The United Church</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bethlehem Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Springfield Avenue and Iowa Street. Reverend H. Oftedal, pastor. The Luther League meets every Tuesday at 8 P. M.</p>
   <p>The St. Timothy Evangelical Lutheran Church, Humboldt Boulevard and Dickens Avenue. Reverend R. O. Sigmund, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Bethel Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Dickens and 42nd Avenues. Reverend E. E. Tiller, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Zion Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Artesian and Potomac Avenues. Reverend C. K. Solberg, pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0458.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Nazareth Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Yale Avenue, Pullman. Reverend K. M. J. Mjaanes, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Trinity Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Sherman Avenue and 80th Street. Reverend K. M. J. Mjaanes, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Christ Church, Kedzie Boulevard and Milwaukee Avenue. Reverend J. H. Meyer, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Evanston Norwegian-Danish Lutheran Church, Greenwood Boulevard and Sherman Avenue. Reverend J. H. Meyer, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Moreland Norwegian Lutheran Church, Indiana Street and 50th Court. Reverend T. C. Thompson, pastor.</p>
   <p>Our Saviour's English Lutheran Church [Danish], Hoyne Avenue and Le Moyne <pb facs="5423969_5_0459.jpg" n="3"/>Street. Reverend T. Sigmond, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Covenant English Lutheran Church [Danish], Fullerton Avenue and Ballou Street. Reverend Jens C. Roseland, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Synod</p>
   <p>Our Saviour's Church, May and Erie Streets. Reverend Hils M. Ylusaker, pastor.</p>
   <p>St. Paul's Church, North Avenue and Leavitt Street. Reverend G. A. Gullixon, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Johannes Norwegian Church, Humboldt Boulevard and Cortez Street. Reverend H. P. Ausan pastor.</p>
   <p>St. Matthew's Church, Dunning and Ballou Streets. Reverend Lewis Moe, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Roscoe and Osgood Streets. Reverend P. A. Kittilsby, pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0460.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>St. Mark's Church, Tripp and Wabansia Avenues. Reverend J. A. Molstad, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Irving Park Norwegian Lutheran Church, Monticello and Elston Avenues. Reverend M. G. Fretheim, pastor.</p>
   <p>Hauge's Synod</p>
   <p>The Emmanuel Church, Maplewood Avenue and Cherry Place. Reverend J. N. Walstead, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Elim Lutheran Church, Byron and Whipple Streets. Reverend L. Ellingsen, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Ebenezer Evangelical Lutheran Church, Wentworth Avenue and 52nd Street. Reverend K. M. Mjaanes, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Trinity Church, Wabansia Avenue and Humboldt Street. Reverend H. A. Hanson, pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0461.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Hauge's Church, Wabansia and Central Park Avenues. Reverend E. L. Jothen, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Free Church</p>
   <p>The Salem Evangelical Free Church, California and McLean Avenues. Reverend E. T. Dyrness, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Bethel Evangelical Free Church, Central Park and Diversey Avenues. Reverend S. M. Andreason, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Salem Free Church Mission, 4411 Armitage Avenue. The pastorate is vacant.</p>
   <p>The Moreland Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, Ontario Street and 50th Avenue. Reverend K. S. Wang, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Silo [probably Siloam] Evangelical Free Church, Armitage and 44th Avenues.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0462.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The pastorate is vacant. [Editor's note: A Skandinaven article of 1910 lists a "Silo Church" at 1728 Armitage Avenue.]</p>
   <p>The Betheseda Evangelical Free Church, Indiana Avenue and 113th Street. Reverend A. J. Andreason, pastor.</p>
   <p>Norwegian-Danish Methodist Church</p>
   <p>The Bethel Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, 72nd Street and Ingleside Avenue. Reverend O. Nielson, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Kedzie Avenue Norwegian-Danish Methodist Church, Kedzie Avenue and Cortland Street. Reverend T. M. Hauge, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Bethany Methodist Episcopal Church, Albany Avenue and Byron Street. The pastorate is vacant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0463.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Emmanus Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, 41st Court and Pierce Avenue. Reverend G. Mathieson, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Maplewood Avenue Methodist Church, LeMoyne and Maplewood Avenues. Reverend O. H. Wilson, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Bethania Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, Albany Avenue and Byron Street. Reverend A. Berggren, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Moreland Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, Fifth Avenue and Ontario Street. Reverend P. Haugan, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Immanuel Methodist Episcopal Church, Kimball and Wrightwood Avenues. Reverend F. L. Trellestad, pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0464.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Baptist Churches</p>
   <p>The Logan Square Norwegian Baptist Church, Humboldt Boulevard and Wright-wood Avenue. Reverend P. Stiansen, pastor.</p>
   <p>The First Danish Baptist Church, LeMoyne and Talman Avenues. Reverend A. B. Hanson, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Bethel Danish Baptist Church, Cortland Street and Nebraska Avenue. Reverend T. E. Tystrup, pastor.</p>
   <p>Danish Churches</p>
   <p>The Siloam Danish Evangelical Church, Lowell Avenue and Cortland Street. Reverend Axel Christiansen, pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0465.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The Gethsemane Danish Evangelical Church, Fairfield Avenue and Humboldt Boulevard. Reverend C. E. Mengers, pastor.</p>
   <p>St. Ansgar's Danish Evangelical Church, Washtenaw and Wabansia Avenues. Reverend P. Gothe, pastor.</p>
   <p>The Ebenezer Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church, Rockwell Street and Wabansia Avenue. Reverend L. Pedersen, pastor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
