<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-13">Sept. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Jubilee Gift to Norway</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Decisions of the Jubilee Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-09-13">Sept. 13, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE JUBILEE GIFT TO NORWAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Decisions of the Jubilee Committee</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee on a jubilee gift to Norway in 1914 convened in Minneapolis, Minnesota, on September 8, with L. O. Thorpe presiding. Attending the Meeting were Dr. H. G. Stub, Dr. T. Stabo, Messrs. L. O. Thorpe, M. F. Hegge, C. D. Morck, O. E. Ray, O. O. Sageng, and H. G. Solem. Letters were received from Dr. J. de Besche, Consul H. Bendeke, and Reverend N. J. Ellestad stating that they were unable to be present at the meeting, but that they could report having done preparatory work and having met with good will everywhere.</p>
   <p>The president appointed two committees, one to prepare a working plan, the other to prepare an appeal to the public. Letters from the committee members and vice-presidents for the various states, who had been selected at the previous meeting, were then read. From some states came the request that more officials be appointed. These requests were complied with, and additional members of the State committees were appointed for Iowa, Illinois, <pb facs="5423969_5_1064.jpg" n="2"/>Wisconsin, and Minnesota. The members in North and South Dakota expressed a wish that the new members for these states be selected by the local constituency; they authorized the president to appoint the men recommended by the state directors for the Dakotas.</p>
   <p>At the afternoon meeting, Mr. Solem proposed that the collection of funds for the jubilee gift be undertaken by the organizations which so far have done the great work among our people, that is, the churches. Others pointed out, however, that ministers and congregations could not very well undertake to collect money for funds other than those directly connected with their work. In addition, it was pointed out that the jubilee gift is a national undertaking, something concerning all the Norwegian people regardless of whether they belong to churches or to other organizations. It was also mentioned that the people outside the churches might be reached most easily through the newspapers. Mr. Amundsen, editor of the Decorah-Poster, who was present, informed the committee that except in cases involving some accident, or when some other factor directly appealing to people's sympathy was present, <pb facs="5423969_5_1065.jpg" n="3"/>newspaper appeals had invariably proven of but slight effect. In addition, the task of collecting the needed funds would entail more work than the newspapers could undertake.</p>
   <p>Dr. Stub read a proposal to an appeal, prepared by Nicolay Grevstad and himself; it was applauded by all the members of the committee.</p>
   <p>The committee on a working plan presented a proposal for rules and regulations for the collection of funds. The proposal was considered point by point; certain changes were made and paragraphs added, after which the amended proposal was adopted.</p>
   <p>The suggestions and sketches submitted by the secretary for books and other documents were adopted. An artistic receipt for funds contributed toward the jubilee gift, showing the picture of the Eidsvold convention of 1814, will be sent to all the contributors as soon as the contribution is paid in full. Every collection agent will receive written authorization from the vice-president or director of his state, together with a specially designed <pb facs="5423969_5_1066.jpg" n="4"/>receipt book. The contributions are to be sent either to the head treasurer, Mr. Hauman C. Haugan, State Bank of Chicago, or to the head scretary.</p>
   <p>The various states will now start the work of organizing, and as soon as a report on the appointed officials has been received, a complete list of all the officials of the jubilee gift movement will be published. The appeal to the public for contributions will be sent to all the Norwegian newspapers some day during the coming week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
