<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-10-06">Oct. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Welcome-Social for Rev. Fr. Ring</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-10-06">Oct. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WELCOME-SOCIAL FOR REV. FR. RING</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The social welcoming the Rev. Mr. Ring and Mrs. Ring, earlier mentioned in this paper, took place last Thursday at the Immanuel M. E. Church, and was one of the coziest and best attended socials of recent years. It was a social of welcome for the ministerial couple, but it was also a wedding party for them, because the date of the social also marked the 38th anniversary of their wedding. This added greatly to the interest of the occasion.</p>
   <p>The church was filled with people; among them were the newly appointed and highly esteemed district superintendent, J. O. Hall, and most of the Mr. Rev. Ring's associates of the ministry in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0605.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was a stirring moment when the Rev. Mr. Ring and his wife were escorted into the church by H. Torkildsen and E. Eliasen, accompanied by the tones of the organ.</p>
   <p>The social was opened with singing and devotion, and then the secretary of the congregation, O. B. Evans, welcomed the audience on behalf of the church.</p>
   <p>The Rev. A. Haagensen gave the oration for the guests of honor. It was touching to watch this old hero, a minister in the Methodist church for more than 50 years, who has known the Rev. Mr. Ring and Mrs. Ring for many years, as he tried to find the choicest words with which to express his joy and pay his homage to the couple. His speech was strongly appealing, and his enthusiasm increased as he progressed. Then, standing in the midst of the Norwegian M. E. ministers of Chicago, he ended by <pb facs="5423969_5_0606.jpg" n="3"/>stating that no minister was more popular in Chicago than the Rev. Mr. Ring, and that this popularity was a fruit not especially of his sermons, but rather of his pastoral work, his visits, his being ever ready to extend a helping hand to everyone in need. In conclusion, he made some felicitous remarks concerning Mrs. Ring, and as he ended his speech the audience applauded most heartily.</p>
   <p>The new district superintendent was then asked to speak, and in a brief but inspiring speech, he congratulated the ministerial family and the congregation upon their chance for co-operative work during the coming year. Mr. C. Tonnessen was the last of the speakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0607.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On behalf of the congregation, he presented the Rev. Mr. Ring with an envelope containing a gift to the ministerial couple, and Mrs. Tonnesen presented Mrs. Ring with a beautiful bouquet from the Ladies Aid Society.</p>
   <p>The occasion being the first affair at which the new district superintendent was present, a beautiful bouquet was given to him also, with appropriate best wishes for his work during the coming year.</p>
   <p>Between speeches the audiences listened to beautiful singing by Miss Constance Andersen, Dr. Lawson's Ladies Octette, sister's Nelson Sextette, and by the choir of the church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
