<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-16">Mar. 16, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Mournful Memoirs]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-16">Mar. 16, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[MOURNFUL MEMOIRS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mournful members of the travels of Thoralf Klaveness through the states, and the sorry pictures he drew of Norwegian-Americans in general, have culminated in a sour-smelling spasm of pen-work work appearing in Normands Forbundet's (The Norsemen's League's) publication of recent date, and what a belittling attack it was!</p>
   <p>Scandia does not feel any necessity for defending our people against the mouthings of a man like Klaveness, as Klaveness and his idiotic ideas are known on both sides of the Atlantic to be absolutely insignificant. We Norwegian-Americans, like sensible humans, admit we are open to criticism, but we have an unholy desire to discover the source of such criticism. We must say it strikes us as queer that this publication, being the organ published for the purpose of drawing the Norsemen of the world closer together, should accept and print the lies of a "sour grapes" fanatic like Klaveness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1014.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>His article is in direct opposition to the aims of the League, and far from being an attempt to increase the good feeling between Norway and her decendents in America, it would tend to isolate the Norwegian-American, and even create a hatred between us and those in the land of our forbears.</p>
   <p>We in turn, and rightfully, criticize the editor of the League's publication for printing such a dirty article by such a man(?) at this time, i.e., so near "1914" and that anniversary's appeal to the world's Norsemen. We would also caution against the acceptance of further articles of such caliber on the basis of their effect on the gathering of funds for our memorial gift to be presented to Norway on the 100th anniversary of her constitution day.</p>
   <p>Assuredly the magazine whose slogan is "unity among Norsemen" should close its columns to sore-heads and cranks who desire an outlet for their personal spleen and jealousy toward a few individuals (their betters, by far, at that).</p>
   <p>As for writings by Klaveness, nothing good ever did or will come from them, and no paper of the Norwegian-American press will print one; we know Klaveness far too well.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
