<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-25">May 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Chicagoans Take Part in Milwaukee Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-25">May 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGOANS TAKE PART IN MILWAUKEE CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to the fact that one of our prominent Chicago Norwegians was the speaker of the day on May 17th, the celebration of that day in Milwaukee is of interest to our Norwegian Colony. For the first time in Milwaukee's history, all Norwegian organizations really got together, worked together, and triumphed together on this day of days. One of the most pleasing aspects of the day was the number of Swedes and Danes that turned out for Norway's festival. To the best of our knowledge, this is an unknown thing in our own Chicago and is an example of good fellowship that could be profitably emulated wherever a holiday of either Scandinavian country is celebrated.</p>
   <p>The speaker of the day was Benj. Blessum, a Chicago artist and author, who was introduced as a direct descendant of John Blessum, of "fairy tale" fame. Mr. Blessum was so different from the usual May 17th speakers that he was likened to a fresh spring breeze. He put his listeners in the best of humor and held their interest throughout his lecture. One of the reasons Milwaukee liked <pb facs="5423969_5_0075.jpg" n="2"/>Ben Blessum was that, though he has lived in America from early childhood, he speaks Norwegian as fluently as a college professor of Norway, and his knowledge of Norwegian history, culture, and traditions is even more astounding.</p>
   <p>Another Chicago contribution to the festivities was the program of songs by the Nordmendenes Male Chorus, with Joel Mossberg as director and baritone soloist.</p>
   <p>Milwaukee's May 17th Committee really put on a successful festival and deserves a new and elegant feather in its collective cap.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
