<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-26">Mar. 26, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Jubilee Gift to Norway in 1914</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-26">Mar. 26, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">JUBILEE GIFT TO NORWAY IN 1914</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first proposal for a jubilee gift to Norway in 1914 was that one million dollars be gathered for the furtherance of some objective of benefit to the entire homeland. This proposal has influenced all subsequent discussions of the matter. To gather such an amount is considered by most of the writers on the matter as something magnificent, something worthy of the Norwegian-Americans.</p>
   <p>A million dollars in one lump sum is a good deal of money, but it is only a fraction of the sum which the Norwegians in this country are sending to Norway every year. Here, as so often happens in our thinking, we find, when investigating a matter more closely, that the small things are the big things, and <pb facs="5423969_5_1081.jpg" n="2"/>vice versa--that that which seems great, may really be rather insignificant.</p>
   <p>Soon the practical work, that of collecting the funds for the memorial gift, is to be started, and we must take care that minor considerations are not ranked before those of greater importance. Our work for the jubilee gift should not disturb the steady flow of small money gifts which steadily pass from America to Norway. If we are to collect one million dollars during the five years before the year of the jubilee, it means that we must gather about seven hundred thousand kroner per year during the period. This is a tidy sum, but it does not measure up to the fifteen million kroner quietly sent every year to Norway, without the aid of any committee carrying a high-sounding name. The jubilee gift is something which is sent once, and then it is done with. The small gifts have done their work over a long period of years; these small gifts were being sent long before a jubilee gift was ever mentioned, and will continue lone after this jubilee gift is forgotten by the people.</p>
   <p>It is evident that the work for the jubilee gift must be planned and arranged <pb facs="5423969_5_1082.jpg" n="3"/>in such a manner that it will in no way overshadow the really great work which our people are doing every year to settle their debt of honor to our fatherland and to achieve objectives in their local districts. The greater part of the numerous small sums that are sent to the old country go to relatives of the sender, perhaps to parents or to a wife....in brief, to the thousands of homes in the various parts of the country.</p>
   <p>During the discussion about the jubilee gift many advocated the need for some way by which the needy in Norway could be aided. There is plenty of opportunity to do this without resorting to a central committee. Anyone feeling the urge to do something for poor people with whom he is acquainted in Norway will know how to lend a helping hand. And it might be remembered that the "Good Book" states that when doing good one ought not let the left hand know what the right hand is doing.</p>
   <p>Besides the purely personal gifts to Norway, considerable amounts are sent in support of various local objectives. Most of these amounts are gathered by, <pb facs="5423969_5_1083.jpg" n="4"/>and among, the people who immigrated to America from the locality in question. The donors show by their donations that they have not forgotten the district in Norway where they first saw the light of day. One of the objectives most frequently considered by such donors has been a suitable organ for the church of their parish. There are many churches in Norway which, in this manner, have been supplied with organs.</p>
   <p>This type of gift has contributed greatly to the development of the organ industry in Norway. In former days it happened altogether too frequently that organs for the Norwegian churches had to be supplied from abroad--from Germany, America, or some other foreign country. But Norwegian-American donors stipulated that the organs which they gave as gifts should be built in Norway, and this has given great impetus to the Norwegian organ industry, providing work for many people who otherwise would have had to emigrate. Nowadays the organs built in Norway can measure up, both as to quality and price, with the best <pb facs="5423969_5_1084.jpg" n="5"/>in any other country, and for this thoughtfulness Norway has reason to thank the Norwegian-Americans.</p>
   <p>Many other local objectives have found substantial support here. At least two homes for aged people have been built in part by Norwegian-Americans, and two orphanages received constant support from Norwegians here. Sizable sums have been sent to Norway for the building of churches and chapels; for the restoration of old churches; and for the erection of halls where the young people can gather.....[Translator's note: A partial list is here presented of homes for the treatment of consumptives, built by money supplied largely by Norwegian-Americans.]</p>
   <p>As will be seen from the above, a number of the objectives which have been advocated as suitable for the jubilee gift have already been taken care of by the many donations to individuals and to localities. It will also become clear from a study of what has been done, that co-operation with the home <pb facs="5423969_5_1085.jpg" n="6"/>district provides the best method for accomplishing the desired end. To gather money here among the people from various districts in Norway and then send the money to the Norwegian government for distribution in the district, would be a roundabout way and entail much red tape. In addition, the government has nothing to do with such matters.....Gifts for various purposes would be regarded as alms if they were presented to the Norwegian government. But they are not alms if applied to local objectives in co-operation with the people of the districts in question. Most of those who were born in Norway have local interests there, and by supporting local objectives they advance their own interests, as well as those of the people living in the home districts.</p>
   <p>In this manner it will also be possible to urge the people of the home districts in Norway to greater exertions. Follow the methods in vogue here: "We will do so much if you will do the rest." In this manner, true competition for good objectives will be started, and added impetus will be given to efforts on both sides of the ocean....In every case, the Norwegian-Americans should <pb facs="5423969_5_1086.jpg" n="7"/>support that which the people in the home district in Norway feel is of most importance. Or, if no suggestion is made from the people in Norway, the initiative may be taken by the people here who came from the district in question....</p>
   <p>The work referred to here is greater than any unpaid committee could handle. More than twenty thousand postal money orders were sent from America to Norway last year; in addition, much currency and money bank checks were sent. The work of the very best committee could hardly be compared [to the effect of these contributions].</p>
   <p>A special collection of money is frequently followed by a period of declining interest. But there is no period of declining interest following this constant, quiet work by our people--without the aid of any committee. On the contrary, the interest has been increasing, and the remittances have been increasing from year to year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1087.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>There is another side to the matter which is significant to all those who desire to preserve Norwegianism here in America; every one of us is tied to Norway through our home district. There are our roots; and without those roots, our Norwegianism would soon lose its force. The Skandinaven is emphasizing this fact because by being interested in the affairs of the home districts we become more and more closely connected with Norway as our homeland.</p>
   <p>It seems evident that whatever we may do on a special occasion--however great and inspiring the occasion may be--we need first of all take care not to disturb or weaken the work which our people have been doing and are doing, quietly and voluntarily--work which is based on a touching love for the old home and the old country and which brings joy to all good Norwegians and to all good people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
