<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-23">May 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Deaconess Society Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-23">May 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEACONESS SOCIETY HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Deaconess Society held a monthly meeting at Bethel Church last Monday evening. The meeting was opened with reading of the scriptures by Mr. Johannes Liabo.</p>
   <p>Mr. Adolf Larsen was elected chairman of the meeting. The reports by the secretary, the superintendent, the financial secretary, and the treasurer were read and accepted. Five new members were received.....</p>
   <p>The committee of five, elected at the last meeting to prepare plans for the adoption of the Deaconess Society by the United Church, reported that advice on the matter had been sought from an attorney. The Reverend Ofstedal moved that the Norwegian Lutheran Deaconess Society in Chicago request the United Norwegian Lutheran Church to select a committee to meet with a similar committee, selected by the Deaconess Society in Chicago, to prepare plans for the <pb facs="5423969_5_0682.jpg" n="2"/>adoption of the Deaconess Society by the United Church, as an activity under the latter, this combined committee to report to the annual meeting of the United Church and to the Deaconess Society in Chicago. It was decided that the chairman is to place this motion for a joint committee before the coming meeting of the United Church, which is to be held in Minneapolis, Minnesta, from June 13 to June 21 of this year.</p>
   <p>The meeting concluded with the singing of a hymn and with a prayer by Reverend Ofstedal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
