<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-30">Mar. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-03-30">Mar. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scandia's expose of the egotism and narrow-mindedness of the (Norwegian) Lutheran Almanac for 1912 has caused a sensation throughout the country. This infamous almanac has awakened our people, and indignation though thoroughly aroused, is the some extent mixed with pity for the crass ignorance displayed. That anyone, in this enlightened 20th century, could commit such a senseless blunder and write such a "middle-ages," Roman Catholic article in what is considered the official publication of the Lutheran Church, is unthinkable and criminally scandalous.</p>
   <p>Where does our Norwegian-American press stand in this matter? The fight for greater personal and religious liberty for our people in America is in our opinion-a fight for our culture, and should be carried on vigorously by our entire press. Our conception of a proper Norwegian-American press is a group of papers whose editors are more interested in the advancement of our culture and liberties than in publishing statistics on crops or the number of flies a <pb facs="5423969_5_0444.jpg" n="2"/>chameleon can eat in a day.</p>
   <p>We have a right to expect signs of life and intelligence from our press, but in the matter of the Almanac the press remains as silent as the grave. There is nothing in the world as dead as a dead press, unless it be a dead oyster. The deadness of the press cannot be attributed to inefficiency; there must be some other underlying reason, an unconceivable power that has, even in the 20th century, been able to make our American press the champion "say-nothing-press" in the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
