<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-14">Aug. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[The Festival in Norway]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-08-14">Aug. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[THE FESTIVAL IN NORWAY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dagbladet, Christiania daily newspaper, has interviewed Consul H.T. Gade regarding the number of Norwegian-American guests expected to visit Norway during the 1914 festivities. Mr. Gade expects a great pilgrimage for the occasion, having been informed by thousands here of their intention to make the trip. He suspects that even with the two new Norwegian American Line boats in operation, Norwegian ships will not be able to accommodate the expected number of passengers, and suggests the advisability of having two or more additional boats running the entire season. Several of the larger fraternal organizations are considering to make the trip in a body by chartering a boat, in spite of the expense and difficulty of such an arrangement.</p>
   <p>The great concern in Christiania and other cities is how they are going to accommodate the thousands of guests; but we Norwegian-Americans are neither high-hatted nor snobbish, and will enjoy the smaller hotels or private homes <pb facs="5423969_5_0999.jpg" n="2"/>as much, if not more than the larger hotels.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gade, during the interview, also broached the subject of having a big celebration on July 4th during the 1914 festival and a special American Day at the exhibition grounds as a compliment to visiting Americans and to their country. Dagbladet's editor favored the idea, adding that in carrying out Mr. Gade's suggestions, the good will between Norway and the United States would be strengthened more than ever and would create a good impression wherever our Norsemen may be found.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian-American interest in Norway and its big year, is greater than ever before, and 1914 may see the greatest throng of visitors in the entire history of Norway. Visitors from the United States will constitute by far the greatest number from any country in the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
