<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-23">Jan. 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Social at the Deaconess Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-23">Jan. 23, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL AT THE DEACONESS HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A festive air prevailed throughout the Norwegian Deaconess Home last Friday.</p>
   <p>The entire interior of the Home was decorated; wherever one turned one met the smiling faces of deaconesses who were at hand, ready to aid the visitors in every way. It was apparent that the deaconesses were accustomed to think first of others and of themselves afterward, a rare attitude in our day. In this attitude they have the bright example of their superiors to follow.</p>
   <p>As the readers know, it was the gift from King Haakon that drew the people to the Deaconess Home on this occasion. The tapestry had been hung in the basement in a room that might have been larger for better effect, for one can fully appreciate the beauty of the tapestry only when standing at a suitable distance from it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The room was appropriately decorated with flags and evergreens, palms and wreaths.</p>
   <p>On entering the brightly lighted room, the tapestry made an imposing impression. Anyone, no matter how ignorant he might be of the art of weaving, would have realized that the tapestry was a real work of art.</p>
   <p>The drawing was done by the Norwegian artist, Gerhard Munthe, and the weaving by a lady signing her name as D. N. H. Thus it is understood that the weaver is not the renowned Frida Hansen; some visitors took the stand that the weaver was the daughter of Frida Hansen.</p>
   <p>The tapestry became even more interesting after Dr. Ingeborg Rasmussen had told its saga. It is the type of story that will fasten the tapestry in the minds of the people, so that they will be able to recall it in memory at will.</p>
   <p>After a few remarks about the origin of the art of tapestry weaving and its <pb facs="5423969_5_0589.jpg" n="3"/>development down through the centuries, the Doctor turned to the tale of the particularly Norwegian development of this type of weaving. Finally she came to the fairy tale represented on the tapestry in question.</p>
   <p>Once upon a time there was a king who had three handsome sons, and another king who had three beautiful daughters. The princes fell in love with the three beautiful princesses, and everything appeared to be sunshine and song. There were some wicked trolls living in a mountain nearby, however; they, too, wanted the princesses, and they carried them away into their mountain. The princes became sick at heart when they learned of this and did not know what to do. The queen, however, was an orphan, adopted in her childhood. Her foster father was wiser than anybody else, and to him the princes went in their distress. He told the young men that he could see where the princesses were but he could not see where the key to the palace of the trolls was hung. If the princes could find this key, he said, and get the princesses out of the abode of the trolls without their touching the threshold with their feet, they would be delivered from the domination of the trolls. It was also specified that each princess <pb facs="5423969_5_0590.jpg" n="4"/>must recognize her prince. In order to facilitate the task for the boys, the wise man changed them, one into a hart, one into a fish, one into a bird. The bird discovered the key at the bottom of a hollow tree; the fish fished it out; and the hart carried the princesses across the threshold. Each princess recognized her prince; the power of witchery of the trolls over the princesses was destroyed, and the three beautiful princesses were in their father's palace again. And then there was held a wedding that was spoken of in seven kingdoms.</p>
   <p>After the interesting fairy tale was told, refreshments were served. Afterwards there was music and singing in Mother Ingeborg's room.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
