<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-05-18">May 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Keep Norse Fete Day Children of Norway Celebrate Anniversary of Constitutions's Adoption Memories of Fatherland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-05-18">May 18, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">KEEP NORSE FETE DAY CHILDREN OF NORWAY CELEBRATE ANNIVERSARY OF CONSTITUTIONS'S ADOPTION MEMORIES OF FATHERLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With children's exercises in Humboldt Park in the forenoon, a "folkfast" at Brand's Park in the afternoon and evening, and with "nationalfests" in Wicker Park and Schoenhofen Halls in the evening. Chicago Norwegian citizens commemorated the ninety-first anniversary of the adoption of the Norwegian constitution.</p>
   <p>More than 1000 school children gathered at the playground at West North Avenue, and North Leavitt Street, at 9:00 A.M. Carrying the flags of Norway and of the United States, the children formed a procession and marched to Humboldt Park, where exercises were held in the pavilion. Several thousand grown people listened to an address by Rev. L. Harrieville, who said in part: As Norwegians today and as citizens of the United States, we may take a lesson from our Viking ancestors <pb facs="5423969_5_0134.jpg" n="2"/>of old. They fought for many different things, but when they had once made an agreement they served that king no matter who he was, and kept his laws. I want to urge on every boy and girl here today the necessity of obeying the law and keeping order.</p>
   <p>Tells of Magnus Falsen</p>
   <p>Rev. Alfred Johnson reviewed the life work of Magnus Falsen, the great Norwegian democratic salesman, who did much to secure the adoption of the constitution under which Norway is ruled today.</p>
   <p>A large Norwegian flag flying from one side of the entrance and the Stars and Stripes from the other welcomed the sons of Norway to Brand's Park. Nearly every-one wore streamers or little flags of the Norwegian colors, which are red, white and blue.</p>
   <p>The evening program was opened with the singing of "Ja Vi Elsker Dette Landet", the Norwegian national anthem by the Norwegian Glee Club of which Emil Biorr is director.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Senator Hopkins speaks</p>
   <p>O. Harveland, president of the Norwegian National League, which includes most of the Norwegian societies in Chicago, acted as chairman and introduced Senator Albert J. Hopkins who said: "You are celebrating today because you have liberty and are proud of your manhood and womanhood. Every possibility is open to the boys and girls here tonight. If I wanted an illustration I would point to my friend H. A. Hangar, who sits on the platform. His life shows what can be done, and today he is regarded as a leader in the financial work. Some of the best citizens in this country represent the Northland Knute Nelson of Minnesota is one of the leading men in the United States Senate. You know the story of his life."</p>
   <p>Rev. J. W. Finfall addressed the audience in Norwegian. The celebration closed with a display of fireworks.</p>
   <p>Songs of the fatherland and an operatic sketch formed the evening exercises at Schoenhofen Hall. Those who took part in the costumed musical piece were: R. Langosith, Mrs. C.Rosenberg, F. Askwold, J. G. Olsen, Christian Olsen, and R. N. <pb facs="5423969_5_0136.jpg" n="4"/>Broehke. The members of the arrangement committee were Julius Jager, Knud Johnsen, Carl Rosenberg, Anton Ness, Christian Olsen and Elnor Andersen.</p>
   <p>At Wicker Park Hall a musical program was enjoyed by 1500 people. Alderman William E. Dever addressed the audience. Upon the arrangment committee were Isaac R. Rasmussen, H. Optedahl, N. Hoffstad, H. Mathisen, and N. Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
