<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-15">Mar. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal District League</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting of the Cabinet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-15">Mar. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO NORWEGIAN-DANISH METHODIST EPISCOPAL DISTRICT LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Meeting of the Cabinet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Methodist Episcopal District League held a cabinet meeting last Saturday at the residence of Mr. Thor Loberg, 2123 Maple Avenue, Evanston. As usual, the meeting opened with the singing of a hymn, after which the president of the District League, Reverend Edward Ericksen, read from the Scriptures and led in prayer.</p>
   <p>Reverend Ericksen then gave a survey of the work of the League since the previous meeting. He called special attention to the position of the ministers within the League, stating that the minister of a church in which a league had been organized invariably ought to be consulted concerning the work of such a local league.</p>
   <p>The various departments of the District League then presented their reports. President Ericksen was requested to see to the printing of the League <pb facs="5423969_5_0556.jpg" n="2"/>constitution. Written invitations for the coming convention were received from the Bethany Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, of Racine, Wisconsin, and from the First and Immanuel Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church, in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Reverend Ericksen suggested that the District Convention be held at Desplaines, Illinois this year in connection with the fiftieth anniversary celebration of the Desplaines camp meeting. After a thorough discussion of the suggestion, which was changed into a motion, the matter was tabled. It was then voted to accept the invitation of the Bethany Church, in Racine, and a committee consisting of Reverend Edward Ericksen and Messrs. T. Loberg and Skudstad was appointed to arrange a suitable date for the convention. Reverend Ericksen, Mrs. Nielsen, and Miss Hansen were appointed to the program committee for the convention and Messrs. Skudstad and Olson were appointed to the transportation committee.</p>
   <p>Mrs. T. Loberg served refreshments and the president expressed the cabinet's <pb facs="5423969_5_0557.jpg" n="3"/>thanks for the hospitality shown. Lodging had been provided, and most of those present stayed to attend the evening services of the Norwegian-Danish Methodist Episcopal Church in Evanston, of which Reverend Ericksen is the pastor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
