<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Publishing Co., Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 179
<title level="a">[Church of the Veritans]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Publishing Co., Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 179
<title level="a">[CHURCH OF THE VERITANS]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Church of the Veritans was organized July 15, 1901 by members of the order of the Magi, the most ancient of all the secret orders on our planet. The Church Society was instituted for the purpose of extending to the public through its open meetings such teachings as could properly be brought before the uninitiated showing the most ancient philosophy in the light of the most advanced modern science and also explaining the various phenomena of occultism as necessary factors in the development of the religion of science.</p>
   <p>Through the able and well-directed efforts of Mr. B. C. Peterson, who is a charter member and who holds the office of secretary of the society many a progressive mind among the Scandinavians of Chicago as well as from the country at large have graviated towards the temple of knowledge, which was founded upon the divine law of evolution, has become a firm stepping stone from the infinite past to the likewise infinite and invisible future a place where those who have sought enlightment upon the great subject of origin and the destiny of</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>humanity and divinity, have found an opportunity to worship Truth itself without the usual attachment of intermediary personal deities and without any creeds or dogmas, ancient or modern.</p>
   <p>Based upon the principles of mathematics, chemistry and geology, the aims and objects of the society are probably best explained as set forth in its constitution article #2. The purpose of this society shall be to teach demonstrable truth and to deal with logical destruction regarding the universe. B. C. Peterson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
