<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1911-09-13">Sept. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegians [And America]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0857</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0857.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-09-13">Sept. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIANS [AND AMERICA]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is part of a speech given by M. A. Michaelson at a Seventeenth of May festival. Many of our readers have requested a reprint of this particular portion of the address.</p>
   <p>"The earliest recorded date in world history of a Norwegian people is about 800 A. D. In that early day and age our ancestors came upon the scene of the then known world as a fierce, plundering, murderous horde of warriors whom the English chroniclers described as 'Stinging Wasps' and 'Savage Wolves'.</p>
   <p>"These Norsemen--'Vikings', they were called--lived as heroes, lords, and conquerors. Sailing out of the icebound, bleak land on which they were born, they conquered England, Scotland, and Ireland; ravaged Brittany and Normandy; discovered and colonized Iceland and Greenland; and in their open, oar-manned sail boats, crossed the Atlantic Ocean and found a new continent five hundred <pb facs="5423969_5_0858.jpg" n="2"/>years before Columbus.</p>
   <p>"But our modern Norwegian people are different. We probably are not a bit less brave than these early ancestors. We have been tempered by Christianity, and contact with other peoples and Nations over a long period of years has made us see that it is the meek that shall inherit the earth, and that peacemakers shall be called the Children of God.</p>
   <p>"The ancient Norsemen had always been independent. There is no record to the contrary, and the typical modern Norwegian is an ardent champion of democracy and personal independence. The people of classical countries were free men because they belonged to a powerful and free state; they boasted of their citizenship. The Norseman was a free man because he was a man; he boasted of himself and the deeds he performed. This passion for freedom runs throughout Norwegian history. It accounts for the exodus of the Norwegians to Iceland and Normandy. It accounts for the fact that Norway has never had a nobility. The Norwegians were the last people in Europe to submit to the Catholic yoke, and the first people to throw it off.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0859.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Here in Chicago we have taken a foremost place, and we play a leading part in every laudable human endeavor. In industry, finance, education, art, literature, science, politics, and sports, our record of great achievement fills us with pride and serves as our inspiration for the future.</p>
   <p>"Ever since the arrival of David Johnson, the first Norwegian settler in Chicago, in 1834, when Chicago was only a small village, our people have been closely identified with her marvelous growth and success. And today there are more Norwegians in Chicago than in any other city in the country. We believe we have made substantial and lasting contributions toward her upbuilding; we claim a share in her greatness, and an honorable part in her development; as a result of which we feel highly justified in suggesting to her citizenship as a whole that we be granted a slight recognition of our worthiness and of work well done in her behalf, to the extent that her latest monument to civic progress and achievement--the new outer harbor drive--be named in honor and commemoration of a Norwegian, Leif Ericson, the discoverer of America."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
