<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Scandinaven Medical Society]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1914-06-27">June 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[SCANDINAVEN MEDICAL SOCIETY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian Medical Society passed the following resolution at its regular monthly meeting, June 11, 1914:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, It is with deep sorrow that we, the members of the Scandinavian-American Medical Society, of Chicago, record the passing of another of our colleagues, our honorary member, Dr. Niles Theodore Quales; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we hereby express the sentiments of respect, admiration, and regard with which we cherish the memory of our old Nestor. Dr. Quales was a hard worker and his generosity was unusual. He was not only the family physician, but also the counselor and friend in whom the patients could,place their fullest confidence.</p>
   <p>His friendship for the poor was well known. He would respond to their calls day or night, even though he knew that he would receive no compensation for his services. And it frequently happened that he took his own money to help procure the necessary medicines. In his relations with his professional colleagues, <pb facs="5423969_5_1249.jpg" n="2"/>Dr. Quales showed no rivalry, no petty jealousy, no selfishness, but was always kind, sympathetic, and ever ready to serve his colleagues.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Quales was identified as the founder and benefactor of various charitable institutions which will preserve his name forever.</p>
   <p>"Although he had a large practice, he found time to keep up with the progress of medicine. He was modest and unassuming, and tried to avoid ostentation, Both his social and professional career may well serve as an example for all of us. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we extend our sincere sympathy to his bereaved wife and family, and that these resolutions be spread upon the minutes of this Society.</p>
   <p>"A.B. Oyen, President</p>
   <p>Carl Nielsen, Vice-President</p>
   <p>Hugo A. Oldenborg, Secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
