<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-12-25">Dec. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Journalists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0957</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0957.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
     <item>IV (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-12-25">Dec. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN JOURNALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A festival was given by the combined Norwegian clubs and societies in honor of the visiting journalists. Judge Harry Olson [Swede] was the main speaker of the evening. He stressed that to him there were no Danes, Swedes, or Norwegians, they were all Scandinavians. He spoke of a society that had existed years ago, a society whose purpose it was to unite the three people here in America, but at that time the people did not understand unity, and the society soon fell apart. He pleaded with the Scandinavians to unite and stay united. He then presented Henry L. Hertz [Dane], the toastmaster for the evening. Mr. H. H. Merrick, who is a descendant of Norwegian stock, also elaborated on Scandinavian unity.</p>
   <p>Carl Antonsen [Dane] then asked for the floor; he spoke of Denmark, the beloved country the Danes had left; and of America, the new beloved land they had adopted. C. S. Peterson [Swede], spoke for Sweden. He pointed <pb facs="5423969_5_0958.jpg" n="2"/>out that the Swedes were law-abiding and industrious, and even though they had not arrived in America with great wealth, they came from a country where there were no poorhouses and few prisons.</p>
   <p>Edwin Bjorkman corrected Judge Olson on his remark about the society. Mr. Bjorkman said the society was organized by a woman, Magrete Valdemarsdatter who, though a woman, was "man" enough to hold the society together as long as she lived. It was the men who followed that broke the society apart.</p>
   <p>The guests then spoke as follows: Emil Marrot, from Denmark; Arthur Rathe, from Norway; and Otto Johnson, from Sweden. Each of the above brought regards from their respective homelands, and each spoke at length on the Scandinavian-American press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
