<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1920-03-19">Mar. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Lutheran Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-03-19">Mar. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a conference held last week by the National Lutheran Council, it was reported that a consolidation had at last been made with the Norwegian Lutheran Church. The following resolution was passed:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, It is evident that the organization and operation of the National Lutheran Council has not met the approval and sanction of a large membership of Lutherans represented by it; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Our own church body (the Norwegian Lutheran Church of America), by affiliating with the National Lutheran Council, sanctions and approves the teachings and practices of its members; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Some of the pastors and leading members of the National Lutheran Council tolerate and subscribe to the teachings of Freemasonry; and</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0256.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Whereas, Our own church body (the Norwegian Lutheran Church of America), through its affiliation with the National Lutheran Council has created a barrier to the harmonious co-operation of its members; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, "Unionism" is tolerated, and even now, according to press reports, pastors are petitioning for co-operation with the "inter-church movement"; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, By the Pastoral Conference of the Norwegian Lutheran Church of America, that co-operation with the National Lutheran Council, under present conditions and practices, be and is hereby disapproved, except for relief of temporal distress in overseas Lutheran communities."</p>
   <p>The above resolution speaks for itself. The affiliation is in part only, but it is a beginning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
