<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Great Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0086</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0086.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>4.................May 17, turned out to be an ideal summer day for the Norwegian national holiday celebration. During the several days preceeding the 17th, signs of activity and a coming event evident all along West North Avenue, the American "Karl Johans Gade" (Karl Johan St.). Norwegian flags and other decorations in the national colors were prominently displayed in every place of business; from Western Avenue to California Avenue and throughout the park, the route to be taken by parade was a veritable avenue of flags. As early as 9:00 A.M. Humboldt Park was teeming with milling crowds of celebrants seeking advantageous points from which to view the colorful parade. Their early gatherings was made pleasant by an informal concert by a band provided by the Norwegian National League) playing a group of Norwegian marches and folk songs. The Leif Eriksen Statue was marked by a large Norwegian flag. The excitement, already great, was increased when a street car caught fire sending up a cloud of smoke worthy of a good sized building. The fire was put out, however, when a hose was run out from Scandia's office and, to the volunteer smoke-eaters credit, it must be said that the usual damage by water was reduced to a minimum. The children's parade, arranged by Chicago's Norwegian churches was a sight long to be remembered and an honor to our people. Heading the parade was a detachment of twelve police officers, <pb facs="5423969_5_0087.jpg" n="2"/>all Norwegians. The first banner in the parade was that of"Henrik Ibsen"Lodge of the I.O.G.T. (organized in 1906) the first Scandinavian local of this order in the Mid-West. The members of this group carried a number of banners and penants proclaiming their principles in no uncertain terms. Many of our pastors headed groups from their individual churches. This list included Pastor Solberg, president of the May 17th committee, and pastors Harrisville, Gullinksen, Sigmond, Fretheim, Roseland, Ausan, Hauge, Meyer, Kildahl and Filler. Sunday schools sending childrens groups were Irving Park Lutheran, Maplewood Avenue, M.E., Bethal Lutheran, Salem Evangelical Free Church, Elin, Emmans, Our Saviors and several who carried no identification. The line of march was from Humboldt Park to Western Avenue and return, thense to North on Humboldt Blvd., to Palmer Square where it disbanded. It is estimated that six-thousand took part in the parade while the main celebration at Brands Park drew a crowd of nearly ten-thousand. Speakers were Professor Flon and Merriam.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
