<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 270-271.
<title level="a">[Biography of Sigvald Asbjornsen]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 270-271.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF SIGVALD ASBJORNSEN]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sigvald Asbjornsen, the sculptor, was born in Christiania, Norway, Oct. 19, 1867. He is a graduate of the Royal Art School of Christiania and a pupil of the great sculptors Middelthun, Bergslien and Sceibrok.</p>
   <p>At the age of 16 he was granted a royal stipend to help him along in his studies. This he received for five years. He arrived in this country in 1892 and went to Michigan. He came to Chicago during the World's Fair, making this city his permanent home. He made a bust of Grover Cleveland and one of Blaine. Mr. Asbjornsen's public works embrace Lief Erikson statue at Humboldt Park, Hon. Robert William Moore statue, Memphis, Tenn. Defiance of the Flag, a group of three soldiers, Decatur, Ill. Pennsylvania State Monument, Andersonville, Ga.; Illinois State Monument, Chattanooga; John Monaghan Monument, Spokane, Wash.</p>
   <p>He has also made the following busts in bronze: John Anderson, Prof. H. H. Borjesen, Walter Grasham, Benjamin Franklin, Edwin Westgaard and a marble bust of Paul O. Stensland. He has also made some striking <pb facs="5423969_5_1438.jpg" n="2"/>medallions particularly one in bronze of Bjornstjerne Bjornson on the Bjornson Bareta Fargo, N. D.; also medallions of Ibsen, Grieg, Robert Ingersol and others. Mr. Asbjornsen married Margaritha Steehr of Norway. They have three children. The family resides at 1075 Wabansia Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
