<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-08-14">Aug. 14, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian-American Line</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-14">Aug. 14, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN-AMERICAN LINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reports in the Norwegian press show that the idea of a Norwegian-American steamship line is being considered with increasing interest throughout Norway and among all classes of the population. The sale of stock started only a few weeks ago, and already one third of the stock has been sold. The leaders are confident that the whole issue will be sold before long.</p>
   <p>The sale of stock in this country is, as mentioned earlier in Skandinaven, under the direction of Consul E. H. Hobe, St. Paul, Minnesota. Norwegians in America have also evinced great interest in the sale of stock, but because of the large distances involved, it will naturally take time before the work will have really started.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hobe has tried to arrange things in the best way possible, so that Norwegians from every section of the country may have a chance to <pb facs="5423969_5_1068.jpg" n="2"/>participate. Among the readers of the Skandinaven there are undoubtedly many who wish to buy stock, so as to have a hand in the building of the new bridge between us in America and our relatives in Norway, between our old and new homelands.</p>
   <p>The conditions under which stock may be purchased are discussed elsewhere in this issue. Those who wish to be included in the list of the builders of the new line to Norway may apply to Consul Hobe or to Skandinaven. We shall be glad to do our best to aid this great undertaking of the Norwegian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
