<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1914-10-17">Oct. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Synod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1914-10-17">Oct. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN SYNOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report of the annual meeting of the Norwegian Synod is as follows:</p>
   <p>The usual committees were set up. Judge Grindeland submitted a resolution to protect President Stub, and to take issue on all that the press and the laxity have accused him of. The Judge then followed with:</p>
   <p>"I sincerely regret that it has become necessary to offer this resolution, but the sense of duty forbids silence. If the Norwegian Synod is to maintain its dignity and good standing, it should act favorably upon this resolution.</p>
   <p>"While we are confronting the question of church union, a question around which centers the interest of all Norwegian Lutherans of America, it becomes highly important that we take a favorable attitude toward the subject matter of this resolution. While our able, faithful, and considerate president is <pb facs="5423969_5_0376.jpg" n="2"/>engaged in the great cause of the union, shall our attitude be to mistrust him, to give him our ill will and impugn his motives, or, shall we give him our good will and confidence and treat him with the respect and confidence that his high official position demands?</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen of the convention, I offer this resolution in a kind and Christian spirit, having in view only the duty we owe to our worthy president, the duty we owe to ourselves, and the duty we owe to the welfare of our Synod. I appeal to your sense of justice to adopt this resolution."</p>
   <p>The resolution was passed with only one voting against it: Reverend R. Brandt asked that his name be entered in the minutes as one who voted against the resolution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
