<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-15">Jan. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">St. Paul Norwegian Lutheran Church Celebrates</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-15">Jan. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ST. PAUL NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN CHURCH CELEBRATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Wicker Park Ladies' Aid Society of the St. Paul Norwegian Lutheran Church had the honor of presenting the most excellent Norwegian dinner served in these parts. The schoolrooms at 596 West North Avenue formed the dining room. The occasion was the twentieth day after Christmas. [Editors' note: the twentieth day after Christmas is of little significance today, but it was previously celebrated in Norway, and is associated with Norwegian mythology.] It was the first time this day was celebrated in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The spirit of the occasion was noticed in the decorations. As many Christmas trees as possible had been collected and placed about the room which also held other Christmas decorations. It meant the old Norwegian goodbye to Christmas.</p>
   <p>The guests gathered in the Church where a brief program was presented. The organist, Miss Ora Johnson, played; a duet was sung by Misses Martha Bergslien and Evelyn Christofferson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0208.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At 7:30 P.M. the guests were led to the tables and it was found that there were seats for nearly all who were present. Genuine Norwegian dishes were served; they had been prepared in correct Norwegian manner under the direction of a competent Norwegian dietician, Mrs. Sponberg. All the members of the committee on arrangements agreed in giving the credit for the excellency of the food and the plan which had been followed to Mrs. Sponberg.</p>
   <p>The waitresses were young girls under the leadership of Mrs. Gullixon, and they did their work to the satisfaction of everybody. About three hundred guests dined during the evening and rarely have a group of diners been more satisfied with food and service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
