<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-10-21">Oct. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Deaconess Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Annual Reports are Favorable; the Society Will Build</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-21">Oct. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEACONESS SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Annual Reports are Favorable; The Society Will Build</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Deaconess Society held its annual meeting at the Zion Church, corner of Potomac and Artesian Avenues. Mr. Adolf Larson was chosen chairman of the meeting.</p>
   <p>The report presented by Treasurer Holstad showed that the Society owns property valued at $9,203.86, and has no debts. The Society owns five lots at the corner of Haddon Avenue and Leavitt Street, and in the spring intends to build one wing of the Deaconess Home there. Mr. A. P. Johnson, member of the building committee, estimated that the wing would cost from $18,000 to $20,000. Part of Chairman Larson's report read as follows:</p>
   <p>"The important events of the year, in the history of our Society, are as follows: The bazaar for the benefit of the building fund, on December 7, 8, 9, 1899, netted $665. The donations day at the Home, January 1, 1900, <pb facs="5423969_5_0667.jpg" n="2"/>was not well attended; perhaps we ought to change the date to Thanksgiving Day.</p>
   <p>"Sister Caroline Williams served as deaconess in Bethlehem Congregation from November 6 until February 6. The Congregation in question has again sent in a request for a deaconess to undertake the same kind of work, but we have not been able to send anyone. Two courses of instruction were arranged for the sisters, one for the senior class and one for the junior class. The courses lasted from January to June. An annual report of this course was published at the beginning of the year and distributed among the friends of the society. The board of directors of the Lutheraneren [newspaper] kindly let us use one page of the paper once a month, and Reverend Olaf Guldseth has been the editor of this page.</p>
   <p>"Reverend C. W. Waswig gave a most interesting and instructive lecture on the Deaconess movement, on April 23, at the Church of the Covenant... On May 9 there was a graduation festival at the Bethlehem Church for <pb facs="5423969_5_0668.jpg" n="3"/>four sisters and soon afterwards two of the sisters were sent to Crookston, Minnesota, to take over the work at the Bethesda Hospital.</p>
   <p>"On May 24, Mr. Johannes Liabo gave a most interesting lecture for the benefit of the building fund. The lecture netted forty-five dollars.</p>
   <p>"This Deaconess movement in Chicago has been thus far, and is still a private undertaking. The Deaconess Society, a part of whose membership live in Chicago, elects the board of directors for the Home. This board of directors accepts Sisters, appoints a Sister Superior, takes care of the needs of the Home and is responsible to the Society for the conditions existing in the Home. So far, this arrangement has worked very well, yet it hardly holds sufficient security for the future. The Deaconess movement is a church movement, a missionary movement, a sociological movement of immense importance and of vast extent. The Society and its friends have raised the question, therefore, of placing this movement into the hands of <pb facs="5423969_5_0669.jpg" n="4"/>somebody who could carry it onward and give it the greater development which a private society is unable to give...For this reason, the Society has found it desirable to seek a closer connection and union with the United Norwegian Lutheran Church in America. In this connection, I was sent to the annual conference of the United Church at Minneapolis, in June, to present the matter to that body. As a result, the United Church selected a committee of three to confer on the matter with a committee of three to be appointed by the Deaconess Society....The committee has not yet held any meetings."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
