<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-02-02">Feb. 2, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Compliments from the Sage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-02-02">Feb. 2, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">COMPLIMENTS FROM THE SAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ignatius Donnelly informed the delegates to the Farmers' Alliance Convention that if his paper could be brought out in a Norwegian and Swedish issue, the populists would surely carry the election next fall. A dozen Scandinavian populist editors in Minnesota, more or less, will appreciate this delicate compliment to their ability and influence. Their journals, of which there are at least six professing the creed in full, were in the field long before the first issue of Donnelly's paper appeared. But the sage evidently considers their work as being of no significance whatever. This matter is a family affair, however, and it may be left to Mr. Donnelly and his Scandinavian brethren of the quill to be settled among themselves as best they can.</p>
   <p>Whether the Scandinavians will appreciate the compliment paid to them by Mr. Donnelly in his statement, is somewhat doubtful. The essence of his assertion <pb facs="5423969_5_0234.jpg" n="2"/>was that they are not populists because he cannot reach them; that they would join the populists in great numbers if he could talk to them through the Scandinavian issues of his paper. The sage has been somewhat quiet of late. It is, therefore, all the more refreshing to learn that his proverbial modesty has lost none of its old time charm. But his fatherly concern for the Scandinavians is likely to remain unappreciated. To be classed as voting cattle is not to their liking, nor do they relish Mr. Donnelly's assumption concerning their intelligence and votes. If he doubts this statement, he would better put the matter to an actual test by publishing Norwegian and Swedish issues of his paper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
