<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1890-06-12">June 12, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Lutherans United</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1890-06-12">June 12, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN LUTHERANS UNITED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This morning three of the five divisions of the Norwegian Lutheran Church in America, opened what is destined to be the most important convention ever held by that denomination. For two years negotations have been going on between the anti-Missourians, the Norwegian-Danish conference, the Angustana Synod and the Hange Synod with a view to a union of their disunited church. Although in sympathy with the movement the Hange Synod is not yet prepared to enter the union, but will no doubt do so during the coming year, of the other three, each division will hold separate meetings, at which the affairs of the old organization are to be wound up and the constitution and articles of union, which have been particularly agreed upon, adopted. Then the United Norwegian Lutheran Church of America will be a reality.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Lutheran Synod a distinct body from the above, and which has been in annual session here, denounced the Bennett law today. The principal underlying <pb facs="5423969_5_0725.jpg" n="2"/>the law was admitted to be just. The state was justified in demanding that its citizens should receive a certain degree of education. The Bennett law went further and deprived the parents of the right to educate their children. The law was more of Russian than of our own free country. Ansbury Seminary will be endowed with $115,000.00 and will be the theological school of the United Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
