<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1915-05-26">May 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Pioneers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-05-26">May 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN PIONEERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago District of The Norwegian Pioneers' Association of the United States held it's first annual banquet at the Norwegian Club, Kedzie and Milwaukee Avenue. Judge Oscar M. Torrison was toastmaster. The main speaker of the evening was the Minister to Norway, Mr. L. S. Swenson. None of the members had arrived here during the period of 1830-40. The toastmaster called on Mr. Peter M. Balken who came to Chicago in 1849. He remembered the names of all of the Norwegian settlers who arrived here as early as 1836. He told a great deal about the early struggles and privations of the early days; he spoke of the great cholera epidemic of 1849. He pointed out that the first "corners' settled in the district, then called "The Sands," on Pine Street between Chicago Avenue and Superior Street. We will mention a few of the early arrivals.</p>
   <p>Captain Halvor Michelson came in 1854; Hauman G. Hauman arrived in 1862; his <pb facs="5423969_5_0904.jpg" n="2"/>father rounded the Horn in 1849; Captain Reierson came in 1860; Reverend Hans Oftedahl arrived in 1871; Otto C. Erickson came in 1870. Mr. J. B. Nordhem, who arrived in 1859, was the only one of those present who had participated in the Civil War. Dr. Anders Doe arrived in 1880.</p>
   <p>The first settlers had little or no money, but most of them struggled and saved, and are today quite wealthy. The arrivals in the 40's, 50's and 60's were for the most part farmers; the city dwellers came later. The Norwegians were mostly pious and ambitious; they cleared the land, built churches and schools, and before long Norwegian culture had mingled with other European culture, forming the present American culture.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Pioneers' Association was organized by such men as Knute Matson, John Andersen, P. M. Balken, and Halvor Mickelsen, of Chicago; Halle Steensland and J. A. Johnson, of Madison; Carl Joys, of Milwaukee;</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0905.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>pioneers from Minnesota and Iowa were the ones who really conceived the idea. </p>
   <p>The master of archives, Mr. C. H. Tollefsrude, Rolfe, Iosa, has some very interesting data about the early pioneers. In his files there are biographies and portraits of all the members. The Chicago branch has about fifty members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
