<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title> Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 219-20
<title level="a">[Biography of Knud Langland]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Ill.</title> Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 219-20
<title level="a">[Biography of Knud Langland]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Knud Langland, spent some of the most active years of his life in Chicago as editor of Skandinaven. It was during the period from 1866 to 1872 that he did the work which firmly established his reputation as a thinker and writer. It is quite proper, therefore, that a brief sketch of his life appear in this volume. Knud Langeland was born October 27, 1813, in Sammanger, Bergen, Norway. Though obliged to work hard for a living, even in his early youth, he managed to secure a good education through his own efforts. He went to Bergen where he pursued his studies for a time and then became a school teacher. Afterwards he was appointed public vaccinator. In 1835 he made a short visit to England and on returning home he engaged in business in Bergen. An older brother,Mons A. Adeand, emigrated to <pb facs="5423969_5_1426.jpg" n="2"/>America in 1837 settling in Racine County, Wisconsin. Knud Langland followed him in 1843 making his home in same place. In 1849 he bought Nordlyset, the first Norwegian paper published in America. He changed the name to Democraten. The venture was not a financial success and publication was suspended in 1852. The next year he issued a monthly paper in Janesville, Wisconsin, but soon sold out and returned to the farm. In 1856 he was editor for a short time of the Norwegian Americanner published in Madison, Wisconsin, but the pro-slavery views of its proprieter caused him to resign. In 1866, when the Skandinaven was established by John Anderson and Iver Lawson; father of Victor F. Lawson, Mr. Langland was asked by them to become its editor. He consented and came to Chicago to which place he moved his family in 1868. He was connected with that paper which proved a remarkable success, until a year or <pb facs="5423969_5_1427.jpg" n="3"/>two after the great fire of 1871. Perhaps the most notable of the editorials contributed by him to Skandinaven were those in defense of the American public schools and in opposition to certain views, entertained by a part of the Norwegian Lutheran Church in regard to slavery. It was in recognition of his attitude on the school question that one of the public schools of Chicago was named after him some years later. With the exception of a brief connection with a new Norwegian paper, the Amerika which was subsequently consolidated with Skandinaven, all the editorial work performed by him until he was compelled by ill health to retire from journalism was for Skandinaven. He retired, and died in Milwaukee, Feb. 8, 1886.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
