<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Union of Norwegian Churches of America Considered]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-17">Feb. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[UNION OF NORWEGIAN CHURCHES OF AMERICA CONSIDERED]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As will be recalled by our readers, advances were made by various synods of the Norwegian Lutheran Churches of America, toward a union of these branches. The joint committee of a year ago met and adjourned without coming to an agreement. A new committee was appointed, and this body appointed a sub-committee to draw up a series of propositions for consideration by the entire committee. Should the proposals of the sub-committee be acceptable to the main body, it will be submitted at the annual business sessions of each synod during the coming summer.</p>
   <p>We deduce, from reports on the subject, that competition in church work is a hindrance to the religious progress of our people, and it is to be hoped that unity and co-operation will be brought about at last. The division was caused by a mere triviality, a difference in the interpretation of non-essentials in the scriptures. So "worked up" were both the clergy <pb facs="5423969_5_0449.jpg" n="2"/>and the laity that actual hatred has existed between the several factions. The controversial points have long since been forgotten in Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Germany, etc., and there, they are puzzled over the condition of the Lutheran churches in this country.</p>
   <p>We are pleased to note, however, that the leading men of each synod are now ardent workers for a reunion, where harmony will reign and united effort will get results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
