<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-10-28">Oct. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Lief Eriksen's Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-10-28">Oct. 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">LIEF ERIKSEN'S DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Columbus had the honor last week. Leif Eriksen had his turn last night at Scandia Hall at West Ohio Street near Milwaukee Avenue, where a large company of sons and daughters of the land of Vikings paid their tribute to the man whom they claim discovered America four-hundred years before Columbus set fort on San Salvador. Speech making, dancing, songs and instrumental music were the features of the Eriksen "Fest".</p>
   <p>Pretty little girls with red frocks and garlands in their hair gave away grapes to the guests out of big baskets to commemorate the discovery of Vineland the Beautiful. It was an evening that bore much significance from the Northland, for it meant nothing less than a claim on the part of the Norwegians to the honors for discovering America. It was no idle boast either, for the speakers of the evening backed up their claims with testimony from such eminent historians as Prof. John Fiske of Harvard University, Prof. Harsford, Prof. Bancroft, Prof. Gustav Storm, and Prof. Anderson, who concede that Lief Eriksen touched Americas shores <pb facs="5423969_5_0186.jpg" n="2"/>long before Columbus was born. The Norwegians lay much stress on the statements of Prof. Harsford who believes so thoroughly in Eriksen that he has erected three monuments to his memory. One in Baltimore, one in Boston, and another near Boston. On the stage behind the speakers table was a painting of Eriksen, said to have been taken from sketches found among the archives of Iceland. The program was as follows:........The celebration was sponsored by L. E. Olsen and a committee;......Many prominent persons were present;.......Addresses and speeches were made by Mr. Elvig, and P. A. Conrodi;..........The adherents of Lief Eriksen continued their music and dancing at Scandia Hall until a late hour.</p>
   <p>The Norwegians of Chicago are planning to have a big celebration in honor of Eriksen during the World's Fair. They will dispute the claims of Columbus on his own grounds.</p>
   <p>May 17, is the Norwegian national holiday, and on that occasion next year the grand celebration will be held. An effort will be made to have the royal family <pb facs="5423969_5_0187.jpg" n="3"/>of Norway in Chicago that day at least. A procession will parade the streets as an escort for the guests of honor. There will be floats representing Lief Eriksen in his ship and landing on American shores.</p>
   <p>The projectors of the celebration intend to make the demonstration compare as favorably as possible with the Columbian display. Prof. Harsford and other historians will be asked to prepare addresses.</p>
   <p>The Lief Eriksen Memorial Association is having a $3000.00 portrait of the famous Viking for exhibition at the Columbian Exposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
