<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Technicians Convene</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TECHNICIANS CONVENE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Norwegian American technicians were gathering for their convention this morning in the club rooms of Chicago Norwegian Club. About one-hundred engineers and architects of Norwegian birth or descent. A large proportion from out of town, arrived at about 10:00 o'clock in the morning and were received by the chairman of the Chicago committee, Engineer Joachim G. Giaver who welcomed the guests to the convention. During the forenoon, the members of the convention were busy renewing old acquaintances and making new ones. Many of those present had been students together at Trondhjem, Christiana, Bergen, or had met at technical institutions elsewhere in Europe. Several of the men had not seen each other for many years, some had merely heard each other's name in connection with this or that important architectural or engineering work, and now were <pb facs="5423969_5_0224.jpg" n="2"/>meeting each other in person for the first time. Then again, many were among the less known in the profession; they would here get their first opportunity to know persons of importance within the group.</p>
   <p>After having greeted each other and inspected the club the members convened for lunch which was served in the form of "Smorgaas Bord". During the afternoon the participants were the guests of the city of Chicago being conducted on a tour of inspection through the subway for good transport.</p>
   <p>A formal welcome dinner and dance will be given tonight at 7:00 o'clock.</p>
   <p>The convention will continue tomorrow and Saturday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
