<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-10-22">Oct. 22, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Citizen's Papers for Norwegians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-10-22">Oct. 22, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZEN'S PAPERS FOR NORWEGIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It makes so much difference to Sven Andreasen whether he renounces allegiance to the "King of Norway and Sweden" or the "King of Sweden and Norway" that the may fail to become an American citizen in consequence. Andreasen appeared before clerk Salomonson (Dane) in the County Clerk's office yesterday and made application for his first papers toward becoming a citizen of the United States. Mr. Salomonson wrote his name down and then asked him where he was born.</p>
   <p>"Norway," was the reply.</p>
   <p>"Take off your hat and be sworn," said the clerk. "You do solemnly swear that you will waive allegiance to all foreign potentates, especially the King of Sweden and Norway."</p>
   <p>At that point the man stopped the clerk. He asked him to say "King of Norway and Sweden." The clerk told the man the proper title was "King of Sweden and Norway," and that he had no power to change it. The would-be citizen <pb facs="5423969_5_1186.jpg" n="2"/>said he was born in Norway, but if he acknowledged the authority of the "King of Sweden and Norway" instead of "Norway and Sweden," he might be taken for a Swede. This he did not want to do.</p>
   <p>It was arranged that the matter would be laid before Chief Clerk Knopf and if he permitted the use of the inverted title, the papers would be issued. If not, Andreasen would be compelled to go without papers.</p>
   <p>Mr. Andreasen was right in protesting against the royal title as read by clerk Salomonson. It is understood that Mr. Salomonson only insisted upon a practice which has been followed hitherto in the County Clerk's office, and that in all printed blanks intended for the use of Norwegians and Swedes applying for citizen's papers, the title of the king reads as Mr. Salomonson put it. But that does not prove that the clerk and his blanks are right. As a matter of plain law and fact, they are clearly wrong.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1187.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Norway and Sweden are two independent and sovereign kingdoms united under a common king. Each of the two countries has its own separate and independent government, the executive head of which is the king, who is at the same time also the executive head of the government of the other country. The dual functions of the king find expression in his title. In all Norwegian state papers and on all Norwegian coins his title reads "King of Norway and Sweden." In all Swedish state papers and on all Swedish coins his title reads "King of Sweden and Norway."</p>
   <p>In the present instance, a citizen of Norway and subject of the King of Norway applied for citizen's papers. By taking the oath as read to him, he would have sworn to an absurd proposition, and moreover perjured himself. The man was honest and knew what he was about, and hence naturally refused to swear falsely. The County Clerk ought to revise the practice of his office. Norwegian citizens ought to be permitted to take leave of their sovereign without <pb facs="5423969_5_1188.jpg" n="4"/>having him stand upon his head as they waive their allegiance to him. Nor will it be seriously asserted that compulsory perjury is the most auspicious gate to American citizenship.</p>
   <p>Readers of the Skandinaven would better preserve this article. It may be of service when another election comes around. Norwegians are entitled to receive their citizen's papers in due form; but Mr. Salomonson is probably not the only officer of the naturalization mill in this country who is unfamiliar with the constitutional law of Norway and hence needs some elementary instructions on the point.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
