<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-22">Mar. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Hundred Years of Peace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-22">Mar. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A HUNDRED YEARS OF PEACE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year 1914 will be a real anniversary year, not only for Norway, but for the rest of the Scandinavian countries and their immigrants throughout the world, as well. The year 1914 marks the 100th anniversary of the ending of the last war between any of the Nordic peoples, and there is a movement, well on the way, to erect an impressive peace monument on the borderline between Norway and Sweden. All classes in the Scandinavian countries are of one mind regarding this idea. The peace monument is to bear an inscription that has proven to be a prophecy fulfilled. The inscription quotes the words of Oskar I, a hundred years ago:</p>
   <p>"War between these brother nations in future years is impossible."</p>
   <p>The monument is a wonderful idea, and the inscription still more wonderful. The memorable words cut into Nordic granite will indelibly impress upon the hearts of the Nordic people the fallacy of war and enmity between countries so closely related that they are, in effect, one people-whose language, culture, <pb facs="5423969_5_0073.jpg" n="2"/>and traditions are so interwoven that other peoples seldom realize that these two countries are really one people in separate states. The monument will be a reminder of the idiocy of the racial feeling-bordering on hatred-that today is an undesirable and hindering inheritance of the Nordic peoples. In that way, the monument will help promote a feeling of unity of purpose and co-operation along all lines for mutual benefits.</p>
   <p>The stronger feeling of brotherliness between Norway and Sweden will spread to descendents of the two countries throughout the world. especially to those in the U.S.A. In our larger American cities the Scandinavians have not been able, due to lack of understanding and co-operation, to become an influence in the social or political life of the country. The erection of the peace monument by the mother country will, in time, eliminate the barriers here, and we will no longer be strictly Norwegians, Swedes, Danes, or Finns, but Americans of Scandinavian or Nordic descent. The influence of this combination will shortly become noticeable in the politics, business, arts, and social life of all communities and nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
