<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1918-06-17">June 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Lutheran Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Women's Mission Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-06-17">June 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN LUTHERAN CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Women's Mission Federation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Women's Mission Federation met yesterday and passed the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>1. The Women's Missionary Federation of the Norwegian Lutheran Church, in convention assembled, June 11, 1918, thanks God for having prospered work, and for the privileges and blessings which this work has brought us during the past year. The Lord is opening hearts to give still more freely to the noble and sacred cause of inner and foreign missions, and our prospects are bright as never before for a more active and wider sphere of usefulness. For this we humbly thank the Giver of all good things.</p>
   <p>2. The Federation feels strongly that the motherhood of our nation stands ever ready for loyal service to our government, and makes willing sacrifices toward the ultimate establishment of a just and righteous peace.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>3. The Federation expresses its hearty thanks and appreciation to the civic and commercial bodies, for the unstinted hospitality and courtesies extended, courtesies which have made our stay in this beautiful city a real pleasure to us. We also appreciate the courtesy of the press and the reporters who have given our affairs an interested and kindly mention.</p>
   <p>4. The Federation also thanks the congregations and the local committees for all their thoughtful help and interest in our meetings, and thanks most heartily all who have so ably contributed to our programs.</p>
   <p>5. The Federation prays that the dear Lord will continue to bless our work for the missions and ever help us do His will, through all our understanding, in ways acceptable to Him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
