<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-20">May 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Seventeenth of May Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-20">May 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">SEVENTEENTH OF MAY FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Turner Society celebrated the Seventeenth of May [Norwegian Independence Day] with a social at Normania Hall. The Hall was decorated with flags--Norwegian and American. More than fifteen hundred persons attended.</p>
   <p>The social opened with music, after which Attorney Lars Rand spoke in honor of the day. A speech was also delivered by Mayor Gray.</p>
   <p>The rest of the program consisted of turner exhibitions, at which three prizes were distributed; a wrestling match between Theodore Sjonneson and Olaf Larson, and several numbers by the Norwegian Singing Society of St. Paul, Minnesota. The social concluded with dancing.</p>
   <p>The Society Fram gave a Seventeenth of May social at Dania Hall. Nearly six hundred people were present. The Hall was decorated with birch branches and with Norwegian flags.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0157.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Johannes Groseth gave the speech of welcome. Mr. Anton Sannes, in Norwegian national costume, gave a reading: "Can you forget Old Norway?" for which he won thunderous applause. Mr. S. M. De Vold sang Norwegian folk songs. Professor Wraaman spoke in honor of Norway, and the audience sang, "Ja, vi elsker [dette Landet]" (Yes, we love this country). Mr. Wretteland spoke in honor of the day. The Fram Dramatic Society presented "Rational Dairying," by Hulda Garborg, a one-act play which caused much laughter. After the social, dancing continued till far into the night.</p>
   <p>The society Sons of Norway celebrated the Seventeenth of May at Turner Hall. The Hall was crowded to the doors. The social opened with music by the Sons of Norway's orchestra, after which the singing societies Viking and Varden sang several numbers under the direction of Mr. Erik Oulies. Mr. Ludvig Arctander delivered a speech in honor of Norway. A speech was also given by Mayor Gray. Dancing continued until the small hours of the morning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0158.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the Norwegian Lutheran Trinity Church, a Seventeenth of May festival was held at which an excellent musical program was presented by the church choir under the direction of Mr. F. Melius Christiansen. Mrs. B. Heiberg presented two vocal solos, and Attorney James A. Peterson delivered the speech in honor of the day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
