<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-27">May 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Independence Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-27">May 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN INDEPENDENCE DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May 17 was fittingly celebrated by the Norwegian Club at the Svithiod Singing Society's clubhouse. The hall was beautifully decorated and a real holiday spirit ruled throughout the evening.</p>
   <p>A hundred members and guests joined in singing the loved songs of the old country and in dancing the old folk dances and American dances as well. The scene was the more picturesque and enjoyable in that so many were dressed in the colorful national costumes from various parts of Norway. At midnight all gathered around the banquet board, spread with good old-fashioned food. The speaker of the evening was Joachim Giaver, who spoke eloquently of the wonderful friendship between Norway and the United States of America, and of the excellence of the citizenship of our Norwegian-Americans, who still retain such love and respect for the mother country and its tradition.</p>
   <p>A pleasant surpirse was given the club by Mrs. Signe Lund Robert when she presented the club with a new melody for the club song. The melody was her <pb facs="5423969_5_0085.jpg" n="2"/>own composition. Soon the whole gathering was singing the good old club song to the new and beautiful melody. Other speakers during the banquet were Professors Merriam and Flom, who had spoken during the day at Brand's Park, and Mr. Haugan, the Norwegian Consul.</p>
   <p>The sumptuous banquet was followed by more dancing to the entrancing music of Ludvig Haugan's orchestra. When the festivities ended, at daybreak, the celebrants were unanimous in stating that this was the best festival ever put on by any group of our Norwegian colony in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
