<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Pub. Co., Chicago, 1905, pp. 504-505.
<title level="a">[Biobraphy of Judge Oscar M. Toarison]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Pub. Co., Chicago, 1905, pp. 504-505.
<title level="a">[BIOBRAPHY OF JUDGE OSCAR M. TOARISON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Oscar M. Torrison was born in Manitowoc, Wis., August 29, 1861. He received the degree of Bachelor of Law at Luther College, Decorah, Iowa, 1881. In 1882 he received the degree of Bachelor of Law at the State University of Iowa City, and in 1884 he took the degree of Bachelor of Laws (cum laude) at Columbia College, New York City. He has been admitted to practice in the supreme courts of Illinois, Iowa, Minnesota, Wisconsin and the Supreme Court of the United States. In 1890 he came to Chicago where he soon acquired an extensive and varied practice and has taken an active part in matters of public interest. In 1896 he was appointed a member of the Board of Education of Chicago and served in that capacity on important committees of the board in 1896 and 1897. He is a member of the board of directors of the Chicago Bureau of Charities and for the past three years has been president of its Northwestern district. He is also one of the directors of the Association House on West North Avenue, which is extensively engaged in settlement work on the Northwest Side. He has always donated to numerous Norwegian charitable institutions both in and outside of Chicago. In November 1906 he was elected judge of the new municipal court of Chicago and received the solid support of the Norwegians of the city. He received the largest <pb facs="5423969_5_1450.jpg" n="2"/>vote of all the candidates. In 1889 he married Miss Ida Michelson, a daughter of Captain Michelson. They have four children and reside at 56 Alice Place, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
