<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-07-09">July 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Norsemen in Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0774</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0774.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-09">July 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NORSEMEN IN CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scandinavians have never had as strong a representation in Congress as at present. In the Senate there are three men of Scandinavian birth or ancestry.....In the House of Representatives there are eight Scandinavians. Minnesota has sent three, two Norwegians and one Swede; North Dakota one; Wisconsin two, one Norwegian and one Swede; Iowa one; Illinois one; Utah one.</p>
   <p>Of the eleven Scandinavians in Congress eight are Norwegians: Senators Nelson, Johnson, and Smoot; and Representatives Haugen, Gronna, Steenerson, Volstead, and John M. Nelson. Congressmen Frederick Lundin,Lenroot, and Lindbergh are Swedes. All of those mentioned were born in this country except Senator Nelson and Congressmen Lundin and Lindbergh. The first Scandinavian in Congress was Knute Nelson, elected for the first time in <pb facs="5423969_5_0775.jpg" n="2"/>1882 (to the House of Representatives) and later re-elected several times.</p>
   <p>Nils P. Haugen (Norwegian) served as congressman from Wisconsin for four terms, and M. N. Johnson (Norwegian), of North Dakota, was also a member of the House of Representatives for several terms. John Lind (Swedish) represented the second Minnesota district for two or three terms. Kittil Halvorsen and Haldor Boen (both Norwegians) served one term each. During the nineties, the fourth Illinois district was represented for one term by Justice Woodman (Danish).</p>
   <p>As far as we know, these are all the Scandinavians who have been members of the two houses of Congress. Of this total, eleven are Norwegian, four Swedish, and one Danish.</p>
   <p>In regard to ability and capacity for work, the present Scandinavian delegation in Congress is rather above than below the average. As we know, Senator Nelson is one of the most influential leaders in the Senate, and <pb facs="5423969_5_0776.jpg" n="3"/>Senator Smoot is also a man of more than usual ability.</p>
   <p>In the House of Representatives the older Scandinavian Representatives, Messrs. Haugen, Gronna, Steenersen, and Volstead, have won strong and respected standing, and the younger ones, Messrs. John M. Nelson, Lindbergh, Lundin, and Lenroot, have already shown that able work may be expected from them.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavians are reaping honor from the work of their representatives in the Senate and in the House of Representatives. All their representatives in Congress are vigorous and able spokesmen for progress and the rights of the American people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
