<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 426 ff.
<title level="a">[Biography of Martin Newgard]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 426 ff.
<title level="a">[Biography of Martin Newgard]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Martin Newgard, of Henry Newgard &amp; Company, was born in Ullensaker, Norway, July 4, 1864. He came to Chicago in 1882 and immediately entered the electrical business with his brother Henry, in Chicago, shortly having charge of all the electrical installations. The company was afterwards incorporated under the name of Henry Newgard &amp; Company, and our subject became a member of the firm now located at 225 Washington St. Mr. Martin Newgard is vice-president and general superintendent, and they are now one of the largest electrical contractors and manufacturers in the city. He is kept busy looking after the construction and manufacturing departments when large power and lighting switchboards and other special devices are being built for themselves and other electrical contractors over the country. Henry Newgard &amp; Company have built up a large supply business, they found it advisable to organize and incorporate a new company and accordingly the American Supply Co. was incorporated over a year ago. The companies are controlled by the <pb facs="5423969_5_1422.jpg" n="2"/>same stock holders, the later concern doing business at 87 5th Avenue, but larger and more spacious quarters at the corner of Lake and Franklin Sts. have been secured to which they soon will move. Mr. Newgard is well known among electricians and engineers in Chicago as one of the most practical men in the business. He was elected by the contractors' association to attend the revising committee meeting in changing the rules of the department of electricity to guard against fires. He is a 32 degree Mason. He is married and has three children. He lives at 138 Parnell Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
