<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-06">Oct. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Deacon Ole Anda Honored</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0671</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0671.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-06">Oct. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">DEACON OLE ANDA HONORED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Deacon Ole Anda, of the Zion Norwegian Lutheran Church, was seventy-five years old last Thursday. Although not one of the founders of the church, he has been a member since the congregation was organized. Only those who have been working in co-operation with him during these many years, in the church which he loves so well, can fully appreciate the influence he has had in shaping the life of the congregation. Through his instruction in Sunday school, through his words of instruction from the platform in the absence of the minister, through his execution of the regular duties of his office, he has been a blessing to old and young in the congregation.</p>
   <p>Although knowing that the seventy-fifth birthday of Mr. Anda would bring together all of his children and their families for the celebration, Reverend [J. H.] Meyer and his congregation decided to take Mr. Anda from his home and family for a while in order to give him proof of the attachment of the congregation to him. The day was the date of the regular mid-week service, so that <pb facs="5423969_5_0672.jpg" n="2"/>it was not difficult to make the old man go to church, as usual, before his sons had arrived from their places of business to congratulate their father. As Mr. Anda entered the church, the organist started playing, and the large audience began to sing. Reverend Meyer read from the scriptures and led in prayer. In the meantime Mrs. Anda had arrived, and then Reverend Meyer informed those present of the occasion for the gathering: that the old deacon was beloved by the congregation which had decided to surprise him on his birthday. He then removed a flag, unveiling large, beautiful pictures of Mr. and Mrs. Anda--pictures, the pastor said, to give the couple joy while they remained alive, and to provide consolation and evoke remembrances for the children when the couple had left for the other world. The minister then expressed his thanks to Mr. Anda for all that the latter had meant to the church, and wished him joy and blessings during the remainder of his life.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anda, deeply touched, expressed his appreciation. Afterward Reverend Oefstedal spoke...as did several members of the congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0673.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Refreshments were then served, and the old birthday celebrant moved along the aisles shaking hands and exchanging remarks and greetings with young and old.</p>
   <p>The social was a credit to minister and congregation and will never be forgotten by Mr. Anda and his family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
