<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-10">June 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Norway Must Wake Up]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-06-10">June 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[NORWAY MUST WAKE UP]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6..............It is high time that Norway wakes up and become aware of the absolute necessity of an intense publicity regarding her status among the nations of the world.</p>
   <p>America does not know Norway; knows nothing of its resources, laws, tourist interest, sports, utilities etc. Norway is entitled to the recognition that she fondly imagines is already accorded her, especially in the U.S.A. where she is so extensively represented.</p>
   <p>A striking example of how little is known of Norway was presented recently at a meeting of the Chicago Association of Commerce. A number of guests were invited, to the meeting, including foreign consuls and among these was Mr. Haugan, Norwegian Consul. A commission was being sent to Europe to study various large cities and their governments. Speakers galore extolled the virtues and accomplishments of Hamburg, Dusseldorf, Berne and other Swiss cities, cities in Poland, Hungaria, and Italy, urging the commission by all means not to miss visiting any of these places, but no mention was made of a city in any of the Scandinavian countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1028.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To thus ignore these little though wonderful countries was too much for Mr. Haugan and he requested permission to speak on behalf of Norway. So ably did Mr. Haugan portray the advances made by Norway that all who heard him were given a revelation of surprises that stunned and intrigued them. The result was that the little country of Norway ( and the other Scandinavian countries) will in no way be ignored by this or future seekers of knowledge as to how the other half of the world lives.</p>
   <p>It has hitherto been the almost invariable rule that in discussions of foreign countrie and their qualification, Norway has been ignored from start to finish.</p>
   <p>If Norway ever expects to be recognized for what she truly is and has her people will have to shake off their mantle of complacency and put on an advertising campaign, commensurate with what Norway has to offer the rest of the world and to those of us who know that means plenty in capitol letters. Norway cannot forever live on the publicity and popularity of Ibsen, Bjornson and Greig as "Big Business" cares nothing for art, literature etc., except to what extent they may be commercialized. To become properly known, Norway must use powerful, systematic and modern methods of publicity and use them freely.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
