<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand, <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 318-19
<title level="a">[Biography of Fredrik Herman Gade]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand, <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, pp. 318-19
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF FREDRIK HERMAN GADE]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fredrik Herman Gade, Consul for Norway at Chicago, also lawyer was born, Aug. 12, 1871, at his father's estate near Christiania. His father was for twenty-five years United States Consul at Christiana. In 1889 he entered Harvard University Law School and graduated with L.L.B. degree in 1895. He settled in Chicago and soon formed a law partnership with his Harvard classmate, Charles B. Pike, which continued until 1903, when Mr. Pike retired from the law business. Later Mr. Gade formed a law partnership with Theodore Stensland and John Waage, since dissolved. In 1905, Mr. Gade was Appointed consul for Norway at Chicago, including the states of Illinois, Indiana, and Michigan. In 1906 Mr. Gade attended the coronation of King Haakon, and handed to the King, as a greeting from Norwegians in America, a portfolio containing poems, musical compositions, and artistic designs. Mr. Gade received the coronations medal during the festivities. He is one of the trustees of the national Theater Association interested in elevating the stage by productions of high dramatic and literary value. He is a member of the University Club of Chicago <pb facs="5423969_5_1406.jpg" n="2"/>and New York; secretary of the Onwentia Club; Member of the Norwgian Quartette Club, and the Society of Mayflower Decendants. Mr. Gade resides in Lake Forest and was Mayer of that municipality for three terms, from 1903 to 1906.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
