<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 361-362.
<title level="a">[Biography of Reinert August Jernberg]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, pp. 361-362.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF REINERT AUGUST JERNBERG]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reinert August Jernberg, was born in Norway and was educated in the Latin School of Sarpsborg until about sixteen years of age when according to the usual custom in the coast towns of Norway he went to sea and spent five years of his life before the mast. For two years he was employed in the U.S. revenue service. Here he found time to begin his preparation for college and later entered the academy at East Greenwich, R.I., from which he graduated in 1879. The following year he entered Yale College where he graduated in 1884. He then entered the Theological Seminary in New-Haven to study for the ministry. About this time the Chicago Theological Seminary opened its foreign departments and Mr. Jernberg was invited to come to Chicago to give instructions in this department while he completed his own theological studies in the American course of the same institution. This offer he accepted and graduated from Chicago Theological Seminary in 1887.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1413.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For ten years he continued as an instructor in the Danish-Norwegian department until 1895, when he was inagurated professor of biblical and practical theology in the professorship then established by an endowment from Mrs. D. K. Pierson an instructor, Mr. Jernberg also served as their pastor two American churches for some time.</p>
   <p>In 1890 the religious weekly paper Evangelisten was started in connection with the missionary work among the Danes and Norwegians in America, and Prof. Jernberg was its editor and business manager for ten years. This responsibility he surrendered to a publishing society in 1899 and the paper has grown to strength and influence under the new management.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
