<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-17">May 17, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">May Seventeenth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-17">May 17, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MAY SEVENTEENTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As usual in the past few years, the Norwegian Independence Day will be celebrated in all localities where the Norwegians are numerous enough to hold some kind of social or festival. Even the lonely settler, on the prairie or in the forest, will remember the day and in his thoughts visit his former country, which the May sun has decorated for the Independence Day. In Chicago, the day used to be frequently celebrated in a manner which was far from dignified. Usually there was a large number of socials and some of these were not of a desirable type. Last year this unfortunate habit was discontinued. The recently organized Norwegian National Association invited the people to an Independence festival at the Auditorium, and all the Norwegians joined in the undertaking. The festival was brilliant, a great success--to a far greater degree than most of the Norwegians had dared to hope. It was a festival in which our people could take pride, and which raised our nationality in the eyes of our fellow citizens. The general <pb facs="5423969_5_0169.jpg" n="2"/>opinion after the festival last year was that the day ought to be celebrated in Chicago only in this same worthy manner.</p>
   <p>In conformity with its program and with the general opinion among the Norwegians in Chicago, the Norwegian National Association has arranged for a festival at the Auditorium also this year.</p>
   <p>The Committee has planned well and is offering a very satisfactory program. Strong efforts have been made to secure the support of all strata of the Norwegian group, to gather all the Norwegian people in Chicago to the support of this festival.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped that our people will rally strongly about the leaders in this movement. The Norwegians have shown that they can fill the Auditorium on their Independence Day, and they must show it again today.</p>
   <p>Our people are good citizens of the United States, and they place the flag of <pb facs="5423969_5_0170.jpg" n="3"/>this country above that of any other. Yet, the country of their fathers and of their childhood is close to their hearts, too.</p>
   <p>Let us celebrate the Norwegian Independence Day in a worthy manner today: let us gather about the Norwegian flag at the Auditorium.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
