<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-29">Nov. 29, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Thanksgiving Day Is Being Celebrated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-29">Nov. 29, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THANKSGIVING DAY IS BEING CELEBRATED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thanksgiving Day is being celebrated in most of the Norwegian churches in Chicago. In the Church of Our Savior, corner of Erie and May Streets, there will be religious services both morning and evening. At the services collections will be taken up for the poor, especially for the poor within the congregation.</p>
   <p>At St. Paul's Church, corner of West North and Irving Avenues, there will be evening services.</p>
   <p>At Bethlehem Church, corner of Center and Huron Streets, there will be morning services.</p>
   <p>At Trinity Church, Grand Avenue and Peoria Street, there will be a social with a turkey dinner in the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0148.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Zion Church, Artesian and Potomac Avenue, will give a musical entertainment in the evening. The program will consist of singing by chorus and soloists, piano music, etc.</p>
   <p>At the Norwegian Orphanage a reception will be held in the afternoon. Undertaker A. F. Lindberg, 261 Grand Avenue, has sent some turkeys to the Orphanage for the occasion.</p>
   <p>At the Maplewood Avenue Church, corner of Le Moyne Street, a program of music will be held in the evening. Reverend H. K. Madsen will be the chief speaker, and the Grieg Singing Society will sing.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian-Danish Methodist-Evangelical Church, North and Forty-first Avenues, will celebrate the day by laying the cornerstone for the new edifice of the congregation. The ceremony will take place in the afternoon after services have been held in the present building.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0149.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the First Methodist Church, Grand Avenue and Sangamon Street, Reverend H. K. Madsen will deliver the sermon at the morning service.</p>
   <p>At Nora Lodge No. 1, R. H. K., Thanksgiving Day will be celebrated with a social....in the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
