<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, p. 504.
<title level="a">[Biography of George Abraham Torrison]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, p. 504.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF GEORGE ABRAHAM TORRISON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>George Abraham Torrison, M. D., was born in Manitowoc, Wis., March 23, 1865, his parents came from Norway. He was educated at Luther College, Decorah, Iowa, from which he graduated in 1885 with the degree of A. B. He studied medicine at the medical department of Columbia College, New York, from which he received the M. D. degree in 1889. He pursued his medical studies at the University of Vienna in 1889-90 and in 1893-94. In 1891 he began the practice of medicine in Chicago, and since 1895 has devoted his attention to diseases of the throat, nose and ear.</p>
   <p>Dr. Torrison is instructor in diseases of the chest, throat, and nose at Rush Medical College, Chicago; is atttending physician to the Central Free Dispensary (Throat Department), laryngologist to the Norwegian-Lutheran Deaconess Home and Hospital, and lecturer on diseases of the nose and throat at the Presbyterian Hospital training school for nurses. He has been a director of the Norwegian Lutheran Tabitha Hospital and for one year was president of the board.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He holds membership of following societies: The American Medical Association, the Illinois State and the Chicago Medical Societies, the Chicago Otalogical and Laryngological Society, and the Scandinavian Medical Society of Chicago. Dr. Torrison was married to Miss Emma Irene Johnson of Chicago on January 5, 1898. They have two children. The doctor's office is at 103 State St. and the family resides at 46 Alice Place, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
