<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-08-27">Aug. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A New Lutharan Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cornerstone of Our Savior's Church Will be Laid Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-27">Aug. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW LUTHARAN CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cornerstone of Our Savior's Church Will be Laid Sunday</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Savior's Lutheran Church congregation of the Norwegian Lutheran United Church will lay the cornerstone of its new church building in Irving Park, on Sunday, August 29, at 3 P. M. A good program has been arranged for the occasion. A chorus of fifty voices will sing; an orchestra will play; Miss G. Heiman will render a vocal solo; several ministers of various denominations will speak.</p>
   <p>The services in the new church will be conducted in English. But why build a church in Irving Park for English services? Simply because it is needed. East fall Reverend J. T. Sigmond was requested to canvass Irving Park for the purpose of determining the possibilities for a Lutheran church in the district. He went from house to house, and frequently he found Lutheran people, Scandinavians or Germans. With but few exceptions these people seemed interested in getting <pb facs="5423969_5_0536.jpg" n="2"/>a Dutheran church for the district. Not only those who designated themselves as Lutherans, but others whose parents had belonged years ago to the Eutheran denomination were also interested in the matter. Soon Aeverend T. Sigmond became convinced that a Eutheran church was needed for the neighborhood.</p>
   <p>It did not seem advisable to organize a congregation exclusively Norwegian, because the majority of those who had been approached desired the use of English at the various services. Only a few desired to have the services conducted in the language of their former homeland, and this was true even of those who had been born abroad. These immigrants wanted the English language used for the sake of there children. As one mother said, "What is best for my children is good enough for me".</p>
   <p>When it was determined that a church was needed--that so many Lutheran people had moved into the district, had bought their own homes and moved their families into them--the next step was to find a suitable place for church services and <pb facs="5423969_5_0537.jpg" n="3"/>Sunday school. There was, however, no suitable building available at any price. The only way out would be to build.....An appeal was made to the general public, stating that their financial, moral, and spiritual help was needed.....The response was satisfactory. Mr. Arthur W. Dickenson gave two lots for the building.....Temporary Sunday school accommodations were had from Mrs. J. A. Gardner.</p>
   <p>....The Sunday school started on January 17, 1909. At the first meeting there were twenty-one children and thirty adults present. The school has kept on growing, so that now there are seventy members enrolled.... Now the task was to determine how many wanted to join a Lutheran congregation in which services were conducted in English. In a short while more than seventy had joined.</p>
   <p>On July 1, 1909, the congregation was organized. The board of trustees consists of Messrs. A. Svensen, president; W. O'Marraw, secretary; Thorvald Nelson, treasurer. A ladies' aid society has been organized; the ladies are working splendidly for the Church.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0538.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The architect, Mr. C. S. Michaelson, has completed the plans for the Church. Messrs. Thorvald Nelson and A. W. Dickenson of the building committee have given their services free, thereby saving much money for the Church. Mr. A. K. Sorenson has promised to put in the foundation walls free of charge. Many others have contributed, some giving money, others giving materials.</p>
   <p>The congregation has arrived at the point where the cornerstone is ready to be laid. As mentioned before, it will be laid on the coming Sunday afternoon. Of course, additional gifts are still needed for the completion of the work. Gifts may be sent to the pastor of the congregation, Reverend J. T. Sigmond, 1908 West Berteau Avenue, Chicago. Reverend Sigmond will acknowledge all gifts in Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>Reverend T. Sigmond was born in Stavanger, Norway. He came to America when about eighteen years of age... He graduated from Chicago English Lutheran Seminary in 1903, and was ordained in the same year... He has been a member of the St. John <pb facs="5423969_5_0539.jpg" n="5"/>English Butheran Church, and a student of the University of Chicago. In 1908 he married Miss Bertha Michaelson... He is now going to devote all his energy to the work of building up the congregation in West Irving Park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
