<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-14">Sep. 14, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Honoring Professor Colberg</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-14">Sep. 14, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">HONORING PROFESSOR COLBERG</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Singing Association will give a concert and social in Bjorgvin Hall, Sunday evening, September 29th, in honor of John W. Colberg to whom much credit is due for the high standard of Norwegian singing, and, in consequence, national sentiment and unity among the Norwegians in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A considerable part of the program will be given by Professor Colberg with his present and former music students. The Singing Association and the various singing societies will sing; Dr. Doe and Dr. Warlow will speak, and Mrs. Smulski and Miss Ethel Olsen will assist, so that those attending the concert-social will be assured of a rich and enjoyable evening.</p>
   <p>Everybody knows Mr. Colberg. He has resided in Chicago since 1870 with the exception of two years when he was teaching music and singing at Illinois State University. It is a fine undertaking on the part of the Singing Association to give this splendid old man a benefit concert, but then, the association owes him a great deal.</p>
   <p>Tickets cost 50 cents. They may be obtained from the representatives of the <pb facs="5423969_5_1370.jpg" n="2"/>Singing Association who are members of the committee on arrangements; for Bjorgvin, Julius Jaeger; for the Glee Club, P. Iverson; for the Quartet Club, Emil Bjorn; for the Norwegians' Singing Society, G. A. Ellingson. Tickets may also be had from the treasurer of the committee, John Jersin, 925 West North Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
