<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-06-22">June 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-06-22">June 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are still hearing repercussions of the Lutheran Almanac controversy. It was discovered that on the "Tree of Satan" pictured in the famous (or infamous) almanac, hangs a piece of fruit labeled "Boy Scouts," thereby, pictorially condemning them to inferno along with the Sons of Norway, Masons, educational institutions, and all other groups not resting safely in the bosom of the Lutheran Mother Church. Even the poor old veterans of the G.A.R. are classed with these unmentionables.</p>
   <p>We have recently been informed that the illustration of the two tress (good and evil), is attributed to one man of a committee of five, none of which knew what the others had contributed until the book was off the press. Since the almanac came out, the store of protect has brought statements from a majority of our Lutheran Pastors decrying the publication of the picture, and so far as the Scouts are concerned, it is a known fact that hundreds of our churches are sponsoring Scout troops.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0431.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the Chicago Lutheraneran (Lutheran), official organ of the Christ-Church in Logan Square, whose pastor is Rev. John Meyer, we find a very complimentary article on the Boy Scout movement under the heading, "The Boy Scout Movement, What it is." Relative to the religious aspect of the Scouts, the article states:</p>
   <p>"It is not a sectarian movement; Section 12 of the Scout Law reads: "He (the Scout), is reverent toward God. He is faithful in his religious duties, and respects the convictions of others in matters of custom and religion.' It is not Scandia's aim to defend or recommend the boy scout movement; we are rather in the other side of the argument. In spite of all the good things taught a scout, we feel that the good is offset by the bad-the military spirit that is apparent throughout the organization. Militarism and snobbery have had their day; to revive these through the boy scout movement is but to waste time and money trying to liven up a corpse. There are other methods, and better, by which our boys can be taught principles of righteousness, and whereby they may become manly, strong, healthy, and practical as they grow up.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, we feel that the Scouts owe a vote of thanks to Pastor Meyer for <pb facs="5423969_5_0432.jpg" n="3"/>so bravely and effectively picking them off the devil's tree of condemnation, and for defending them in the very organization that painted the "trees."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
