<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-10">Aug. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Old Settlers Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Preliminary Meeting Held</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-10">Aug. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN OLD SETTLERS ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Preliminary Meeting Held</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the invitation of the president of the Norwegian Old Settlers' Association some of the members of the Society, together with a number of Civil War veterans, held a meeting at Scandia Hall last Thursday evening. Mr. Peter M. Balken, the president, opened the meeting and Mr. J. B. Nordham was elected secretary.</p>
   <p>The president informed those present of the reason for calling the meeting. The Scandinavian veterans of the Civil War are to hold their convention in Chicago during the period from August 27, to September 3. The Norwegian Old Settlers' Association intends to receive the veterans in a suitable and dignified manner. The present meeting was called to prepare for such a suitable reception.</p>
   <p>Mr. C. R. Matson informed the meeting that Mr. C. A. Strand had offered the <pb facs="5423969_5_0796.jpg" n="2"/>use of Scandia Hall as headquarters for the veterans and suggested that today's meeting select a reception committee. Mr. Ole Hegg agreed that the Scandinavian veterans ought to be kept together as much as possible during their stay in Chicago. Mr. Nels Arnesen read a communication from Lieutenant Ellend Erickson, secretary of the Fifteenth Wisconsin Veterans, inquiring whether there be easy access to some hotel or lodging house for the old soldiers in the proximity of Scandia Hall. Mr. Arnesen had replied to the letter, but thought it wise to read the letter to the meeting. Mr. John Anderson thought that as much as possible should be done to entertain the old veterans who were visiting Chicago. He suggested tours through the parks, or trips by steamer out to the crib. Mr. Sporland recommended that another meeting be held at an early date to give more people a chance to be present. Captain Williams of the Fifteenth Wisconsin agreed that a committee ought to be chosen at once, and Colonel C. R. Matson moved that the president appoint a committee on arrangements to consist of eleven men, with authority to collect funds as needed, and otherwise take charge of all matters pertaining to reception, entertainment, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0797.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The motion was adopted unanimously, and the following committee was appointed: Messrs. C. R. Matson, Nels Arnesen, Ole Hegg, S. T. Gunderson, Captain William Johnson, Dr. N. T. Quales, A. P. Johnson, Isaac Rasmussen, John Anderson, Peter M. Balken, and J. B. Nordham. The Committee will hold its first meeting on Saturday evening at Scandia Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
