<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-08-01">Aug. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">A Pioneer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-08-01">Aug. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">A PIONEER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The passing away of George Helm brings to light his interesting past here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago in 1834, and then began an interesting career that in many ways reads as fiction.</p>
   <p>He has lived in Chicago for about sixty-four years. He was a member of the "wolf hunt" in 1834, when the people of the little village of Chicago went out to kill the wolves that had menaced the lives of stock and of people for a long time. The hunters surrounded a large pack of wolves just about where the Board of Trade now stands and killed about forty of them. Helm saw the first large ship enter the Chicago River, where until then, only canoes had paddled. He was offered all the land on the west side of the river, as far west as what is now Crawford Avenue, for a dollar per acre, but he refused to consider the offer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0877.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He filed a claim on the Desplaines River, near Wheeling, about eighteen miles northwest of Chicago. This land was nothing more than a wilderness, but he lived there for a short while, just such a life as Daniel Boone lived in the South. He was considered the best wolf hunter of the time, and many are the stories told about him, as he roved the wilderness where Chicago now stands.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago early in 1834, traveling by water, as far as Detroit, and from there continued west in a "prairie schooner".</p>
   <p>Chicago at that time was very small; there were probably not more than a dozen houses, and less than 800 people living here. The land west of the river was low and swampy, but many of the pioneers attempted to cultivate it, with little success. The Illinois and Michigan Canal was started, and here Helm earned his first dollar. He, we can say, was the first Scandinavian to work on the canal. He also built the first wooden bridge across the Chicago River.</p>
   <p>Three years after his arrival, Chicago was incorporated and held its first election. In the same year Helm bought another large parcel of land from the government for $1.25 per acre.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0878.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By 1867, Helm was worth $60,000, a fortune which grew rapidly, so that at his death, he was extremely wealthy.</p>
   <p>Early in the year of 1867, he built a house at 659 Warren Avenue, where he lived until his death.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
