<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1911-02-24">Feb. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. (N. T.) Quales Answers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-02-24">Feb. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DR. (N. T.) QUALES ANSWERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I have read the dispatch in Skandinaven of February 10, to which you called my attention--an Associated Press report of a lecture on infantile paralysis delivered before the American Academy of Medicine by Dr. Jocelyn Manning.</p>
   <p>Dr. Manning says: "All of our infantile paralysis appears to come from Scandinavia. There, in those little homes where, throughout the long, dark winters, people live in dark quarters, in close proximity to their animals, we find much infantile paralysis. There is a sailor in nearly every family there, and naturally these sailors carry the germs to other ports, whence they are brought inland."</p>
   <p>When our esteemed colleague says that "there is a sailor in nearly every family there", it strikes me that he has in mind the west coast of Norway, as most of the Norwegian sailors live there. When we consider that the greatest part of the Scandinavian population are tillers of the soil, and only a small <pb facs="5423969_5_1040.jpg" n="2"/>percentage follow seafaring as a livelihood, we take it that the Doctor is not as well posted as he should be. But suppose we take the west coast of Norway where there are a good many sailors. The picture he draws by no means fits. The people along the coast do not shut themselves up in dark cellars together with animals in the fall of the year to hibernate during the dark winter months. The Norwegians are outdoor people. Theirs is a strenuous life and they are both intelligent and tidy.</p>
   <p>I was born and brought up on the west coast of Norway; yet I never saw and never heard of a case of infantile spinal paralysis--better known as anterior pallid myelitis. In 1908 I visited Norway and spent considerable time on the west coast. I came in contact with a number of medical men whom I questioned on the prevailing diseases in that part of the Country. Among other diseases I made inquiry about poliomyelitis. Some told me they have met with sporadic cases, while most of them said they had never seen a case. Judging from this, I should think that the disease was not endemic or even prevalent in that part of the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1041.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Neither is the doctor's assertion borne out by the history of the disease. Dr. Michael Underwood, in 1784, and John Badham, in 1856--both English physicians--described the disease; both took it to be an affection of the brain. Dr. Jacob von Heine, in volumes published by him in 1840 and 1860, was the first to diagnose it as a spinal disease. He gave a complete and true clinical picture of it.</p>
   <p>In 1851, Dr. Rellist and Dr. Boathax, of Geneva, established the fact that it was a disease peculiar to childhood. In 1885, Dr. Duchenne, of Bologne, made a special study of the disease and called attention to the absence of reaction to the Fasodic (sic) current in the paralyzed muscles. In 1863, Dr. van Reinecker and Dr. van Recklinghausen published the findings of an autopsy. By microscopic and minute examinations of the spinal cord, it was found that the ganglion cells of the anterior gray horns of the nerve fibers of the anterior lateral columns had undergone atrophy and degeneration. These facts and findings have been amply verified by later investigators.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1042.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From this brief historical review it will appear that infantile spinal paralysis was general all over Europe, and it has never been claimed that it was peculiarly a Scandinavian disease. Nearly all epidemics have been inland and not in seaports. It has never been claimed and substantiated that the disease was brought to America by Scandinavian immigrants.</p>
   <p>The few cases of poliomyelitis that have come under my observation have not been among Scandinavians. The cause of poliomyelitis anterior is unknown. It is supposed to be a germ disease, but thus far it has not been demonstrated, and we don't know how it enters the system.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
