<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>. Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, p. 274.
<title level="a">[Biography of Victor Fleming Bendixen]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>. Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., <date when="1905">1905</date>, p. 274.
<title level="a">[Biography of Victor Fleming Bendixen]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Victor Flemming Bendixen, of the Standard Architectural Iron Works at 627-43 Bloomingdale Avenue, was born in Christiania, Norway, Dec. 1, 1865. He had a college education in Norway, graduated from the Christiania Art School and worked as an apprentice for Henrik Nissen, architect, in Christiania. He came to Chicago in 1888. After his arrival in Chicago he took a course at a business law school, from which he graduated. He began work here as a draftsman at the stock yards. After six months there he was employed by Winslow Bros. &amp; Co., as designer and draftsman, where he remained for three years, the last year as general superintendent. He took a trip to Norway in 1902, and upon his return accepted the position of chief engineer for Beers, Clay and Dutton, architects, in Chicago. In 1903 he started the present firm, the Standard Architectural Works, first located at 30 N. Clinton St. and later at 181 Newberry Avenue, and from there to his present location on Bloomingdale. Here he erected a substantial two-story brick building especially adapted for the business. The company <pb facs="5423969_5_1431.jpg" n="2"/>of which our subject is president and treasurer manufacture iron work for building and also do general foundry work. Mr. Bendixen was married to Lillian Olesen of Chicago on July 9, 1902. They have one child, Kathryn Josephine, born April 11, 1903. Mr. Bendixen is a Mason. The family resides at 20 Evergreen Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
