<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-07">May 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">British Impudence</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-07">May 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">BRITISH IMPUDENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Associated Press cables from London what purports to be the views of King Oscar II on the war in South Africa. The King, who is on a visit to England, traveling incognito, is reported as saying, among other things:</p>
   <p>"I am entirely on the British side in this war in South Africa. You may make it quite clear that I have no sympathy whatever with the Boers, and I shall tell you why. I find it difficult to understand either the principles of a religion which is apparently a monopoly of the burghers of the two states, or the present manifestations of a government which seems to have refused most of the reforms suggested by the British and which closed the negotiations by invading British territory. In my opinion, the English-speaking races are the exact opposite of the Boers, because they are among the best colonizers in the world when savage and uncivilized territories have to be reclaimed. You <pb facs="5423969_5_1157.jpg" n="2"/>may make it quite clear that I have no sympathy whatever with the Boers, and that I will give no support to the attempts they are making to secure the countenance or co-operation of our countries".</p>
   <p>King Oscar is probably "on the British side," but it is not probable that he has spoken as represented. If the interview is not a fabrication, the King has undoubtedly been misquoted. The King is an intelligent and well-informed gentleman. It is impossible to believe that he could be guilty of the nonsense about the monopoly of the burghers' religion, or would make himself ridiculous by refusing in advance a support of the Boer cause that he knew he would not be requested to give. Neither can he have censured the Boer for "refusing most of the reforms suggested by the British;" for he well knew that the British government had no more right to force "reforms" upon the South African republic than upon Norway or Sweden.</p>
   <p>Being a guest of Great Britain for the time being, the King may have said something intended to please his host. But if he consented to the publication of <pb facs="5423969_5_1158.jpg" n="3"/>what he may have said, he certainly was unaware of the ulterior purpose of the interview, which is disclosed in the following postscript:</p>
   <p>"Theodore Andrea Cook, who has just resigned the editorship of the St. James Gazette, and who secured specially for the Associated Press the above very striking declaration of King Oscar's sentiments in regard to the war, writes: 'It is clear that the King does not wish the Scandinavians in the United States to be in any doubt about the feelings of the Monarch to whom they or their parents once owed allegiance, and whose opinions they will still accept with deference and respect in a question now agitating the civilized world. Taken in conjunction with the recent improvement of feeling between Great Britain and Germany, this expression by the King of Norway and Sweden is a contribution to international politics which solidifies the Baltic area to a remarkable degree.'"</p>
   <p>This is a fair illustration of British stupidity and impudence. It shows that the interview was obtained and garbled, if not manufactured out of whole <pb facs="5423969_5_1159.jpg" n="4"/>cloth, for consumption in the United States.</p>
   <p>Befogged as he is by British arrogance and prejudice, it is very likely that Mr. Theodore Andrea Cook is unable to understand that, while the Norwegians and Swedes in the United States credit King Oscar with good intentions and have more or less respect for his political wisdom, they are otherwise entirely indifferent to his opinions on the Boer war or any other question. They are Americans and in the habit of doing their own thinking. Nor does King Oscar labor under any misapprehensions in this respect; he knows that they are good American citizens and esteems them the higher for it.</p>
   <p>The impudence of the British jingo is not surprising; we are so used to British assumptions that we bestow but scant attention upon fresh outbreaks. But it is to be regretted that the Associated Press should be used as a vehicle for such unseemly attempts at influencing public opinion in the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1160.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Their stupidity and harmlessness do not by any means excuse their offensive and insulting impudence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
