<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-09-08">Sept. 8, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Luther Statue</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter M. Balken Approves of the Idea and Starts the Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-09-08">Sept. 8, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE LUTHER STATUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter M. Balken Approves of the Idea and Starts the Fund</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Editor of Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>"I became very much interested when I read the articles written by Reverend Alfred Johnson, wherein he suggests to the Scandinavian people the splendid idea of erecting a statue to the memory of the world's greatest reformer, Martin Luther. I think with him that Mount Olive is the ideal place for a colossal statue upon a grand pedestal facing the contemplated grand entrance soon to be erected, with the inscription of his own famous declaration: 'Here I take my stand. I cannot do otherwise, so help me God. Amen.'</p>
   <p>"It seems to me that every man, woman, and child who loves the great name of Luther will be glad to contribute their bit. Therefore, allow me to <pb facs="5423969_5_0712.jpg" n="2"/>suggest that Reverend Johnson go right to work and appoint a secretary and a treasurer, he himself acting as chairman until such a time as it will become necessary for him to make up an active working committee of men thoroughly known to the Scandinavian public for their honesty and integrity.</p>
   <p>"I,like many of the Scandinavian old settlers of Chicago, own a lot in Graceland, and I am afraid it will not be many years before the fashionable residences on grand Sheridan Drive will compel its removal, the same as we were driven out of Lincoln Park. Naturally, Mount Olive will be our choice, at least mine. It is so far removed that it will never be disturbed by any of those disturbing influences, and at the same time within easy reach for all.</p>
   <p>"Please permit me to become the first to lay my little offering as a nucleus. I hope that I am the first to donate the twenty-five cents as suggested by the pastor, and that one hundred thousand will in like manner follow suit. And I earnestly pray that God in his bountiful <pb facs="5423969_5_0713.jpg" n="3"/>mercy will add his blessing, as I remain</p>
   <p>"Yours truly,</p>
   <p>"Peter N. Balken."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
