<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-04-14">Apr. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Norway's Charter to Freedom</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1047</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1047.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-04-14">Apr. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NORWAY'S CHARTER TO FREEDOM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The constitution of Norway was born amid storm and stress. While Napoleon, in the early part of 1814, with the spectacular brilliancy of his marvelous genius was struggling with the allied armies on French soil, the representatives of the Norwegian people, assembled at Eidsvold, were framing a charter of liberty for their country.</p>
   <p>The united kingdom of Denmark and Norway had cast its lot with Napoleon. When his defeat at Leipzig foreshadowed his early downfall, the powers of Europe decreed that Norway should be separated from Denmark and ceded to Sweden. The Danish-Norwegian king was compelled to bow to the verdict. But the people of Norway would not be sold. They knew that under the law of nations their country was now left without any entangling alliances, without any royal house to claim the crown--absolutely free and of right the mistress of her own <pb facs="5423969_5_1048.jpg" n="2"/>destiny. She was not prepared for a great struggle. The population was small, less than a million souls, and the people were weak. The financial system was disorganized and the currency bad, and famine stalked abroad in the land as a result of bad crops and the English blockade of all the seaports of Norway. The armies of Napoleon were scattered and in the councils of Europe absolutism was supreme and might was right.</p>
   <p>In the face of such overwhelming difficulties and dangers, the people unanimously resolved to shape their own destiny and elected representatives to a constituent assembly. With the thunder from the mighty struggles in continental Europe reverberating among the mountains, these men, worthy of the best traditions of their race, took up their task with a stern determination to do or die. They saw the importance of rapid work, but their deliberations were thorough and calm, and on the seventeenth of May, 1814, the freest organic law that Europe had known was promulgated. History has few parallels to the sublime courage of the Norwegian people and their chosen men during the momentous crisis of 1814.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1049.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The organic law of Norway was a gift of a free people to themselves. No people among whom liberty is dead can make laws of liberty. Norway is the only country in Europe that was not conquered by the Roman law or the Vatican power, and where feudalism never obtained a foothold; through all the vicissitudes of fateful centuries the freeholder of Norway remained a free man, a king of his manor, and when it sounded, the historic call of 1814 found him strong and ready and equal to the task.</p>
   <p>The lawmakers at Eidsvold were familiar with the famous work of Montesquieu (L'esprit des lois), the free constitutions that had been adopted in recent years in America, France, and Spain, and with the constitutional practices of England as well. The Eidsvold law, like the Constitution of the United States, incorporates the Montesquieu trinity of co-ordinate powers--the legislative, the judicial, and the executive. The prerogatives of the lawmaking power were guarded with especial care.</p>
   <p>The constitution is still in force and is now the oldest written organic law <pb facs="5423969_5_1050.jpg" n="4"/>of a sovereign nation in existence, barring the Constitution of the United States. It remains today essentially as it was framed. Norway's subsequent union with Sweden and its recent dissolution necessitated only slight changes in the constitution. The adoption of the principle of ministerial responsibility to the parliament is probably the most important change that has been made. The right of suffrage has been gradually extended, and the franchise is now universal for men and women.</p>
   <p>The past century has seen constitutions born only to die, in many lands. But Norway's organic law remains. During the first years of its life it was the object of many insidious attacks at the bidding of the powers of the unholy Holy Alliance. They had crushed every other organic law that sprang from the great revolutionary awakening of those times, and proposed to cripple that of Norway as well. But the people were ever watchful, ever on guard, ever ready to thwart intrigues or threats, and their constitution stands today a glorious monument to the courage, wisdom, and sleepless vigilance of a free people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1051.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Norwegians who have become citizens of the United States and their descendants take pride in the liberty and laws of Norway. As loyal American citizens they can celebrate Norway's day of freedom because the Seventeenth of May and the Fourth of July symbolize the same principles and teach the same lessons of government and citizenship. Every Norwegian who lands on our shores comes schooled in the rights and duties of popular government. To him the change of country does not involve a change of social or government system. The red, white, and blue flag of America and the red, white, and blue flag of Norway both alike represent popular liberty and justice. Hence, if he is a good Norwegian he will become a good American; and his heart may well beat stronger and quicker on the national holiday of his native land because, in the history of modern constitutions, next to the great organic law of the United States ranks that of Norway.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
