<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-12-01">Dec. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Nordealles Social</title><title level="a" type="sub">Supreme Lodge Holds Well-Attended Thanksgiving Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-01">Dec. 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NORDEALLES SOCIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Supreme Lodge Holds Well-Attended Thanksgiving Festival</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Nordfalles (Northern United) Supreme Lodge held a Thanksgiving social Wednesday evening in Scandia Hall where the attendance was very large. The Northern Light Band furnished the musical program. Attorney Olaf E. Ray spoke in honor of the day. He said, among other things:</p>
   <p>"We are prone to find fault, and we forget to express gratitude for the many things in life which are good. If we are to attain inner peace and harmony it is necessary for us to acknowledge the good things about us and let the spirit of thankfulness fill our hearts; if we do not do this we will develop within ourselves an inability to evaluate life's good offerings, and we will become a people bereft of hope and courage. He who is able to show successful use of life in temporal as well as spiritual affairs, leaves trails covered with gratitude for all the advantages won from time to time. Lack of gratitude means lack <pb facs="5423969_5_0146.jpg" n="2"/>of the power to give returns for the good things received.</p>
   <p>"Even during the heathen era our ancestors gave thanks for life's good things every fall, and paid respect to the fruit of the soil. We have reason to be grateful for health and strength; for the fact that our country has extended its boundaries for popular government and liberal laws; for the fact that we are approaching spring with the assurance that the miserable conditions in our city are abating; that we may expect a cessation of labor strikes with the consequent enforced idleness and criminal acts....that under our free flag we are all brothers and sisters together."</p>
   <p>The speech was received with great applause. Mr. Harry Dahl sang.... a comic song composed by himself....Mr. Sverre Skagen gave interestings readings, and late in the evening, "Uncle Sam" gave six large turkeys and eight other premiums to the fortunate winners at a free lottery drawing.</p>
   <p>The social was a great success in every way; it surpassed every one of the socials which Nordfalles has given during the past ten years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
