<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1910-05-17">May 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Churches in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-05-17">May 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN CHURCHES IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian Evangelical Lutheran Church, corner of Superior and La Salle Streets, is the only church that had the honor of hearing Jenny Lind sing in its choir. The congregation was organized in 1843 with Paul Anderson as its first pastor. The first church building was erected in 1855 on the corner of Franklin and Erie Streets.</p>
   <p>Paul Anderson served the congregation until the latter part of 1860, and was followed by Reverend Abraham Jacobsen who led the congregation for a few months. Reverend C. J. Petersen then became pastor and served for some twelve years. The congregation became a part of the Norwegian Synod in 1866. In 1871 the church building was destroyed in the great Chicago Fire.</p>
   <p>In 1874, Reverend A. Mikkelson brought new life to the Church, which was rebuilt in December. Reverend S. Kvaase served as pastor from 1889 to 1891;</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0515.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Reverend O. E. Brandt served from 1892 to 1896. The present pastor is P. A. Kittilsby.</p>
   <p>Our Savior's Norwegian Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>Our Savior's Church was organized in 1858 with Gustav A. Dietrichson as the first pastor. The church was located on North Market Hall. In 1863 Reverend J. Krohn was called from St. Louis. The cornerstone of the first church building was laid in the early part of 1871, and the partly completed church was destroyed in the Chicago Fire. The church was rebuilt at a cost of $42,000. The second pastor was Reverend O. Juul. The Church became a part of the Norwegian Synod in 1889, and for a short time thereafter Reverend C. R. Preus served as pastor.</p>
   <p>Johannes Norwegian Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>The Johannes Church has been served by the following pastors: L. Hagerup <pb facs="5423969_5_0516.jpg" n="3"/>Nissen, 1890-91; Thomas Nelson, 1892-97; <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> K. Bleken, 1897-1906; the present pastor is H. P. Hanson. The Church joined the Norwegian Synod in 1891. The first church building was erected on Washtenaw Avenue in 1892, at a cost of $3,731.71. In 1894 a new church, costing $4,200, was built on the corner of Humboldt Boulevard and Cortez Street. The present church and rectory, built in 1901, cost $12,000.</p>
   <p>Bethlehem Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>The Bethlehem Church congregation was organized March 2, 1870, in a hall at 80 West Erie Street. The first pastor was Reverend S. M. Krogness who served from 1870 to 1874. A church was built on the corner of Sangamon Street and Phillips Avenue in 1871. In 1874 Reverend C. B. Jacobsen was called to lead the church. He served until 1876. The congregation has been served by: C. B. Jacobsen, 1874-76; O. Bostep, 1876-77; N. C. Brunn, 1877-1889; H. B. Kildahl, 1889-99; George T. Rygh is the present pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0517.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Zion Norwegian Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>The Zion congregation was organized as a mission in 1891, at Crystal Street and Washtenaw Avenue. Reverend Ellestad was the first pastor. In June, 1891, the mission bought two lots and a cottage on the corner of Artesian and Potomac Avenues. On February 15, 1892, the congregation was officially organized. The following pastors have served the congregation: O. Guldseth, 1893-97; H. Meyer, 1897-1904; C. K. Solberg, 1904 to date. In 1901, a church costing $19,000 was built; the value of the entire property at this time was $26,000.</p>
   <p>Bethel Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>The Bethel Church was organized on December 29, 1889, by Reverend N. C. Brun. In the spring of 1891, the congregation bought a church on Humboldt Boulevard, near Armitage Avenue. The following pastors have served the Church: N. C. Brun, 1889-93; A. S. Anderson, 1894-96; H. Oftedal, 1897-1900; C. C. Tiller, <pb facs="5423969_5_0518.jpg" n="5"/>1900 to date.</p>
   <p>Timotheus Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>The Timotheus congregation held its first meeting in a store at 1639 Armitage Avenue, October 2, 1899. Reverend C. C. Tiller was the first pastor. The Church was officially organized on January 14, 1904 by Reverend C. C. Tiller, at 1062 North Tripp Avenue. Reverend Tiller was succeeded by Reverend O. R. Nelson. The present pastor is Reverend Richard O. Sigmund.</p>
   <p>Hauge's Norwegian Lutheran Church</p>
   <p>Hauge's congregation was organized in 1900. The church building was erected on the corner of Wabansia and Central Park Avenues, and cost $9,000. The congregation has had three pastors: T. Lund, S. J. Skarpness, and the present pastor, C. L. Jothen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0519.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Other important Norwegian churches are: Covenant Church, corner of Fullerton Avenue and Ballou Street; Elim Lutheran Church, 2210 North Whipple Street; Irving Park Church, Clifton Avenue and Irving Park Boulevard; Maplewood Avenue Norwegian-Danish Methodist Church, Le Moyne Street and Maplewood Avenue; Kedzie Avenue Methodist Church, Kedzie Avenue and Cortland Street; Bethel Methodist Church, in Grand Crossing; Moreland Methodist Church, in Moreland Park; Bethel Evangelical Church, Wisner and Milwaukee Avenues; Salem Evangelical Church, California and Mc Lean Avenues; and Logan Square Baptist Church, in Logan Square.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
