<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, p. 270.
<title level="a">[Biography of Nils Arneson]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
A. E. Strand. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, Chicago: John Anderson Pub. Co., 1905, p. 270.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF NILS ARNESON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nils Arneson was born on a farm (Steensmyhren) near Drammen in Norway, in 1840. He went to school until he was confirmed. He learned his trade as a wagon maker in Christiania and came to America on a sail boat in 1861. He worked in Chicago until the fall of the same year and enlisted in Company A, 15th Regiment Wisconsin Volunteers, serving three years and two months in the civil war, coming back to Chicago in 1865. Worked at his trade until 1868 when he began the manufacture of furniture on Canal St., but was burned out in the great Chicago fire. From that time the firm was Arneson &amp; Company. In 1880 it was changed to Johnson &amp; Arneson. In 1884 he with others started the Central Manufacturing Company, a corporations chartered under the laws of Illinois, to Manufacture office desks. He is president and treasurer. He is also director of the Union Bank of Chicago. In 1870 he was married to Hilda Taftner from Christiania. They have one son and one daughter; only the daughter is living, she is married to Alf Normann, secretary of the Central Manufacturing Company. Mr. Arneson is a director of the Chicago Manufacturers Association and a member of Lyons Post No. 9, G. A. R., office 37-41 Armour St. Residence 672 N. Hoyne Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
