<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-05-17">May 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[The Memorial Gift to Norway]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-05-17">May 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[THE MEMORIAL GIFT TO NORWAY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Will someone kindly awaken the men of our Norwegian colony? About a year ago, we of the Norwegian Women's Federation of Chicago were asked to organize a committee to work in the interest of the Memorial Gift to Norway in 1914. We understand we were to be an auxiliary to the main committee and have been patiently waiting for this committee to be organized. To date this has not been done, though our women's branch has been working at it since our group was brought together. In other words, we have worked one year while the men have slept.</p>
   <p>We have addressed many meetings on the subject, and in every instance, we have found our people ready to give and enthusiastically in favor of the proposed gift to our mother country. The Norwegian Literary Club has pledged $100; Ulrikka F. Bruun, the veteran temperance worker, has pledged to raise $100; and other individuals and smaller groups have pledged themselves to put forth every effort to make our campaign a success. Now, where are our men? We have looked forward to seeing an announcement stating that the Memorial Committee had been organized and that the list would include our most outstanding Norsemen, men whose names alone would be a guarantee of a successful finish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0988.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have done the preliminary work. Now it rests with the men to get busy and reap the harvest from the seeds we have sown, and the sooner the better. For this gift appeals to the heart of every man, woman, and child in whose veins runs the good old Viking blood. Our slogan is, "Up and Hard At It."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
