<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-21">Apr. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Mount Olive Cemetery</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Board of Directors Decides on Improvements</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0691</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0691.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-21">Apr. 21, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MOUNT OLIVE CEMETERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Board of Directors Decides on Improvements</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of directors for the Norwegian Cemetery, Mount Olive, has decided to make a number of improvements at the cemetery during the spring and summer. Mr. Ole T. Nygaard, the man in charge of the cemetery, told one of the reporters of the Skandinaven that an artesian well nearly two hundred feet deep has been dug. This well will deliver about sixty gallons of water per minute. The well has been supplied with the necessary pump arrangement. During the winter about three hundred trees have been planted for the beautification of the cemetery. New barns have been built during the winter, and a drain for the excess water is under construction. About thirty men are employed at this task every day. Also under consideration is the construction in the near future of a gate with office building connected, containing living quarters for the director. The work on this ought to have been started already, but it had to be postponed on account of the strike of the carpenters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0692.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A number of private burial lots have been sold of late and several societies have bought burial lots for their deceased members. The land upon which Mount Olive Cemetery is located has a higher elevation than that of any other cemetery in the city; a mass of monuments have been erected and Mount Olive is spoken of as one of the most beautiful cemeteries in the United States. On the west side of the railroad track the cemetery has a large plot of land, now fenced in, where burial lots are being sold at a lower rate. In time this plot will become part of Mount Olive and as beautiful as the southern part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
