<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegians of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Pub. Co.; Chicago, 1905, pp. 264-265.
<title level="a">[Biography of Jonas Anton Anderson]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Strand, A. E. <title>A History of the Norwegian of Illinois</title>, John Anderson Pub. Co.; Chicago, 1905, pp. 264-265.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF JONAS ANTON ANDERSON]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jonas Anton Anderson, the manufacturer of cameras and photographic specialties at 65 E. Indiana Avenue, Chicago, was born Nov. 28, 1840. In 1852 he left Christiania, Norway, with his parents, and came to America, locating in Detroit.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago in 1857. Here he continued to work at his trade as a carpenter until 1862 when he engaged in the building business on his own account. In 1869 he started making cameras and other photographic supplies which he has followed since with great artistic and financial success. He is credited with having made the largest camera in the world, which at the time attracted the attention of expert photographers everywhere. He has been favorably written up in trade papers, magazines and journals in all languages of the civilized world. He was awarded a gold medal at the St. Louis Exposition in 1904 for a camera which did photo-machanical work. Mr. Anderson was married to Sarah <pb facs="5423969_5_1418.jpg" n="2"/>C. Nichalson of Chicago, May 24, 1864. They had six children. His youngest son, Walter E. Anderson, has mastered his father's business and is now associated with him. The family resides at 2612 Lowell Avenue. Mr. Anderson is a Mason and a Knight Templar.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
