<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-07-14">July 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Somewhat Overdrawn</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-07-14">July 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SOMEWHAT OVERDRAWN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A correspondent who writes to the Daily News from Bergen, Norway pays a glowing tribute to Norway's famous musician, the late Ole Bull. She--the correspondent evidently is a she--says in part:</p>
   <p>"The man who, above all, helped the people of Norway to struggle on from their first step in independence to their present proud position in music, drama, fiction, and exploration was Ole Bull. He saw from afar the vision of a Norway free, peaceful, and prosperous. He beheld, even in the hour of darkness and doubt, the coming of a golden age, and he proclaimed the truth of the vision. Not only did he proclaim it, he also inspired others to believe in it and to make it a reality."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1133.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now this is very pretty, but prosaic historians are likely to disagree with the fair writer. While they regard Ole Bull as a man of wonderful genius they may not be ready to admit that "the man who, above all, helped the people of Norway to struggle on from their first step in independence" was none other than Ole Bull, a child of four years when he, according to the enthusiastic correspondent, first began to help the people to struggle on.</p>
   <p>The correspondent would better make haste to leave Bergen. Ole Bull was one of the greatest and best sons of modern Norway, and the people of Bergen, above all others are jealous of his fame and will be quick to resent anything that is likely to expose it to ridicule.</p>
   <p>Our American newspaper correspondents are exceedingly stupid. They should read more and write less.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
