<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1872-07-19">July 19, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">Norway's National Day Chicago Descendants of Thor and O'din Celebrate the Event</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1872-07-19">July 19, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">NORWAY'S NATIONAL DAY CHICAGO DESCENDANTS OF THOR AND O'DIN CELEBRATE THE EVENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the local events yesterday was the celebration by our Norwegian residents, of the 1000th anniversary of their federation or union.</p>
   <p>The day was celebrated in a manner befitting the occasion. Thousandth anniversaries do not occur every day. They are scarce even in the all-embracing cycle of nature.</p>
   <p>The sturdy and jubilant Northmen and Northwomen, gathered about Norwegian Hall 170-188 North Peoria Street, and by eight o'clock the assemblage numbered about 2000.</p>
   <p>At 8:30 a procession was formed of the following participants: Northmen Singing Society; Carpenter Union No. 5; Workingsmens' Society; Sailors' Society, in uniform; ten carriages containing the chorus of young ladies dressed in white.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0193.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The attendance at Haas Park was estimated at about 5000 and the exercises at the park were of a varied and interesting character.</p>
   <p>The park was decorated with garlands and Norwegian, Swedish, Danish, and American flags. The musical part of the program was under the direction of Prof. Lindner. This was followed by the speeches delivered by Rev. Petersen, in Norwegian. Mr. Ingwell Olsen, in Norwegian. Dr. Julson followed in a short address on Norway's half sister, Denmark, and the chorus sang a Danish song.</p>
   <p>A grand ball, at Aurora Turner Hall on Milwaukee Avenue, was given under the auspices of the Harmonic Society.</p>
   <p>In the evening, besides the festivities at Aurora Hall, a select company under the guidance of E. T. Thorsen met at the Barnes House and partook of supper. Toasts and speeches also came in order and the festive occasion closed amid congratulations and the expression of the hope that all might again together celebrate another thousandth anniversary, if not in this, in the next world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
