<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-27">May 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Student Chorus to Sing Here</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1031</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1031.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H (Danish)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-05-27">May 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH STUDENT CHORUS TO SING HERE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past few days our Norwegian colony has co-operated with the Danes in welcoming the Danish Student Chorus from Copenhagen, Denmark. These young men are actual evidence of the truth of our claim that in Scandinavian music and song there is youth eternal. Upon the appearance of these enthusiastic singers we felt that here indeed was exemplification of the spirit of the song of the north, and their first selection proved this to be true.</p>
   <p>The entire program was excellent; it showed the result of the unstinted interest and intensive rehearsal so characteristic of our Scandinavian application in art, music, literature, science, and indeed in any undertaking.</p>
   <p>Understanding and co-operation have superseded petty jealousies and self-aggrandizement, making one great, harmonious whole. Mr. Levysohn, the director, knows his music and his people, and through the application of <pb facs="5423969_5_1032.jpg" n="2"/>this knowledge he has developed a chorus that is masterly in every way, and that places Mr. Levysohn among the really great conductors of the world. From the most grandiose to the simplest folk song the spirit of the composition was so well expressed that the audience was moved at will from tears to laughter, and as easily transported to the heights of pride and wonder. Even the simple "Dans Raabte Felen" ("Dance!" Cried the Fiddle) was turned into a word picture so real that the audience moved with every change in the theme; one felt that he was actually taking part in the story the song described. To stir an audience in this manner is an art few directors or choruses ever attain, but this group possesses this power to a marked degree.</p>
   <p>Norwegian and Swedish, as well as their own Danish masterpieces, were given their proper due, all being performed with a beauty and precision that was nothing short of marvelous.</p>
   <p>Mr. Helge Nissen, the group's baritone soloist, is the possessor of a beautiful, melodious voice that gives evidence of thorough training and <pb facs="5423969_5_1033.jpg" n="3"/>diligent use, and its appealing mellowness holds his listeners enthralled with emotion.</p>
   <p>We are grateful to the Danish Students for the wonderful entertainment they have given us and we sincerely trust that their concert tour will awaken a new interest in Scandinavian song, and stir some of our sleeping choruses to new life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
