<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-05-18">May 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Celebrate Norse Fete Day Thousands Take Part in Centennial of Constitution Native Costumes Are Worn Parade Marches from Palmer Square to Brand's Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-05-18">May 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATE NORSE FETE DAY THOUSANDS TAKE PART IN CENTENNIAL OF CONSTITUTION NATIVE COSTUMES ARE WORN PARADE MARCHES FROM PALMER SQUARE TO BRAND'S PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The flag of Norway brightened thousands of coat lapels in Chicago yesterday and floated from thousands of housetops and dotted the business streets and the store windows. It was the hundreth anniversary of the adoption of the Norwegian constitution, and the Norsemen in Chicago, took charge of the celebration. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and girls walked the streets in the costume of their mother country, bands played and leading speakers told of the glories of Norway.</p>
   <p>Various churches held Norwegian programs</p>
   <p>Parade at Palmer Square</p>
   <p>Men, women, and children formed a giant parade from Palmer square to Brand's park early in the afternoon. It is estimated that 5,000 persons marched in line.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0069.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Evanston also celebrated the feast. Addresses were delivered in Norwegian at the Evanston theater by Prof. Carl. W. Schvenius of the Danish-Norwegian Theological seminary and the Rev. J. H. Meyer of the Logan Square Norwegian Lutheran church. About 400 persons were present.</p>
   <p>Celebrate in Religious Way</p>
   <p>Several hundred Norwegians who did not approve of going to Brand's park gathered in Wicker Park hall to celebrate the centennial in a religious way.</p>
   <p>"The speakers who are announced to speak at Brand's park are able men," said the Rev. P. A. Kittilsby, who was chairman of the Wicker park meeting, but we do not like the place where the meeting is held. We do not like to spend Sabbath that way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
