<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-20">May 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Seventeenth of May Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Olaf E. Ray [Chairman of the Committee on Arrangements]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-20">May 20, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE SEVENTEENTH OF MAY FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Olaf E. Ray [Chairman of the Committee on Arrangements]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following letter came to me through the mails:</p>
   <p>"To the Committee on Arrangements, May 17.</p>
   <p>"We are pleased to learn that the attendance was small at the Seventeenth of May festival held at the Auditorium; it was to be expected. The more educated and music-loving Chicago public do not go out into the rain in order to listen to village talents and scab musicians, who think that anything will be accepted by the public if only the title of professor is hung before the name of the performer.</p>
   <p>"It has always been the case here in Chicago that when the Norwegians plan some undertaking, certain self-chosen semicultured leaders find their way to the front--leaders who are only seeking to get their own names advertised while <pb facs="5423969_5_0162.jpg" n="2"/>they do not consider the public at all.</p>
   <p>Your admiring</p>
   <p>Criticus."</p>
   <p>It is unfortunate that "Criticus" does not give his name. There may be a valid reason for this: his letter is decorated with twenty-one misspellings, [and it is] just as well not to sign such evidence of ignorance.</p>
   <p>The first part of the letter seems to be aimed at Mr. Emil Bjorn, in charge of the singing and of the orchestra at the Auditorium. If our Committee had known in advance how badly Mr. M. Pedersen felt about competing with Mr. Emil Bjorn for the leadership of the orchestra at the Auditorium, it may be that his sensibilities might have been considered, so that he might have been engaged for the job. In such a case one could have counted on Mr. Bjorn to have given his best assistance anyhow.</p>
   <p>As Mr. M. Pedersen was not selected to direct the orchestra at the Auditorium, <pb facs="5423969_5_0163.jpg" n="3"/>he decided to do some directing anyway, and so he, with the assistance of Mr. C. A. Strand, started an "opposition" celebration of the day at the Scandia Hall.</p>
   <p>The fact that Mr. Bjorn is a member of another musical union than the one to which Mr. Pedersen belongs, does not justify anybody in calling the former a "scab," since it is a debatable question which of the two organizations is the more orthodox one. In choosing Mr. Bjorn as director of the musical part of the Auditorium festival, the Committee on Arrangements took the relative ability of the two men into consideration, without in anyway depreciating Mr. Pedersen's standing. Of course, there could be no question of engaging more than one music director.</p>
   <p>The fact that the attendance at the Auditorium was scant,was of course due to a number of diverse causes. For one thing, this was the third time in one year that the Norwegian public had been called on to go downtown to the Auditorium in connection with national festive occasions. Our Committee had a premonition that the choice of the Auditorium for the May 17 festival this <pb facs="5423969_5_0164.jpg" n="4"/>year was unfortunate, but we could do nothing about it, since the place had been rented for the purpose one year in advance, and the Norwegian National Association did not want to go back on its word and lease.</p>
   <p>Then the weather turned bad--cold and wet--and many decided to remain at home under the circumstances.</p>
   <p>The festival at Scandia Hall was intended to draw the people away from the Auditorium. Some people went to Scandia; some kept away from both places, bewildered by the situation.</p>
   <p>The Committee on Arrangements for the Norwegian National Association's Seventeenth of May festival this year, took the standpoint that the day is an exclusively Norwegian holiday, and for this reason it decided to offer a straight Norwegian program. No political freaks of foreign origin were on the program; but this fact hardly contributed to the lack of a larger audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0165.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For several months a large number of Norwegian craftsmen in Chicago have been on strike, and at present they lack the means required for a celebration; this fact kept many away from the Auditorium.</p>
   <p>The Committee on Arrangements for the Norwegian National Association's Seventeenth of May festival this year, is convinced that the various societies of which the Association is composed did everything in their power to promote the success of the festival. The singers practiced several times and added to their repertoire new Norwegian songs which had a strong appeal to the Norwegian patriotic sentiment. The Turner Society and the Athletic Club Sleipner gave good account of their art on the stage. Mr. W. C. Thorp presented, at considerable expense to himself, excellent slides of Norwegian landscapes. The speakers and our splendid young Norwegian violinist came from far off, at their own expense, to tie the bond of friendship between Norwegians here and those living farther west. Miss Ragnhild Johnson gave of her best in beautiful songs for the day, and if Mr. Criticus had striven to bring about unity within our circle, rather than to permit himself to be carried away by his enthusiasm <pb facs="5423969_5_0166.jpg" n="6"/>for our lack of talent and co-operation, then he might have had more authority in appearing among his compatriots, and would not have needed his incognito shield when writing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
