<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1899-10-24">Oct. 24, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The Pick of the Earth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D (Swedish)</item>
     <item>III D (Danish)</item>
     <item>I G (Swedish)</item>
     <item>I G (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-10-24">Oct. 24, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE PICK OF THE EARTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his breezy interview with representatives of the press upon his arrival in New York, Admiral Dewey found occasion to allude to the conversion of the archbishop of Manila, the gentleman who predicted that the Spanish fleet would wipe "the scum of the earth" from the face of the waters.</p>
   <p>In time the warlike archbishop and the admiral became good friends and spent many pleasant hours together on the "Olympia". One day the archbishop, after witnessing a muster of the men, suddenly exclaimed:</p>
   <p>"Admiral, you must be proud to command such splendid men. These men are not the scum of the earth; they are picked men from all lands. I have seen warships and their crews from all countries, but I never saw anything approaching <pb facs="5423969_5_0800.jpg" n="2"/>what I have seen on this American man-of-war."</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that Dewey endorsed the sentiment. Our bluejackets are in truth the pick not only of the United States but of the earth. Our Scandinavian citizens are proud to know that in proportion to their numerical strength they have furnished by far the largest quota of our magnificent seafighters. To illustrate, take Dewey's flagship. Upwards of twenty per cent of the boys whose manly bearing aroused the admiration of the archbishop were Norwegians, Danes, and Swedes, the Norwegians predominating.</p>
   <p>The Norsemen are renowned seafighters and were in their element at Manila and Santiago. Fighting on our unexcelled warships and led by men like Dewey, Sampson, Schley, Evans, Philips, and others of equal ability and dash, the Norsemen, like their Viking ancestors, court danger and laugh at death, and strain every nerve to be "the pick of the earth."</p>
   <p>With such warships as we can build, such leaders as we can produce, and such sailors as our Norsemen make, the day is not far distant when Columbia will <pb facs="5423969_5_0801.jpg" n="3"/>rule the waves.</p>
   <p>From Chicago, a great number of Scandinavians participated, both at Manila and Santiago. We shall very soon give a complete list of these heroes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
