<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-08-07">Aug. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Norway's Day of Liberty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1910-08-07">Aug. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NORWAY'S DAY OF LIBERTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[This speech was entered into the State Assembly Journal for 1909, pages 952-54.] The occasion was the ninety-fifth anniversary of Norwegian independence. The chair called the Hon. Ole A. Buslet to the floor [to speak] in behalf of a large, influential class of citizens. In response to a request for a speech, Mr. Buslet made the following remarks which, on motion, were ordered entered into the minutes for the day:</p>
   <p>"The Seventeenth of May! This does not mean altogether the same as the Fourth of July does to us. Indeed, a proclamation of 'Independence and Liberty' was issued on this day ninety-five years ago, although the kingdom of Norway was established nearly a thousand years ago and is the oldest kingdom in all Europe.</p>
   <p>"Should I discourse so that you might be able to follow me up the winding path of history to the Seventeenth of May, 1814, I should have to relate not only the history of Norway, Denmark, and Sweden, of the Orkney and Faeroes <pb facs="5423969_5_0107.jpg" n="2"/>Islands, and of Iceland and Greenland, but also that of Scotland, Ireland, and England together with that of the Isle of Man, where the old Norse is spoken by the people today. I should, especially, have to relate that of Normandy in France, not mentioning that of Vineland the good! For, it is through the histories of all these, and, in some degrees, of other countries, that the veins of liberty and independence run from that throbbing heart--that little kingdom of a thousand years, the land of the midnight sun.</p>
   <p>"I shall not relate nor recite history today, for history is and ought to be familiar to a body of this kind. I shall only answer this question: If the government of Norway is a thousand years old, why is its Independence Day only ninety-five years old?</p>
   <p>"Norway has never been conquered, but the little country has twice been joined with her neighbors. The first instance was with Denmark for a period of four hundred years. Norway married Denmark! A Norwegian prince, Hakon VI, if my memory is good, wedded the Danish princess, Margaret and died soon after without issue, leaving Margaret the queen of the two countries. In <pb facs="5423969_5_0108.jpg" n="3"/>the long run, the succeeding kings and queens came to look upon Denmark as the mother country, and most of the time they sat upon the throne in Copenhagen.</p>
   <p>"But Norway never accepted this view and always maintained Home Rule until the Napoleonic Wars made it impossible for Denmark to hold her own without granting something to the war dogs. Then she ceded Norway to Sweden, which had been forced to yield Finland to Russia. Norway did not want to be ceded and deeded away. Indeed, she would not have been Norwegian if she had! All Europe told her, 'You must, you shall!' Norway, however, answered the whole circus of them, 'I will not!' She called upon her farmers, her army officers, her ministers of the church, her learned men, the professors, and lawyers. These men met--farmers, preachers, professors, military men and lawyers--and wrote the new constitution, and declared themselves independent.</p>
   <p>"When the last man had set his name to this little document of one hundred and twelve paragraphs, the most democratic constitution in the world in spite of its king, they joined hands and formed a ring and sang, 'United and <pb facs="5423969_5_0109.jpg" n="4"/>faithful until Dovre [Dovre, a mountain range] shall fall!' I can understand this act, can you? If you can, then you can understand what the Seventeenth of May means.</p>
   <p>"Europe would not give in: the countries sent their representatives to Norway, who found out the situation and the old right of the land; and, these representatives stated publicly that the order of the nations had to be complied with; but, privately, they encouraged the Norwegians who stood at the helm! When Carl Johan, the crown prince of Sweden, by the grace of Napoleon, found that such was really the case, he thought it best to accept the Norwegian crown and become king of Norway. Thus, Norway, remaining an independent land, joined with Sweden through the person of Johan who became king of the two independent countries.</p>
   <p>"Note the words of the Norwegian constitution upon which the king took his oath: 'Norway is an independent, indivisible kingdom, united with Sweden by one king.' But in this union, as in that with Denmark, all was not happiness. The king thought that in time he could get more power, that little by little <pb facs="5423969_5_0110.jpg" n="5"/>the larger country could overcome the smaller; moreover, Sweden was always harping on her superiority and pointing to the Treaty at Kiel where Norway was ceded [to Sweden], and the Norwegians, who would not have been Norwegians if they had not, resented this.</p>
   <p>"You remember what happened on May 7, 1905. It had its effects on the politics and government of our state--more so than many of you were aware. Never mind this now! Let me continue by painting a pleasant picture. In the central part, in the very heart of Norway, in the greatest farming district of the land, lies an inland lake, some 20 x 84 miles. At the lower end of this lake reposes the little village of Eidsvold. Sloping slowly upward from the water on both sides of the lake are the best farms in all Norway. Here one can see farmhouses, churches, schools, villages, and cities, all bathing in the sunshine, and on the horizon above them a green belt of evergreen, spruce and pine trees, where the orioles sing all day long. Above it all loom the mountains, higher and higher.</p>
   <p>"At that little village of Eidsvold, in a hut somewhere back in the country, <pb facs="5423969_5_0111.jpg" n="6"/>the new Magna Charta of Norway was written. And right here, let me mention, is another Magna Charta with which our lawyers are better acquainted, that of Runnymede with the habeas corpus act upon which our liberties rest today. Both of these documents were written by the same blood, by that same race while fighting for freedom. And if, once upon a time, they had been victorious at the Stanford Bridge, the language in which the Seventeenth of May and the Seventh of June have been sung into the land of the North by the poets of the land--I say that language might have been the language of this assembly today. Such is history!</p>
   <p>"But I forget my picture-painting rambling into past possibilities, and scenes from the pages of history loom up before me like fleeting shadows of friends I have known in bygone days. And now, let me get back to the Eidsvold valley. At the upper end of this inland lake which I mentioned, some 20 miles northward near where another mountain range shoots across the valley and shuts off the view, your humble servant was born--fostered and fed, so to speak, in the Eidsvold hall upon the liberty and poetry of the land.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0112.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"I love my father's land, but do I love my country any less because of this? No! My friends: The Norwegians are a patriotic people and great lovers of personal liberty and freedom of speech. At the same time, they are a law-abiding people, slow to come as avengers, but when they do, there are good reasons to cry with the Romans of old, 'God deliver us from the madness of the Northmen!' I want to cry this out to you on the Seventeenth of May, 'Remember the past, look into the future, and then act in the present! Stop your creation of government by the few, your commissions, and your inquisitions! Stop repeating the history of the Roman Republic and the Spanish hades of the Middle Ages, or I will be after you!' The blood of that old man Rollo of Normandy is just as red and full of the germs of freedom for soul and body on the American soil as it was when it fought for the Magna Charta, and the Seventeenth of May!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
