<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-05-18">May 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Our Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0805</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0805.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-05-18">May 18, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">OUR COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Colonial Congress met in Philadelphia in 1774 and tried to agree on the basis of representation for the various American colonies, the delegates from the smaller colonies wanted equal representation with the larger, while the delegates from the larger colonies maintained that representation should be based upon population. Then it was that Patrick Henry expressed a sentiment which, in the light of earlier as well as later history, must be considered a memorable one. Addressing that Congress, he said: "British oppression has effaced the boundaries of the several colonies; the distinction between Virginians, Pennsylvanians, New Yorkers, and New Englanders is no more; I am not a Virginian but an American."</p>
   <p>And this is likewise true today, notwithstanding the sectional feeling in the past between the North and the South; notwithstanding that more than one-third of the population of the United States is of foreign birth or parentage. In the crisis confronting our country, in the face of a foreign <pb facs="5423969_5_0806.jpg" n="2"/>foe, the distinctions between the North and the South, between the native American and the German-American, the Scandinavian-American, the Scotch-and Irish-Americans, are no more. We all stand united, rallying 'round the flag, satisfied with no other name than that of American citizens, no other fame than that of the American soldier. So, when I speak of Americans, I do not mean merely the New Englander, the New Yorker, the Virginian, the South Carolinian, or the descendants of the inhabitants of the original thirteen colonies. History has been in the making since the American Revolution. New States have sprung up, inhabited largely by people from Germany, Norway and Sweden, Scotland and Ireland, and their descendants. These new States take equal rank and claim equal rights with the original thirteen. Their inhabitants claim to be just as true and loyal Americans as the Sons of the Revolution and the Colonial Dames. The spirit of America is broad enough and great enough to include under the name American, every citizen, no matter what his origin or descent, who gives his unstinted allegiance to American institutions, or who, at his country's call, stands ready to march under The Stars and Stripes to the martial music of the grand battle hymns of the Republic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0807.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is something about the institutions and conditions in our country which makes loyal Americans of all who come to dwell within her borders. It is a country of wonderful opportunities and possibilities for the individual, whatever his origin. Yet the past has always been, and ever will be, a source of patriotic inspiration. If our people must go beyond their present institutions to seek inspiration from the past, let the sons of New England recall the Pilgrim Fathers and the memories that cluster around Bunker Hill, Lexington, and Concord; let the sons of Virginia remember the principles of constitutional liberty engrafted upon our national life by the master minds of Washington and Jefferson, Madison and Monroe; let the South Carolinian remember Marion and Sumter; the Pennsylvanian, Benjamin Franklin and Robert Morris; let the German-American cherish the personal liberty, the freedom of thought and conscience of the Teuton of old, and the services of Baron von Steuben and Baron De Kalb, of General Franz Siegel and General Carl Schurz in the cause of American liberty; let the Norwegian-Americans remember the blow their ancestors struck for liberty and independence, when in 1814, with the powers of Europe against them, they met in the churches throughout the country, vowed that Norway should be free, declared that they would risk <pb facs="5423969_5_0808.jpg" n="4"/>their lives for the fatherland; let them remember the heroic stand their representatives took at Eidsvold and the constitution they adopted, based largely on the constitution of the United States; let them remember Colonel Hegg and the gallant Norwegian Regiment, the Fifteenth Wisconsin, which went through the thickest of the fight from '63 to '65 in our country's cause.</p>
   <p>It is fitting at this time and on this occasion to pay a tribute to the memory of this little regiment, which fought so nobly in the dark days of our country's trial. They fought at Island No. 10, Perryville, Knot Gap, Stone River, Murfreesboro, at Chickamauga and at Missionary Ridge, and what was left of them marched with Sherman to the sea. All but two companies of this regiment went into battle at Chickamauga; only seventy-five men came out uninjured. Colonel Hegg, who commanded the brigade, was mortally wounded; but before he died, he said to Colonel Johnson that he was glad the Fifteenth had remained in the ranks and had done its duty like men. While regiments to the right of them and regiments to the left of them were retreating, they stood their ground against fearful odds and terrible slaughter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0809.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>They had been ordered to hold their ground! They were there to obey orders, and they did so--a noble example of Norwegian character. They did their duty, trusting in God for the result. General Caplin said of this regiment that "on the field of battle they had no superior in bravery." When Major Wilson of this regiment was introduced to General Howard, the general said: "I have heard of your regiment and of Colonel Hegg; it is a splendid regiment. I wish we had a whole brigade of them." At the Chickamauga National Military Park, on the battlefield of Chickamauga, where our armies [preparing for service in the Spanish-American War] have just been assembling, our soldiers of Norwegian birth and parentage will find a monument erected by the State of Wisconsin to mark the hallowed spot where this hero [Colonel Hegg] fell and where this regiment [the Fifteenth] fought so nobly and so well--an inspiration to them and to us all, and to our children for all time to come.</p>
   <p>So let all Americans cherish the deeds and historic memories of their own ancestors; let them hand down these traditions to their children after them, so that our country will be richer in sentiment, greater in historic memories, grander in her patriotism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0810.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The aid offered by the spirit of American liberty is as broad as humanity. It has been the proud and just boast of America that her shores have been open to the oppressed of all nations; but [it is also true that] her mission and her sympathies extend beyond the confines of her own border. She hates oppression and oppressors in all lands. When the Armenians were being massacred and the Cretans were struggling for liberty, America, herself powerless to act, prayed that the powers of Europe would put an end to the tyranny of "the savage Turk." When, on our own continent, the cruelty and inhumanity of Spain toward the patriots struggling for liberty in Cuba, and their innocent women and children, continued after the repeated warning of Presidents Cleveland and McKinley; when the cruelty and inhumanity were brought home so forcibly to the hearts of our people by the blowing-up of the "Maine" and her crew--martyrs to the cause of liberty and humanity!--the people of the United States declared that this cruelty must stop and demanded that Spain withdraw her forces and authority from the island of Cuba. They properly placed this demand on the broad ground of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0811.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>This struggle is one between Teutonic and Roman civilization, between tyranny and oppression on the one side, liberty and humanity on the other. There can be but one result--"the survival of the fittest". And when the struggle shall be over and the Spanish tyrant be driven from the American continent; when peace shall be restored in Cuba, and our government shall permit the people of Cuba to establish their own free and independent government, as it has declared its intention to do, then these acts of the United States will go down to posterity as the crowning glory of the nineteenth century, the grandest achievement of any nation for the cause of humanity, without a parallel in the history of nations. The world will know that the aim of our country is not greed or self-aggrandizement; they will know that the American flag stands for liberty, equality, and humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
