<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-08-29">Aug. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">An Insult to Norway</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-08-29">Aug. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">AN INSULT TO NORWAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A "special cable dispatch" to the Chicago Record-Herald reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Christiania, August 27. In answering the ministerial journal of Denmark which advocated a Scandinavian federal alliance for purposes of defense, the chief organ of the Norwegian home rule party, Dagbladet, which is also the mouthpiece of the present Norwegian ministry, declares that Norway must control its own army. The journal, however, is willing that the Scandinavian countries should have a common defensive policy if Denmark will support Norway in its contest against Sweden so that it will get full home rule."</p>
   <p>This "special cable dispatch" is a joke or a falsehood that does not hail from Christiania. There is not a man or woman in all Norway that could or would have wired such a silly misrepresentation of the international status <pb facs="5423969_5_1130.jpg" n="2"/>of the country. There is no chief organ or any other organ of "the Norwegian home rule party," because Norway neither needs nor knows any such party. Norway has no "contest against Sweden" for "full home rule" or any other kind of home rule, because Norway, like the United States, is an independent and sovereign nation that rules its own destinies.</p>
   <p>The Record-Herald has published a series of letters from Norway from the pen of the well-known writer, William E. Curtis. Though he has made some mistakes, his statement defining the constitutional and international status of Norway was correct and so clear that nobody could fail to understand and remember it. But in fourteen days the Record-Herald has forgotten what its own correspondent had taught it, and published a dispatch that for insulting stupidity caps anything that thus far has appeared in the American press concerning Norway.</p>
   <p>If the Record-Herald desires to gain the good will of the Norwegians in <pb facs="5423969_5_1131.jpg" n="3"/>America, it must cease misrepresenting their fatherland before the American people. They will not brook insults to their native land. They do not assume that any responsible newspaper prints misleading information on purpose. But whether such breaks are intentional or unintentional, their effect upon the public mind is the same. In the present instance the Record-Herald has no excuse whatever to plead. The statement of Curtis, published only a few days ago in its own columns, makes it plain that the alleged dispatch from Christiania is a gross misstatement of facts--an insult to a free and sovereign nation and to all its sons and daughters in America.</p>
   <p>Norway is entitled to fair and intelligent treatment at the hands of the American press. Occasional write-ups, however well-intentioned or well done, will not compensate for persistent misrepresentation or atone for the injustice of denying the freest country in Europe its rightful place among the sovereign nations of the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
