<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-08-30">Aug. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Fifteenth Wisconsin Regiment</title><title level="a" type="sub">Reception at Scandia Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-30">Aug. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTEENTH WISCONSIN REGIMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Reception at Scandia Hall</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reception for the Norwegian veterans at Scandia Hall on Wednesday evening was attended by more than two hundred and fifty guests. The Hall was well decorated, and the tables were arranged in horseshoe form.</p>
   <p>After the refreshments had been served President P. M. Balken introduced Mr. Olaf E. Ray who, in his speech said, among other things:</p>
   <p>"I congratulate the Veterans of the Fifteenth Wisconsin Regiment on their belonging to the race which during the eighth, the ninth, and the tenth centuries was moving from the island lined coast of Norway to England, Ireland, Iceland, the Orkneys, the Fareys, Scotland, etc. The Veterans are to be congratulated on the fact that the Napoleon who is hidden by the uniform of the Veterans is the apostle of liberty and enlightenment who has recently entended his dominion <pb facs="5423969_5_0789.jpg" n="2"/>to reach people outside of the American continent, and said to them that if they cannot help themselves onward to liberty, then must others do it for them. The Veterans are further to be congratulated on the fact that by their fine, noble behavior in our midst here in Chicago they are placing before our young people an inspiring example. Judging from the virility of these Veterans they will yet be in the places of leadership for many years to come, and will set as fine an example for the third generation as they have done for the second."</p>
   <p>The Norwegian Glee Club surprised the Veterans with some songs, after which the president displayed the banner which ladies of Chicago had donated to the Regiment when the latter went to war, and which on the Regiment's return was presented to Nora Lodge No 1, R. H. K.</p>
   <p>The president of the Fifteenth Wisconsin, Mr. Chantland, on behalf of the Regiment thanked the committee on arrangements and the Norwegian Old Settlers' Society <pb facs="5423969_5_0790.jpg" n="3"/>for what they had done for the out-of-town guests.</p>
   <p>Afterwards there was singing and speeches and good humor, and all those present enjoyed the reception. Late in the evening when many of the out-of-town guests had left, the Norwegian Singing Society came marching up, one hundred men strong, and sang "Olav Trygvason" and several other numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
