<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1914-06-22">June 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The United Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_0387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_0387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1914-06-22">June 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Church held its regular annual meeting last week. It was reported that the income of the foreign Mission was a little less than $18,000, against the income last year of $85,000. The income of the inner mission was not quite $16,000; last year it was $62,000. The current value of the property is only $277, 025, compared to $1,920,796 for last year; yet, twelve years ago, the total income was only $536, 974.</p>
   <p>The next point on the agenda was the report of the secretary. He reported that today there are 605 pastors and professors, and 1,609 congregations. In the schools there are 35,789 children studying Norwegian, 2,707 studying English, and 7,785 studying both languages, a total of 46,281 children enrolled in the various grade schools operated by the United Church, School days were as follows: Norwegian 37,294, English 1,250, both languages 6,646 a total of 45,190. Sunday-school days were: English, 19,977; Norwegian, 23,396; both languages, 16,747; a total of 53,120. There are 1,032 teachers <pb facs="5423969_5_0388.jpg" n="2"/>connected with the Church. During the year the Church baptized 12,619, and has a total of 280,025 members. There are 873 youth organizations.</p>
   <p>The following figures will show the growth in 1913 as compared to 1912: During 1913 the Church acquired 16 additional pastors, 39 additional congregations, and increase of 1,042 children in the grade schools, 2,159 children in the Sunday school, 91 teachers in grade schools, and 160 new youth societies. The only department that showed a decrease was marriages; during 1913 there were 520 marriages less than in 1912.</p>
   <p>The treasurer's report was as follows:</p>
   <p>A total of $57,452 was turned into the central fund, an increase of $13,337 over last year. The expense has been unusually large this year. Last year the convention appropriated $69,044.55; in this was included a deficit of $22,034.90 from preceeding years. A total of $75,840.44 was paid out for the year, leaving a deficit of $18,388.10, but at the same time last year's <pb facs="5423969_5_0389.jpg" n="3"/>obligations were reduced by $3,646.80. These figures are complete. Many of the congregations have not sent in any money whatsoever, others have increased their offerings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
