<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-11">May 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Stop Foreign Panhandling!]</title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_5_1007</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1007.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-11">May 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[STOP FOREIGN PANHANDLING!]</title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Away with eternal begging! One of the worst plagues the Norwegian-American public has suffered from has reached the proportions of an epidemic. We refer to the number of instances where people have come to this country begging money for projects in Norway. We are sick and tired of being pestered for donations to an assortment of causes which are none of our business and in which we as American citizens are not interested.</p>
   <p>No race of people is more generous and ready to assist our people, both here and in Norway, when an emergency arises; this has repeatedly been demonstrated, but when it reaches a point where every school, church, home or scheme starts its campaign with a raid on the purses of our Norwegian-American citizens, we put on the brakes and yell, "Halt! enough is plenty."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_5_1008.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To be generous and helpful in time of need is a sacred duty that has never yet been neglected by our people, but we are beginning to think our compatriots on the other side regard us as the original cornucopia to be tilted by every ambitious near-great in the field of art, literature, music, lectures, and land knows what not. If Norway wants to send us a finished product in various fields of endeavor, we shall be glad to back these people in establishing themselves as useful American citizens, but we are fed up on building foreign greats and industrial or other institutions. Something must be done to effectively stop this promiscuous and never-ending foreign panhandling.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
