<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-04">Apr. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">Democratic Party Wins; Mayor Thompson's Faction Defeated; Stanley Adamkiewicz and Stanley Kunz Victorious; Thieda Defeated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-04">Apr. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Democratic Party Wins; Mayor Thompson's Faction Defeated; Stanley Adamkiewicz and Stanley Kunz Victorious; Thieda Defeated</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The citizenry waited last night for the returns of yesterday's elections under a great strain. In general, the election was very quiet, except for a few minor rows in several polling places.</p>
   <p>As was expected, the Democrats, most of whom are opposed to Mayor Thompson's politics, were victorious. Old and faithful comrades of the Mayor were defeated, and the Republican candidates who were elected do not generally subscribe to the Mayor's ideas.</p>
   <p>Twenty-two aldermen, the city clerk, and the city treasurer elected yestarday are all Democrats. This means that, with one exception, all the Democratic candidates were victorious. Only twelve Republican aldermen were elected. From the Socialist party only two men will occupy seats in the <pb facs="5423968_3_1451.jpg" n="2"/>City Council. They are Charles V. Johnson and John C. Kennedy.</p>
   <p>The results of yesterday's election delight some and sadden others. Mayor Thompson cannot be very happy. The majority of votes which his party had in 1915 was 147,477. Yesterday everything was changed.</p>
   <p>All those who supported Judge Fisher's bill (fifty-year franchise)--designed to give the street car companies many privileges to the disadvantage of the citizens of Chicago--are also dissatisfied. All their friends who were running for the office of alderman yesterday were defeated without a single exception. This indicates that the people are beginning to look at things more closely and will no longer allow themselves to be cheated by exploiters.</p>
   <p>For us Poles the results of yesterday's election are very gratifying. Although we did lose one candidate in the person of Stephen Thieda, Republican, of the Twelfth Ward, two of our candidates were victorious. These are men well known to the Chicago Poles. One of them is Stanley Adamkiewicz, Democrat, <pb facs="5423968_3_1452.jpg" n="3"/>of the Seventeenth Ward. Everyone knows what a furious battle he had to fight with a man of another nationality. People of other nationalities did not stint funds in order to have Adamkiewicz defeated. They employed dishonest weapons in order to draw the Poles to their side. But our man won. Mr. Adamkiewicz defeated his opponent by eighty-three votes, getting 1,970 male votes and 959 women's votes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Adamkiewicz owes his election exclusively to the Poles, who fulfilled their civic duty by casting their votes for a fellow Pole. Had it not been for the women, Mr. Adamkiewicz would have been defeated, since he was dealing with a very influential opponent.</p>
   <p>The other Polish candidate who won in yesterday's election is Stanley Kunz, Democrat, of the Sixteenth Ward. In this ward the political fight was not a hard one, because the Republican party has no candidate, and the Socialist party has done nothing to earn the recognition of the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1453.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We judge that the newly elected Poles will fulfill the duties of their offices honorably for the benefit of their community, and that they will properly present all Polish matters before the City Council, and defend them when the need arises.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
