<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 257,
<date when="1908-11-02">Nov. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Alma Mater on Behalf of All Polish Candidates</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 257,
<date when="1908-11-02">Nov. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ALMA MATER ON BEHALF OF ALL POLISH CANDIDATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Resolution of the central administration. To all loyal members of Alma Mater Society in particular and the selection of all Polish candidates in general.</p>
   <p>Brother compatriot:</p>
   <p>Proceed according to the mandate of our organization's constitution which imposes on us an obligation to help our members in every respect, in all possible ways, and to support everything that pertains to uphold the welfare of the American "Poles"; we are calling to you with a brotherly word to please remember at the coming election our Polish <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> and our work in behalf of solidarity; to uphold the Polish <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> as <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> respect to our good candidates.</p>
   <p>The Poles should know the name of the Polish Alma Mater Society, and its</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0818.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>attempts to bring before the eyes of all Polish citizens the names of its members who are seeking election on Election Day, Nov. 3rd. They are:</p>
   <p>Walter Schrojda, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> candidate for the country commissioner's office. Peter Rostenkowski, Democratic candidate for the country commissioner's office. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Budzban, Democratic candidate as a member of the State Board of Equalization.</p>
   <p>Polish candidates not members of the Alma Later Society should also get the votes of all Polish voters. They are as follows: Phillip Ksycki, Republican candidate far the office of congressman from the 8th district; Mr. Martin S. Furman, Democratic candidate for the Sanitary District Board; Joseph S. Gieszkiewicz, Democratic candidate for the office of state representative. We are wholeheartedly wishing that all Polish candidates will be victorious, for their own good as well as for the Polish name.</p>
   <p>Max Brochocki, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
