<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 197,
<date when="1907-11-05">November 5, 1907</date><title level="a">Attention!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 197,
<date when="1907-11-05">November 5, 1907</date><title level="a">ATTENTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are people who fear nothing in this world. No perils exist for those who are filled with hope of victory.</p>
   <p>These are doubtless people of contentment. Naturally a person satisfied with himself and the world hasn't any reason to complain. His only activity is to attend to his own welfare.</p>
   <p>But there is also another class of people who are never tranquil, always lacking something, always reaching toward something better, always fighting.</p>
   <p>The former people are individualists, while the others are socialists.</p>
   <p>But alas, even the individualists are beginning to complain. Evidently everything isn't running as smoothly as they would wish it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Truly: for some time there has been some corruption in their world. Instead of loving one another they hate each other; instead of always thinking about themselves, they seem to see a new horror, even at a time when they spezk one tongue.</p>
   <p>Ah, that is startling!</p>
   <p>It is deplorable that none, none at all of the Polish organizations, whether national or "catholic", do anything toward setting the Poles in America upon their feet economically, in the realm of trade, industry or finance.</p>
   <p>This is a priceless statement - for the socialists; secured without any demonstration or persuasion on their part.</p>
   <p>God protect us from those who think that only the Poles should work, and not "Germans" or any other nationality.</p>
   <p>Another suggestion is that of a known songstress, who thinks that America is for those born here, and not for those newcomers from far across the sea. Therefore, begone from hence, all you Poles!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
