<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-04">Apr. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Ballot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-04">Apr. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE BALLOT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once again we wish to point out the importance of voting tomorrow, especially in the 16th Ward. Pre-election mass-meetings, the press, and private announcements should have enlightened all voters on the proper method of marking the ballot in tomorrow's election. We will not try to publish all the information that has been given out by the above sources, but we will gladly assist anyone who will come to our offices this afternoon or tomorrow morning.</p>
   <p>Because of the importance of tomorrow's election, we wish to point out to every citizen that it is his duty to cast his vote. Those who, because of sheer negligence or laziness, will not cast their votes tomorrow, will deliberately help the opposing candidates succeed. Last year's election results should be a good lesson to us. Some of our candidates lost by a few hundred votes; others by a few score. As a consequence of this let us remember that even one vote can determine victory.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1039.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us remember above all that we are primarily concerned about our own Polish candidates. This year's election shows us that not only one but several of the wards have Polish candidates on the ballots.</p>
   <p>We should elect August J. Kowalski, candidate for West Town Collector, and Julius Piotrowski, candidate for South Town Supervisor. All our votes are needed in every ward in the West and South sides. We expect every Polish citizen to perform his duty tomorrow by voting for our candidates. We also hope that everyone of our citizens will fill out the ballot correctly, so that none of the tickets will be voided.</p>
   <p>No matter what party a person belongs, let him bear in mind that in city government political parties play a small part and that it is more important to elect those officers who will do his group most good while in office. Who will doubt the fact that a Polish public official will do more for the Polish people than a German or an Irish? We have <pb facs="5423968_3_1040.jpg" n="3"/>no doubt that every Pole voting tomorrow will cast his vote for his fellow candidates. To those who have no desire to vote, let us point out that their vote maybe a deciding factor for our candidates. Remember, every vote cast is without question an important one!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
