<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            cc
<title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 28
<date when="1922-02-03">Feb. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Extremists (Editorial)</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>cc
<title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 28
<date when="1922-02-03">Feb. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">EXTREMISTS (Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are people who throw themselves from one extreme to another. They are, in other words, unendurable and intolerant fanatics, holding themselves blindly, like drunkards onto a fence, to one or to another foreign phrase.</p>
   <p>Fanatics, otherwise known as extremists, are exclusively persons of weak mental development, not knowing how to think critically and not understanding the natural laws of human mental development, behavior and the shaping of communities.</p>
   <p>From such dull-minded people are likewise composed the extreme conservatives, who imagine that every new relatively improved thought and its resultant act brings about ruin and the end of the world. There are also included the self-styled radical progressives, who believe blindly that with the help of any fashionable phrase one will be able to bring about paradise on earth after removing everything which reminds one of <pb facs="5423968_3_0254.jpg" n="2"/>the past and the complete stepping aside from the path of the good, old, and tested principles.</p>
   <p>To such dull and thoughtless people belog all the Socialist leaders in the world, provided they are not cunning bandits, and to such people also belong those of the founders and leaders of Russian bolshevism, who today admit that they erred, when unknowingly, prompted only by the ideals of Socialism, committed voluntarily such terrible crimes upon the Russian nation.</p>
   <p>Such a weak and dull person, as he himself admits, is Nicholas Lenin, who in such a manner was to have expressed himself according to a correspondent of the Berliner Tageblatt:</p>
   <p>"In the present situation we can only support the peasant exclusively by the help of trade. A new economic form of politics is unconditionally needed for Russia.</p>
   <p>"We all have made the mistake of not caring to learn anything.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0255.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Revolution and war could have been brought to an end with enthusiasm, although economic problems cannot be effected with enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>"One talks and writes about the proletarian movement, meanwhile the proletariat disappears without trace, together with the decline of big business. We have come to such poverty, as I could never before imagine.</p>
   <p>"Labor organizations ought not to interest themselves in politics. They should learn that which they do not yet know; above all, methods of increasing production."</p>
   <p>Behold! Here you have in Lenin a typical specimen of a fanatic and extremist, a specimen of a man knowing only how to persecute, falling from one extreme of comprehension into another.</p>
   <p>Up to a short time ago, Lenin still insisted that through the playing of politics by the proletariat itself and its governments, it would be possible to bring about paradise on earth. Now, when he has been convinced that his present beliefs have kicked and stepped upon like itself, <pb facs="5423968_3_0256.jpg" n="4"/>he denies the workers the complete right to interest themselves in politics, and is making efforts to forge them as slaves exclusively to one wheelbarrow as long as the live, and force them to think exclusively about the increase in production.</p>
   <p>Not long ago, Lenin stil believed that the worker exclusively is able to enact laws, governing, and creating a paradise on earth. When he became convinced that a worker does not know all of this on account of his having no experience in governing and an insufficient education, knowing only how to stir up politics of the state and not knowing how to build, he falls at once into another extreme, and claims that the said worker should only think about increasing production and nothing else.</p>
   <p>Such comprehension of community life and duties of citizenship are held by all dull-minded people, who consider a phrase as a final edict, not knowing how to think critically and believing solemnly that they have swallowed all the minds and that they can solve all world problems with a phrase.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
