<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. (?),
<date when="1908-10-10">Oct. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Walter Schrojda</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. (?),
<date when="1908-10-10">Oct. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WALTER SCHROJDA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Walter Schrojda, Republican candidate for the office of county commissioner.</p>
   <p>The Central Republican officials of Chicago and the County of Cook combined their efforts by nominating by an overwhelming majority Mr. Schrojda for the county commissioner's office.</p>
   <p>His work in the past few years in the office as county commissioner was devoted mostly to the aid of the suffering and poor hard workers.</p>
   <p>He himself, as a young man, had suffered from hunger and cold, that is why he has done everything in his power to seek out the poor and needy and offer them aid. He has made it his personal business to check up on the needy people himself, to see that only those that are hard pressed really get what is coming to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1675.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A true Pole in flesh and blood, he felt that it was his duty to help his fellow countrymen, the Poles in their hour of need. Thousands of Polish families can thank Mr. W. Schrojda because it was through him that they received help.</p>
   <p>Through his efforts hundreds of sick and neglected have been placed in hospitals free of charge; hundreds of parents have been saved from tears and hours of grief, suffering and shame, by having their children freed from various reformatories, and many from being sent to jail. Mr. W. Schrojda is not only known and respected by the Poles but by all other nationalities for his splendid work as a Samaritan.</p>
   <p>It will be our duty on election day to give him our votes, regardless of the party we stand for, because he did favors for all people regardless of their political party, so please all voters go to the polls and cast your votes for Mr. W. Schrojada, so that he may be victorious over his opponents by an overwhelming majority.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1676.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore all Poles on the third of November cast your vote for the Republican candidate for the office of County Commissioner; he is Mr. W. Schrojda. Show the other nationalities that the Poles believe in solidarity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
