<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Reflections on the Recent Primary Eleciton</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">REFLECTIONS ON THE RECENT PRIMARY ELECITON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the Polish-American citizens have no cause for being overelated at the results of the primary election of September, 1918, since no Polish candidate gained the nomination for Congressman of the Eighth Illinois District, where we had the best chances of victory, nevertheless this primary contains a great deal of encouragement, for us, and Polish-American citizens will certainly benefit by it in the future. Our citizens, after so painful an experience, will perhaps now understand that it is essential for our well-being to eradicate the dissenting elements from our politics, elements that are disloyal to our Polish cause. We should learn hereafter in selecting candidates to foresee all the obstacles to their election. To do this effectively, it will be necessary to eliminate in advance all dissenting elements. Such dissenters should not be treated delicately, and every effort should be exerted to prevent them from carrying out their diabolical schemes. In the selection of candidates it is also necessary to take into consideration all factors and to remove in advance all the obstacles that might stand in a candidate's path to success. Every candidate should enjoy general popularity <pb facs="5423968_3_0647.jpg" n="2"/>and be acceptable to all. The candidate for a position so important as that of Congressman must necessarily be a coalition candidate. The compromise [agreement] must be adhered to even to the minutest detail. A candidate so selected should not be governed by any factions or political bosses but should have in mind the general well-being of Polish-American citizens. If we keep these simple rules in mind, then perhaps in the future our Polish-American citizens will correct the evil which they have been doing to themselves.</p>
   <p>We note that in the Fifth Congressional District Mr. R. S. Zalewski, a Pole, gained the Republican nomination. Unfortunately the chances for the election of a Republican, and a Pole at that, are very slim in that district. In the twenty-seventh senatorial district Mr. Albert Rostenkowski gained the Republican nomination for State senator. He has every probability of success in the fall election.</p>
   <p>Two Polish candidates gained Democratic nominations for county commissioner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0648.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These are the two incumbents, Messrs. Thomas Kasperski and Albert Nowak. We also note that outside Chicago two other Poles gained nominations for county commissioner, also on the Democratic ticket. These are Messrs. Anthony Maciejewski and Paul Kamradt. Their victory in the election is assured.</p>
   <p>Mr. Francis Rydzewski gained the nomination for the office of clerk of the municipal court. It is certain that every Polish-American citizen will aid him in the fall election. Our municipal court judges will be the Democratic nominees, Judge Joseph La Buy and Alderman Stanley Walkowiak.</p>
   <p>Mr. Emil O. Kowalski was nominated by the Republicans as candidate for State representative from the fourth senatorial district, while the Democrats of that district have given the nomination to the incumbent, Joseph Petlak.</p>
   <p>Had our people demonstrated more good will and greater solidarity, our triumph might have been more complete.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
