<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-27">Jan. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Political News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-27">Jan. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish-American Democratic League of Cook County held a mass meeting on Thursday, January 21, 1915, at the Briggs House, the main Democratic headquarters. The large hall was filled beyond capacity with Polish businessmen from the entire city. Among the more prominent Polish leaders were Mr. Frank Koralewski, the Assessor of Cook County; Stanley Kuflewski, a former County Commissioner, and Vincent Zwiefka. These last three, as is well known, belonged formerly to the Sullivan faction, which now supports the candidacy of Robert Sweitzer. The three have now joined forces with Mayor Harrison's party. All three spoke in enthusiastic support of the candidacy of Mr. Harrison. Mr. Koralewski in his speech expressed himself thus:</p>
   <p>"I have supported the candidacy of Sullivan for Senator, but, as a Pole, I cannot in any way support the candidacy of Mr. Sweitzer for Mayor against Mr. Harrison. Mr. Harrison is the only civic leader who has shown himself <pb facs="5423968_3_1480.jpg" n="2"/>to be a true and sincere friend of the Poles. He has manifested his friendship in action. He conferred upon Poles great and distinguished positions which they had never before held. The position of City Attorney is now held by Mr. N. L. Piotrowski. A member of the Improvement Committee of the Department of Public Works is a Pole, Mr. F. Rydzewski. The Assistant City Prosecutor is a Pole, Mr. Z. Kadow and the two Assistant City Counselors are J. Brenza and D. Herman. Mr. F. Danisch, another Pole, was elected for the office of Clerk of the Municipal Court, where sixty of our fellow Poles are now employed. This is credited to Mr. Harrison, because without his support Mr. Danisch would never have been elected. It is also due to Mr. Harrison's influence that two Poles are municipal judges, J. La Buy and E. Jarecki, and two are County Commissioners, T. Nowak and W. Kasperski. Dr. S. Pietrowicz, a member of the Board of Education, and Mr. J. Ksycki, a member of the board of the Chicago Public Library, were appointed to these distinguished positions by Mayor Harrison. Recognition is also due Mr. Harrison for giving the much coveted and lucrative position of Sheriff of Cook County, formerly held by Mr. Traeger, to Mr. J. Czekala. In addition to that we also have two Assistant <pb facs="5423968_3_1481.jpg" n="3"/>State's Attorneys, J. Prystalski and A. Kwasigroch. It was through Mr. Harrison's efforts that these Polish leaders obtained their positions. As far as the smaller positions given to Poles are concerned, there are so many that time does not allow us to enumerate them all.</p>
   <p>"And what have the Poles received from Mr. Sweitzer? He, in his office as county clerk, has as many positions to distribute as the Mayor, if not more, and is not restrained by a Civil Service law. He (Mr. Sweitzer) states that he gave thirteen positions to Poles. Yes, he has given them because he aspires to be Mayor. The thirteen positions for Poles, if there really are that many, do not amount to much in view of the large number of positions he controls. But let Mr. Sweitzer show an official list and point out how many Poles worked for him one, two, three, or four years ago, when he did not aspire to be Mayor. If he did have a few Poles in his employment, I am certain that they held only secondary positions, with a pay between $100 and $125 a month at most.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harrison has appointed Poles to positions that pay from two thousand to <pb facs="5423968_3_1482.jpg" n="4"/>six thousand dollars annually. Moreover, these positions were not given to our compatriots before elections for the purpose of gaining Polish votes and then taken away immediately after the elections. The positions received from Mr. Harrison have been held by the Poles for the past four years. Recognition of that kind has never before been accorded to our people by any political leader. He who would deny this is a liar.</p>
   <p>"In view of all this, and being convinced of Mr. Harrison's sincere friendship to us Poles, my Polish heart would not permit me to utter one unfavorable word against Mr. Harrison. Our sacred obligation is to express now our appreciation for all that he has done for our people. That is the reason why I too have left the other faction and have come over to your League, which works so sanely and so successfully for our people in the political field, under the able leadership of our Mayor, Mr. Harrison. In the future I want to work with you for the same purpose, and I want to exert all my efforts to re-elect Mr. Harrison Mayor of our city."</p>
   <p>Mr. Koralewski's speech was accepted with loud applause. Messrs. Kuflewski and <pb facs="5423968_3_1483.jpg" n="5"/>Zwiefka talked on more or less the same topic--and said that the same reasons that caused Mr. Koralewski to come into the League and to support Mr. Harrison had also influenced them. Mr. Kuflewski stated that it is impossible to say anything to Poles against Mr. Harrison, because they will immediately say that it is a lie. "There is no doubt," said Mr. Kuflewski, "that Mr. Harrison has done much for our people, and our gratitude is due him. I, too, as a Pole, will support him wholeheartedly."</p>
   <p>Mr. Harrison spoke to the Polish-American Democratic League and thanked the Poles for their expression of friendship toward him. He thanked all the Poles for the constant support they had given him, which, he said, he would always remember. The League accepted the Mayor's speech with indescribable enthusiasm. Among the other distinguished speakers were: Sexton, the former corporation counsel, and Traeger, the sheriff of Cook County.</p>
   <p>This meeting of the Polish-American Democratic League created a profound impression in the Democratic headquarters in the Briggs House.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
