<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-04-07">Apr. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-04-07">Apr. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist party gained a victory in Milwaukee, Wis., where Socialists claimed the offices of the Mayor, of twenty one Alderman, of comptroller, a judge of the Circuit court, a city prosecutor, and the treasurer. This should neither sadden nor amaze its opponents, because for the first time in the history of this country, the Socialist party will have the opportunity to prove to the people that the Socialist are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> managers of public affairs than either the Democrats or the Republicans.</p>
   <p>Nothing should stand in their way. Having a majority of votes, they now control the city government, and therefore, can <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> right ahead with their proposal reforms.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0374.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They can give the public a sample of their kind of administrative efficiency. It is now up to they to prove, that the Socialist party is more reliable than either of the other two. If they can prove this, they will in a short time have millions of followers throughout the country, and other cities will be following the example set by Milwaukee, and will also put Socialists into office.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, if they are found to be of the same calibre as the officials of the other parties, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> accomplish nothing, then the public will lose faith in them also, and all their theories and all their shouting went do them any good.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0375.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="unk" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0376.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Finally, there is a great difference between the German Socialists of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the handful <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> our crack-brained Polish Socialists, who do not know or understand Socialism and its aims. This statement may offend them, and they may say that we are not writing the truth, because they are just as <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> socialists as the others. But we are convinced, and will stick to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> conviction, that our Polish Socialists in this country, are just very poor imitators of the German Socialists.</p>
   <p>The latter do not engage in religious, racial or anti-organizational persecutions, whereas our Socialists do. The German Socialist are engaged in an educational <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> they contribute to the elimination of various social and economic ills. These common sense tactics constantly attract new adherents to their cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0377.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>They are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> but they do not spread <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> our thoughtless and prejudiced Socialists. That is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> they won in the last election. Now, if they prove to be good public servants, their services will be demanded by other cities and communities where graft <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> corruption are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and the people are tired of it and demand that these evils be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
