<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-05">Jan. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Home Owners Demand Widening of Augusta Street</title><title level="a" type="sub">Max Adamowski and Stan. Adamkiewicz Promise to Bring Plan to Realization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-05">Jan. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HOME OWNERS DEMAND WIDENING OF AUGUSTA STREET</title><title level="a" type="sub">Max Adamowski and Stan. Adamkiewicz Promise to Bring Plan to Realization</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of city officials and members of the West Park Board held last night, the question of widening Augusta Street, and changing it into a six mile boulevard was discussed. John Dill Robertson, president of the West Park Board, said that the developing of this street into a boulevard would give the city an important vehicular artery from practically the center of town to the West Side. The plan includes the improvement of the street from Elston Avenue to Austin Avenue.</p>
   <p>Dr. Robertson informed the delegation that he will consent to widening the street if the question is supported by the City Council. This plan would entail the widening of the street by ten feet. The completion of such a plan would cost ten million dollars. This would mean that a bond issue <pb facs="5423968_3_1350.jpg" n="2"/>would have to be floated in order to raise the necessary funds.</p>
   <p>Augusta Street practically passes through a neighborhood that is populated by the Polish people. If the plans are completed and the improvement finished, many Polish property owners will benefit thereby.</p>
   <p>At this meeting were: Alderman Max Adamowski and Stan. Adamkiewicz. Both promised to support the issue if it should go before the City Council. Within the near future, petitions will be sent out to all the property owners of Augusta Street and the question; Do you favor the plan of widening Augusta Street, will be asked. The support of this plan by the property owners will greatly improve the chances of materialization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
