<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Spring is in the air, and with it appear, as our cartoonist so aptly has remarked, the first swallows to announce increased political activity. There will again be unusual activity in the press and in all strata of society in our city; cliques of all kinds will crawl out into the open, like yellowed blades of grass denuded of snow, and will smile coquettishly to "the dear voters," promising them mountains of gold but forgetting them after election as completely as the snows of yesteryear.</p>
   <p>The political campaign promises to be all the more interesting because of the unusually lively agitation in regard to our streetcar transportation. Already Mayor Thompson with his notorious political gangsters is preparing the nets to gather barkers, "workers," and "pollcatchers," and with their help to capture the votes of the uncritical masses with never-to-be-fulfilled promises.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0637.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our Mayor is bringing out his heavy artillery against all those who are impeding his restoration of the prewar nickel fare, and he promises to ride his little wooden horse in this great battle until he has recovered for us that famous nickel. But we are afraid that the unfortunate Chicagoans will have to wait too long to see his promises realized, and that they will get tired of their Mayor long before he finally recovers for them that elusive nickel streetcar fare. We feel that the surest way to accomplish this reform and many others that are so urgently needed in our city is to change the city administration as soon as possible and to drive out the Thompson gang, which only cheats and exploits the citizenry, leading them by their noses into its own yard to milk them there like patient cows and finally to cut their throats. There is not the least doubt that such is, figuratively speaking, exactly our fate now, under the present city administration of Mr. Thompson and his gang.</p>
   <p>This important question of streetcar transportation which Mayor Thompson has raised as his banner for this year's political campaign is nothing else but <pb facs="5423968_3_0638.jpg" n="3"/>the old political shibboleth, slightly changed in form, which has been known these many years as municipal ownership; it is nothing else but the assumption by the city of the public utilities. Of course streetcars can also be included under this head, and because Chicagoans have suffered in them since they began to run on our streets, this question of streetcar transportation has become so pressing that it is a catchword in local politics; it haunts our political crooks like a continually reappearing spectre. For several years this perpetual question has been dormant, but lately it has been revived, resurrected by Mayor Thompson, who rode it during his last campaign, rode it, in fact, into the City Hall and into the mayor's chair, having promised to give us such streetcars that the citizens would ride in as much comfort as if they were angels. In the meantime they are [still] hanging on streetcar straps and being unceremoniously pushed around and stuck in the ribs, as has always been their lot. In the present campaign the Mayor again parades the question of streetcar transportation because it happens to be the most popular and the most appealing argument for everybody, since everybody must ride in streetcars, and everybody in town complains about them. But the real <pb facs="5423968_3_0639.jpg" n="4"/>reason this time is to get the Mayor's clique elected to office, to important jobs in the city and the county and even in the State legislature, so that [using as a pretext] the improvement and even the appropriation of the whole streetcar transportation system, the city gang may continue to collect its graft.</p>
   <p>But under present conditions their ambition may prove hard to realize. People are beginning to open their eyes and rub them, and whoever is still blind must have his eyes opened by force so that he may see that our City Hall gangsters are parasites living on our citizenry, parasites who must be got rid of; and the sooner this is done, the better and the healthier we all shall be for it. And it can be done! The last judicial election absolutely proved it. At present the people are better informed about these questions and are willing to put a stop to these attempts. The Democratic party is naturally the most serious, the most important, and the strongest opponent of Thompson's Republican faction. There is not the least doubt that this party will show in the next elections great and steadily growing strength. It has every chance <pb facs="5423968_3_0640.jpg" n="5"/>of success, especially since it will obtain, without a doubt, a great many votes of decent and honest Republicans who do not care to have anything to do with the Thompson faction and would be only too glad to get rid of it, to defeat it, and to exterminate it completely. They are absolutely right in thinking that they would be better off, as of course they would be, if their party opponents, the Democrats, won, so long as these opponents are decent and reliable people. The Democratic party, therefore, has the best chance of cutting off the head of that dragon which is the Thompson clique and of dealing it such a mortal blow that it will never rise again but will be buried forever and ever, amen.</p>
   <p>In fear of this Democratic party and of the possible co-operation with it of an important Republican faction, the Mayor's clique is striving beforehand to win the people's favor, to buy followers, to buy votes, with this streetcar-fare nickel.</p>
   <p>We must not be misled and cheated, as we have been so often when we have <pb facs="5423968_3_0641.jpg" n="6"/>permitted politicians, especially the Thompson politicians, to mislead us and cheat us. We must enlighten and fortify the people, so that they will think and not be blindly led by the husks of empty promises. Among our Polish voters, who constitute a splendid political field, our workers, our Polish politicians, should initiate an intelligent, strongly organized, serious, and decent type of action. Because the Democratic party is going to play so important a role in the next election, our Polish Democrats have a wonderful opportunity to distinguish themselves and to gain important positions. But we must act in unison. The news has reached us, and we have given to it a great deal of space in our newspaper, that the Polish Democratic organizations are not all of the same opinion and do not work in harmony but on the contrary even fight one another. This must stop, by all means. It will again be a grave menace to our cause if Polish politicians fail to show enough patriotic and civic feeling to curb their own ambitions and to hold in check their personal sympathies and antipathies and their selfish aspirations for political jobs, continuing to press stubbornly on toward their own personal ends. They will surely go down in defeat, and with them we shall suffer defeat <pb facs="5423968_3_0642.jpg" n="7"/>also if they do not show a change of heart but continue in their old ways. It is essential that there shall be concessions and compromises and more of the spirit of self-sacrifice and solidarity. We appeal to you most urgently to adopt such an attitude, and we shall not cease to point out the need of it, and though we are willing and ready to give recognition to all decent and honest workers in this political campaign, we shall not hesitate to reprimand most severely all those who work at cross purposes, who are obstacles to unity and co-operation. Let us unite and go to work, Polish Democrats!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
