<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Democrats of Thirty-Ninth Ward Hall the New Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMOCRATS OF THIRTY-NINTH WARD HALL THE NEW YEAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With singing and dancing, over two hundred Polish Democrats of the Thirty-ninth Ward welcomed the New Year Saturday evening at Warszynski's hall. The Saint Sylvester's evening was planned by Attorney Stephen Adamowski.</p>
   <p>The participants braved the cold weather and tripped the light fantastic to the tunes of Getsla's orchestra. Dawn was not far in the offing when the party ended. Although the guests went home, memories of the affair remained with them and will do so for a long time.</p>
   <p>Prizes were carried away by Miss Hedwiga Stankowicz, 2928 Milwaukee Avenue, who won a beautiful hat; Francis Muhloff, who received an ornamental gold fish bowl; Walter Prosik, who was given a lovely fern; and Miss Cieselska, who received a water lily. Many other gifts were also given out. In honor of his birthday, Paul Makowski was presented with a special tart. Many outstanding persons attended the affair, namely, S. Adamowski, president of the <pb facs="5423968_3_1110.jpg" n="2"/>Thirty-ninth Ward Democratic organization; S. A. Przybyszewski, vice-president of the club, and family; John Schwaba and wife; H. Weimer, vice-president of the Gilmore Coal Company; Walter Orlikowski, well-known real-estate man and owner of a few subdivisions; Michael Moffet, president of the Polish Building Company; and many others.</p>
   <p>Bruno Bezdun, one of the most active members of the organization, reigned supreme at the refreshment counter. Walter Orlikowski, former candidate for the state legislature of the Twenty-fifth District, was the life of the party. The entertainment throughout the evening was a delightful success.</p>
   <p>The officers of the Thirty-ninth Ward Democratic organization are the following: Stephen Adamowski, president; John Schwaba, first vice-president; Attorney S. A. Przybyszewski, second vice-president; H. Weimer, secretary; Bruno Bezdun, assistant secretary.</p>
   <p>The women's branch of this organization numbers over two hundred. Mrs. Cecilia <pb facs="5423968_3_1111.jpg" n="3"/>Schwaba is president, Mrs. Genevieve Walters, secretary, and Mrs. Ann Adamowski, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The members who spoke on the speakers stand not only wished everyone the best of the New Year, but also victory in the coming elections, and the early completion of the bus communication line, which is being pushed by Attorney Ray O'Keefe, Martin Powroznik, John Schwaba, and H. G. Weimer. They represent the committee which has been chosen to facilitate the transportation communications in the Thirty-ninth Ward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
