<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-06">Apr. 6, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-06">Apr. 6, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night a meeting was held at [school] hall number 1 near Bradley Street, for the purpose of creating in Chicago a Polish labor organization based on Catholic principles.</p>
   <p>This important movement was initiated by the Polish Patriotic Organization of St. Cantius Parish. The meeting, which was attended by many workers, was opened by Reverend Vincent Barzynski, who pointed out that although one of our principal concerns is prosperity we should not forget that sound spiritual life, morality, and religion are important too. Most of the Poles in America are workers and for this reason they should unite, work together, and fight exploitation by legal means. Likewise, they should not listen to the whispers of wicked people but should remain loyal to their faith. The proposed organization will help them obtain this twofold objective.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Peter Kiolbassa, who pointed out that he himself was a <pb facs="5423968_3_0516.jpg" n="2"/>workingman and that his sincere desire was to help every workingman. The speaker advised workers to organize and help one another. There were also other speakers, among them Reverend F. Matuszewski, J. Ligman, and A.Chabowski. The discussion was impartial and of a preparatory character. Various objections were raised and refuted.</p>
   <p>After last night's meeting of Polish-American laborers and artisans.....it may be said that our people possess good qualities and that they are beginning to see better what their present position is and what their future problems will be.</p>
   <p>Finally, after the decision had been made that a labor organization was necessary, the meeting proceeded to name a committee of eight to prepare an outline of organization. Reverend Vincent Barzynski was invited to help the committee, which consists of Anthony Chabowski, Basil Kowalski, John Osman, W. Lukaszewski, Michael Poteracki, Francis Radzinski, J. Ligman, and Albert Singer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
