<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, 
<date when="1928-03-06">March 6, 1928</date><title level="a">Protection Against Machinery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, 
<date when="1928-03-06">March 6, 1928</date><title level="a">PROTECTION AGAINST MACHINERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When machines began to replace hand labor and the workers became servants of machinery, production increased rapidly, but the need for workers decreased.</p>
   <p>The tradesman, Smith, and apprentice who have always worked with small tools will now remain idle as colossal machinery takes their places.</p>
   <p>In the presence of this machinery, composed of saws, anvils, and hammers moved by large suspended fly-wheels, or amidst transmissions, huge turbines and dynamos, one negligent move may result in death or physical injury.</p>
   <p>A good example of casualties in industry is brought to light in the manufacture of shoes. Here small machinery does all the hand work of the shoemaker. Of course the work is done much easier, however, it is also easier to suffer an injury of one kind or another. The shoemaker could at the most hurt his fingers as he wielded his hammer upon the nails in the leather of the shoe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0194.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is said that man has become the salve of the machine, that the machine greedily drinks up the blood of the worker and that tending of these machines is always spreading, thereby hindering mental development by becoming the master of the worker.</p>
   <p>The inventor of the machine had in mind developing machinery to increase production but also the safeguarding of the individual who operates the machine.</p>
   <p>The accidents in factories are twofold. One is due to the improper construction of the machine, and the other to the negligence of the worker. Safety methods and equipment must be introduced in both directions.</p>
   <p>Every passing day brings greater safety development in the construction of the machines. These remove the worker from the natural hazards, leaving him only <pb facs="5423968_3_0195.jpg" n="3"/>with the automatic controls, thus eliminating many of the dangers of carelessness.</p>
   <p>These modern improvements are becoming recognized in the steel industry. Glowing blocks of steel and iron were at one time drawn out of the melting pots by the struggling efforts of several men. Today a large crane operated by one man does all this work, thus eliminating the vulcanian work and its hazards.</p>
   <p>Colossal magnets lift all the heavy objects, which ordinarily took all the strength of a score of men.</p>
   <p>Still the greatest source of accidents is due primarily to the carelessness of the worker, who does not follow the safety precautions. A careless individual crossing a street can as easily be run down by a horse as by the fastest automobile.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0196.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the modern factories more stress is placed upon the psychological sides of these accidents. The worker is educated beforehand about the various accidents, and everywhere he steps he sees signs warning him to be careful. At the most important intersections there are posted placards, illustrating many kinds of accidents resulting in injuries.</p>
   <p>Now instead of offering bloody sacrifices to his new machine, the worker is trying harder to safeguard himself from the hazards and is constantly trying to make them his slaves, indulgent and industrious.</p>
   </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
