<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 81,
<date when="1922-04-06">April 6, 1922</date><title level="a">About Our Solidarity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 81,
<date when="1922-04-06">April 6, 1922</date><title level="a">ABOUT OUR SOLIDARITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a very short time, on Tuesday April 11th, the primaries will take place in Chicago. Our fellow countrymen are aspiring for various and important offices. All Polish candidates without exception, claim that they can acquire the offices desired by them if the Polish voters will stand solidly on their side, if all those qualified to vote and those Americans of Polish descent will give them their vote.</p>
   <p>That is the claim of all those who are acquainted with Chicago's politics. And if it is so, then why should not our people receive higher offices? And if it is so, which we do not doubt, then why should Americans of Polish descent be defeated for the benefit of Americans of Irish blood or German blood?</p>
   <p>Are our people worse than others?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0607.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Would it be that the immense number of Chicago Poles should be so indiscreet, that due to their own fault, they should deprive themselves of the representation due them in the government of the city, county and state?</p>
   <p>Indeed, those of other nationalities the selves that there are here about one hundred thousand Polish men and women voters, and we imagine that there are at present a few more. Why, those of other nationalities themselves admit, that the Polish votes constitute a very important percentage at the polls.</p>
   <p>In the presence of this should we not let it be known about our power and maturity in citizenship, if we have the opportunity?</p>
   <p>Many years of experience and good common sense has taught us that we will be swept up, disregarded and laughed at by others as long as we fail to prove not only our streagth but also our maturity as citizens, until we show them at election that we are as powerful as they in local politics, in the privileges and duties of citizenship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0608.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That we are no worse and no more foolish than others, but on the same plane with them, or, even better in some cases, we can best show by collective voting for Polish candidates, of our blood, for our brothers.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that the people in America to this day disregard the Polish immigration, even if it is relatively numerous.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that there is due us the same right that others have in the government of this country; let us remember that if we will not work together, if we will not stop to think seriously about pushing our people forward to higher positions in American society, then before long there will begin here such a persecution of the Polish element as there was in Prussia, because the Poles have here no less a number of obstinate enemies.</p>
   <p>We are not agitating here for any political party, but we express the desire <pb facs="5423968_3_0609.jpg" n="4"/>that all the Polish candidates who are at present aspiring for office, should receive the solid and unanimous support of the Polish voters.</p>
   <p>This will be to our immigrants' interests, and concerns above all everyone's "skin", not only that of the candidates running for office.</p>
   <p>And this is why, as a paper, standing on guard for the guard of our immigrants, we call upon everybody in whom flows Polish blood, to vote unanimously for Polish candidates.</p>
   <p>If we all stand as a wall, solidly, then almost all Polish candidates will gain the office which they are seeking and will be in their offices as guardians of our good.</p>
   <p>For once we must hide deep in our pockets personal offenses, ambitions and party convictions and act with unanimity when it concerns the good of everyone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
