<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Alderman Szymkowski Receives Magnificent Funeral</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ALDERMAN SZYMKOWSKI RECEIVES MAGNIFICENT FUNERAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The funeral of the late John Szymkowski, alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, who died at St. Elizabeth's Hospital after a short but severe illness, was held today. It was a funeral such as is rarely seen, surpassing in splendor any before it.</p>
   <p>The funeral cortege set out from the residence of the deceased at 1500 West Division Street and proceeded to Holy Trinity Church at Noble and Chapel Streets, where requiem mass was said. Upon leaving the church the cortege moved through the principal streets of the Sixteenth Ward. Forming in front of the church, it moved along Noble Street to Division Street, on Division Street to Holt Street, on Holt to Blackhawk, on Blackhawk to Paulina, on Paulina to Wabansia, on Wabasia to Wood, on Wood to Cortland, and thence to St. Adalbert's Cemetery in Niles. Automobiles awaited the aldermen and city officials at Wood and Cortland Streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1659.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The funeral procession was headed by fifty mounted policemen carrying banners, followed by a company of policemen and firemen on root, followed in turn by the Kipkowski Brothers' orchestra, consisting of thirty-six musicians.</p>
   <p>The guard of honor consisted of members of the regular Democratic organization of the Sixteenth Ward and officials of the Eagle Brewing Company, of which the deceased was a stockholder and the treasurer. Following the guard of honor came five automobiles bearing flowers, and beyond these the Polish Cavalry Society.</p>
   <p>Then came the members of the societies of which the late Szymkowski was a member. These were the Pulaski Club of St. Stanislaus Kostka's parish, the Fraternal Harmony Society (Group 996 of the Polish National Alliance), the St. John the Baptist Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka's parish, St. Adalbert's Society (Group 260, Polish Roman Catholic Union, the Polish Alma <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ater), the Association of Poles, the Kosciuszko Club (Council 285 of the Catholic Foresters), and the Michael Reese Society of the Royal Arcanum. These were followed by <pb facs="5423968_3_1660.jpg" n="3"/>the members of the city council, headed by mayor Thompson. The organists, [B.] Rybowiak and [S.] <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, and eight priests followed. The remains were escorted by the Reverend Rector <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> who was followed by the hearse, behind which a horse was led.</p>
   <p>The friends of the deceased sent many floral wreaths, among which we noticed the names of Mayor William Hale Thompson, the [Chicago] City Council, State Senator Broderick, Roger Sullivan, F. Koraleski, Klee Brothers' Department Store,....the Polish Democratic Club, the <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>agle Brewing Company,....and a great many others.</p>
   <p>The farewell address over the open grave was delivered by the Reverend Father <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>apala. A great many friends and acquaintances participated in the funeral; the procession consisted of some hundred automobiles.</p>
   <p>May the late John Szymkowski rest in peace, and to his bereaved family our sincere condolences.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
