<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 262,
<date when="1908-11-07">Nov. 7, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Socialists in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 262,
<date when="1908-11-07">Nov. 7, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIALISTS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Endeavor to Unite Polish-American Socialists with the American Socialist Party - The Polish Branches.</p>
   <p>Right now, at the time when a decomposition is going on within the ranks of the Polish Socialists' Alliance in America, causing the destruction of the organization, and when the partisans of the remaining faction show more and more dissatisfaction, the number of Polish branches belonging to the American Socialist Party is growing very rapidly.</p>
   <p>This is an undeniable fact. Every one who can see and who can observe life, must have noticed it. This phenomenon should awaken the partisans of the Polish Socialist Alliance from their fanatical stubborness, establish among them a mental balance, and impel them to consider the realities of life. Otherwise, life will pass on without any meaning.</p>
   <p>The number of Polish branches in the American Socialist Party probably equals the number of the Polish Socialists' Alliance, but strength does not lie in numbers alone; for while the Polish Socialists' Alliance is going through a process of decomposition, the ranks of the American Socialist Party are full of <pb facs="5423968_3_0396.jpg" n="2"/>life and energy.</p>
   <p>Let us take, for example, Chicago. The community of the comrades has joined the Socialist Party and the comrades feeling the necessity for a local newspaper which would consider the interests of the working class, accomplished a great work. They established Dziennik Ludowy and later Pochodnia, (Torch).</p>
   <p>When the crisis came and they needed help, they organized the Unemployed Aid Society and the Sick Benefit Society. When they needed amusement, they organized a theatrical and singing society, Nowe Zycie.</p>
   <p>Enlightenment was needed badly, so they founded a Polish Self-Taught Club and a Lecture Club, which later became a part of the Polish People's University of the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
