<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-27">Feb. 27, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Sixteenth Ward Political Meeting; Poles Urged to Participate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-02-27">Feb. 27, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">SIXTEENTH WARD POLITICAL MEETING; POLES URGED TO PARTICIPATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once again we urge the Polish citizens of the Sixteenth Ward to attend en masse the political meeting to be held at A. Schultz's Hall, Blackhawk and Noble Streets, tomorrow evening. Very important matters are going to be discussed. The choice of an alderman will also be debated. Many prominent speakers will be on the stand to give their views.</p>
   <p>The question of sending a representative to the State Convention is of vital importance to the Poles. At the present time there has arisen public sentiment against the choice of the present candidate for alderman August J. Kowalski. In order to assure his nomination it is imperative that all the Polish citizens of this ward take part in the meeting and <pb facs="5423968_3_1051.jpg" n="2"/>give their countryman their whole-hearted support. If any dissension occurs, the Germans will be certain of victory. This would certainly belittle the Polish faction of this ward.</p>
   <p>It seems that there is a candidate of the Polish minority who is giving ardent support to a candidate of German choice. This Polish minority should look over the candidates carefully and favor the one who will be the choice of the majority. Whenever dissension is created over two of their candidates, it is always a better policy to arbitrate and choose the better of the two, thereby avoiding a split and assuring victory. This would eliminate any possibilities of having a candidate of some other nationalistic group elected. It is because of such discord that others are able to benefit.</p>
   <p>The certain road to victory is co-operation and uniform agreement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1052.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are informed that this opponent of our well-liked candidate will pass out circulars tomorrow. The main purpose of this act is to discredit candidate Kowalski. But no matter how abusive they may be we feel certain that they will not do any harm to him nor to our group. We know with whom we are dealing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
