<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 38,
<date when="1921-09-23">Sept. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Fight </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 38,
<date when="1921-09-23">Sept. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A FIGHT <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There never has been such a furious struggle for the spirit of the people, their manner of thinking and their viewpoint on social conditions as there is now.</p>
   <p>There never had been so many "saviors" and so many reformers as there are now, after the World War, which stirred the souls of the masses throughout the entire world.</p>
   <p>Various reformers and saviors of nations are springing up everywhere.</p>
   <p>Any "slicker," or any clever person, who does not know how to make an honest living or does not care to, preaches a new kind of gospel which in reality is as old as the hills, promising to the most ignorant <pb facs="5423968_3_0275.jpg" n="2"/>masses a paradise on earth through the destruction of the present social system.</p>
   <p>Whereas it is easier to destroy than to build, we have hosts of social reformers who belong to the people of a poor mentality and a weak spirit, people who have degenerated to such a low degree that they have the audacity to preach that which they do not comprehend themselves; that which was inoculated into their weak minds and souls by their mortal enemies.</p>
   <p>Let us take under consideration, for instance, the principles of Socialism, which were created in the clever minds of the Semitic race for the purpose of destroying Christianity and civilization in order to gain later on the control of the Aryan races and to make slaves out of them.</p>
   <p>There is nothing in the world so fanatical, less logical, and more <pb facs="5423968_3_0276.jpg" n="3"/>fatal for every Christian community than the doctrine of Socialism.</p>
   <p>This will be admitted by anyone who has any idea about the human character, formation of society and the attitude of one group towards the other. In spite of the fact that the doctrine of Socialism is so destructive to the Christian nations of civilization, which are based on private ownership, personal freedom and neighborly love, in spite of its great stupidity, it finds very many adherents among the ignorant masses of many nations.</p>
   <p>Why? The answer is simple. It promises to the ignorant and uncritical people a paradise on earth without any hard labor or hardships; it teaches that even a most ignorant man is just as smart as one who has a good education. The creators and teachers of Socialism and other progressive doctrines reject the teachings of the past; they forget about the past experiences of humanity, on which is based our whole civilization, and think only about the present and the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0277.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is not strange that this doctrine finds so many sympathizers among those who lack in spirituality, because it places them equally with the educated ones, without any study or other preparations.</p>
   <p>The unenlightened masses, who do not know criticism, like that kind of teaching. One who does not know that everything humanity possesses was acquired by hard labor of many generations will believe in such reforms and a paradise on earth without work.</p>
   <p>The world is divided into two camps: the constructive or Christian camp building the world by hard labor with the neighborly love, and the destructive camp, trying to destroy everything that has been built.</p>
   <p>Those two camps war continually. It is a war for the possession of the soul, the soul of the common masses. Which camp will win? To which camp do you belong? We fight with the constructive camp because we believe in the victory of Christian Love. Will you help us?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
