<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Jarecki Receives Recognition for His War on Election Cheaters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">JARECKI RECEIVES RECOGNITION FOR HIS WAR ON ELECTION CHEATERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Citizens' organizations are requesting the general public, to give Judge Jarecki their full moral support. County Judge E. K. Jarecki, who for over a period of months, relentlessly fought the election cheaters, has received recognition from the Chicago Citizens' Associations.</p>
   <p>An editorial by Mr. S. M. Singleton, representative of one of the oldest citizens' organizations in Chicago, brings to light, some very interesting facts relating to Judge Jarecki's war on these cheaters. We are now assured of clean elections in the future. States Attorneys C. C. Case, and G. C. Niemeyer are also to be highly commended, for their efforts in bringing these culprits to trial; and thanks to Judge Jarecki for sending them to prison. We have analyzed the whole problem very minutely; the point is to inform the average voter, of the existing evil, affecting not only the lives of the voter, but the whole state. We believe that if the average citizen is informed of this menacing situation it will, in a measure, awaken in the community a responsibility and result in clean elections, without which, it is impossible to elect honest officials.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Jarecki, our county judge, is guardian of the public ballot, and has, under these unusual and difficult circumstances, proved that his courage was not lacking, when he sentenced 15 election judges and clerks to prison, as election cheaters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1761.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He deserves especial commendation for this action. Our case, was very carefully presented with facts and evidence obtained by special prosecuting attorney C. C.Case; yet, after these cheaters were sentenced to prison, various judges, took it upon themselves to issue writs of habeas corpus, turning them free. This is a sad and unpleasant state of affairs, and it is our aim to bring it to public attention.</p>
   <p>These are facts that should be of interest to every patriotic citizen, so that public officials may be chosen by honest electors. To conduct clean elections is one of our government's most important obligations, and will insure in each citizen the right-of life and liberty in his pursuit of happiness, to which he is entitled. 169 cheaters, or election law violators were found, through an investigation conducted by the afore mentioned citizens' organizations.</p>
   <p>After indictment, these cheaters filed applications in the Circuit and Superior Courts, in order to obtain their freedom. All but 2 of them have been released. If the honest efforts of Judge Jarecki are to bear fruit it is necessary that he and the two prosecuting attorneys, Case and Niemeyer, receive the full support and cooperation of every honest citizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
