<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 75,
<date when="1905-03-30">March 30, 1905</date><title level="a">John F. Smulski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0880</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0880.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 75,
<date when="1905-03-30">March 30, 1905</date><title level="a">John F. Smulski</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a few days separate us from the day of election, in which the mayor of this city is to be elected, besides the other offices, and the one that is most important to us the office of city counsellor.</p>
   <p>For us Poles who represent the largest per cent of people in the city of Chicago, the most important question of the election arises: that is, what kind of politics should we support.... shall we follow the old tradition and stand by our party or shall we support the kind of politics that is for us Polish citizens the best and most beneficial? This question is not very difficult to answer.</p>
   <p>We are positive that the largest per dent of Poles in Chicago agree with us, that the only way to continue national politics is to support Polish candidates, forgetting for a moment the different parties which they represent.</p>
   <p>In regard to politics of this calibre, we the Polish candidates agree that this means of supporting us is practiced by all Polish citizens in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On this basis of politics, we have Mr. John F. Smulski, a candidate for the city counsellor's office who stands out as a man of distinction, one who puts his heart and soul into anything he undertakes, thus he is the best man for any kind of political office in this city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0881.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only the Polish organizations are backing John F. Smulski, but all the other organizations of different nationalities are supporting him in the coming election, even the Germans,who are the strongest opponents to any Polish candidate seeking office, are pledging him their votes.</p>
   <p>It is without a doubt that Mr. Smulski is as well as elected, judging by the support promised by the different organizations and groups; the different groups cannot praise Mr. Smulski enough for his splendid work in the past.</p>
   <p>It is our hope and wish that all true Polish citizens will turn out in full strength for our fellow-countryman. We hope that not even one Polish vote will be cast for his Democratic opponent.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. F. Smulski deserves our support because everywhere he went he proudly represented the Poles. Now we Polish citizens can do our share by helping to elect him as city counsellor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
