<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-06">Feb. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Congressman Runz's Opinion of the Political Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-06">Feb. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CONGRESSMAN RUNZ'S OPINION OF THE POLITICAL SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last few days several local political leaders have visited us. They have wanted to be sure of our Dziennik's co-operation in the present political campaign. The campaign is very important, and the Poles, if they only act intelligently and honorably, have a great opportunity to play a first-class role and to win a few important offices. We assured them all that having assured an attitude of strictest neutrality toward all Polish political organizations, we desire to be friendly to all Poles so long as we see that their activities are for the good of the whole community, especially of the Polish part of it. At the same time we must emphasize our determination to fight with the utmost energy all forms of intrigue, dishonesty, and duplicity; the so-called double-cressers will be mercilessly exposed in order to make them harmless once for all. And again, as we have been doing these many years, we urge all[Poles] to unite because only in unity is our victory possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0633.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among others we conversed with Congressman [Stanley H.] Kunz, the present leader of the Polish Democrats in Chicago. We wanted to know his opinion of the present political situation. Mr. Kunz was very optimistic about Polish possibilities if only Poles will work in unison. He expressed himself very favorably about the candidacy of Mr. Edmund K. Jarecki for county judge, saying that it was one of the most important offices for which Poles have ever had a candidate, and that the chances of winning this office at the present time were very good. He also expressed his satisfaction that it had been possible to place a few other fellow countrymen [on the ballot] as candidates for municipal judge, such as Messrs. Peter H. Schwaba, Prystalski, and Walkowiak. The Congressman expressed his regret that it was impossible to list the name of Mr. [Frank P.] Danisch also, but it was not feasible because Mr. Danisch and Mr. Schwaba live in the same ward.</p>
   <p>We asked Mr. Kunz what he thought of our candidates for county commissioner, and we expressed our regrets that their names have been placed at the very end of the list. To this Mr. Kunz answered that it all depended on the candidates <pb facs="5423968_3_0634.jpg" n="3"/>themselves; they should make themselves so popular in the campaign that their fellow countrymen will look for them on the ballot. This cannot be changed now because the Irishmen, who constitute a majority of the Committee of Fifteen, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> ganged up against us, and because they were forced to concede to us so many candidates for judge and even the office of county judge, they got even with us [by placing the names of our candidates for county commissioner, an office which they would like to take away from us, at the bottom of the list. Mr. Hunz is of the opinion that the greatest harm here was done by the same double-crossers who have been playing this type of low and treacherous politics for a long time. He mentioned their names, names known only too well to all Poles who are interested in politics; they are the Same men who have been working at cress purposes with us for many years. They went to the Irishmen, to this Committee of Fifteen, with the intention of injuring Mr. Jarecki, saying that Poles care more for a few small jobs than for one big one; they opposed the candidacy of Mr. Jarecki for county judge. Mr. Kunz learned this of members of this Committee, of which he is a member him self. He had no words of condemnation strong enough for such traitors! He <pb facs="5423968_3_0635.jpg" n="4"/>said that he had had a hard time to convince the Irish that we wanted Mr. Jarecki for county judge, and that we deserve this office because of the strength of our votes, if for no other reason. And so they were compelled to concede the office to us, but they took revenge on the Polish candidates for commissioner, whom they placed at the very end of the ballot because, as they say, there is no unity or harmony among Poles. Messrs. Nowak and Kuflewski should thank those double-crossers for digging the pit into which they fell.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kunz said also that not everything was lost yet; that now it was necessary to work hard, harder than ever. It is essential to get the people to go to the primaries; especially our Polish women should go en masse, to turn in the largest possible vote, and thus the chances of all our candidates will be improved. Congressman Kunz asked all to work in harmony, in sincere brotherly co-operation, in this campaign. He was confident that our victory was assured, or at least that we had a wonderful chance of victory that will be ours if we do not ruin it through our stupidity or intrigue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
