<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1907-04-01">Apr. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Who Shall Rule the City?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1907-04-01">Apr. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHO SHALL RULE THE CITY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Polish friends:</p>
   <p>Let us fulfill tomorrow our citizenship duties. Let us denounce the administration of our city and of cur State.</p>
   <p>Around us we see the dreadful results due to the mismanagement of these in power. As an example of capitalistic misrule let us for instance consider Chicago. What do we see there? Daily murders, swindles, exploitation of labor and court decisions in favor of the rich. The city administration is at the service of criminals. Filth and squalor defile the streets inhabited by the poor, while sxtreme care is given to the residential districts of the rich. These are facts which are duplicated in other cities of this country.</p>
   <p>It is time that the public awakens and abstains from voting for the capitalistic parties.</p>
   <p>Street transportation furnishes us an example of the attitude of the Democratic and Republican parties. For the past ten years the capitalistic candidates <pb facs="5423968_3_0843.jpg" n="2"/>have advocated better transportation. Our present mayor Dunne, has been elected on the condition that he would appoint himself receiver and confiscate all means of transportation owned by private parties. However, during his administration, the city council resolved to entrust the transportation system to corporations.</p>
   <p>The Republicans as well as the Democrats are machine-bidden. When their candidates are elected, they must obey the wishes of their sponsors, regardless of the reforms they had promised. They are the servants of capital and must obey or face defeat at the polls.</p>
   <p>The people ought to realize that they belong to the working class and they must stand up for their own interests. We should side with the party that protects the worker and wants everyone to receive an adequate compensation for his work.</p>
   <p>We have in mind the Socialist party. We should vote for it, if we want a change of administration. If the Socialist party gets into power, the following reforms <pb facs="5423968_3_0844.jpg" n="3"/>will take place:</p>
   <p>An eight hour working day--care for the workers employed in various enter-prises--beginning of public works for the unemployed--lowering of living costs--laying out of pavements--construction of bathhouses and gymnasiums in the sections inhabited by the working men--election of a school committee which would make education compulsory for children under eighteen years of age.</p>
   <p>This program should be realized at once. It will become a fact if we elect our Socialist candidates. Let us thus fulfill our duty tomorrow. In case we should not be victorious, our votes would still be a protest against today's disorders and crimes.</p>
   <p>It is better to vote for justice and right, no matter what the outcome may be, than to support a mob of criminals.</p>
   <p>The time will come when the people will realize their error and then they will support their own interest and their own party. Remember! Vote tomorrow for the Socialist Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
