<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 283,
<date when="1922-12-04">Dec. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Judge Edmund K. Jarecki.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 283,
<date when="1922-12-04">Dec. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE EDMUND K. JARECKI.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday marked the entry into office of the newly elected Cook County Judge. Cook County is the second largest county in regards to population in the United States. The judge is an American of Polish descent, Mr. Edmund K. Jarecki.</p>
   <p>It is the first time in the history of this state and country, that a Pole has reached such a high office, the highest in Cook County. The most important, not only from a judicial character, but mainly because the whole election department comes under the jurisdiction of the County Judge.</p>
   <p>Judge Jarecki possesses those good qualities of character, which have mainly helped him work himself up to this responsible position. He was elected by, not only his own countrymen, but by all honest fellow citizens, without whose support one could not even dream of gaining the office of County Judge. In Jarecki they have confidence that he will clean up the spoils system regime that has held sway in county politics up to this time. That is why, not only <pb facs="5423968_3_1636.jpg" n="2"/>the Democrats voted for him, but also the Republicans.</p>
   <p>The new judge will not deceive this confidence of his fellow citizens. We believe in him, and we know at the start, that he will answer to his task with dignity in all respects. Judge Jarecki will lay out the path to higher offices for other Poles. That is why his election has an added meaning to the Poles in America.</p>
   <p>To the many congratulations that Judge Jarecki is receiving today, due to the occasion of his installation, are added also the best wishes from "Dziennik Zjednoczenia": Success in office and the ascending of still greater heights.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
