<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-09">Oct. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter from Mr. N. L. Piotrowski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-09">Oct. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER FROM MR. N. L. PIOTROWSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(We have been requested to publish the following letter):</p>
   <p>After my defeat in the primaries as a candidate for congressman of the United States--a defeat which harmed the Polish cause--the three leading Polish newspapers of Chicago not only lamented this setback but also urged me to run on an independent ticket and in that way save the situation. This request was supported by many Polish citizens who asked me time and again to accept this proposition.</p>
   <p>Were this public office not so closely connected with the Polish national cause, I would have refused without the least hesitation; I would not have been a candidate even during the primaries. But the office of congressman is at this time closely connected with the Polish cause, with the interest of Poland itself, and with its unfortunate fate. This fact, I surmised, was understood by every right thinking Pole, regardless of party affiliation. Since I have worked all my life <pb facs="5423968_3_1469.jpg" n="2"/>with this idea in mind, I consented to run for the nomination, hoping that if elected I could serve the cause more effectively. During my campaign I felt the conviction that the Poles in the Eighth Congressional District understood the importance of the matter and our need of congressional representation in Washington. I was, therefore, sincerely convinced that the Poles would unanimously support my nomination--not for my sake, but for the cause in behalf of which I have always worked to the best of my ability. The Polish newspapers, recognizing the fact that I possess the proper qualifications for the post, and regardless of their political and factional views, gave me their enthusiastic support. My qualifications were also acknowledged by our Polish organizations, by our clergy, and by the best part of our society. My competence was acknowledged even by those who at times criticized me severely when they did not agree with me in local matters.</p>
   <p>In view of this, I felt that the nine thousand Polish citizens residing in the district--to whom the Polish press appealed so earnestly in behalf of the Polish cause, so sacred to every true Pole--would solidly support my candidacy. I was <pb facs="5423968_3_1470.jpg" n="3"/>of the opinion that at least 75 per cent of the Poles in the Eighth District would give me their votes. All the Poles in America were of this opinion, too.</p>
   <p>But what a disappointment! The result of the primaries showed only too well that of these nine thousand Polish voters only one third could be found for whom the Polish cause had any significance at all. About 10 per cent of the votes were cast for another Pole who ran only to help the election of an Irishman. In other words, 10 per cent of the Polish voters cast their ballot for this Irish candidate or for a German. About four thousand Poles did not vote at all. This means that these Poles are not in the least concerned about their honor or the good name of their nationality in America or the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>I am deeply grieved by this. I feel even more grieved when I think of the so-called "Poles" who, after succeeding in gaining influential political positions through Polish voters, use that influence to betray the Polish cause by helping to bring about the defeat of a Polish congressman. Resorting to various tricks at their command, including the giving away of money, jobs, and beer, these "Poles" <pb facs="5423968_3_1471.jpg" n="4"/>succeeded in depriving me of many Polish votes.</p>
   <p>I now have undeniable proof of that, and on the basis of that proof I wish to state definitely that the entire blame for my defeat in the primaries falls upon four Polish "politicians" in the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Wards.</p>
   <p>In view of all this, I have come to the conclusion that the prospects of my election are doubtful and the expense which I would have to bear would be colossal. I cannot and should not make such a sacrifice. What I have done at the primaries should, in my opinion, be sufficient for the time being.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, allow me to avail myself of this occasion to express my gratitude to all those who worked in my behalf during the campaign and who wished to continue to work to bring about my election as congressman. They have done that for the Polish cause, and full recognition is due them. It is too bad that there were not more of them. Although we have lost now, this defeat should not discourage us. We should persist in our determination until victory is assured us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1472.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We did not succeed this time, it is true, but we will not fail at some other time.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>N. L. Piotrowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
