<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-05">Nov. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Poles Furnish a Large Conningent for the Democratic Army Mass-Meeting in St.Stanislaus School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-05">Nov. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLES FURNISH A LARGE CONNINGENT FOR THE DEMOCRATIC ARMY MASS-MEETING IN ST.STANISLAUS SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish people of Chicago are just as loyal now to the Democratic Party, as they ever have been. This was clearly demonstrated in recent weeks by the mass-meetings, which were held in the different Polish districts. Only one Republican meeting took place during this campaign in the Polish district, which is bounded by Milwaukee, North, Ashland, and Chicago Avenues, and the river. This respective meeting was held in Ward's Hall, close to the 14th ward, and was attended almost exclusively by people of the 14th ward.</p>
   <p>Fully 4000 Polish voters have been registered in the 16th ward. Of the 505 voters of the 18th precinct of the same ward only two are Irish, and one is a German, all the other 502 are Polish. These 502 Poles will vote as one man for the Democratic Party, as a prominent Polish citizen assured us. Similar conditions prevail in other Polish districts. Under the auspices of the Polish Democratic Clubs, a mass-meeting was held last night in the St. Stanislaus School, which was attended by approximately 1000 Polish voters. About three weeks ago a similar mass-meeting was held in the same building, and was attended by about 6000 Polish voters. Since most of these citizens belong to the laboring class, it is difficult to induce them to attend a political meeting on working days.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1011.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Rev. W. Barzynski, Mr. Kunz, Kowalski and Piotrowski, delivered speeches in Polish, which were received with much applause. The Polish Democratic Club had thousands of copies of the Edward Law printed and distributed among the Poles. With it, a splendid explanation of the law and its effect was given. This excellent campaign literature has done an effective work among the Polish voters. The speakers explained the issues of this election quite thoroughly.</p>
   <p>Ex-Alderman Kowalski made the following statement: "Andrew Carnegie persuaded his men four years ago to vote the Republican ticket, assuring them that the Republican tariff system could bring them advantage only. But what were these advantages! We saw that last year, in Homestead; when his men expected a raise in wages, they were told to accept a reduction instead. Those who tried to oppose his plans and defend their rights, were shot down by Pinkerton's detectives. Such and similar kinds, are the blessings of the high-tariff system." Judge Yanin gave an excellent address about the tariff problem.</p>
   <p>Rev. Barzynski spoke about the compulsory school law. He urged the audience to vote, on the day of election, and not to stay away on account of fear of losing their jobs. Judge Altgeld had promised to appear, but another engagement prevented him from doing so. However, he is certain of the Polish voters. The Poles will prove again next Tuesday that they are good Democrats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
