<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-13">Mar. 13, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Political Parties in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-13">Mar. 13, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL PARTIES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Besides the two major political parties in the United States, that is, besides the Republican and the Democratic parties, there is also a newly organized Farmers Party, or third party. This party is getting more and more supporters every day; in other words, it is becoming important. This importance is strengthened by the circumstance that the two old parties are at present equally strong. It is quite true that here and there one of the major parties predominates over the other, but this predominance is so insignificant in some places that a third party, even if small, may very often precipitate a victory for one of the major parties. Sometimes, on account of discord or antagonism between the two old parties, the third party may, by stubbornness or solidarity, gain a complete victory over the old ones.</p>
   <p>This was almost the case at Springfield, Illinois, during the last United States senatorial election, for, during the first few days of this week, <pb facs="5423968_3_1752.jpg" n="2"/>it seemed as if Mr. Streeter, a representative of the Farmers' Party, would be elected United States Senator. Even though the Farmers Party had only three candidates running for the Legislature, an insignificant number if it is considered that the Democrats had one hundred and one and the Republicans one hundred, there was the danger that the farmers might win, even when Mr. Streeter was abandoned because of betraying his own party by yielding to the Republicans in order to gain their support. The Republicans have promised to give all their votes to Mr. Moore for not voting for Mr. Palmer, but Moore resisted the temptation and was honest enough not to break his promises and Mr. Palmer was finally elected.</p>
   <p>In this particular case the candidate of the majority has been elected, but there are instances in which a very small group of people may gain a victory over a very large party or over a large majority representing the entire nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1753.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is apparent that the system of electing a United States senator, who is a representative of the entire state (and we would add: and the system of electing the President of the United States; because some day we may have a similar experience at a presidential election), is fundamentally wrong and ought to be changed. Such an important representative of the State should be elected by the citizens themselves and by a majority of votes as it is only then that we may rightly say that he is elected by the will of the people. Senator Palmer is planning to change this system.</p>
   <p>We know from the history of the United States, that some of the Presidents were elected by a minority of votes from the people, just because this minority had a bigger representation in Congress.</p>
   <p>Adams, Polk, Taylor, Buchanan, Lincoln, Hayes, Garfield, Cleveland, and Harrison did not get half of the popular votes. Besides, Hayes and Harrison received less votes than their opponents. In other words, if our presidents were elected by a majority of the popular votes, Tilden, a Democrat, not Hayes, a Republican, would have been elected in 1876, for Tilden received <pb facs="5423968_3_1754.jpg" n="4"/>more votes than all his opponents. Also instead of Harrison, we would have Cleveland as president now, for he received 107,438 more votes than Harrison.</p>
   <p>We are not going to discuss the platform of any political party or try to point out which party has a better policy, for this is not time for it. However, we wish to point out to every conscientious citizen that a party cannot be judged by its name. It is an established fact that the policies of political parties change so much in the course of time that they degenerate into something different from our convictions.</p>
   <p>The principles adopted by the Democratic party are accepted later on by the Republican party, and vice versa. Consequently, there is nothing steady about a political party, with the exception of its name.</p>
   <p>It is not a good policy to adhere to one political party all the time just because we are affiliated with it. It is not true that it is treason to abandon one political party to join another. However, it <pb facs="5423968_3_1755.jpg" n="5"/>is very important to know the platform of a party before making our decision to join it.</p>
   <p>The most respectable people, the most honorable citizens, and the most brilliant statesmen have left their parties and joined the opposite camp as soon as they realized that the principles of the opposite party was better and more useful to the country. They should not be condemned for such an act; on the contrary, they deserve admiration for their good sense and courage, because such an act could only be condemned by ignorant masses or unscrupulous politicians.</p>
   <p>Such example of good judgment and wonderful courage was given to our nation by Mr. John M. Palmer, who has been just elected United States Senator from our State. He is seventy-three years old now. Originally belonging to the Democratic party, he took an active part in it; but when the Republicans took very vigorous measures against slavery in the United States, a thing which once was favored by the Democrats, John M. Palmer left the Democratic party and, as a Republican, joined the ranks of the Union Army against the Democrats, fighting so bravely that he was made a major-general. After <pb facs="5423968_3_1756.jpg" n="6"/>the Civil War, when the Democratic party changed its policy in respect to slavery, John M. Palmer, then a Republican governor, seeing weak points in the Republican party and better principles in the opposite camp, left the Republicans and joined the Democrats. By this decision he displayed his great courage, good judgment, and his firmness of principles even under the presence of the unsteady principles of his former party.</p>
   <p>The example given to the citizens of the United States by John M. Palmer is worthy of imitation, and the state of Illinois should be congratulated for electing him United States Senator and for not electing Streeter, who proved by his conduct to be unsteady in his principles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
