<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 284,
<date when="1905-12-07">Dec. 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Central Organization of Polish Democrats in Cook County</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 284,
<date when="1905-12-07">Dec. 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL ORGANIZATION OF POLISH DEMOCRATS IN COOK COUNTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the courtesy of the Polish Daily News this article is given about the results of the meeting of the Polish Democratic organization at which some of the wards and towns in Cook County were represented; the wards represented were: the 6, 8, 12, 16, 17, 24 and 28.</p>
   <p>The committeeman of the 16th ward, John Czekala, called the meeting to order and stressed the point that a central organization is very important and should be settled once and for all, which was approved by those present.</p>
   <p>Mr. John Czekala was made temporary president and Mr. Peter Jezierny of the 12th ward was made secretary.</p>
   <p>After the speeches that were made by prominent businessmen, the citizens that took part in all these meetings were admitted unanimously as members of the central organization.</p>
   <p>Two committees were selected; the first committee was picked to organize all Polish people in wards where this Polish Democratic organization did not exist, the second committee had to outline the statutes of the central organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The members chosen as the organizers' committee were Alexander Wisniewski and Julius Smietanska from the 8th ward: Peter Jexierny and Simbicki, from the 12th ward; Joseph F. Helminiak and J. Jozwiakowski from the 16th ward; Mikodem Kwidzinski from the 24th; Francis Landmesser and Stanley Glomski from the 28th ward.</p>
   <p>For the statute committee the following members were chosen: Alderman Nowicki (16); Julius F. Smietanka (8); Julian Szczepanski (17); Peter Jexien (12); Gus Susralski (24); Julius S. Cirzana (16); and Bernard G. Matz (16).</p>
   <p>The central organizers' committee will select members from the committee to organize Polish Democratic clubs in the 4th, 5th, 11th, 27th and 29th wards.</p>
   <p>The first mass meeting, after the above mentioned wards have organized their clubs, will be January 9, 1906 in the Schiller building, room 301-2 at which all wards and towns in which Polish Democratic clubs are existing have the right to send nine representatives to this meeting.</p>
   <p>At this meeting the regular election will take place and the officers and the statute committee will be voted upon. The administration will serve regular terms and will at last be on the road to success as the Polish Democratic organization in Cook County.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
