<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 257,
<date when="1908-11-02">Nov. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Open Letter of a Prominent Jurist</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 257,
<date when="1908-11-02">Nov. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN LETTER OF A PROMINENT JURIST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Certain newspapers and parties are circulating a story to the effect that Phillip M. Ksycki, Republican candidate for Congress from the 8th Congressional District of Illinois, appropriated money belonging to Wood County, while he was County Clerk for Wood County from 1895 to 1897.</p>
   <p>This is rank slander and the lowest kind of political mud slinging, if the charges were true.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ksycki would have been indicted under the Criminal Statutes of Wisconsin and would now be serving a sentence, instead, we find him a hard working, trustworthy and honorable gentleman who has the respect and esteem of thousands of his own nationality as well as that of many thousands of men of other nationalities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1670.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>His accusers have not produced one single word of evidence of an official nature that would show that Mr. Ksycki ever defranded Wood County out of one penny. The reason is that there is no such evidence. The local clique which he helped to defeat the previous fall made a mountain out of a molehill.</p>
   <p>It is a fact that Mr. Ksycki's books did not balance, but on official investigation it was found that this was not caused by his having appropriated public funds to himself, but solely by an error in accounts.</p>
   <p>No criminal intent has ever been shown neither has any one suspected the same.</p>
   <p>I have known Mr. Ksycki since 1894 at Grand Rapids, and from such acquaintance I believe him to possess those qualities that will make him an excellent representative in Congress.</p>
   <p>He is well thought of at Grand Rapids, and is greeted by a host of <pb facs="5423968_3_1671.jpg" n="3"/>friends every time he visits there.</p>
   <p>R. O. Wipperman.</p>
   <p>R. O. Wipperman, being first duly sworn on oath, says and deposes that he resided in the City of Grand Rapids, from October 1892 to September 1907.</p>
   <p>That he is personally acquainted with Phillip M. Ksycki, Republican Candidate for Congress from the Eight Congressional District of Illinois, such acquaintance dating back to 1894.</p>
   <p>That he recalls Mr. Ksycki's election to and incumbency of the office of County Clerk for Wood County, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>That he remembers the incident of reported shortage to Mr. Ksycki's accounts during his term of office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1672.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>That no action has ever been started by any officer or person against Mr. Ksycki because of this reported shortage and that at there is no evidence in any of the records of Wood County that Mr. Ksycki ever appropriated one dollar to his own use unlawfully.</p>
   <p>That Mr. Ksycki is at liberty to go to Grand Rapids and has done so repeatedly since the incident referred to but no effort has been made by anyone to bring him before the court.</p>
   <p>Further affidavit says not.</p>
   <p>Richard O. Wipperman.</p>
   <p>Personally appeared before me the above named R. O. Wipperman this 31st day of October, 1908, and executed the foregoing affidavit.</p>
   <p>John S. Zawilinski, Notary Public</p>
   <p>Cook County, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1673.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Now you have, dear fellow countrymen, the best evidence of the greedy, devilish methods used by our opponents so as not to allow a Pole to be elected to Congress. Will you allow them to succeed with their devilish work? No, a hundred times no! Tomorrow all Polish voters step out as one great Polish mass and give our votes to our compatriot Mr. Ksycki, regardless of our party, and tomorrow night from the shores of one ocean to the other will be heard the clamour from the chests of all us Poles.</p>
   <p>Long live the first Polish congressman! Long live the valiant Poles in Chicago!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
