<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-02-24">Feb. 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Increased Earnings and Cost of Living</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-02-24">Feb. 24, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">INCREASED EARNINGS AND COST OF LIVING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the past few years, radical movements in United States have weakened considerably. This is admitted by the Socialist and Communist organs, which emphasize, that, recently, the "red menace" has scarcely left a shadow. Even the fanatic Bolshevists have ceased to believe in the possibility of a proletarian revolution in United States.</p>
   <p>Industrialists and financiers control the press, and are directing all of their influence on an attack against the proponents of revolution, which fact automatically elevates the welfare of American labor. We read, that American labor scoffs at the idea of being compared to slaves. Immediately, their thoughts are of pay days, bank accounts, property and of spare time remaining, for leisure, at their disposal. True, if every laborer in America was in this situation, he would be surprised to find himself a slave. However, how many such fortunate laborers have we? The percentage is very small. A great number of American laborers think about these conditions, they also think of, whether they will find themselves without the means of a livelihood.</p>
   <p>A short time ago, a young,man plunged into the Chicago river, because he could not find employment and was penniless. In Utica, New York, a laborer murdered his family and commited suicide, when he could no longer cope with the starvation of his children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0232.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such conditions in a country of wealth, are by no means segregated. A large number of us have more than we need, and enough for the future generation; on the other hand, however, labor conditions are not as good as they would have us believe, either because conditions of labor are unknown to them, or because they do not care to know about them.</p>
   <p>"A laborer's thoughts are of his home." That may be true, but his problems differ from those of the capitalist who plays golf; the laborer must think of his mortgage, which is due, and he is in a difficult position. It was remarked, that at present, labor is far better off than it has been at any time, because labor earnings have increased 44 per cent, the highest since 1909. Without criticism, in this limited time, the cost of living has increased not 44 percent but over 100 percent. Without partiality, American labor in proportion, is far better off than labor of Europe, but we shall not forget that the world has ruined Europe, and made America richer.</p>
   <p>If the radicals of socialism and communism have weakened considerably in America, it is not because labor's fared so well, but because labor understood, that communism did not improve laborer conditions, but made them worse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
