<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-06">Sept. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution of the Polish Republican Club of the Eleventh Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-06">Sept. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION OF THE POLISH REPUBLICAN CLUB OF THE ELEVENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Polish Republican Club was held on September 2, 1910, at the Zientek Hall, 2001 West 18th Street. A decision was made to support Polish candidates for nomination during the forthcoming primaries of September 15. The following candidates were indorsed:</p>
   <p>Dr. E. F. Napieralski, for Trustee of the Sanitary District; Messrs. J. Oglozinski, for County Commissioner; and J. M. Sienkiewicz, for State Senator from the Fifteenth Senatorial District. The following candidates were sponsored for precinct captains: J. Markowski, John Pelka, Joseph Kroplewski, Joseph Zientek, S. Lesner, and M. Kucik; for State Central Committeeman, Mr. Joseph E. Bidwill. The organization has resolved to petition all citizens of Polish descent to be thoughtful of their civic obligation on the day of the primaries and to cast their votes for all Polish candidates.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fellow citizens! Our strength lies in unity. Let us remember at all times that as long as we ourselves fail to do our share of work and will not endeavor to aid our fellow countrymen to occupy proper positions, so long will our people be ignored by other nationalities. Co-operation alone and a sincere interest in the affairs of this country, of which we are citizens, can place us on a par with others. It will allow the Poles to obtain such positions as are justly due them.</p>
   <p>J. Zientek, President.</p>
   <p>John Pelka, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
