<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-10-16">Oct. 16, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Politics - a Victory of the Poles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-10-16">Oct. 16, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH POLITICS - A VICTORY OF THE POLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It appears that the Democratic ticket is now complete. The nomination of the ten candidates for the City Council brought considerable objection from many sources and the Executive Committee was flooded with requests for a change.</p>
   <p>The Poles wanted a representative on the County Board and many Democrats of the North Side felt that discrimination was shown, since the number of the Commissioners for the North Side had been reduced to only two. A part of the disgruntled constituents could be appeased, since John J. Corbett, one of the nominees, tendered his resignation. He sent the following communication to the committee. "In the interests of, and to promote harmony in the ranks of the Democratic Party, I decided to withdraw my name from the Democratic ticket which proclaims my candidacy as a member of the County Commissioners. I hope that my resignation will be accepted and a Polish gentleman be nominated instead." Nothing could have been more welcome to the Executive Board.</p>
   <p>An explanation was published immediately, wherein J. Hutchinson and two others took cognizance of the resignation which had been tendered to further party interests. It was accepted with laudatory comment, and Victor Bardonsky was proposed at the behest of the Committee of Eleven.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Bardonski is a Russian Pole by birth, about thirty-five years of age, and the owner of two drug stores at 707 Milwaukee Avenue and 615 Noble Street.</p>
   <p>During the evening the Central Committee held a meeting, and under the leadership of Mr. Hutchinson, Mr. Bardonski's candidacy was ratified. Other topics of the session were confined to campaign matters. A mass-meeting for Democrats has been arranged to take place in the Hall of Battery "D". The voting list contains about 200,000 names at this time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
