<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 210,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of Polish Fellowship League of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 210,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF POLISH FELLOWSHIP LEAGUE OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the Polish Fellowship League of Illinois will take place next Sunday. Our general public is not yet sufficiently informed as to what kind of a society this is, or what its aims are. The name itself does not speak for anything. It may be a good thing or it may be a newly born freak. So far it cannot pride itself on any remarkable action. We do not even know how long it has existed, and under what influences it operates. We do know, however, that it is calling together a great convention.</p>
   <p>In due form this will be a convention of citizens of Polish descent from the state of Illinois. All kinds of assemblages, all kinds of societies, alliances, and clubs, can take part through their delegates. Special mandates are not demanded. All who come with good intentions will be accepted by the group of deliberators.</p>
   <p>The convention will take place in St. Stanislaus Auditorium and will <pb facs="5423968_3_1120.jpg" n="2"/>present only the most important problems, and most likely, a more suitable name will be accepted and established.</p>
   <p>Desiring, nevertheless, to appease the curiosity of American readers, we will disclose at least the chief aim of this society. It is a citizens' organization. Its problem is to strengthen Polish power in politics and in social work, - educational and cultural. The society wishes to have the Polish element compact, uniform, and strong.</p>
   <p>We all complain that the American public does not calculate on the Poles, that there are so few of us in higher positions,that we are a tool in the hands of outsiders. But we make no effort to remedy this condition. Internally we are organized, but on the surface, in our relations with other nationalities we act individually. We have no organization to which we can appeal or depend on.</p>
   <p>American society has accustomed itself to deal with organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1121.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Individuals are not imposing upon them very much. For this reason an assemblage, the kind that could present and represent all citizens of Polish descent, at least in the most important times and affairs, has the greatest right to exist.</p>
   <p>We do not know whether with our own ardent passion we are able to create such a powerful general organization. What is needed here is an amount of good will and freedom from bias. We Poles rush at new things and undertakings with precipitation and with no less haste drop them again. We hope sincerely that this new society will come to the right road at once and will meet in accord with the good wishes of all citizens of Polish descent.</p>
   <p>We find ourselves surrounded by various nationalities. Every one of them tends to the consolidation of its own powers. Each one is trying to improve the meaning of their co-brothers in all fields of social life. As among individuals so among nationalities there exists a certain powerful rivalry that puts forth its own kind for higher offices, <pb facs="5423968_3_1122.jpg" n="4"/>acquiring greater influence in politics, occupying as many government offices as possible, likewise social,cultural, commercial, and business positions, - here you have the problem of every individual nationality. In this march of rivalry toward a better future, the citizens of Polish descent cannot occupy a passive position. On the contrary, they must extend all of their strength, so as not to let others precede them. Properly speaking, we have remained far behind others in many things. We must now redouble our strength in order to catch up with them, and to stand in an even line.</p>
   <p>If the convention of the Polish Fellowship League of Illinois will comprehend this gigantic problem, it can become a great factor in bringing forth the Polish power.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
