<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-09">Sept. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Go to the Polls</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-09">Sept. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GO TO THE POLLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By the time this issue of Zwiazkowy reaches you, many of you, no doubt, will have done your duty and others will be about to go out to cast their votes. Still others will not have voted and will have no intention of doing so.</p>
   <p>On election day you are free to do as you please with your vote. You may vote or refrain from voting. "For refraining from voting," as a smart aleck, who thinks that he knows everything, said yesterday, "no one will be put into jail."</p>
   <p>It is obvious that for refraining from voting on the day of the primaries or the election, no one will be brought before the judge; but on the other hand, a citizen, man or woman, who has the right to vote and does not go to the polls to perform this duty should not complain later when dirt, swindling, graft, and bribery crop up in the circles of the elected politicians.</p>
   <p>It is especially the duty of Polish voters to take advantage of the right to vote, <pb facs="5423968_3_1770.jpg" n="2"/>because there is no nationality in America which enjoys less political influence than the Poles and there is no nationality for which such influence in American politics, especially at the present time, is of such great importance. Therefore go to the polls and help by your vote to nominate this or that candidate.</p>
   <p>Here is another thing: Zwiazkowy, as the semi-official organ of the Polish National Alliance, supports no party, declares itself to be for none, but merely wants to emphasize that the Poles should in the first place support Polish candidates. On this premise Zwiazkowy yesterday published the names of all Polish candidates, regardless of party and party factions. In publishing the names of the Polish candidates, through an error we omitted the name of candidate Walter Schrojda, who is running for the office of Ward Committeeman of the Sixteenth Ward on the Republican ticket. Therefore we are pleased to add this name to the list published yesterday.</p>
   <p>Zwiazkowy cannot and may not support any American political party, but it can voice a few remarks which it considers just.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1771.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The voters, whose only power is the poll, should understand that they must not vote for grafters and protectors of the moral decay in which the city of Chicago and its environs are immersed up to their neck. Chicago for the past few years has been America's center of moral decay and the scandals which have been noted in the past few months should teach everyone that every citizen, man and woman, should protest with his vote against nominating for office protectors of vice, grafters, and acceptors of bribes. It is high time that the voters cried, "Away with graft and bribes!"</p>
   <p>There are an unusually large number of candidates supported by grafters and all sorts of bribe seekers, running for office this year, thanks to the powerful influence of organized vice and bribery. In some districts silver and gold are flowing in streams. They are taken from sources of very questionable moral value and showered upon voting hyenas of the worst order to help them push their own candidates through. Later these candidates, having been elected to office, show their gratitude by closing their eyes to the disgraceful prevalence of vice.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1772.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The people have the right and the duty to watch carefully to see to it that bad and debase people who pay homage to vice and bribery do not get political offices.</p>
   <p>"To watch" means to go to the polls to vote against them. "To watch" means to vote early in order not to lose one's vote by chance. "To watch" means to vote for candidates whose honesty and impeccability cannot be doubted.</p>
   <p>Watch then--because the elections depend on the primaries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
