<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-15">Aug. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Great Meeting of Polish Central Democratic Committee Held at Hotel Sherman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-15">Aug. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT MEETING OF POLISH CENTRAL DEMOCRATIC COMMITTEE HELD AT HOTEL SHERMAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish Democrats of all factions gathered at the Italian Hall in Hotel Sherman yesterday evening to hear their own candidates and other candidates on the Democratic ticket speak. The well-known Democratic leader, Roger C. Sullivan also participated in the meeting. The meeting maintained a very high patriotic level; it fairly breathed with the sincere attachment of our people to this country. Alderman S. Adamkiewicz was not present, as he had to attend a very important session of the city council concerning unification of the traction system.</p>
   <p>From a political point of view, credit must be given to the organizers of the meeting and to Sullivan, for they know how to appeal to the Polish voters in order to gain their support. However, they went too far in many cases, for their speeches reflected too great a desire to show the Polish people how generously offices have been distributed amongst Poles, how good the party is <pb facs="5423968_3_0673.jpg" n="2"/>to the Poles, and how liberally it bestows well-paying positions upon them. Roger Sullivan praised beautifully the ambition of the Poles when he declared that, were he not Irish, he would like to be a Pole. Naturally, he emphasized his own purely altruistic desire to serve the public cause, and he gave his assurance that the whole ticket is composed of men in whose victory lies the welfare of the general public.</p>
   <p>Other speakers reached such heights as to declare it positively unpatriotic to vote for candidates other than those on the Democratic ticket, since this would weaken President Wilson, who is a Democrat, and therefore desires the Democratic party's victory. It was not omitted also, to point out to the Polish people that the organization knows the normal Polish vote, and if the Poles should be disobedient, then naturally they cannot count upon the unlimited beneficence of Mr. Sullivan and his adherents in the future, and will be defeated.</p>
   <p>In answer, Dziennik Zwiazkowy, as a Polish organ standing guard over the interests <pb facs="5423968_3_0674.jpg" n="3"/>of our people without regard to party affiliation, takes occasion to point out in advance that the Polish people will not uncritically follow the dictates of even the best laid plans, but will examine the qualifications of each candidate, and look into his guarantees that he can serve the country and the people best.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we take this occasion to protest most vigorously against this manner of treating us. The Polish voters are not a collection of thoughtless childrens' dolls, but an enlightened, thinking people who appraise critically the course of events. Even the "juicy sinecure," as they call it, that is offered F. X. Rydzewski, who can count upon our support because of his capability and the fact that he is Polish, will not blind us to the principal candidates in the coming elections. Sullivan can well know that the congressman from the Eighth District should be a Pole, and yet his organization is not openly supporting Francis Koraleski, Polish candidate for this office; in order not to offend President Wilson, he would like to retain as Congressman from the Eighth District, Thomas Gallagher, an incapable and insignificant politician, instead <pb facs="5423968_3_0675.jpg" n="4"/>of supporting an intelligent and capable man such as Koraleski is, beyond question. The resolution adopted at yesterday's meeting ineffably shows that in the inner Democratic circles, Koraleski will be opposed under a cloak of patriotism and an abuse of the name of President Wilson, whom our people surround with the greatest honor. In this way, they expect to establish a pathway through the Polish voters through which Gallagher can be re-elected. And to us they will say, "Clap hands; you have Rydzewski, Kasperski, and Nowak," while Gallagher, in order to flatter his constituents, will mention Poland in his bungling way once in a while, and will continue to fatten himself on a job that rightfully belongs to us.</p>
   <p>For President Wilson's great heart, the Polish people gave their hearts, their blood, and their money. They have done their patriotic duty in every way. They intend to use their right to vote in such a way as to give President Wilson such men whom they regard as best qualified for public service.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0676.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Polish Democratic Candidates</p>
   <p>The following Polish candidates should be supported to the fullest extent in the coming primaries:</p>
   <p>The incumbent, Judge Joseph S. LaBuy, of tried character, who brings honor to the high office he occupies.</p>
   <p>Stanley Walkowiak, alderman of the 17th Ward, who enjoys great popularity, running for judge.</p>
   <p>Francis X. Rydzewski, candidate for clerk of the municipal court, incumbent election commissioner, a man who has a fine record of public service behind him, and who will undoubtedly fulfill properly his tasks as municipal court clerk,if elected.</p>
   <p>Four candidates for county commissioner: Albert Nowak, Thomas Kasperski, <pb facs="5423968_3_0677.jpg" n="6"/>Anthony Maciejewski, and Paul Damradt. Everyone will undoubtedly support them and thus put these offices in good hands.</p>
   <p>Vincent S. Zwiefka, former alderman of the 16th Ward, who seeks the nomination for state representative. He is young and active and has a record of service and civic courage. He deserves the public's confidence.</p>
   <p>Above all, remember that we need</p>
   <p>A POLISH CONGRESSMAN!</p>
   <p>This evening, Max Kaczmarek, who seeks the Republican nomination for congressman of the eighth district, will speak at a Republican mass meeting to be held at the Republican headquarters on Noble Street and Milwaukee Avenue. The meeting will be especially interesting, and a large attendance is expected. It will begin at eight o'clock.</p>
   <p>The Polish Central Democratic Committee sent the following telegram to President <pb facs="5423968_3_0678.jpg" n="7"/>Wilson:</p>
   <p>"To His Excellency, Woodrow Wilson, President of the United States, Washington, D. C.:</p>
   <p>"The Polish Central Democratic Committee of Cook County, Illinois, gathered here in convention on Wednesday, August 14, 1918, at the Hotel Sherman in Chicago, hereby extends its sincerest belief that your immortal work in connection with the World War will be rewarded with a great victory for humanity and will bring a lasting peace to America, the Allies, and the small nations of Europe, and justice to unfortunate Poland, plundered and starved by the brutal Huns. With your aid, Poland will shake off the chains of a hundred and fifty years of slavery and, in the new history of Poland, your famed name will be the source of inspiration to future generations.</p>
   <p>"We shall support, with all enthusiasm, the Honorable James Hamilton Lewis, that capable and distinguished Senator from Illinois. He will be re-elected as a <pb facs="5423968_3_0679.jpg" n="8"/>proof of the people's confidence in you and your excellent administration.</p>
   <p>"In the eighth congressional district of Illinois, the Poles have chosen as their candidate, Francis W. Koraleski. In 1912 he was delegate to the electoral college from this district, and if he is elected to the office of congressman, we are convinced that he will gain your confidence completely, and will be an earnest supporter of your policies.</p>
   <p>"Stanley Adamkiewicz, president,</p>
   <p>"Joseph Ruszkiewicz, vice-president,</p>
   <p>"Joseph A. Lasecki, secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
