<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-01">Nov. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Poles Honor Carter H. Harrison</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions of Condolence Prepared</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-01">Nov. 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO POLES HONOR CARTER H. HARRISON</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions of Condolence Prepared</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In accordance with the announcement made by the Polish Citizen's Committee, a meeting was held yesterday at the St. Stanislaus Kostka School Hall for the purpose of determining what part the Poles will take in the funeral of Carter H. Harrison, Mayor of Chicago, who was assassinated [on Saturday, October 28]</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vincent Barzynski opened the meeting, which was attended by more than a hundred people, and was elected chairman. Judge [M. A.] LaBuy was secretary.</p>
   <p>Because of the limited time and the unexpectedly large gathering, it was decided that the first thing to do was to prepare resolutions of condolence, expressing the sympathy of the Polish people of Chicago to the bereaved <pb facs="5423968_3_1272.jpg" n="2"/>family. The resolutions will be submitted to the newspapers.</p>
   <p>The resolutions, which were duly <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> by a committee consisting of J. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and accepted unanimously by the gathering, read as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Polish citizenry of Chicago hereby expresses its deepest sorrow and highest indignation at the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the death of its friend, Carter H. Harrison, Mayor of Chicago, at the hands of a maniac; the news is tragic indeed, for it comes on the eve of what was to have been a great occasion--the closing of the World's Columbian Exposition.</p>
   <p>"The Polish citizenry of Chicago wishes to pay homage to the late Mayor for the many occasions on which he has shown himself its friend, and desires to unite itself with the rest of Chicago's citizens for their noble and splendid leader; in these resolutions, the Polish citizens of Chicago wish <pb facs="5423968_3_1273.jpg" n="3"/>to express their highest <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for this great man, of whose good will and friendship they were so proud.</p>
   <p>"Finally, the Polish citizenry of Chicago hereby expresses its deepest sympathy to the bereaved members of the late Carter <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. Harrison's family."</p>
   <p>The gathering also decided that the funeral ought to be attended by the greatest possible number of Poles. An announcement will be published in Dziennik [Chicagoski] urging all societies, especially military societies, to participate. The <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> troop, organized for Polish Day, will also take part. All participants will were <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> [arm bands] and music will be supplied if necessary. Further information can be had at the mass meeting to be held tonight at the St. Stanislaus Kostka School Hall.</p>
   <p>A committee to take charge of the music consisted of B. Klarkowski, E. Roland, <pb facs="5423968_3_1274.jpg" n="4"/>and J. Czekala. Bieszke was appointed to distribute <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> arm bands, and Judge LaBuy entrusted with the task of notifying the city clerk, at nine o'clock this morning, of the Poles' intention of participating in the funeral. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
