<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 15,
<date when="1902-03-09">March 9, 1902</date><title level="a">"Remarks"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 15,
<date when="1902-03-09">March 9, 1902</date><title level="a">"Remarks"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Municipal League took under consideration the qualifications of state representatives for their office. It seems that many of our lawmakers in Springfield are very meagerly equipped mentally and inadequately prepared educationally for the important office that the people elect them for. The state representative should know absolutely more than "how to mend shoes or wash the glassware." It wouldn't interfere with proper and efficient performance of his assumed duty if the legislator had a better education and was making those occasionaltrips for legislative sessions in Springfield, not for the sake of the remuneration, but for the good he was able to do for his community.</p>
   <p>Because Poles elect few representatives to the state legislature it would be well to keep in mind that in future elections they should send men to represent them who are worthy of esteem and have a certain amount of education.</p>
   <p>Among our young people there are so many really capable individuals that we could easily elect proper candidates for political office.</p>
   <p>We, personally, know a few who are able to express themselves beautifully orally and in writing in both the English and Polish languages, who also take active part in patriotic and church activities, possess the <pb facs="5423968_3_1696.jpg" n="2"/>necessary qualifications; in short, they are energetic, active, earnest, willing workers for the good of the community. Only such people and no others should we send to the legislature because only they will be able to bring honor and glory to our Polish name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
