<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-08">Sept. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Tomorrow's Primaries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0758</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0758.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-08">Sept. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TOMORROW'S PRIMARIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have several times in the past published, for the benefit of our readers, lists of the candidates running for various offices in the present election. We have done this for the purpose of acquainting the Polish voters with our candidates and helping them orient themselves in preparation for voting at tomorrow's primaries.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that our countrymen, in doing their duty as citizens of this country, will, when the opportunity is offered, cast their votes for Poles, and will vote for only those candidates of other nationalities who, either by their public work up to the present or by their friendly attitude towards the Poles and Polish matters, deserve the support of the Poles.</p>
   <p>This year we have an unusual list of Polish candidates, representing all of the political parties. The Poles should support their candidates whenever they can and should give them their votes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0759.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to elect the greatest number of Polish candidates, we must all go as one man to the polls tomorrow and vote for Polish candidates. Any qualified voter who does not cast his vote tomorrow should not call himself a Pole. Everyone who has the right to vote must and should vote tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Polish. Candidates for Congress</p>
   <p>Joseph P. Gorecki, residing at 2241 Marshall Boulevard, Republican candidate for Representative of the Fourth District.</p>
   <p>Joseph Mendrzycki, residing at 1045 West 32nd Place, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Fourth District.</p>
   <p>Ignace F. Dankowski of St. Adalbert's Parish, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Fifth District.</p>
   <p>Dr. E. F. Napieralski, candidate of the Progressive Party for Representative <pb facs="5423968_3_0760.jpg" n="3"/>of the Fifth District.</p>
   <p>Joseph L. Lisak, a young and energetic lawyer, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Seventh District.</p>
   <p>John Czekala, former Alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Eighth District.</p>
   <p>Stanley Kunz, present Alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, opponent of Czekala, Democratic candidate for Representative of the same District.</p>
   <p>Albert J. Danisch for Representative at Large on the Democratic ticket. (The entire State of Illinois has the opportunity to vote for Mr. Danisch, and for this reason all of the Polish voters of the entire State of Illinois should cast their votes for him.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0761.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Polish Candidates for the State Legislature</p>
   <p>Johs S. Rybicki, young lawyer of St. Adalbert's Parish, the Republican candidate without opposition for Senator from the Fifteenth District.</p>
   <p>Walter Orlikowski, the only Polish candidate for Senator from the Twenty-third District, Democrat.</p>
   <p>Walter Herman, lawyer of St. Casimir's Parish, running on the Democratic ticket for Representative of the Ninth District.</p>
   <p>Francis Chamski of South Chicago, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Ninth District.</p>
   <p>John J. Sulski, Democratic candidate for Representative of this same District.</p>
   <p>Joseph Spiker of Kensington, Republican candidate for Representative of the <pb facs="5423968_3_0762.jpg" n="5"/>Thirteenth District.</p>
   <p>Walter Laskowski, of St. Adalbert's Parish, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Fifteenth District.</p>
   <p>Peter Kielminski, also of St. Adalbert's Parish, running for the same office on the Democratic ticket.</p>
   <p>Walter Pietras, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Nineteenth District.</p>
   <p>Paul Schmidt, residing at 2433 West Division Street, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Twenty-third District.</p>
   <p>Peter H. Schwaba of Avondale, a young lawyer, Democratic candidate for Representative of the Twenty-fifth District.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0763.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Feliks Wilkowski of St. Hedwig's Parish, also Democratic candidate for this same office in District Twenty-five.</p>
   <p>John Remus, Republican candidate for Representative of the Twenty-fifth District.</p>
   <p>Albert Rostenkowski, Republican candidate for Representative of the Twenty-seventh District. (Mr. Rostenkowski is now occupying this office and has fulfilled his duties well. Having no opponent, he is assured of re-election.)</p>
   <p>Joseph Pittlock, Francis Kortas, Joseph Trandel, and Bruno Mindak, Democratic candidates for Representative of the Twenty-seventh District.</p>
   <p>Walter Gieldzinski, Progressive candidate for Representative of the Twenty-seventh District.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0764.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Polish Candidates for the Municipal Court Bench</p>
   <p>The Poles in Chicago have too small a representation in the municipal court. At present we have only two judges of our nationality: Judge Edmund K. Jarecki and Judge Joseph La Buy. In the present primaries three Poles are seeking nomination and all three should receive it. Every Pole, man and woman, going to the polls in Chicago should remember that there are three Polish names on the ballots, as candidates for judge: Edmund K. Jarecki, Stanley S. Walkowiak, and John Przystalski. Let all Poles check the ballot before the names of these three candidates. All three have the support of political machines: Jarecki and Walkowiak are from Sullivan's party: Przystalski is supported by Harrison's faction.</p>
   <p>Polish Candidates for Important County Offices:</p>
   <p>For the first time in many years a Pole is running for the important office of County Treasurer. This office is not meaningless: it is probably the <pb facs="5423968_3_0765.jpg" n="8"/>best of all the county offices. The candidate is Mr. Francis Koraleski, the present County Assessor. Koraleski has the support of the Czechs and the Jews and many votes of other nationalities. The votes of other nationalities will be divided because six other candidates are running for this office and, for this reason, all Polish votes should go in a bloc to Koraleski.</p>
   <p>Walter Armknecht, Republican candidate for Clerk of the Criminal Court, enjoys great support among the Poles and among other nationalities. Francis Szarkowski seeks nomination for the same office on the Democratic ticket. Medard Kunz seeks nomination as Clerk of the Appelate Court. Francis Rydzewski is the only Polish candidate for membership on the Board of Review.</p>
   <p>Three Polish candidates are seeking membership on the Drainage Canal Board on the Democratic ticket: Vincent S. Zwiefka, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. F. Talaczynski, and Henry Nowak. There are more than thirty Democratic candidates for this office and only three can be elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0766.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Sixteen Polish candidates are seeking nomination to the office of County Commissioner on the Democratic ticket. There are, in all 148 candidates of various nationalities seeking this nomination. Some of the Polish candidates stand a very good chance of being nominated. The names of some of them are:</p>
   <p>Stanley Kuflewski, Albert <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Dr. Victor Schiller, John Piotrowski, Francis Okon, Thomas Kasperski, Joseph <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Miss, Bernard Petka, Michael Kolassa, and Michael Dominowski.</p>
   <p>Several Poles are running for the office of Ward Committeeman. Joseph Ruszkiewicz and Stanley Kielczynski are running in Ward Seventeen. Ruszkiewicz will probably get the nomination because he enjoys the widespread support of both the men and the women voters.</p>
   <p>In Ward Sixteen two Polish candidates are running on the Democratic ticket, Walter Mazurek and Francis Truschki, and on the Republican ticket John Rybcinski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0767.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Andrew Plocinski and Michael Dominowski are running for the office of Committeeman in Ward Twenty-seven.</p>
   <p>Women can vote at the primaries on September 9, for the following:</p>
   <p>Clerk of the Appelate Court, state committeemen, senatorial committeemen, members of the Drainage Canal Board, assessors, members of the Board of Review, municipal judges, ward committeemen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
