<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-10">July 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Miserable Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-10">July 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">MISERABLE LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We all have vivid memories of the textile strike at Lawrence, Mass., and of other strike in many industrial cities of New England, where bloody battles took place; and we owe a debt of gratitude to the ruthless officials, brutal police and deputy sheriffs, who did not hesitate to injure and kill the unprotected strikers who were fighting for a livelihood. Just because of their wanton brutality this strike was brought to the attention of the entire country, and such indignation was aroused by the lawlessness of the police and militia, that shocked public opinion forced Congress to investigate the causes of the strike and to determine who was responsible for the bloody warfare.</p>
   <p>Under pressure of public opinion, Congress was compelled to carry out an investigation. This investigation was entrusted to a special committee, with Hon. Charles P. Neill, Secretary of Commerce and Labor, as the chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Congressional committee performed its task very satisfactorily, when it immediately made a thorough investigation. The committee heard both sides of the story from the many witnesses, and then presented its report to Congress.</p>
   <p>This report is very interesting, illustrating perfectly the conditions that exist in the textile factories, where the majority of the people employed are of foreign extraction; namely, Poles, Italians, Slovaks, Hungarians and Greeks.</p>
   <p>According to the report of the committee, which confirms the recommendations of Secretary Neill, the average income of a family, consisting of a husband, wife and several children, amounts to eight dollars and seventy-six cents per week, and that at a time when the factories are going full force.</p>
   <p>In many cases, a poor weaver was compelled to support a wife and two children on a weekly income of five dollars and ten cents. On these <pb facs="5423968_3_0060.jpg" n="3"/>starvation wages, 21,922 textile workers were forced to support their families.</p>
   <p>In one family a husband, wife, two sons, and three daughters were employed in one of these factories, and, pooling their earnings, they still were unable to live in comfort or to lay aside any savings. But there were many families where small children prevented a mother from working; therefore, the burden of supporting the family fell on the shoulders of a husband and father who was earning starvation wages. You can realize the kind of life that had to be lived by a family whose breadwinner earned but five or, at the utmost, six dollars per week. Even though there was plenty of work to be had, starvation existed in many families, because of such meager wages and the high cost of living.</p>
   <p>When Congress passed a law that women should not be employed in textile factories more than fifty-four hours per week, instead of fifty-six, the heartless employers immediately cut wages, taking advantage of the women <pb facs="5423968_3_0061.jpg" n="4"/>employees. This caused a strike, which the hirelings of the capitalists checked by the use of clubs, imprisonment, and bullets, killing poor innocent workers, and treating them like dangerous beasts, just because they demanded better living and working conditions.</p>
   <p>The report of the committee further confirmed the charge that boys as well as girls, not over fourteen years old, were employed in these murderous factories, instead of attending school and improving their education. Of these factories' employees, forty-four per cent are women and young girls. Let us imagine the misery that would exist if the mothers and girls were not employed, and a family had to rely exclusively on a father's starvation wages!</p>
   <p>This report, without a doubt, caused "great surprise" in Congress, as if the members did not know that such conditions existed in these factories, Why, many of them are textile manufacturers and exploiters of labor themselves. Will Congress do anything to remedy these conditions in the textile industry of the New England states? This is very doubtful. The <pb facs="5423968_3_0062.jpg" n="5"/>representatives of the people seem to think of everything but the improvement of the standard of living of the working masses.</p>
   <p>The one sure way the workers can improve their lot is by organizing into a united group; and then rejecting the capitalistic politicians. The workers must cast their votes for true representatives of the working class, because only a man of the people can understand the hardships of our modern slaves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
