<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 2,
<date when="1920-01-14">Jan. 14, 1920</date><title level="a">The Raids on the "Reds"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 2,
<date when="1920-01-14">Jan. 14, 1920</date><title level="a">THE RAIDS ON THE "REDS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American government is making raids in this country on the "reds" or radicals, Bolsheviks, Socialists, etc.</p>
   <p>Our government, seeing the fatal consequences of the Soviet rule in Russia, is trying to save our country from such misfortune while there is still time.</p>
   <p>This affair concerns every citizen of the United States, including ourselves, and that is why we devote so much of our time upon it.</p>
   <p>Why does out government raid private homes, arrest thousands of people, place them on the Soviet's ark and ship them to the "Sovietland?"</p>
   <p>DOes not the COnstitution of the United States allow every citizen to criticize high officials? Does the constitution of the United States <pb facs="5423968_3_0296.jpg" n="2"/>forbid to convince the American citizen that any individual at the head of the government is incapable if he is such?</p>
   <p>Only sick persons, anarchists, bigamists and a few others are forbidden to enter the United States; all the rest may stay here and voice their opinions, and here in the meantime the federal government arrests the "innocent" editors of Glos Robotniczy (Voice of the Workers) in Detroit, Mich., and probably will deport them to the Soviet Union.</p>
   <p>All this is true. Our government is liberal and patient, but it is also just.</p>
   <p>Our constitution does not forbid any one from convincing the citizens of this country that certain administrative acts are no good, but the constitution provides that the convincing should be accomplished by words, not by bombs or revolvers.</p>
   <p>The newcomer in this country should study the Constitution of the United <pb facs="5423968_3_0297.jpg" n="3"/>States before he starts to criticize our government.</p>
   <p>Some right-thinking Americans, and among them President Wilson, have expressed themselves that most of the dissatisfactions among the newcomers are caused through ignorance and lack of the understanding of our institutions.</p>
   <p>Among the raided Reds there are thousands who can neither read nor write; who do not know anything about our country, our constitution, or the language.</p>
   <p>They are dissatisfied because the think that this government is worthless like the one they left in Europe, a government of oppression, their enemy.</p>
   <p>It seems to them that in order to change our government, it is necessary to use the same means as are being used in the old Europe, that is, bombs, dynamite and bullets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0298.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>American has plenty of such radicals: Reds and Socialists. Those people think very little or do not think at all. They are under the influence of the real agitators, who know what they are doing and use the ignorant people for their purpose, whenever it is dangerous for themselves.</p>
   <p>The common people, blinded by Russian and German bolsheviks, are to be pitied. It would be wrong for our government to get rid of these people/ All is necessary is to separate them from the real Red leaders and agitators, especially the Jews, and then they will become good citizens.</p>
   <p>Today these people are blind and stubborn but not wise; they do not know that their leaders are Jews, germans and Russians. They do not suspect that their leaders are false, that they only pretend to be friends of the people; that they also claim falsely to have the welfare of the people at heart, when in reality they prey upon their pocketbooks.</p>
   <p>Who and what is the leader of the ignorant radicals for whom are the government agents are looking? He is an enlightened man who is well acquainted <pb facs="5423968_3_0299.jpg" n="5"/>with our form of government, but he does not like it and is trying to change it by persuading unenlightened people in American to start the revolution and establish a so-called "people's government."</p>
   <p>Those people are really responsible for their actions and they were placed by the United States government on the "Soviet's Ark," which will take them back where they belong.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
