<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Personal Appeal of Alderman S. S. Walkowiak to the Voters of the Seventeenth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PERSONAL APPEAL OF ALDERMAN S. S. WALKOWIAK TO THE VOTERS OF THE SEVENTEENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Citizens!</p>
   <p>On the eve of the aldermanic elections which will be held next Tuesday, I turn to you with a last appeal for the same sincere support you have given me in previous campaigns, and, at the same time, I want to present special reasons why I should be re-elected to the office I now hold, and to answer the unjust attacks that have recently been made against me.</p>
   <p>First: A year ago, I was instrumental in defeating the Republican alderman, L. Sitts, who had held that office for fourteen years, and thus made possible the election of our countryman, the incumbent Alderman Stanley Adamkiewicz. For my loyalty to my own nationality and for the support which I had given a Polish candidate, the so-called "Municipal Voters' League" was very uncomplimentary <pb facs="5423968_3_0684.jpg" n="2"/>to me in its report. Let the Poles be judges as to whether I deserved this condemnation.</p>
   <p>Second: That same Municipal Voters' League was in favor of abolishing the twenty-five-per-cent water tax. I opposed this action; I spoke and voted against it, for, in my opinion, abolishment of this tax would merely increase the tax burden on the less well-to-do citizens, bringing relief to the wealthy tax dodgers who evade paying their share of the taxes. If the tax dodgers paid this tax, there would be no necessity for new taxes on the smaller real-estate owners.</p>
   <p>Thirdly: The Municipal Voters' League is opposing me because I am a "wet," while the League is one of the principal organizations of the "drys". Personally, I do not drink alcoholic liquors, out as a representative of the Seventeenth Ward, I represent the majority of the citizens of that ward, and I know that the majority has no sympathy for the "drys". As long as the majority of the citizens of the Seventeenth Ward want me to co-operate with <pb facs="5423968_3_0685.jpg" n="3"/>the "wets," so long will I conduct myself accordingly, the Municipal Voters' League notwithstanding.</p>
   <p>Fourthly: I am opposed to the preachers and so-called "reformers" who would like to limit the freedom of our societies by passing restricting laws. The principal aim of this movement, among others, is the abolition of the so-called "special bar permits," by which, almost without exception, all our societies benefit. Our societies do not have large and well-furnished club buildings in which they could hold their dances and entertainments without "special bar permits". The proposed discrimination by the reformers against our societies is unjust. Our societies are entitled to some privileges, for they give aid to their members, they patriotically purchase Liberty Bonds and Thrift stamps, and they support the Red Cross and other national matters.</p>
   <p>Fifthly: Until this time, no announcement of my opponent's candidacy has appeared in the daily press, while it did appear in the organ of that organization of which I am fortunate enough to be a member. Now it is well known <pb facs="5423968_3_0686.jpg" n="4"/>that my opponent is not a member of that organization and certainly the first duty of its organ is to support its own members. I do not want to name that organization, for the responsibility does not fall upon it but upon certain individuals. I expect all the members of that organization to ignore the announcement, as it justly deserves.</p>
   <p>Sixthly: In conclusion, I want to emphasize that in performing my duties as alderman, I do not believe that I should allow myself to be directed by suggestions from the Municipal Voters' League, since it is not from them that I have my mandate, but from the citizens of the Seventeenth Ward, for whom I have worked honestly and sincerely as their representative in the City Council, and as a representative of the Polish national group.</p>
   <p>I expect that the Polish citizens of the Seventeenth Ward will not disappoint me and that they will, in general, give me their active support on election day, Tuesday, May 2, and will, as one man, go to the polling places and vote in accordance with the specimen ballot below.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0687.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For all previous support as well as the support I expect will be given me in the coming elections, I thank my countrymen, and I assure them that I will always serve them faithfully.</p>
   <p>I take this occasion to remind you that, in accordance with federal law, clocks will be moved ahead one hour starting Sunday, and that polling places will be opened and closed on the new time, which is one hour earlier.</p>
   <p>I also take this occasion to express my best wishes for a happy Easter to all the voters of the Seventeenth Ward.</p>
   <p>Your Countryman,</p>
   <p>Stanley S. Walkowiak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
