<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-26">Mar. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Stanislaus Kunz, Candidate for Alderman of the Sixteenth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1719</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1719.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-26">Mar. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">STANISLAUS KUNZ, CANDIDATE FOR ALDERMAN OF THE SIXTEENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The future alderman of the Sixteenth Ward should be none other than Stanislaus Kunz, present alderman and well-known Pole of Chicago. All Poles of the Sixteenth Ward must agree upon this.</p>
   <p>No matter what their political affiliations may be, or what personal sympathies they may hold, they ought to vote for Mr. Kunz because he is a Pole. If they act otherwise they will elect a German, George C. Lenke--thereby acting directly against their own interests, and the national solidarity will be betrayed.</p>
   <p>At the present time our ward has two Polish aldermen. [Translator's note: under the old setup there were two representatives from each ward in the City Council.] Relinquishment of these offices to Germans should not be permitted, for they oppress our countrymen. [Translator's note: Specific reference is made to the Germans or Swabians of Swabia or Schwaben--a province of Germany.] There is no alternative. He who is a Pole will vote for a Pole.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1720.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is only too well known to us that our enemies are capable of intrigue. As a consequence such persons will work against their own kind for the gain of a few dollars. Such persons should be driven away and their damaging whisperings ignored.</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Kunz has worked hard to get his name established in the Sixteenth Ward; he has many friends and holds office in many organizations. Because of his abilities and activities he deserves to be re-elected. But even such people as he, through being in the public limelight, have enemies who do not stint to flay and cast slander at them.</p>
   <p>Such calumny, which is directed at diverting the people's interest, will be treated in the future issues of the Dziennik Chicagoski. A biographical sketch of Mr. Kunz will also be given, from which you all will be convinced that he is just as sincere a Pole as any of us.</p>
   <p>In the meantime we say: Vote for Kunz! Do not listen to Schwabian agitators.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
