<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-09-12">Sept. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution of the 26Th Ward Non-Fartisan Polise Citizens' Club of the Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-09-12">Sept. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION OF THE 26TH WARD NON-FARTISAN POLISE CITIZENS' CLUB OF THE TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, the Poles and citizens residing in the Town of lake vicinity, are aware of our duties concerning Polish politics in Chicago, and have come to the conclusion, that without co-operation we are unable to reap any benefits. Because of this fact, we decided at our last meeting of September 8, 1912, to organize and to co-operate for the mutual good of local politics and the Polish element of Chicago, without malice toward anyone because of any previous hardships that we may have suffered in battling the politicians of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Taking into consideration the fact that by splitting up into different political groups we are hurting only ourselves and get no political consideration from politicians of other nationalities, we have voted unanimously on the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>1. To support all the Polish candidates without regard to their party affiliation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1172.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. We assume that it is the duty of every good Polish-American citizen, irrespective of personal prejudice and grievances toward the Polish candidates, to vote for them and support them materially, if they need it.</p>
   <p>3. We must prevent our Polish candidates who are aspiring for office, from appearing on different political party ballots, because it is harmful not only to such candidates, but to the Polish element in general, and deprives us of political influence. We realize also that by voting in unison, we will be better able to boost our Polish candidates to higher and more important political positions, and demand the recognition of other nationalities, which will be impressed by our strong Polish vote.</p>
   <p>4. We indorse and recommend all Polish candidates aspiring for political offices in the election of November 5, 1912.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1173.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among the candidates the following deserve special mention: C. J. Tomkiewicz, for Congressman of the 4th Congressional District; Frank P. Danisch, for clerk of the Municipal Court; Dr. <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Napieralski, for coroner; Joseph LaBuy, for Judge of the Municipal Court; Stanislaus Kuflewski, for County Commissioner; Albert Nowak, for County Commissioner; <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Armknecht, for County Commissioner; S. J. <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for elector of the Progressive Party.</p>
   <p>Sincerely,</p>
   <p>Resolutions Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
