<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 260,
<date when="1908-11-05">Nov. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Socialists in America Polish Social-Democrats in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 260,
<date when="1908-11-05">Nov. 5, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIALISTS IN AMERICA POLISH SOCIAL-DEMOCRATS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the Polish Socialists' Alliance in America became a fractional faction; if the Aid Alliance of the Polish Socialist Party has a right to exist; then, why should not the section of Polish socialists called Social-Democrats of the Polish Kingdom and Lithuania, also have a right to exist?</p>
   <p>The Polish Social-Democrats of Poland need material help for revolutionary purposes; therefore, the partisans of that organization organized a separate section of Polish Social-Democrats of the Polish Kingdom and Lithuania on American soil, which is only a branch of that organization. In a similar way the adherents of the Polish Socialist Party may organize another new faction called the Polish Socialist Proletariat.</p>
   <p>Later the comrades who came from the Austrian part of Poland called Galicia, might also form another section of Polish socialists and call themselves the Polish Socialists of Galicia. Then the comrades who emigrated from the German part of Poland called Prussian Poland, might organize and call their branch the Polish Social Democratic Party of Germany; and in that way the entire Polish socialist community in America will be split and divided.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0398.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such a phenomenon is injurious, for instead of uniting and reconciling, it irritates and divides the working masses; and this will be admitted by any comrade after brief consideration.</p>
   <p>All of these organizations and petty organizations have a concrete foundation, they are built on "old country quick sand" and, therefore, lose their bearings and fall down.</p>
   <p>All those factional organizations, like the Polish Socialists' Alliance, lead a very poor existence in America. Being separated since the revolution in Poland, they are lost - wandering to and fro.</p>
   <p>It is a good time to rid ourselves of idle dreams; to free ourselves from the influence of old country factions and to form an independent socialistic organization in the territory where we must exist, driven by fate from all parts of our divided country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
