<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-31">Mar. 31, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title><title level="a" type="sub">Last Night's Polish Political Meeting (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-31">Mar. 31, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Last Night's Polish Political Meeting (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the heavy rain, thousands of Poles gathered at the Polish hall on Bradley Street to hear Senator Palmer. Such order, such attention, such respect for the speakers, aside from the great enthusiasm of the thousands of Polish citizens has probably never been seen at any hall where Senator Palmer has spoken or will speak during the coming week. All of the gentlemen, officials and representatives who were present at that hall last night could see that the Poles in Chicago are politically awake, that it would be advantageous to gain their support and that their influence can not be ignored.</p>
   <p>We have our representative in the State Legislature at Springfield, [one of the Cook County commissioners is a Pole] and at present there are indications that we will be represented in the City Hall and the City Council. From what <pb facs="5423968_3_1057.jpg" n="2"/>we saw last night we may say that the situation is very encouraging and the outcome depends on ourselves.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Mr. A. J. Kowalski who asked Mr. W. Bardonski, a County commissioner to act as chairman. He appointed a secretary and read the list of vice chairmen who occupied seats on the platform. These were the most prominent citizens of our community.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cregier, the present Mayor appeared at the hall greeted by a burst of applause which indicated his popularity among the Polish element: it also showed that the Poles desire his re-election and will vote for him on the 7th of April.</p>
   <p>The first speaker was Mr. Kiolbassa, who was greeted and continually interrupted by applause. Our candidate discussed the importance of the nomination of a Pole for the office of city treasurer by the regular Democratic convention. He was very modest and did not claim credit for the honor bestowed upon him; he said that it was due to the fact that the Poles are gaining influence in <pb facs="5423968_3_1058.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago, and that this influence would grow in proportion to the number of Poles elected to public office.</p>
   <p>With reference to other Democratic candidates, Mr. Kiolbassa pointed out that the Poles have never held as many offices in Chicago as they have during the administration of Cregier. He did not praise or condemn any candidate but stated the facts on which the Poles should depend in order to vote.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kiolbassa also spoke about his own opponents who attack him with silly and sarcastic comments, but have failed to bring any serious charge against him or to prove anything detrimental to his candidacy.</p>
   <p>Those present indicated their love and respect by heartily applauding Mr. Kiobassa.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Stanley Kunz, a candidate for alderman in the Sixteenth Ward, who spoke in Polish about the growing influence of the Polish element <pb facs="5423968_3_1059.jpg" n="4"/>in Chicago and the significance of that influence for the Polish people. His speech was interrupted by the entrance of Senator John M. Palmer.</p>
   <p>It would be impossible to describe the great enthusiasm displayed by the crowd and the applause which greeted this popular statesman and representative of democracy.</p>
   <p>Many had lost hope of seeing him for there were rumors that he was ill, and so everyone was delighted when he appeared on the platform.</p>
   <p>The Senator's speech was significant and convincing, but it was too long to reproduce in toto. However we will endeavor in the near future to outline the important points.</p>
   <p>The Senator declared that he was rewarded for his appearance in Chicago in spite of his illness, because of the opportunity given him to defend the <pb facs="5423968_3_1060.jpg" n="5"/>principles of the Demoratic party which he represents, and to help gain a victory over the Republican party which has no principles. He is ill but stays at a hotel in Chicago instead of a hospital in Springfield, because he considers himself a soldier whom even illness cannot prevent from participating in the struggle.</p>
   <p>He enunciated the lofty principles of the Democratic party and declared that solidarity would mean victory. He stated that he is taking an active part in this fight because he realizes that if the Democratic ticket is defeated, the entire Democratic party and he himself will also be beaten.</p>
   <p>We will also publish in a few days the most important points of Mr. Cregier's speech which will clarify this fight and expose the unjust attacks made against the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>Other statesmen from Springfield also spoke. Congressman Springer's speech was very humorous, but on the other hand the speech of Joseph A. O'Donnel, who as an Irishman understands and sympathizes with the Poles, was rather serious.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1061.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Other speakers followed including Mr. Jan Kwasigroch, and Mr. E. Z. Brodowski, who spoke of the need for unity in supporting our Democratic and Polish candidates. Mr. Kunz then concluded his interrupted speech which provoked great enthusiasm. The meeting was closed by Mr. August Kozlowski, a well-known citizen, who delivered a short but very eloquent speech.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
