<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-16">May 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Swift and His Broken Promises</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-16">May 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">MR. SWIFT AND HIS BROKEN PROMISES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An article bearing this title was received by us from one of the Polish Republicans, and reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Mr. Swift, prior to the elections, contacted all the wards of the city, attended meetings held by the various nationalities, and begged, pleaded and cried for votes, promising that he would distribute city positions impartially, according to the political influence of each nationality.</p>
   <p>"He wrote letters to a couple of outstanding Polish Republican leaders, requesting an audience with them. He conferred with them, and urged them to campaign for him. Finally, he solemnly promised that he would not forget about them and their friends after the election.</p>
   <p>"At the final mass meeting before the elections, held at the Holy Trinity <pb facs="5423968_3_1554.jpg" n="2"/>Parish hall, which was filled to capacity, Mr. Swift said in his speech that it would please him no end if on the following day he read in the papers that the entire Sixteenth Ward, which was always Democratic, unanimously voted straight Republican--and that he would make an effort to see that this ward would always remain in the Republican ranks, or at least as long as he was in office.</p>
   <p>"Practically everything--to the misfortune of the Democrats--happened just as Mr. Swift desired.</p>
   <p>"Did Mr. Swift keep at least one of these promises? No! Mayor Swift not only disregarded all promises made to the Polish people, but what is worse he not only humiliated them but slandered the Poles at large, saying to the delegation [a delegation of Polish Republicans paid the Mayor of Chicago (Swift) a visit relative to getting positions in the administration, Saturday, May 11], <pb facs="5423968_3_1555.jpg" n="3"/>in the presence of a large crowd, that the Poles are not fit for anything else "but the pick and shovel."</p>
   <p>"This is evidence of the great ignorance of Mayor Swift, evidence of his unfamiliarity with the history and accomplishment of the Polish nation, and, finally, proof of his insolence.</p>
   <p>"Mayor Swift is free to break his word, free to ignore regularities, free to issue offices according to his desires, and he is even free to omit the Poles in this respect and give them nothing. But he is not free to treat the Poles, as a nationality, as he did.</p>
   <p>"The delegation representing the Polish Republicans did not represent the entire Polish people in the world or in America, or even in Chicago; therefore, Mayor Swift had no right to insult the entire Polish nationality in his reply <pb facs="5423968_3_1556.jpg" n="4"/>to the delegation. If Mr. Swift was only familiar with the history of the United States, he would not have made such a remark about the Polish people, who were the first, in the past as now, to fight for the protection of civilization and freedom.</p>
   <p>"Who were the forefathers of Mr. Swift, and what were they doing when Washington, Kosciusko, Pulaski, and others were fighting against England for the freedom and independence of this country?</p>
   <p>"Who is this Mr. Swift, who dares to insult a nation whose deeds are written in the history of the world? Mr. Swift was a ward politician for twenty years; he always worked energetically in his hunt for political offices, and for twenty years stood beside the city manger (sic). These are the qualifications which have placed Mr. Swift in the highest municipal position.</p>
   <p>"No wonder, after gaining the mayoralty chair, that he does not even give a <pb facs="5423968_3_1557.jpg" n="5"/>thought to his promises, that he thinks that he is free to tread on everyone and everything that does not belong exclusively to the A.P.A. [American Protective Association] But let Mr. Swift never think that we Poles will permit him to step on our heads.....Never!</p>
   <p>Louis Roland".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
