<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-15">Mar. 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Has 200,000 Unemployed</title><title level="a" type="sub">American Sentiment against European Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-15">Mar. 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO HAS 200,000 UNEMPLOYED</title><title level="a" type="sub">American Sentiment Against European Workers</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Industrial relations statistics reveal that Chicago has an army of 200,000 unemployed. Conditions in this country are becoming worse. American sentiment is growing against foreign tradesmen in this country. Away with alien workers has become a byword. It is estimated that there are about 2,000,000 without work in the United States.</p>
   <p>Previous to this, when America began to notice the marked increase in unemployment, it was believed that this condition arose from an entirely different source. American wealth, based, on the average earnings of the average worker, is on the increase. The earning power is gradually growing, according to statistics, From the years 1919 to 1925 mass production in this country has increased 28.6 per cent, the workers' wages have increased 8.4 per cent. Other sources show that the individual work of the factory hand in industry has increased by 40.7 per cent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0190.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Government computations, show that from 1925 the country's industry has employed 774,000 less workers. This is a marked increase since 1919. Investigation carried by the government in this direction, discloses that machinery produces a great deal more work than the worker did originally. Production is manufacturing increased greatly because the machines can do the work quicker. This in many cases did away with from one to fifteen workers, whose need in industry becomes less important. In other words, out of a population of 118,628,000 there are 8,226,054 out of work.</p>
   <p>The sentiment of the American citizen is beginning to grow against the alien worker in America because of these statistics. He considers him a competitor. In Chicago, this feeling is becoming more pronounced every day. It is his contention that the foreigner is not as productive, yet he draws the same salary.</p>
   <p>Oppose Alien Workers</p>
   <p>According to completed tabulation in relation to the employment of foreigners, <pb facs="5423968_3_0191.jpg" n="3"/>250,000 alien persons are employed by te railroads, 200,000 work in mines, and thousands in other branches of industry. On studying the present situation, one must take cognizance of a new army of workers, the young people finishing school. One must also bear in mind the constant flow of Mexican and Canadian immigrants into this country. This source is creating a situation for American Society. How are we to combat this growth of alien workers?</p>
   <p>The people, therefore, are turning their interest to Congress to forestall this alien invasion. Congress, however, offers no solution nor help. Our representatives admit, although they give heed to most of the demands of the people, that they are helpless in this respect. Meanwhile, the aliens from the border countries keep pouring into the United States. This flow is not greatly desired by the average citizen.</p>
   <p>Figures Do Not Lie.</p>
   <p>The American people are alarmed by the constant growth of unemployment, becoming powerless as each day increases it. There is no country today having as <pb facs="5423968_3_0192.jpg" n="4"/>heavy a burden of unemployed masses as the United States.</p>
   <p>These statistics show that the number of unemployed persons has been steadily increasing since 1919. The production of the individual worker is becoming smaller with each passing day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
