<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-19">July 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Growing Political Activity of Chicago Poles]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-19">July 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[GROWING POLITICAL ACTIVITY OF CHICAGO POLES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski can proudly state that from the time of its inception an entirely new political life has developed among the Poles in Chicago than had existed previously. The interest in national politics among the Polish citizens in Chicago, and especially the interest in it among the citizens and non-citizens who had previously remained entirely indifferent to it, that interest began from the time when the Dziennik was founded, and although a large amount of credit should be ascribed to some of the more experienced citizens, nevertheless Dziennik was undoubtedly such a valiant assistant that without it, not even an approximation of the results we enjoy today could have been obtained.</p>
   <p>A new political life, greater than any previous activity was evident among the Poles as early as the spring of last year. From that time the citizens of other nationalities began to note with increasing wonder how important a role the Poles in Chicago could play in politics, and how remarkably the <pb facs="5423968_3_1608.jpg" n="2"/>Polish vote had increased. In a few years, by constant advance along this road, we will undoubtedly gain very important influence.</p>
   <p>Through the initiative of Dziennik, besides the Sixteenth Ward Club that was formed in the past four weeks, a committee was created whose aim is to unite the Poles in the city, or even in the entire state, into a strong political organization. Indeed, because of petty jealousy or the hostility of one of these committeemen, Dziennik was overlooked when it came to informing the citizens of the formation of such a committee, but this circumstance does not change the situation and cannot harm Dziennik.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, however, the Sixteenth Ward formally passed under the administration of the Poles. Listening to those congregated at yesterday's meeting, one could be convinced that a great many of them were thankful to Dziennik, for having learned of the meeting, they attended in that number, and no one will take it as evil on our side when we say that at this time we note this fact with pride and joy, although thus far, in the pattern of other periodicals, we have never proclaimed hymns of praise for our own glory. We did not make public the letters favorable to us nor did we use thousands of methods to elevate ourselves in an ostensibly innocent manner and to lower others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
