<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1908-04-13">Apr. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Club Is Mightier Than the Constitution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1908-04-13">Apr. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE CLUB IS MIGHTIER THAN THE CONSTITUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>These words were uttered by city police to the committee sent by the conference of working men's societies to complain that the police had acted unlawfully at the meeting of the unemployed on March 28.</p>
   <p>As we know the American Constitution guarantees very distinctly the right of American citizens to assemble publicly and discuss anything which they please to discuss.</p>
   <p>The purpose of that meeting of the unemployed, which took place on March 28 in Union Square, New York, was to discuss peacefully the situation caused by the business depression. The speakers engaged by the conference intended to explain to the assembled workers what to do in order to get the work which they so much needed. This meeting was therefore neither anarchistic nor socialistic. The signs announcing the meeting did not indicate that it was going to be a revolutionary gathering.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The police of New York know very well that the organizations which help the unemployed in that city respect the laws of the country and the city and have been able to keep order in the past.</p>
   <p>Why is it that the police with the brutality of Cossacks attacked innocent people walking on the sidewalk about two hours before the explosion of Silverstein's bomb? The authorities stated that the police had a right to disperse the crowd because it had no permit to hold a meeting and for that reason was an unlawful gathering. It is true that the permit was not granted when it was applied for at the police stations and at the park commissioners' office. But it is also true that according to the Constitution of the United States neither the police nor the park commissioners had any right to refuse to give a permit to a conference which was to be held in a public place by workingmen. Furthermore, such meetings had been held in Union Square for the same purpose by the same people, who were the initiators of the Unemployed Aid Conference. The authorities in this case acted <pb facs="5423968_3_0424.jpg" n="3"/>despotically; they deprived American citizens of the great right which was handed down to us by the fathers of the Nation, the right to assemble in public places for discussions.</p>
   <p>If any one is guilty of violating the Constitution of the United States, it is the park commissioners and the police. No less guilty is the mayor of New York, who sided with these authorities. If any one is to be punished, it should be these public servants and not the participants in the meeting, who had a right to gather in Union Square, a right which was denied them.</p>
   <p>Had they submitted to the despotic decree of the city authorities, they would have given them a precedent for similar refusals in the future, and they would have endangered the right of citizens to assemble in public places. Indeed, we all know how easy it is to lose personal liberty if we allow any one to <pb facs="5423968_3_0425.jpg" n="4"/>go unpunished who deprives us only of a very small part of that liberty, and this is a matter which concerns the whole nation. The proverb says, Give a finger to a dog, and he will want the whole hand. If American working-men allow their capitalistic government to deprive them of only one right guaranteed by the Constitution, then in a very short time they will lose a second right and a third. To-day they forbid men to hold a meeting; to-morrow they will forbid them to organize for their protection, and on the third day they will forbid them to publish a paper by which to serve their interests; for such is the nature of those who wish to dominate their fellow-men, whether in Russia or in America.</p>
   <p>Therefore our brothers in New York City were justified in what they did, in defying the police and holding their meeting in spite of any one's prohibition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0426.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In this case they acted as any patriotic and liberty-loving American citizen would act.</p>
   <p>We are positive that it was not the lack of a permit to hold a meeting in Union Square which caused the police to attack the participants like infuriated bulls, hitting any one with whom they came in contact. We are quite positive that the police would not have acted differently even if the workers had had a permit to hold their meeting. The police desired to discourage the unemployed of New York City from holding such meetings in the future. It was for the purpose of brow-beating the Socialists and preventing them from teaching the working-men about their rights.</p>
   <p>The dominating class in America is responsible for the poverty of a million and a half of the working-people, and it has not a clear conscience. It knows <pb facs="5423968_3_0427.jpg" n="6"/>how badly the affairs of the country are managed. It knows that the people are indignant on account of the greed, the brutality, and the arrogance of the capitalistic government. Therefore, it hates the sight of the working-people.</p>
   <p>The police of Chicago and New York know very well the attitude of the dominating class toward the army of hungry and despairing working-men. The police know that they may commit outrages against the working class. Not only do they know this; they know also that for so doing they will be rewarded by the working-men's employers. The police also know that the capitalists and their servants, the politicians, will look on indifferently while they, the police, tickle the working-men with their clubs.</p>
   <p>The police know that the capitalists ignore the Constitution and this is the <pb facs="5423968_3_0428.jpg" n="7"/>reason why policemen adopt the attitude of Cossacks in dealing with American working-men. For so doing they are praised by the capitalistic press and by their hirelings, the politicians, from Roosevelt down to common aldermen. These people freely forgive the heroes in blue uniforms for being very closely allied with every species of scoundrel.</p>
   <p>The police captain knew what he was talking about when he said, "The club is mightier than the Constitution."</p>
   <p>Jan Wolski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
