<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-22">Mar. 22, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Democratic Club of Tenth Ward Holds Pre-Registration Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0912</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0912.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-22">Mar. 22, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMOCRATIC CLUB OF TENTH WARD HOLDS PRE-REGISTRATION MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, March 19, a general meeting of the Polish Democratic Club of the Tenth Ward was held at M. Parozynski's Hall. The members unanimously agreed to take an active part in the present registration of voters, in order that every Polish citizen having the right to vote may be registered.</p>
   <p>Dear compatriots! The Republican bosses realize that they are going to be defeated in the April election, and that their political machine is going to be put out of action. Consequently, in order to avert this dreaded catastrophe, the Republican bosses have begun to complain about the shortage of precincts in the ward, and claim that there are too many people in each precinct at present, especially in the densely populated Democratic precincts. A division of precincts was made, making many new ones. A redivision of precincts necessitates a revision of registration books for each new precinct, and we know what this means, especially to us Poles. Polish names are difficult to write and pronounce, for people of other nationalities, and at the same <pb facs="5423968_3_0913.jpg" n="2"/>time there are no Polish clerks in the office where the registration books are being revised. The only reward the Polish Republicans have received for their efforts--and are still getting--is charity from the relief office. Therefore, many Polish names will be omitted in the books of the new precincts.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every Polish citizen of voting age to go to the polling place on Tuesday, March 23, to see whether his name is in the book; if it is not, he should register. This is imperative, because it will give us all the right to vote on April 6, and the privilege to vote for C. H. Harrison and Biniak. If we fulfill our duty, surely our candidates will be victorious.</p>
   <p>P. Jezierny, Secretary,</p>
   <p>Tenth Ward Polish Democratic Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
