<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 258,
<date when="1908-11-03">Nov. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Demonstration of Polish Socialists in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 258,
<date when="1908-11-03">Nov. 3, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">DEMONSTRATION OF POLISH SOCIALISTS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our last Sunday's parade in honor of Comrade Debs, who arrived in Chicago, was a great success.</p>
   <p>We gathered at Milwaukee Avenue and Noble Street, and started to march punctually at 12:30 P.M. Our parade marched through Milwaukee Avenue, Canal and Randolph Streets to Michigan Avenue. Must before the march, the Workers' Choir sang the "Marseillaise", and during the march Mr. Zalewski's Orchestra played popular revolutionary songs - "Marseillaise", "Warszawianka", "The Red Banner", "On to the Barricades", and others.</p>
   <p>The orchestra was followed by a group of women socialists, carrying their own red banners. The group of women numbered thirty at the beginning, but when we reached Randolph Street, the number had increased to sixty.</p>
   <p>We were proud of our women socialists, who kept in step and reached the destination under the red emblem without complaining about the difficulties caused by the long march.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We were encouraged by the willingness of our women to be our companions in the struggle for our ideals.</p>
   <p>The group of women was followed by the red banner of our Chicago Polish Socialists, after which marched our comrades in formation of rows of four.</p>
   <p>When the parade started, it numbered about five hundred, but the streets were crowded with throngs of less daring working people who were afraid to march along through the Polish settlement among the ranks of Socialists. Their hearts are with us, but their souls are held in the clutches of the clerical and nationalistic terror.</p>
   <p>All of those future comrades, but only sympathizers today, joined our parade later. At Canal Street our parade numbered about seven hundred, and at Michigan Avenue, about eight hundred.</p>
   <p>This parade is a proof that our ranks will grow and we are convinced that our sympathizers will cease to remain aloof, and join our group or form a new one.</p>
   <p>March forward, our banner! Our banner marches over thrones!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
