<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. IX, No. 44,
<date when="1890-10-29">Oct. 29, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">About Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. IX, No. 44,
<date when="1890-10-29">Oct. 29, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>November the 4th is election day in Chicago and Cook County. It is very important to take part in this election because if the people don't and the wrong candidate is elected, the poor working classes and the less fortunate ones suffer.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of all citizens to make arrangements as to the best time suitable for them to be present at the polling place, either before or after working hours. This should not be neglected. Many people say, If I do or if I don't vote, it cannot mean much; it is only one vote. But these people never realize that at the end of election day all these single votes count into thousands.</p>
   <p>The number of Polish voters in Chicago is very large, but if the number of Polish people registered is not near the total number of citizens voting, then how can we have any Polish candidates run for office and be victorious if we neglect our duty?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1067.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The trouble with most of the Polish people is that they are easy going and many haven't received their citizenship papers. That is the main reason the Republicans and Democrats are not anxious to place Polish candidates on their tickets.</p>
   <p>They feel that as long as at least one Polish candidate's name appears on their ballot, their worries about the Polish vote is settled.</p>
   <p>The Polish people should take more interest in local politics, and not sit back and watch the other nationalities monopolize the political offices.</p>
   <p>For example, on this present Republican ballot there is not one Polish candidate running for any county office, now it is our turn to do something about this; if they can place their own men as candidates, and are not worried about the Poles, do not vote their ticket, vote for the party that has Polish candidates' names.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1068.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They feel that as long as at least one Polish name is on the ballot, the Polish people will vote for that party. The Democratic Party did its share for the Poles by placing two Polish candidates on the ballot.</p>
   <p>John Kwasigroch, of the 13th Senatorial District, is a candidate for the Illinois State Legislature. His name and character are known, and all the sensible Polish citizens will do their part by supporting him.</p>
   <p>Candidate for county commissioner is Victor Bardonski, a man of integrity, honest and trustworthy, who is well known throughout the county of Cook. The duties of the county commissioner are to take care of all county affairs, including the poor and needy, which is the main thing. If we do not have at least one county commissioner in the United States, who is going to look after the welfare of the Poles, many of whom cannot read or write the English language?</p>
   <p>Victor Bardonski pledges that if he is elected, the Poles can depend on him to do all in his power to make life easier for his fellow countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
