<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-02">Nov. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Platform for Tomorrow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-02">Nov. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PLATFORM FOR TOMORROW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If our Polish people have the right to decide their needs, why should they not take advantage of tomorrow's election to declare themselves for Polish candidates?</p>
   <p>The events of the past few days and the decisions of all of the specifically Polish societies and organizations are examples of united action for the purpose of supporting Polish candidates.</p>
   <p>No one has the right--no one, I say, meaning the Polish people--to place obstacles in the path of lawful Polish work founded on well-established bases. Supporting Polish candidates should not be a matter of fashion or the result of political agitation, but an expression of the understanding of one's national duty. It is the duty and the right of Polish societies and no one has authority to interfere with us in our strivings in this direction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0746.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Tomorrow let us begin to look over our forces--Polish forces.</p>
   <p>Our concern in this case is: to have Polish politicians stop considering themselves members of party machines, which have given the Poles nothing and will give them nothing; to have them stop exchanging Polish votes for the little influence they may enjoy from the " big bosses"; to have Polish voters stop selling their rights as free Americans for crumbs from the political table of a chauvinistic clique and stop forgetting about their duties to their oppressed Mother, Poland; to make voting in the American elections become an act of Polish nationalism which may lead to the path of self-help; and to give our votes to Poles tomorrow regardless of party affiliations.</p>
   <p>It is these things which concern us since we want to prove that our Polish people can determine their own needs. If we need anything at all, we need Polish representatives in important offices in America at the present time. Therefore, in the first place let us vote for Poles tomorrow!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0747.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is our "platform" for tomorrow in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
