<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous--"<title level="a">Should We Organize Politically</title>", <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. II, No. 1, <date when="1923-09">September 1923</date>, p. 4.
<title level="a">[What Did Senator Mccormick Ever Do for the Poles?]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous--"<title level="a">Should We Organize Politically</title>", <title>Chicago Society News, (Monthly)</title>, Vol. II, No. 1, <date when="1923-09">September 1923</date>, p. 4.
<title level="a">[WHAT DID SENATOR MCCORMICK EVER DO FOR THE POLES?]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our April issue we spoke about the future of the Polish National Alliance being assured in view of the fact that new blood was being infused. We touched upon the future of Polish speaking organizations in general, and their needs for the future in our March issue. To round out our subject we will briefly discuss the need of organizing our youth into political and civic bodies, for it is here that we have always been vulnerable.</p>
   <p>We concede at the outset that we will be accused of attempting to play politics, and will be advised that our publication should devote its attention solely to matters pertaining to Chicago Society, and of interest to members of our society. We cannot agree with that conclusion for our mission is broader and less selfish. We owe a duty to our people and their general cause. We are not moved by any personal aggrandizement or selfish motive, but by a desire to point out a few facts which we should seriously consider and attempt to remedy. As a leader of thought and action in our Polish speaking community, the Chicago Society is in duty bound to take a decided though impartial stand on public questions of importance to our people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0579.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is one thought that presents itself like "Banquo's ghost", and that is "Why are we Americans of Polish ancestry overlooked in American activities, political and civic, in our community?" The answer is, "We are not adequately organized." Let us then consider our needs and find our vulnerable spots, and proceed to meet the issue with mature judgment and a determination to act in unison on matters of policy.</p>
   <p>Until we organize thoroughly, whether it be in Political of Civic bodies, in order that we may present a united front, the prejudice against our foreign sounding names will continue, yea, increase in spite of the fact that we measured up to the most exacting standards of Americanism by our sacrifices during the late war. Our right to assert our Americanism and its resulting emoluments was earned by the sacrifices of our boys on the battle fields of Prance. The first Chicago boy to law down his life on the altar of American patriotism was a lad whose foreign-sounding name was Wojtalewicsz. His name may have been foreign but his sacrifice was American, for he made the supreme sacrifice that the ideals of his country might survive. He was typical of thousands of our boys who donned the United States' uniform.</p>
   <p>Each political campaign brings out the spectacle of our voters, honest and trusting, <pb facs="5423968_3_0580.jpg" n="3"/>being exploited by political leaders. Before each election our voters are taken upon the hill and are shown the "world of promises". After the ballots are cast and counted the promises are forgotten and we are unable to obtain entree to remind the successful candidate of his debt to us. Are we satisfied to allow this state of affairs to continue, or will we take heed of Lincoln's forceful aforism and say, "You may fool all of us some of the time, some of us all of the time, but you cannot fool all of us all of the time."</p>
   <p>Our advice is that the Republicans organize a strong club to work for recognition in that party, to regain the prestige enjoyed during the leadership of former Governor Charles S. Deneen more than a generation ago.</p>
   <p>The Democrats should have a better understanding among themselves and there should be greater co-ordination among: the leaders. If it is impossible to bring about this condition within the Democratic ranks, then it is time to change leaders, choosing those who will unselfishly and honestly perform their duties to the greater benefit of their constituents.</p>
   <p>After organizations have been perfected within both parties, then the leaders in each should have an understanding, calculated to bring about concerted action <pb facs="5423968_3_0581.jpg" n="4"/>against the bosses of either party should they attempt to discriminate against us. If the present party leaders cannot come to an understanding, let some of us step into the breach and organize our voters in various centers into militant, political, and civic bodies, and beat the bosses Nolins Volins, elevating to leadership those who will best serve our interests. Politics is a selfish game. Let us be as selfish as others are.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
