<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-06-26">June 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">This Is No Favor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-06-26">June 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THIS IS NO FAVOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p><gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>e read in one of the Polish weekly papers that in a certain city, the mayor appointed a Pole to a subordinate position, and for this generous act of kindness this newspaper is praising the mayor sky-high, and wants him to be remembered not only by citizens of Polish extraction, but by the entire Polish race.</p>
   <p>We, on the other hand, do not consider the appointment of this Pole to office by the mayor or governor as an act of kindness, but as a part payment of indebtedness due us from other nationalities, since their candidates were elected to office with the aid of the Polish vote. Because, after all, it is the Polish vote that elects candidates of other nationalities to important offices.</p>
   <p>There is among the population of some cities a certain percentage of prominent Poles, and these Poles decide who shall be victorious.</p>
   <p>Every important office is crowded by Englishmen, Germans, Jews, Swedes, Irishmen and others; only the Poles, for some petty favor, modestly hold <pb facs="5423968_3_1497.jpg" n="2"/>together and vote for other nationalities. And when one, other than a Pole, is elected to some important office by the aid of the Polish vote, and in return condescends to appoint some Pole to a petty political Job, it appears to some of our countrymen that this official did us a great favor, and they immediately start singing hymns of praise in his honor, as if this person rebuilt Poland. Surely we do not need this favor, for we have the same right to seek every office as other nationalities. Today, we don't have to be under obligation to strangers, for we represent considerable political influence, and they are compelled to deal with us. Each year the Poles grow in strength, and more are becoming naturalized. On the other hand, our young people born and reared here are growing up, and they have boldly thrown themselves into the political whirlpool, and probably will not permit business dictations or favors from others; for they have the same right as others to seek the highest office.</p>
   <p>If the Irishmen, Englishmen, Germans, and Jews break into important offices, then why cannot the Poles climb likewise? Today, in our community, among our immigrants, we have a large number of efficient, competent, and honest men to fill the highest office. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>e do not need any favors, for it is an <pb facs="5423968_3_1498.jpg" n="3"/>insult to our national worthiness, that a Pole is satisfied with some petty office while others grab everything.</p>
   <p>That we need is political organization, and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to our countrymen to apply for their naturalization papers; for with political knowledge and mutual cooperation, regardless of party politicians, we need not be contented with the napkin, while others eat the cream.</p>
   <p>As citizens of this country, we have equal rights with other nationalities. But above everything else let us have self-respect, and with the respect of others, without favors, we will secure what rightfully belongs to us.</p>
   <p>We, 60,000 Polish voting citizens in Chicago and Cook County, are not satisfied with a few park and police jobs, or a position of an assistant to some higher official; we should select our own candidates, vote and <pb facs="5423968_3_1499.jpg" n="4"/>elect them into office. For this is the conduct of other nationalities, and it brings them beneficial results.</p>
   <p>Let us discontinue begging favors from other nationalities, and being grateful for the petty favors thrown to a few of us. Instead let us have self-respect and demand that which rightfully belongs to us as citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
