<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 32, 
<date when="1916-08-09">Aug. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Prosperity Bluff</title><title level="a" type="sub">(reprinted from Polish Standard)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 32, 
<date when="1916-08-09">Aug. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PROSPERITY BLUFF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(reprinted from Polish Standard)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0328.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>before you, and you will find <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> then what great benefits are offered to you by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Work is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> strikes, lay-offs of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and sickness. Working yourself up to a better position goes slowly, and favoritism is in use very often. The work is small and limited after you <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Every day is the same <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> bills start. If you become lisabled, unable to work or crippled, you receive very little or nothing at all. In case of death your family receives what you were able to save from, your small earnings. Almost all your income <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for livelihood. Old age is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> sickness; you saved very little money, your job was taken by a younger person and a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> active man. Behold! What it promises you?"</p>
   <p>Unfortunately that is the way it truly is, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> This country in many ways has remained far behind the rest of the world, even if it hides carefully these deficiencies under an outward pretext of false showing; but in no other direction are we most likely more backward and <pb facs="5423968_3_0329.jpg" n="3"/>negligent than in the of work, in an <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> country. Under the pretense of not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to bind personal liberty, the workingman has directly been taken <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> law, statutes have nor been provided for, regulating the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the workingman with the employer, protecting and insuring financially <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> weaker worker and his family. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of them is sure of tomorrow, health, or life. At any or death lies in wait for him <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the factory or mine, for the economy of the "bose" deprived of protective means and conducted in a frantic way.</p>
   <p>Prosperity! Not lon ago, when the (debate on) limitation of immigration was going on in Congress, an argument was raised there that the immigrants are lowering the standard of life of the American workingman.</p>
   <p>Oh! Pharisees, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> bluffers! We are curious how a workingman with a family can live on a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> standard with this from-day-to-day growing, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of high cost of every day needs of life, with this <pb facs="5423968_3_0330.jpg" n="4"/>constant shrinking value of that sacred dollar, for which he must work so hard, and which he hardly is allowed to smell because at once with a thousand bricks and methods, bordering up on robbery, it is scared out of his pockets by slickers. Some time ago, as is told by older immigrants, this was possible, it was well-being when a workingman could earn several dollars a day, and everything was cheap, when one would live adequately with a family on three to four dollars a week, when meat cost four cents a pound and everything was cheaper in proportion. Today articles of every day life are more expensive here than anywhere else, and the demands are greater right along, even for bare necessities. The workingman can work his hands down to his elbows before he can save anything from his earnings; only the most powerful and the most attentive, at the same time the most conservative, and depriving themselves of the least little things, are able to accomplish that. The rest of them live from day to day, eternally bare, often in debt according to the maxim, "Matthew earned it, Matthew ate it."</p>
   <p>Because that is what is particularly wanted, that is what is desired <pb facs="5423968_3_0331.jpg" n="5"/>by our bosses, capitalists and enterprisers. Toward this aim also is adapted our entire machine, our entire social system. It seems as if there was intentionally contrived thousands of attractive methods of spending money. The people have been driven into an ambition for sports, there has been propagated a mania for sports, there has been propagated a mania for dressing, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> throwing away of money on useless and unnecessary silly things. The thrifty workingman, having some sort of small <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> begins to value his own worthiness, does not allow himself to be treated with contempt, or quits his hard, murderous labors, going into an <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> or on a farm; he has to be kept in a state of continuous life from day to day, continuous want and dependence on the boss and his capital, in a continuous working yoke.</p>
   <p>Prosperity today already belongs to the past, and small is our <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that it will again so soon arrive in this country. We have a few kings, true self-possessed <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of millions, who <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> this country with the help of several millionnaires; the remainder are their subjects, the millions of dark masses, working hard for profits for them (the millionaires).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0332.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Self-dependent trade has <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the great manufacturing industry, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> business, farming is on the graces of trusts and the companies, the workingman, a slave of capital. Beyond the slim handful of the wealthy, there are no people or independent classes. There you have prosperity, which so faithfully even if unintentionally is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> characterized by this address to the volunteers.</p>
   <p>Years will pass before these conditions will change for the better. There remains nothing else for our Polish immigration but to save themselves with self-help. Let us have as much as we possibly can, let us deprive ourselves of all kinds of luxuries, let us live modestly, not put ourselves out for sports and pomp. Let us stick together, as it becomes brothers, let us organize and insure ourselves in Polish societies, let us help each other in business. Let us not allow ourselves to be fooled with idle talk about prosperity, when poverty is already vexing us and maybe a greater depression can come. Money, that is our only weapon, our worth and our deliverance in this country, whose brand is uncertainty of tomorrow and life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
