<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-04">Sept. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">An Agreement between Messrs N. L. Piotrowski and Z. H. Kadow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0730</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0730.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-04">Sept. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN MESSRS N. L. PIOTROWSKI AND Z. H. KADOW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dziennik Zwiazkowy is pleased to inform its readers, and especially the Polish Democratic voters of the Eighth Congressional District in Chicago, that an agreement has been reached between two Polish candidates of the same District aspiring for nomination to Congress in the forthcoming primary election.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stanley Kunz has visited the editor of the Dziennik Zwiazkowy and has stated that at a meeting at the main Democratic headquarters of the Sixteenth Ward a motion was passed to call a mass meeting of voters at Schoenhofen Hall, on Thursday, September 7, 1916, at 8P.M. At this meeting the candidacy of one of the aspirants to Congress is to be indorsed.</p>
   <p>It will depend upon the will of the voters of the Eight District which of the candidates the Poles will support on the Democratic ticket. If the audience <pb facs="5423968_3_0731.jpg" n="2"/>declares itself in favor of Mr. Z. H. Kadow, then Mr. [Nicholas] L. Piotrowski will withdraw his candidacy. If, on the other hand, the voters at this meeting express their desire to have Mr. N. L. Piotrowski as their candidate, then Mr. Z. H. Kadow will withdraw. Moreover, he will also ask his followers to cast their votes at the primaries in favor of Mr. N. L. Piotrowski.</p>
   <p>The former alderman, Mr. Stanley H. Kunz, also exhibited the original copy of the agreement entered into by the two candidates. It was signed by Messrs. N. L. Piotrowski and Z. H. Kadow. Both candidates agree that at the mass meeting of voters of the Fifteenth, Sixteenth, and Seventeenth Wards, which is to be held at Schoenhofen Hall on September 4, they will yield to the will of the majority of those congregated at the hall, and in accordance with [the voters'] recommendation that candidate will withdraw his candidacy who shall not have obtained a majority of the votes.</p>
   <p>This agreement was signed by the two candidates in the presence of two witnesses, namely, Messrs. S. H. Kunz and A. H. Sikorski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0732.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is worthy of note in this connection that at that meeting all candidacies of Poles in that district will also be passed upon in like manner, provided, however, that the aspirants agree to it. It is the opinion of this newspaper that they should agree. Let the majority decide, and in that way the election of [our] candidate will be assured, since the Polish vote will not be divided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
