<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-17">Mar. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Caucuses and Conventions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-03-17">Mar. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">CAUCUSES AND CONVENTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before every election, each political party in the United States holds a preliminary election, called a caucus, which is followed by a convention of the party,at which candidates are nominated and the platform of the party is adopted. The party is supposed to adhere to its platform and it is the duty of every candidate, when he is elected, to defend the principles embraced by whatever platform be adopted.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the caucus, which is not official or obligatory, is to find out which candidate is the strongest and best qualified to represent the entire party, and to prevent the splitting of the party's vote at the general election.</p>
   <p>The city elections will be held on April 7th of this year. In the mean-time, <pb facs="5423968_3_1749.jpg" n="2"/>there will be held other caucuses and conventions.</p>
   <p>There are several political parties in our city, but the strongest and most important of them are the Republican and the Democratic.</p>
   <p>The Republican Party held a caucus last Friday and a convention on the following day; the Democratic Party will hold theirs next week, on the same days.</p>
   <p>At their last caucus, which was held last Friday, the Republicans chose their candidates for city officials. They nominated Hemsted Washburne for mayor, Jacob H. Tiedeman for treasuer, B. F. Richolson for city counsel; and J. R. B. Van Cleave for city clerk.</p>
   <p>Since these men are respectable and capable, they will be of great opposition to the Democratic candidates, who probably will be defended by <pb facs="5423968_3_1750.jpg" n="3"/>the majority, to which most of the Poles belong. At their caucus, the Republicans nominated thirty-four candidates for alderman. Besides these, there are other city offices for which candidates were chosen. At the last convention, the Republican party formed its platform, which will be discussed in to-morrow's issue of our paper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
