<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII,
<date when="1914-09-02">Sept. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Vote Is Our Weapon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0778</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0778.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII,
<date when="1914-09-02">Sept. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE VOTE IS OUR WEAPON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This watch-word was announced on the eve of the elections by Dziennik Chicagoski, and it is a true statement. The standing of every nationality in the United States is measured by the quantity of its votes.</p>
   <p>It is a fact which does not need to be proved that the vote is our weapon. It means that we should support our own people in election. We will win and we will reach the place where a Polish name will be respected.</p>
   <p>On the eve of election in Chicago, on the 9th day of September, we are imploring all brothers of the Union who will go to election booths to vote for their fellow countrymen. Brothers, fulfill your duty of citizenship, support the Polish candidates on the day of election. Wherever you see a Polish name, vote for him. The vote is our weapon. The watch-word describes correctly this article. Our standing in politics is very low. People of other nationalities scorfully speak about Poles when it comes to political matters. We have no right to blame them for it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0779.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Up to now we have played politics badly. That is why Poles were disregarded. A very important election is coming to a close. On the 9th day of September, in the County of Cook and in the State of Illinois, is the election of candidates for important offices. In this election more Poles are candidates for all kinds of offices than at any other time before. The politicians are beginning to take us into consideration just because we are awakening. Will our Poles, in this election, wish to serve for this cause? For the Polish people it is a big moment, important developments are taking place at present in the old country. Our countrymen are shedding blood on three fronts. All Europe is in blood and in flames. All Europe hears the moans of the wounded, from these moans one can hear the spirit of Poland, our fatherland.</p>
   <p>We are not allowed to return to the old country. The United States will stay neutral. Until now we could not help our countrymen. The time for this would come after the war. In the United States we are free, we can do much good for Poland, for a free and independent Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0780.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The vote is our weapon. The European war will not last forever. The time will come when some European country will ask for negociations for peace. In this case, in the role of judges, will enter representatives of other countries which did not take part in the present war. The United States has offered its plan for mediation. The United States is willing to arbitrate for peace. Polish interests are foremost. The whole world is thinking about independent Poland. Everybody knows that it is the time to rebuild Poland. Polish affairs will be discussed in conferences for peace.</p>
   <p>In these conferences the government of the United States will have its representatives. God forebid the Germans, or we, the Poles of America, to give these representatives of the United States certain recommendations.</p>
   <p>At this moment we are without a vote. We have to sit behind the stone because in the Lower House of Representatives, in Washington, there is not a single Pole, neither is there one in the Senate. We have not a single <pb facs="5423968_3_0781.jpg" n="4"/>Pole in Congress, even at this critical moment. In the coming election, the 9th of September, we must send one, two or three men to Washington; we have four candidates for Congress, and we have got to have men in Washington. Don't forget to vote!</p>
   <p>The vote is our weapon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
