<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Alliance of Polish Mercantile Corporationns</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ALLIANCE OF POLISH MERCANTILE CORPORATIONNS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last several years there has been a movement afoot among the Polish people in America to organize numerous mercantile organizations, both co-operatives and [independent] corporations. These have for their purpose the saving of money for their members in the purchase of merchandise.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that at present there are more than three million Poles in America. They further show that their annual expenditure is in excess of six hundred million dollars. This is a comparatively conservative estimate, since upon closer inspection it [simply] indicates an average per capita expenditure of two hundred dollars per year per person. Of the six hundred million dollars annually expended by our people, at least sixty million dollars finds its way into the coffers of middlemen and speculators, people who for the most part are not Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Poles in America are too poor and have too many needs of their own to enrich those who are not Polish. Were we to save the money which we spend today in non-Polish business establishments, we should be able to contribute more than three times ten million dollars toward the Polish National Fund. In what way can we accomplish this? In what way can we retain in Polish pockets the millions of dollars that are now flowing in a wide stream into the hands of people not Polish, people who are often ill disposed toward Poles? There is but one answer, but one way to solve this question. It is necessary to cover all Polish settlements with a network of members united in a single powerful organization, the Alliance of Polish Mercantile Corporations.</p>
   <p>We know the amount of good which co-operatives have done, what great benefits have been derived in Poland through such organizations as the Tradesmen's and Farmers' Alliance, the Tradesmen's Protective Association, and the Alliance of Co-operatives. Here in America likewise we know of the great <pb facs="5423968_3_0157.jpg" n="3"/>amount of money saved for our Polish element by the Polish League of Building and Loan Associations. We also know what great progress has been made in that direction by similar American organizations,such as, for example, the Co-operative League of America, the United National Clothiers, the Retailers' Co-operative League, and many others. In view of this why should not our Polish people create entire networks of Polish commercial organizations and unite them in one powerful alliance? Many Polish settlements in America already have commercial organizations. The thing to do now is to unite them.</p>
   <p>The aims and the purpose of the Alliance of Polish Mercantile Corporations will be as follows: 1) To organize Polish corporations and co-operatives in all Polish settlements throughout the United States; 2) To give legal and professional aid to Polish business concerns of that type already existing; 3) To audit the [records of] the concerns affiliated with the Alliance; 4) To supply professionally trained people to conduct the businesses of affiliated concerns; <pb facs="5423968_3_0158.jpg" n="4"/>and 5) To promote co-operative wholesale purchases.</p>
   <p>An alliance of that type would not only save large sums of money for the Polish people in the purchase of their goods but would also prepare the way for numerous Polish businessmen to leave for Poland at the termination of the present European war. There they would be in a position to apply themselves to the task of nationalizing Polish trade and commerce.</p>
   <p>In order that a project of so vast importance may not terminate in words but be made an active reality, the Polish Palatine Corporation has extended a credit of one thousand dollars to the newly organized Alliance. In addition to that the president of the Palatine Corporation, Mr. Joseph Mierzynski, has made a voluntary personal contribution of one thousand dollars toward the Alliance of Polish Mercantile Corporations to cover organization expenses. All that is left for our people to do is to become active for the benefit of the Alliance, and in a short time we shall be in a <pb facs="5423968_3_0159.jpg" n="5"/>position to show to the world at large of what accomplishments Poles are capable.</p>
   <p>The first thing to do is to come to an understanding among ourselves. Consequently all Polish business organizations now existing, as well as groups which contemplate forming corporations or co-operatives in their vicinity, should communicate with the temporary organization committee. This committee is composed of the executives of the Polish Trade Alliance. All interested persons should address their inquiries to the Alliance of Polish Mercantile Corporations, 1112-1114 Milwaukee Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
