<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-09">June 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[The Convention of the Liberty]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-09">June 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[THE CONVENTION OF THE LIBERTY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have finally received some information as to why the Liberty League gives no evidence of its presence. The "Zgoda" press offers an explanation to the answer of the Committee of the All-Republican Congress, from which we are informed that the convention of the Liberty League has been postponed until the fall or Oct. 12, 1892. Hence, let us wait until that time. We fear however, that the selection of that day for a convention was again ill-chosen and a new postponement will be necessary. The convention was postponed from April 30 to October 12, because on April 30, a conclave of the Sons of the American Revolution was held, and many members of the League also belong to other organizations. Consequently, one of these conventions had to be set aside until a later date. On October 12, however, a great event will take place in Chicago: the dedication of the fair, a true commemoration of the four hundredth anniversary of the discovery of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Perhaps many members of the Liberty League will be obliged to participate in this national festivity in Chicago and perhaps another postponement will follow. Why do they select such unsuitable dates?</p>
   <p>The Zgoda press charges us for not greeting sincerely the newly published Telegraf. This charge is unjust. Our greeting was very cordial, and, whoever read it will admit it. The Latin saying at the outset, did not detract from the ensuing words that were truly sincere; it was only a very delicate reproach for impolite conduct toward us. We are not at fault if the Telegraf accepted our welcome with incredulity; it has noted deceit, Pharisaism and many other similar endearing qualities in our sayings. That is not our fault. Any impartial person will acknowledge justice on our part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
