<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-12-22">Dec. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Public Charity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0333</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0333.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-12-22">Dec. 22, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC CHARITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The best prepared plans and the noblest social enterprizes often fail or bring about contrary results. This happens in all organized charity work. Despite the culture and civilization of which the Twentieth century is so proud, frequently all the splendor and riches result in vulgarity, primitive misery, and hunger.</p>
   <p>Among all the miracles of civilization in our great cities and the centers of the cultural world, we find on the one hand hoarded riches, and on the other hand miserable people perishing from hunger and, because of despair, even committing suicide. These conditions should not prevail in our great country with all its riches and resources. Evidently there <pb facs="5423968_3_0334.jpg" n="2"/>is something wrong with our social machinery. What shall we do to improve these conditions?</p>
   <p>Many people, vitally interested in these social problems, are daily devising ways and means to correct that evil and as an antidote they turn to charity and social work.</p>
   <p>The newspapers are appealing for help for the needy.</p>
   <p>Many charitable societies are being organized, special funds collected, government and communities allotting large amount of money, but misery is as prevalent as in the past and is not decreasing. Many noted philanthropists, seeing their money and work misused and not bringing about the expected results, are losing all interest in charitable work. Often, crooked individuals, abuse public confidence and under guise of charity, use collected funds for themselves. Aid often is given to persons who are not in need of it. Many times the generous and amazed <pb facs="5423968_3_0335.jpg" n="3"/>public learns that institutions, which are built with the money collected for the purpose of aiding the needy, the homeless and the orphans, are in reality becoming a haven for the lazy clique of supervisors and so-called social workers. In Catholic institutions, where thousands of needy orphans could be cared for, we can find but a few of them, while a large band of lazy and well fed nuns are living in luxury.</p>
   <p>Charity will not abolish poverty. As long as there is merciless exploitation, there must be needy people. The rich philanthropists refuse to see and understand this inequality. They are giving very little to charity, while with the other hand they grab as much as they can from the poor. They exploit them by paying them low wages, and they leave them unprotected against the danger of unemployment, and against the hardships caused by the high prices of the necessities of life. They cannot thus abolish poverty; on the contrary, they are increasing it. The present system of charity, as a temporary remedy, is a total failure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
