<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 180,
<date when="1922-08-03">Aug. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Strikes and Representative of the People.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 180,
<date when="1922-08-03">Aug. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">STRIKES AND REPRESENTATIVE OF THE PEOPLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editorial Observation.</p>
   <p>It is beyond question of a doubt that the democratic form of government, built on the fundamental principle that the governing of the entire nation or its absolute majority by its representatives, is in its foundation the most just. What then can be more ideal than the government of the people for the people?</p>
   <p>However, that ideally intelligent form of government is not always and not everywhere an ideal government. Quite often there come into the government weak persons or those caring more about their own good than that of their own government.</p>
   <p>What we see at present in the United States, creates an impression that the <pb facs="5423968_3_0245.jpg" n="2"/>representatives of the people in congress, as well as representatives of the people in the individual states, countries, and cities, do not completely measure to their task! Why?</p>
   <p>Because at the present time those representatives, chosen by the people to maintain law and order in the entire nation and to guard the good and welfare of the entire nation, are allowing a civil war to go on unfinished between an insignificant group of industrialists and the greater group of workers; thus bringing about huge losses to the entire nation.</p>
   <p>The coal miners strike has already been going on for several months. Due to that, the country is threatened with a shortage of coal, which is an indispensable factor for today's welfare of the country. This strike was already caused billions of dollars of material losses for the whole country, for the entire nation, not counting the moral losses.</p>
   <p>For several weeks a strike of the workers in railroad workshops has been <pb facs="5423968_3_0246.jpg" n="3"/>going on, which is likewise causing great losses to the community. In Chicago, a city of three million population, we have a street car strike, both elevated and surface. A city, the business center of the central states, is deprived of means of communication and transportation and threatened with financial losses. On account of a war between a few financialists and 20,000 workers, a city of 3,000,000 people is made liable to huge losses and inconveniences.</p>
   <p>And all of this is happening in a country, governed by the representatives of all the people, whose duty it is to care about the welfare and interests of all the population and not a fleeting minority.</p>
   <p>These representatives of the people, having the authority in their hands, are doing practically nothing to remedy this evil, to divert the huge losses, which the nation sustains due to strikes.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the people make excuses that they do not have sufficient laws to prevent strikes and the losses caused by them. And certainly <pb facs="5423968_3_0247.jpg" n="4"/>upon them and not upon anyone else depends the enacting of laws to protect the interests of the people against losses.</p>
   <p>Why don't these representatives of the people in congress, state legislatures, and city councils give the executive authorities the proper sanctions for energetic action in defense of the endangered interest of society? Whom are they serving, all of the people or just an insignificant group of industrialists?</p>
   <p>It is their duty to think of preventive means against all social ailments. It is their duty to serve all of the people. It is their duty to know exactly all kinds of social ailments and to know what to prescribe as a remedy for them.</p>
   <p>President Harding not long ago proposed a suitable remedy to prevent strikes, and it was supposed to have been to create special courts to investigate the dispute between capital and labor and them to render impartial and just verdicts, <pb facs="5423968_3_0248.jpg" n="5"/>binding upon both sides. The representatives of organized labor opposed violently this sensible proposition, and the representatives of the nation in Congress did not even care to take this project under consideration and did not think of any method by which the right could be given to the executive authorities for an effective means to prevent strikes, which are creating more destruction throughout the country than the late war.</p>
   <p>It is bad when a nation's representatives do not care about vital interests. It is bad when a nation does not know how to call to order its representatives, does not know how to guard effectively its own interests, allows a knife to be held at its throat by a fleeting minority without punishment and pays dearly for the capriciousness of individuals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
