<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 264,
<date when="1908-11-10">Nov. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Socialists in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proletarians! Unite!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 264,
<date when="1908-11-10">Nov. 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIALISTS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proletarians! Unite!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because the proletariat in the United States is awakening from its slumber and the masses of our countrymen remain ignorant, very energetic work is required in this field.</p>
   <p>Shall such elections like that in Milwaukee, Wis., be repeated? A socialist candidate for mayor was defeated, simply because the Polish voters of that city were influenced by the clergy to vote for a capitalist, who was an enemy of the working class.</p>
   <p>If our principles are the same, then we should not split up into factions, the more so because these factions are of no importance in the political and social evolution of this country.</p>
   <p>In America we have no confiscation. It is not necessary to organize fighting units, join Russian S.D.'s or S.R.'s, (Socialist Democratic Party or Socialist <pb facs="5423968_3_0388.jpg" n="2"/>Revolutionary Party) who demand a parliament or a constitution, fight for autonomy, or for an independent Polish republic.</p>
   <p>We have only one purpose. And what is that purpose? That question which we must solve was answered in "Everybody's Magazine" by the standard bearer of the Socialist Party, Mr. Debs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Debs said, "There is one question in America which must be solved. That question is capitalism, and the way to solve it is by socialism."</p>
   <p>Capitalism is the most powerful enemy of the working people. Let us go on fighting the capitalistic bourgeoise. Above all, we should unite our forces in agreement with the great communistic manifesto.</p>
   <p>Proletarians of all countries unite in the use of the slogan we see on every copy of Robotnik Polski, but alas! This slogan of the Polish Socialists Alliance betrayed its great and profound significance.</p>
   <p>United, therefore, we should not split the Alliance into factions. We should <pb facs="5423968_3_0389.jpg" n="3"/>not stand apart from the local Socialist Party.</p>
   <p>We should not repeat the words taken from the great commandment of the proletariat with an empty echo like a symbol. We should desire with all our hearts that there be a place in the workingman's organization for every proletarian who comes to us with the sincere desire to take an active part in class struggle.</p>
   <p>It makes no difference what his personal views are on tactics; what his theories are; whether he believes in God, or is an atheist.</p>
   <p>We can not reject or keep away from organization workingmen in whose minds there is an idealistic confusion, or those who are supporters of cliques which are unfriendly toward us.</p>
   <p>Our most important duty is to enlighten the ignorant masses of the people having confidence in the strength and logic of class struggle, which will sooner or later lead every proletarian on the right track if he joins the Socialist Party.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0390.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I remember very vividly, how, in the agitation during the great revolution in the country of the Czar, the working men were pointing to the slogan, "Proletarians of all countries, unite.", which was printed on even the smallest proclamations. They asked, "Why do you ask us to unite when you yourselves split and divide into all kinds of parties and factions?"</p>
   <p>In the name of that slogan, we must unite all alliances and organizations, disregarding the names, into a single Polish socialist unit as an autonomous part of the Socialist Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
