<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 150,
<date when="1904-06-20">June 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">John K. Szuminski - Candidate for County Commissioner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 150,
<date when="1904-06-20">June 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN K. SZUMINSKI - CANDIDATE FOR COUNTY COMMISSIONER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Szuminski is the only Polish candidate seeking the highest office in Chicago, County of Cook, at the coming election. He was born in 1859 in the town of Orze Lek, county of Ziotow.</p>
   <p>After graduating from grammar school, his parents sent him to the Chojnacki gymnasium, which has the same classification as our colleges. In the year 1877, he went to Bydgoszoz to act as manager of a magazine, where he was employed until 1882. Part of the following year he spent with Simon Ascher in Warbzenie. At the close of 1883 he emigrated to America and settled in Chicago. He was hired as assistant manager at Pavlicki's concern, located at Milwaukee Avenue near Noble Street, and later worked for Mr. E. Ahlswede, where he stayed until 1896. In February 1896 he opened his own business at 604 Noble Street, where he carried a complete line of silk wares and silk materials. The great concern of Marshall Field and Farwell gave him credit, and showed him the utmost consideration as a business man.</p>
   <p>Mr. Szuminski is a member of the Polish National Alliance, the Order of Faithful Catholic Seminaries, the Catholic Guards, and a member of St. Stanislaus Church. His family, as well as himself, were supporters of the Sisters of Nazareth, when they were first organized in this city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You, Polish people and citizens, please study the work, ambition and records of Mr. Szuminski, and you will no doubt agree that he is the man for the office of country commissioner. Take part in this coming election and help elect a man of true Polish blood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
