<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-10">July 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Poles and Bohemlans Hold Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0115</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0115.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-10">July 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLES AND BOHEMLANS HOLD MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday afternoon, the citizens of Polish and Bohemian extraction held a meeting at Pulaski Hall in connection with the recent occurrences.</p>
   <p>Originally this meeting was called for the purpose of protesting against the removal of the police from that neighborhood as this removal encouraged the lawless element to commit all kinds of outrages on the streets; but when the sad incidents, known to the readers of our newspaper, took place at St. Adalbert's Parish, the plans for which the meeting was called were changed. As Poles and Bohemians were being accused of having anarchistic and disturbing tendencies, it was decided that a public protest should be made against these accusations.</p>
   <p>J. Hapieralski presided over the meeting and Julius Smietanka acted as secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0116.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After a lively discussion a committee was chosen which drew up the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We, citizens of the United States of Polish and Bohemian extraction, residing in the Eighth and the Ninth Wards of Chicago, have been falsely represented by the Chicago press and accused of being the leaders and promoters of the late riots and disturbances in the City of Chicago, and of being supporters of anarchistic principles; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, From time to time false charges have been made by the press that we are not loyal to American government; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we protest most energetically against these unjust representations, and demand that this protest be published in the Chicago press, in order that the blot with which our good name has been besmirched may be removed, and that we may be cleared in the eyes of the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0117.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Signed: V. Taterrmarz, Julius F. Smietanka,</p>
   <p>Joseph Zolek, K. Zychlinski, K. J.</p>
   <p>Belinski, J. Smetana, J. Napieralski,</p>
   <p>Francis Marausek, J. Jereczek, K. Raus,</p>
   <p>J. Herman, J. Daniel, Anthony Stefanowicz,</p>
   <p>J. Suchmann, M. Parozinski, J. J. Mallek,</p>
   <p>"Members of the Committee."</p>
   <p>The foregoing resolution was published in today's Times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
