<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-19">May 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Press and Mr. Kiolbassa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1733</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1733.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-19">May 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESS AND MR. KIOLBASSA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The action taken by Mr. Kiolbassa relative to the City Council, of which incident we have previously written, has been widely publicized in other papers. Truly, the Democratic press is replete with praise of the first City Treasurer of Chicago who acted honestly toward the city and saved large sums of money for the municipality. Moreover, in comparison with his predecessors, it can be said that he donated vast amounts to the city. The Republican press, on the other hand, is to a great extent treating this matter in an unbecoming manner. Not favoring the obvious significance of Mr. Kiolbassa's report, they create evil comment about him, distorting the entire case.</p>
   <p>This incident is interesting, and it also casts an equally interesting light upon the local press, hence we cannot allow ourselves to miss the opportunity to answer some of the criticism of such papers. First, to fully understand the matter, we offer a verbatim translation of Mr. Kiolbassa's report. The account is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1734.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Gentlemen, the banks in which the undersigned deposited the money belonging to the city, have paid to the undersigned the sum of $44,500.70 in interest for the municipal funds for the year ending May 1, 1892. It has cost the undersigned $16,600 for salaries of the officials and for other incidental expenses. Adding to this the yearly [treasurer's] compensation $15,000, we have an entire expenditure of $31,600 for the year just mentioned, which leaves $12,900.70 as the balance of the unused interest money, which amount will be used to pay the expenses for the ensuing year, since the City Council did not appropriate funds for the maintenance of my office for this year. The sum of $18,000, appropriated by the City Council for the past year, was not paid out and the undersigned could not make use of it; consequently, it is left as the City's property. The expenses of the bureau have increased considerably in the past year because of the increase of business and the weekly payments of pensions.</p>
   <p>The undersigned is not legally bound to present this report, nor has the City any legal right to the interest accrued from the city funds. This accounting is, therefore, merely a courteous gesture toward the Council and the remainder of the interest is set aside, because the undersigned promised the voters before <pb facs="5423968_3_1735.jpg" n="3"/>his election that he would return all interests accrued from the municipal monies, which would be left after paying the expenses of conducting the office and his personal compensation."</p>
   <p>Peter Kiolbassa,</p>
   <p>Treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
