<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-26">Mar. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Poles Shouid Vote for the Democrats in the Coming Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-26">Mar. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE POLES SHOUID VOTE FOR THE DEMOCRATS IN THE COMING ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of the Gazeta Katolicka (Catholic Gazette), there is a very interesting article based on the idea of "Why the Poles Should Vote for the Democrats In the Coming Election." From it we quote some of the passages.</p>
   <p>"After close and thoughtful consideration we have come to the conclusion that it would be for our best interests to support the Democratic ticket. There are various reasons for this. One is that the principal candidates on the Democratic ticket, as has been pointed out in a previous number, are men who above all else are honest, capable and friendly toward us.</p>
   <p>"As to Frank Wenter, candidate for Mayor, even the Republican newspapers have not been able thus far to publish a thing derogatory to his character. This, perhaps, is the most conclusive evidence that the Democratic candidate for Mayor must be a person of irreproachable character. And this is so in reality. Besides this, he is the most popular individual in the City of Chicago today. He <pb facs="5423968_3_0957.jpg" n="2"/>is respected in labor circles because he has always been a friend of the poor, and whenever occasion called he justly protected the interests of the working class.</p>
   <p>"....Those who have worked with him and are working with him today confirm these statements. Further, Frank Wenter always has been a perfect gentleman in public life. He looked after the various offices he held to the best of his ability, and gave general satisfaction to all. At the present he holds the position of president of the Drainage Canal Commission, for which he was unanimously appointed, and it must be remembered that Republicans as well as Democrats hold offices in this commission (sic). And Frank Wenter, the friend of the workers who has introduced several resolutions in their favor, was chosen to head this important department.</p>
   <p>"Such an individual deserves the strongest support of our ranks.</p>
   <p>"As to the other candidates, Mr. Cooke for City Treasurer, Mr. Mangler for <pb facs="5423968_3_0958.jpg" n="3"/>City Clerk, and Mr. Trude for Corporation Counsel all are worthy of the same consideration. Mr. Cooke is a Catholic.</p>
   <p>"The candidate of the Republican party for Mayor, Alderman Swift, is a member of the American Protective Association. [Translator's note: This organization was anti-Catholic and anti-immigrant]. When he spoke to the Poles at St. Hedwig Parish, he told them, among many other things, that when he is elected Mayor the church will be opened. This intrusion of an enemy of the church into our affairs, which does not concern him in the least, has even made the bitterest opponents of the archbishop wonder and ask the question: 'Since when does Swift have the right to open Catholic churches?' Thus far this has been performed only by the bishops. Political mongers should keep their hands off our churches!</p>
   <p>"Mr. Swift has always been in political affairs. A glance through the City Council records will reveal that whenever there was concern over the passage of an ordinace of a suspicious nature Mr. Swift was always on hand (sic). As to <pb facs="5423968_3_0959.jpg" n="4"/>the workers, according to what some of the papers published, he said that fifty cents a day was sufficient for them. When he was Commissioner of Public Works, under Mayor Roach, not one Pole was assigned a job, although they voted for Roach.</p>
   <p>"Swift will not find support from any faithful citizen, for he always belonged to the Republican political machine--and therefore no Pole--no honest person--should vote for him.</p>
   <p>"Let us support the Democratic party with all our strength. Let us remember that the Poles are given recognition under the present Democratic administration, for many have been given important positions. Several hundred Poles had employment during the most critical times.</p>
   <p>"All this will come to an end if the Republican should be victorious; a score or more will be replaced from their high-salaried positions, and several hundred will be dropped from various other city jobs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0960.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Some of the Swift adherents may say that in their place a similar number of Polish Republicans will be given offices and city jobs. But there are none so naive as to believe this.</p>
   <p>"How many positions did Mayor Roach offer to the Poles? What did the Polish voters receive for helping the Republicans win in the November election? A total of two subordinate positions--that is all."</p>
   <p>As is shown by these clear and convincing statements, he who wishes well unto himself and his family--let him vote for the Democrats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
