<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-01-25">Jan. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Awakening of the People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-01-25">Jan. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE AWAKENING OF THE PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, we have millions of working men who barely earn their living, and, on the other hand we have individuals who draw on the resources of the common public, and live in splendor. On one side we have millions who are hungry and thirsty, and on the other-rapidly diminishing groups of selfish individuals, who live in luxury, extermininating, by any means, every healthy thought, and suppressing every revolt directed against their authority with the power of gold. This small unscrupulous group is always victorious, even though the other group, which represents the masses is so many times larger.</p>
   <p>It seems that there is no remedy for this evil, because we are interested only in trifles and forget important matters. It seems that these orgies of the potentates will go on forever, uninterrupted. However, it will not remain so, there is still salvation for us; there is a brighter future, but-we must realize our great strength, our great power, which is capable of controlling those who promise us happiness in the future in exchange for the misery of the present. Let the working masses try to comprehend this simple, but great truth, and let them not agree to the degrading terms of the potentates and their exploiters, but valiantly demand their rights, and protection for the downtroden; then, there will be a regeneration; then, there will be resurrection so long suppressed by the fire and sword.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0451.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The truth is that we are all equal, that we have the right to happiness. Not the kind of happiness which is proffered by the great of this world, but the kind of happiness to which every working man is entitled. As long as we follow the footsteps of those who have corrupted our Master's teachings, and who make a business of it, so long there will be oppression and misery.</p>
   <p>We have had enough of misery, enough of suffering. Let us, every one, realize that we have a right to happiness. It is only then, that that great mass of humanity, which is made up of individuals, will raise that great stone, now oppressing them; and there will be a resurrection, and an awakening of the people, the real awakening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
