<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From the Garment Workers Union Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">Magdalene Milewski, Director of the Polish National Alliance, Speaks at Strikers' Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE GARMENT WORKERS UNION STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Magdalene Milewski, Director of the Polish National Alliance, Speaks at Strikers' Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Magdalene Milewski, director of the Polish National Alliance, was one of the speakers at a meeting held day before yesterday on Milwaukee Avenue by the strikers. Since she is not a member of organized labor, we particularly emphasize the fact that her words come from a person who has no personal interest in the strike.</p>
   <p>"Every individual," said Mrs. Milewski, "sees the injustices which are perpetrated against the girls working in garment factories. Invited by your organizer, who, parenthetically speaking, is a member of our organization, I came here to tell you that although we do not have much in common with the battle which you are waging, nevertheless we observe carefully everything which is happening in this strike.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"If a girl working in a factory cannot earn more than what she does, if, as your organizers maintain, there are among you girls who earn only four dollars a week, then it is high time that the factory owners who pay such wages cease producing dresses and blouses. The average woman who has not worked in a garment factory does not realize that every time she puts on a silk dress to go to a ball, she is putting on a shroud of the tear-stained labor of a sister-woman who is unable even to eke out a mere existence at this work.</p>
   <p>"Your battle is just. It is the protest of women against abuse as such. It should meet with the support of Polish organizations, the Polish press, and all people of good will. Your victory will be woman's victory, because, truly, your battle is against abuse."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
