<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-02-23">Feb. 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">The Comedy in Springfield</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-02-23">Feb. 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMEDY IN SPRINGFIELD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conduct of the Democrats in Springfield deserves great credit, regardless of any objections one may have against their platform and their candidate to the United States Senate. Up to now the Democrats have performed their duties faithfully, and present indications are that they will continue to do so in the future in spite of the obstacles put in their way by other parties. From the very beginning, General Palmer has been receiving uninterruptedly, 101 votes from 101 Democrats.</p>
   <p>This being the case, the Republicans are acting queerly. They have a few candidates, but for some reason or other there is a discord among them, some voting for one candidate and others for another. They have convinced the whole nation that out of a hundred Republicans more than ninety could be persuaded to change their minds in regard to any of their candidates, whether the candidate is imposed upon them or even if he does not support their cause, <pb facs="5423968_3_1758.jpg" n="2"/>provided that no Democrat will be elected. A few Republicans still hold together, but the honor belongs only to themselves as individuals; the party itself is apparently tottering.</p>
   <p>Minor parties stringing with the Republicans are by no means faultless, yet they may be excused on the ground that they still hope to have one of their candidates elected. Ten days ago two of these candidates stated emphatically that they do not trust the Republicans, and that in order to end this shameful comedy and save money to the State, they will give their votes to Palmer. They promised to do this within two days, but so far they have not done it.</p>
   <p>The comedy taking place in Springfield is a disgrace to the State, and it could be avoided if each party would firmly support its candidate. Even if no senator were elected, which would be a very unfortunate circumstance, it would not be a disgrace to the party. As the Republican Party has a few candidates, the whole comedy is only a dishonor to that organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
