<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-22">Apr. 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Hold Mass Meeting to Protest against the Recent Appointment of Judges for West Town</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-04-22">Apr. 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLES HOLD MASS MEETING TO PROTEST AGAINST THE RECENT APPOINTMENT OF JUDGES FOR WEST TOWN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The announcement on Saturday of appointments for justices of the peace for West Town provoked the Poles of Chicago, because not one Polish name was listed among the many appointments.</p>
   <p>The Poles were aroused to such an extent over this that they held a mass meeting yesterday at the New Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets, which was arranged by a committee of Polish citizens to voice protest against this action. Polish citizens from various parts of Chicago and of different political following attended the meeting.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened at 4 P. M. by John Arkuszewski of the Sixteenth Ward. S. F. Adalia Sathlecki (Ninth Ward), president of the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, was called upon to act as chairman, and <pb facs="5423968_3_1564.jpg" n="2"/>August Sawicki of the Fifteenth Ward was chosen as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>After a few words by the chairman, Peter Kiolbassa took the stand as the initial speaker. Serious of countenance, Mr. Kiolbassa indicated that the recent procedure of the judges [Translator's note: the district judges of the Circuit Court during this period had the right to appoint justices of the peace] was a gross injustice. The Poles living on the West Side pay taxes and carry all the burdens equally with the other nationality groups; therefore, they should have equal rights. Our nationality should be given consideration. Up to the present time we have had a Polish justice of the peace [M A. La Buy] in West Town; we should continue to have him. This is a just and necessary demand. Thousands of unpleasant incidents were experienced by the Poles when there was no Polish judge among the large number of judges. In view of the large number of Poles, we ought to have two Polish judges [a justice of the peace also acted as judge]. Consequently, the demand for one judge is not too great a request. There were several Polish candidates for justices of the peace, and if the first one did not prove qualified then the <pb facs="5423968_3_1565.jpg" n="3"/>second or third could have been selected. But this was not done--and we have been wronged.</p>
   <p>"I have been a resident of Chicago for a long time, and I have seen many incidents where Poles have been wronged; but the present one is the worst. It is high time that we voice our protest," he concluded.</p>
   <p>Other impressive speeches were made by Anthony W. Rudnicki, Francis Bieszki and S. F. Satalecki. A few words were also spoken by the editor of Dziennik Chicagoski, Henry Nagiel.</p>
   <p>All the speakers were generously applauded by the audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kiolbassa, J. Arkuszewski and Michael Majewski were chosen to prepare a resolution of protest. At the same time a committee of five was picked out to present the resolution to Governor Altgeld at Springfield during the course <pb facs="5423968_3_1566.jpg" n="4"/>of the week. Similiar meetings of protest will be held in other Polish communities.</p>
   <p>The resolution that was adopted reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Because one fifth of the population in West Town consists of Polish people;</p>
   <p>"Because the courts of justice would benefit a great deal if all cases appearing on the dockets in which Poles are involved or hold interest were tried by a person who knows their language, habits and custom; and</p>
   <p>"Because the district judges of the Circuit Court of Cook County have taken personal interest in appointing four judges of Irish descent, two of Bohemian, one of Scandinavian, one of German, and one American, they have in this way given recognition to the various nationalities; therefore, it is hereby resolved:</p>
   <p>"That, not wishing to stir up the racial question, nor refer to nationalistic <pb facs="5423968_3_1567.jpg" n="5"/>prejudices, not less then as loyal American citizens who pay taxes on an equal basis with others, and carry the burdens of the nation, we are of the opinion that a citizen of Polish extraction, familiar with the Polish tongue, should be appointed to the office of justice of the peace of West Town; and that is why we solemnly protest against the procedure of the judges who have selected, among others, two Bohemians who represent a much smaller portion of the population than the Poles, and ignored the aspirations of several Polish candidates, two of whom are not only capable but well trained for such duties.</p>
   <p>The resolution was adopted unanimously.</p>
   <p>The committee, composed of Peter Kiolbassa, Francis Bieszki, John Biniak, and N. L. Piotrowski, will leave tonight for Springfield to present the resolution to Governor Altgeld.</p>
   <p>Hope is expressed that such energetic action will bring results, and that <pb facs="5423968_3_1568.jpg" n="6"/>Governor Altgeld will consider the request of the Polish citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
