<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-17">Mar. 17, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">We Lack Polish Judges in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-03-17">Mar. 17, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">WE LACK POLISH JUDGES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In proportion to the Polish population of Chicago there is a shortage of Polish judges. Taking into consideration the total number of votes cast by us, and the number of judges seated in the local courts, we begin to realize that our number of representatives is very small and rather weak. We have many able men, prominent in all field of business, as also a great number in the law field. These men, because of their education, their fine character, and understanding of conditions, have qualification necessary to perform the duties of a judge. Yet there are only three that are seated: S. <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>larkowski, Circuit court judge; in the county chair we have Ed. Jarecki; and Peter Schwabe in the Municipal Court.</p>
   <p>In the Municipal court we should have at least six Polish judges. The Polish people of Chicago should, therefore, elect another judge to this court. The Crowe-Thompson Republican group has selected one of our own men from the lawyer ranks to run for office; Marian G. Kudlick has been selected as a candidate on the Republican ballot. It is a privilege and an honor for the Polish voter to be able to vote for <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> own countryman. All Polish-American voters, both men <pb facs="5423968_3_1628.jpg" n="2"/>and women, should go to their polling places on Apr. 10 and vote for Marian Kudlick. This should be done with pride, for they deserve to have their own representative in office.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kudlick was born of Polish parents who resided on the Northwest side of Chicago. He attended the Polish schools until he went to the John Marshall Law School where he received his degree.</p>
   <p>After passing the bar examination, Mr. Kudlick found employment with the well-known firm of Conkling Price and Webb in the law department, where he remained for thirteen years; he then founded the law firm of Myka and Kudlick. Judge Himes, who is Counsellor of the Northwestern Trust and Savings Bank, was his assistant.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kudlick is a member of various organizations, fraternal and political. He served during the World War and helped to organize the Kelly Post, No. 339 of the American Legion. He served as a commander. He is married and resides with <pb facs="5423968_3_1629.jpg" n="3"/>his family at 5350 Hutchinson Street, in Portage Park.</p>
   <p>The primary election will be held Tuesday, Apr. 10.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
