<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 32,
<date when="1919-08-06">Aug. 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Profits to Some Are a Loss to Others</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 32,
<date when="1919-08-06">Aug. 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PROFITS TO SOME ARE A LOSS TO OTHERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few days two incidents happened in Chicago. The first of great importance; the second less important in comparison, but <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> is worth while considering. From Tuesday, July 20th, to Saturday, August 2, the motormen and guards of the elevated lines and the motormen and conductors of the surface lines were on strike. On the streets of a great city we saw only automobiles and wagons. Some workers went to their work on foot; some rode in automobiles; others remained at home. However, we are not so much concerned about that. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> withstood these few days. But what will be the consequences? In reality, the conductors and motormen will receive a better pay because it is now 67 cents per hour. They will gain by this, On the other hand, the factory workers are being wronged, as they must use the street car to and from work, since with the raise in pay to street car men, the price of carfare may be raised.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0043.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>lose nothing. The street car men gain. The owners of automobiles and the wealthier class of people who do not use the surface or elevated lines, will not be touched at all by this. It will be the poorer classes that will be wronged, who cannot afford automobiles or coaches.</p>
   <p>The second incident: In a Polish section there is a Polish theatre named Kosciuszko. We do not know the owner of this theatre, but we did hear that he is not a wealthy man. Generally, Polish owners of theatres in America have not as yet acquired millions.</p>
   <p>During the past week some malefactors placed a bomb which explode and damaged the little theatre. We do not know who was the wrongdoer, but we surmise that it was a person from the poorer class, or maybe, as they are saying, a member of a union, since this theatre employed non-union men.</p>
   <p>And what is the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of this? it is that there was an attempt, <pb facs="5423968_3_0044.jpg" n="3"/>either through jealousy or hatred, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> take away from a non-wealthy man the means of earning his daily bread.</p>
   <p>The above incidents attest to the fact that during the present time a battle is being waged, not only between capital and labor, but also among the working class itself, that is, among workers of different trades.</p>
   <p>To what this will lead us, it is <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to predict.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
