<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 9
<date when="1907-03-26">March 26, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Voting - A Moment of Battle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 9<date when="1907-03-26">March 26, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Voting - A Moment of Battle</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The time has arrived when the working class should think and be active for their own benefit. Equally, the men and women, should cooperate, striving toward their one aim: The possession of people's rights.</p>
   <p>The working people for thousands of years cared for their "masters." They built palaces for them, while they themselves resided in inconvenient huts. In general, the working class created everything possible to ease their master's strife in life.</p>
   <p>These same public workers took an active part in all of the world's battles but never yet staged an important battle in behalf of their own rights.</p>
   <p>Many people have sacrificed their own blood on murderous battlefields in order to gain a throne for some kind of king or nobleman, or with the aim of gaining new territories for their imperialists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0467.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not until now in their own workers' organizations have they learned to think and fight for themselves, for their own class. Also among the series of organized workers there are created better methods or forms of batter with the tormentors of the people.</p>
   <p>At the present moment we also witness the events of a strike for better working conditions, this being a form of battle, a worthy objective for the workers to support. There is still another form of battle, more efficacious, this being the right and power to vote, and aid for the working class.</p>
   <p>To this day great masses of toilers on various fields always voted for others just as they work for others.</p>
   <p>Today we have harnessed the working people and organized them in the various industries; we also organized this working group into two <pb facs="5423968_3_0468.jpg" n="3"/>political parties, a power to help us in various needs.</p>
   <p>Those who create riches should manage them. Those who are leaders of a nation should conduct the nation's government. And so the working class, also being a creator, with its mass of followers, should be given the ruling position, since they are capable of taking over the nation's government into their own hands and becoming of some use for the people. This shall be the Socialist goal.</p>
   <p>If only the working groups would vote for their own interests, there might be a possible chance that a time will come when they will be able to work for themselves and not for anyone else.</p>
   <p>In a strike struggle the laborers buck their cents against the millions of dollars poured out by the capitalists.</p>
   <p>While in the battle of election, when voting for Socialism, the workers <pb facs="5423968_3_0469.jpg" n="4"/>have the support of millions of their votes against the few thousands votes of the mighty ones.</p>
   <p>If we unanimously vote this way and unanimously strike, the time would arrive when strikes would be uncalled for.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
