<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-23">May 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting to Protest Dismissal of E. Z. Brodowski</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolution against Governor Altgeld</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-23">May 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING TO PROTEST DISMISSAL OF E. Z. BRODOWSKI</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolution against Governor Altgeld</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting was held last night at the Bradley Street Polish School Hall in behalf of E. Z. Brodowski, park commissioner, who was so unceremoniously and unreasonably removed from office by Governor Altgeld. Approximately three thousand people gathered at the big school hall.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Thomas Krolik, who called upon F. Bieszka to act as chairman. H. Nagiel, acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>W. Bardonski was the first speaker. He explained the situation thoroughly, pointed out the groundlessness of the charges made against Brodowski, and the brutal way in which he was removed from office by the governor; he demanded that a protest be made against this action, which is an insult to all Poles.</p>
   <p>The next speaker, Stanislaus Slominski, defended Brodowski very ardently and <pb facs="5423968_3_1382.jpg" n="2"/>at some length, pointing out that Brodowski, as park commissioner, had done all he could for his countrymen. They, in turn, should take his part, and protest against this injustice to one of our representatives. Slominski's speech was greatly applauded.</p>
   <p>After this speech, and on a motion made by W. Bardonski, a resolutions committee was chosen. The committee consists of the following persons: W. Smulski, W. Bardonski, A. J. Kowalski, S. Slominski, J. Arkuszewski, Stanislaus Lauferski, and M. Osuch.</p>
   <p>Then W. Tomasik spoke, pointing out that Polish honor is at stake, and that we should defend it by all means. The next speaker, Casimir Zychlinski, explained our rights, and told us how we should defend them, he pointed out that Brodowski, an honest and capable official, had incurred the hatred of the politicians of other nationalities just because he supported his countrymen. The next speaker, P. Gackowski, called for three cheers in honor of Brodowski. P. Roland spoke about the injustice committed against Brodowski, and blamed the governor for <pb facs="5423968_3_1383.jpg" n="3"/>it. P. Sowinski, who lives near Humboldt Park, testified that he himself had seen how Brodowski had worked, and how he had established order in the park. P. K. Dorszynski spoke in favor of our commissioner. A. Rudnicki also spoke. The last speaker was Alderman Kuntz, who said that the governor does not know what he is doing, and warned Poles against exploitation by politicians of other nationalities; he made a motion that a committee be chosen to deliver the resolution, adopted at the meeting, to Governor Altgeld.</p>
   <p>The committee then submitted the resolution, which is as follows:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Governor John P. Altgeld removed E. Z. Brodowski from the office of park commissioner on May 21, 1894, giving incompetence in fulfilling the duties of that office as the reason for dismissal; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We, citizens of the United States, of Polish extraction, who know E. Z. Brodowski very well, are cognizant of his abilities, which he has displayed as businessman and editor, and in his performance of other public <pb facs="5423968_3_1384.jpg" n="4"/>duties during the course of his residence in this city; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, He gave further proof of his ability by being twice elected auditor of the West Park Board; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, citizens of the United States, of Polish extraction, gathered at this meeting, condemn the governor's action as an insult, not only to our nationality but also to E. Z. Brodowski, our representative. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That, if the governor has no other motive for the removal of E. Z. Brodowski than his supposed incompetence, we consider this a poor excuse, which does not justify removal of a competent man from public office, who for some reason, is disliked by the governor or his agents in Chicago. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, Chicagoans of Polish extraction, do hereby protest against <pb facs="5423968_3_1385.jpg" n="5"/>this unjustified act, and express our indignation at the improper manner in which our countryman was removed from an office for which he is quite qualified."</p>
   <p>On a motion made by W. Bardonski, the resolution was adopted enthusiastically by a rising vote.</p>
   <p>The committee for presenting the resolution to the governor consists of the following citizens, Stanley Kunz, W. Bardonski, August J. Kowalski, F. Bieszke, M. Drzemala, S. Lauferski, and K. Zychlinski.</p>
   <p>This concluded the meeting. All of today's English-language newspapers comment on the mass meeting, and publish the protest against the governor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
