<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1938-02-07">Feb. 7, 1938</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Heard in Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1938-02-07">Feb. 7, 1938</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS HEARD IN POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Democratic Organization was called together, to purge itself of all injustice and mistakes. The dominating clique of this organization has no regard for the interests of the Poles; their motives are selfish and they are interested only in their own political welfare. Benjamin S. Adamowski, member of the State Legislature, informed the members, that in their actions, they were not adhering to the Constitution. Governor Horner conducted a lengthy conference yesterday. He concluded that Judge Jarecki, and Benjamin S. Adamowski shall receive his whole-hearted support.</p>
   <p>What Prominent Citizens are Saying about Judge Jarecki---</p>
   <p>The Polish Democratic Club, which is composed of political job holders, who are serving the Nash-Kelley-Democratic-Machine for a pot of porridge, held a very stormy meeting. This meeting was called, supposedly, for the purpose of discussing the most recent cause of the dissatisfaction among Chicago Poles, the removal of Mr. Jarecki from the Democratic slate. The big-shots of the Polish Democratic organization were largely responsible for that removal. However, the purpose in reality of that meeting was to mislead themselves and the whole Polish community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1106.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We all know today, that a few leaders of that organization, serving political bosses, endorse and support only those candidates who are tractable to the central committee which is dominated by Messrs. Nash and Kelly. Why consult all the members of the Polish Democratic Organization? Why pull the wool over their eyes when the matter was already settled by the flunkeys of Nash and Felly, who do as they are told by their political bosses, but who expect something in return for it. In reality these gentlemen are not interested in the welfare of the Polish community; they don't care a rap for the interests of the Polish settlement. They are interested only in their own jobs; only and again only, in their own "I". They do not represent the Polish community because, the Pole's desire is to have honorable and self-respecting citizens as their leaders; not tractable flunkeys, who can be ordered around as office boys, by their bosses.</p>
   <p>At the Saturday's session of the Polish Democratic Organization,which betrayed the interests of the whole Polish community of Chicago, Mr. Benjamin S. Adamowski, the majority leader, and a state senator, was present. He was also troublesome to the Nash -Kelly-Machine, and, like Mr. Jarecki, was removed from the state. The Polish Democratic organization treated Mr. Adamowski in a like manner. The fact that Mr. Adamowski, just as Mr. Jarecki, has made his Polish name famous, so that Americans could have the same confidence in him, and the same respect for him, as they have for Mr. Jarecki does not concern them: neither does the fact that the Polish community <pb facs="5423968_3_1107.jpg" n="3"/>of Chicago wants honest men in office as their representatives. They only care for orders from Nash and Kelly. These orders are filled very scrupulously for a pot of porridge and such other personal benefits. Indeed, these representatives of the Polish community, evoke only contempt, in the members of the Polish Democratic Organization, for their lack of backbone. At that meeting, Senator Adamowski condemned the decision of the Polish Democratic Organization very emphatically. He told them what he thinks of the removal of Mr. Jarecki and himself, from the slate, he also expressed his opinion of the organization which consented to such action, by saying that such an organization is not concerned about the interests of the Polish community of Chicago, but betrays them. His courageous speech was enthusiastically applauded by the members of that organization, which fact proves that the decision of the majority does not count in such matters, the actual decision is made by Nash and Kelly leaders who look for a crumb themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
