<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 122,
<date when="1905-05-25">May 25, 1905</date><title level="a">Banquet in Honor of John F. Smulski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1685</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1685.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 122,
<date when="1905-05-25">May 25, 1905</date><title level="a">BANQUET IN HONOR OF JOHN F. SMULSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About two hundred prominent and esteemed Polish citizens from different sections of the city of Chicago gathered yesterday at the Sherman House Hotel to pay honor to the counselor of our city of Chicago, John F. Smulski, for his wonderful representation of the Polish people in all city affairs and our congratulations for his remarkable victory in the past election and best wishes for success in the future.</p>
   <p>Among this great mass were many prominent women who paid tribute to this Polish idol. After the banquet at these beautifully decorated tables there were toasts. Then began the speeches about different subjects introduced by the members of the committee in charge of this banquet Mr. W. Bardonski. Dr. A. Szwajkart was master of ceremonies, who spoke after each speech introducing every new speaker.</p>
   <p>The following made speeches in this order: Most Reverend Father Casmir Sztucko, spoke about "Our Obligation," Mr. M. Steczynski spoke about "Fourth column"; Mr. A. Czarnecki spoke about "Young Poles"; Mr. R. Klarkowski spoke about "America, our new country" (after his speech was finished he gave a toast for the United States, and for its President, Theodore Roosevelt); Reverend Father Kosinski gave a speech, "Counselor of Chicago," a very interesting talk that was applauded for many minutes. At the finish of this speech, Mr. Bardonski gave an emotional and affectionate speech, "Love each other,"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1686.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>then handed Mr. Smulski a silver dinner set donated by the guests. It consisted of ninety-one pieces of the best grade of silverware obtainable, in a cedar case, with a plate which bore the inscription, "John J. Smulski - As a remembrance, April 6, 1905. Fellow citizens."</p>
   <p>Mr. Smulski took this opportunity to thank all his guests for the wonderful ovation, their speeches, their true love for him and, most of all, for their gift; he also stated that they should remember him as a true representative of all Polish people in Chicago and not forget his name at the coming election.</p>
   <p>This beautiful banquet came to a close at 1 A.M., and showed the interest of the Polish people in a true representative. All the guests were Poles; the programs, tickets, and invitations, were printed in Polish, and all the speeches were in Polish which shows that the true hearts of these citizens are for their native tongue and for the support of their true brother.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
