<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-28">Aug. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Political Front</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-28">Aug. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE POLITICAL FRONT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reliable information has reached the Dziennik Zwiazkowy that Mr. Louis Pinderski is a candidate for clerk of the municipal court on the Republican ticket in the forthcoming election. Mr. Pinderski is an active member of Group 1450 of the Polish National Alliance. He is well known for his past activities in behalf of the Polish people. Mr. Pinderski is a man who deserves the solid support of all our people who have the right and privilege of voting.</p>
   <p>All Poles in Chicago should stand undivided in their support of Polish-American candidates. They should vote for Poles only and in this way put as many as possible of our own people into city positions. By so doing we may have proper representation whenever the need shall arise. It is high time that we Poles demonstrated to other nationalities that we are politically mature. Let others know that we are capable of defending our rights in a manner befitting good citizens. By so doing we shall compel them to treat us as a power to be reckoned with at all times.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0659.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In unity lies strength, and only by united effort can we hope to accomplish anything. Consequently, let us act in co-operation. The best way to do this is to vote for Polish candidates for municipal, state, or even national elective offices, regardless of their party affiliations.</p>
   <p>A meeting will be held this evening at the Morrison Hotel in Chicago. Here the voters are invited to be present to discuss the qualifications of Mr. Pinderski.</p>
   <p>All Polish-American citizens are cordially invited to attend the meeting and to give active support to the candidacy of Mr. Pinderski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
