<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-24">Aug. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Memorial to the Tenth Convention of the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0538</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0538.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-08-24">Aug. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">MEMORIAL TO THE TENTH CONVENTION OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We came upon a very interesting document yesterday. It is a printed piece with the extravagant title, Memorial to the Delegates to the Tenth Convention of the Polish National Alliance. The document is signed by a nameless "Committee"; the addresses of three places are given, where signatures to the Memorial may be obtained.</p>
   <p>The first address is that of the anarchistic Nowe Zycie (New Life); the second, that of the well-known anarchist agitator, S. Modrzewski. The third address, as we already know from Mr. Migdalski's letter, received yesterday by us, was used without authority--its use was an abuse of confidence.</p>
   <p>Upon closer inspection, the Memorial appears to be a monstrosity, created by <pb facs="5423968_3_0539.jpg" n="2"/>people who are mentally deficient. It begins with a declamation on the subject of the oppression and exploitation of Polish workingmen in America, and immediately attacks the "guardians" (clergy) who, "fed with bread and honey by the workers, sacrifice the workers' souls and honor to worldly ideals." It continues further, blaspheming shamelessly about the "dollar on the cross" and reviling the parochial schools, in which the "guardians push the Polish children into an abyss of darkness and slavery". Finally, the Memorial addresses the Polish National Alliance and makes a series of very curious demands. There are four of these three of which do not greatly concern us. "Polish National Alliance" be changed to "Polish National Alliance of Workingmen"--probably along socialistic lines. The Alliance itself must attend to demands of this kinds, which, if put into effect, would imperil the very foundation of this institution, which exists as yet under the national banner. And we are certain that the Alliance will attend to them properly. Whatever the character of some of its officials, the Alliance is strong enough to resist the socialistic demands of this nameless committee. We are not concerned, therefore, with the last three demands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0540.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We would like to call general attention to the first demand, which advises the delegates as follows: "To appeal energetically to the proper authorities in the United States for supervision over thousands of our children in parochial schools, who are misled and degenerated by uninvited internationalists--apostles of oppression and ignorance, so that the proper authorities will control our schools and examine our teachers."</p>
   <p>This is the point that concerns us. What does it mean? It is a shameless denunciation of that which constitutes the dearest treasure of the Polish people in America--Polish schools, Catholic schools. In calling the teachers and directors of these schools, which given us new Polish generations...., "apostles of oppression and ignorance," the authors of the Memorial commit a crime against the Polish cause, against their own nation. Ostensibly, their demand is to put Polish Catholic schools under the control of others--of a different faith. To destroy these schools is their real aim. But the Russians would like the same thing, as do all of the most implacable enemies of Catholics and Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0541.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To struggle with this, to advance arguments against it, is wasted effort. The very fact that the Polish schools have been thus basely calumniated will <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>rouse indignation in all truly Polish hearts. Finally, one may well wonder what nonsense and shamelessness hides beneath a demand that the Alliance, a Polish national institution, help denounce and destroy that which is the very source of our national spirit. It is superfluous to ask what right has the Alliance to say who shall control Polish schools, which it has neither created nor is concerned with.</p>
   <p>Once more we point out the wickedness of this Memorial. Nameless and falsifying other people's signatures, it seeks to inject into our society the poison of calumny and atheistic tendencies. What we have built up, it would tear down. Its author is either insane or an enemy of Poland--which one, it is difficult to say. At any rate, whoever has concealed himself in anonymity in order to spread poison ought to be most severely condemned. The Polish people will forever regard him and his kind as their most dangerous enemies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
