<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 17,
<date when="1921-04-28">April 28, 1921</date><title level="a">Revenge and Hope</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 17,
<date when="1921-04-28">April 28, 1921</date><title level="a">REVENGE AND HOPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The agitators of socialism, communism and bolshevism, touring America and getting rich from the collections taken among American Poles, appeal not so much to the intellect as to the feelings of their audience. They know that the arguments about the profits derived from a social system based on socialism or comunism could be made to appear very simple and explained in a scientific way.</p>
   <p>Therefore they appeal to their emotions because that way they can win their audience. There are two kinds of emotions to which the agitators appeal revenge and hope.</p>
   <p>Revenge for real or imaginary injuries, for supposed oppressions, and in many cases for mistreatment. Revenge on the rich, the priests, the frocked men in general; in other words, revenge on the class that is wealthy, intelligent, industrious, ruling. To deprive these people of all possessions and influence, to remove them from positions and management, and even to murder them, as it happened in Bolshevik Russia, that's the revenge which the Bolshevik agitators are advocating, the revenge to which they are inciting the people and which they promise to the people as a reward for starting the revolution. We said a "reward" because revenge, although a sin, is <pb facs="5423968_3_0284.jpg" n="2"/>nevertheless pleasant. The English proverb says, "Revenge is sweet."</p>
   <p>Another emotion to which they appeal is the hope. The hope of a better life, hope of a comfortable and luxurious life with very small efforts and short working days.</p>
   <p>The agitators claim that as soon as the properties of the rich are confiscated and as soon as the production for profit is discontinued, there will be plenty of everything for everybody for there will be production only for need. Then there will be a continuous prosperity, the working hours will be shortened, all will be able to attend schools, all will be intelligent and happy.</p>
   <p>With that promise of revenge and hope of a better life as a bait are the gullible caught like a fish on a hook with an artificial bait.</p>
   <p>What answer is given by reality? One glance at Russia is enough to convince us of the truth. For three years and a half Russia had been ruled by Bolsheviks. At first it was a socialistic and later on a communistic form of government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Communism means that the whole nation, as a unit, is the owner of all the resources and means of production such as factories, machinery, railroads, which, mines, etc., including the land.</p>
   <p>Today's form of government in Russia is communistic. And what are the conditions today in Russia? Is there prosperity? Is there work for all? Is there enough food, not mentioning clothing, shoes and pleasures of life? No. It is true that there are no rich people there. They were, either murdered or forced to sweep the streets. They took revenge upon them. The desire of revenge has been satisfied but there is no prosperity, on the contrary, there is more misery in Russia now than there ever was in any country of the world. Those who dare to complain or try to abolish communism are placed before the firing squad and the revolution is crushed in a ruthless way. The Bolshevik government is more despotic and more tyranical than was the Czar's government.</p>
   <p>Why is there misery in communistic Russia? Is it because there is no imports? No. Russia is a very fertile and fruitful country. She never needed any grain from other countries. And now there is not enough grain or flour to feed her own people. There is misery because people do not want to work. Of what good is the government's pay for so many hours of work, bushels of paper rubles when they are worthless because nothing can be bought with them, <pb facs="5423968_3_0286.jpg" n="4"/>no bread, no shoes, no coal <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> anything that is needed every day.</p>
   <p>The government is the owner of everything because that is communism. The whole community is the owner of everything and the government is its expression and representation. Where everybody is the owner of everything, there nobody has anything.</p>
   <p>The Russian peasant does not want that, he demands that the soil which he cultivates should be his and not everybody's and for the products of his land the Russian peasant does not want worthless paper but he wants shoes, clothing, farming implements, salt, soap and other necessary articles. He does not get them, therefore he does not cultivate his soil efficiently enough to supply the city people with his products, he raises only for enough for himself.</p>
   <p>The Russian working man who was promised before revolution all the wealth and prosperity for only four hours of work, is starving to death. He does not want to work for some one else and is not allowed to work for himself. He suffers a terrible misery. Such are the conditions in Russia. Such example Russia gives to the world after a three year trial of communism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0287.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And now the communistic agitators are trying to mislead our Polish working man not only in Poland but also here in America by persuading him to join their party or to go on strike and be always ready for the revolution.</p>
   <p>If any one wants to harm our working man in America, if any one wants to harm or destroy our fatherland Poland let him listen and give his dollars to Bolsheviks agitators who come from Poland as Bolshevik agents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
