<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Democratic League of Illinois Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMOCRATIC LEAGUE OF ILLINOIS HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Managing Committee of the Polish Democratic League of Illinois was held downtown on the afternoon of day before yesterday. The committee, which was authorized by all the members of the League to present the Polish political situation to the Democratic leaders in Chicago and Cook County, was of the opinion that Polish voters in our city and county deserve, as a reward for their loyal and solid support of the Democratic party in the coming elections, to have more than the usual candidates of Polish extraction on the Democratic ballot for the primary to be held September 11. After an intensive discussion of Polish voter problems, the following resolution, prepared by Joseph L. Lisak, president of the League, was accepted unanimously:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The American voters of Polish birth or descent have very generally and earnestly supported the Democratic party for years; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Polish Democratic League represents the Polish Democrats of the City of Chicago, County of Cook, and State of Illinois, and any action taken <pb facs="5423968_3_1140.jpg" n="2"/>by the League is indicative of the desires and wishes of the Polish Democratic voters; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The members of the Polish Democratic League of Illinois have been assured by the leaders of the regular Democratic organization of Cook County, Illinois, that the Polish voters should be rewarded by representation in elective offices, to be elected thereto through the efforts and promises of the regular Democratic organization leaders; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We, the members of the Polish Democratic League of Illinois, believe that the time has come when we must expect the fulfillment of the promises made to us; therefore, be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That the Cook County Democratic Central Committee should submit to the Democratic voters of the City of Chicago and the County of Cook a ticket containing a number of worthy and capable candidates of Polish birth or descent to be nominated for the various offices in the City of Chicago and <pb facs="5423968_3_1141.jpg" n="3"/>County of Cook at the primaries on September 11, 1918; and be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That the members of the Polish Democratic League of Illinois hereby empower the Managing Committee of said League to submit the names of prospective candidates to the Cook County Democratic Central Committee at an early date."</p>
   <p>"Polish Democratic League of Illinois,</p>
   <p>"Joseph L. Lisak, president,</p>
   <p>"John A. Koziczynski, Jr., acting secretary,</p>
   <p>"Steve L. Superczynski, John Koziczynski, Sr.,</p>
   <p>John W. Bemka, Frank K. Szarkowski,</p>
   <p>Michael Dominowski, Theophil Pokorny,</p>
   <p>Anthony A. Polczynski, members of the Committee."</p>
   <p>Copies of this resolution were sent, in the first place,to Roger C. Sullivan, leader of the Democratic party in the State of Illinois, and James M. Dailey, <pb facs="5423968_3_1142.jpg" n="4"/>chairman of the Cook County Central Democratic Committee.</p>
   <p>On Saturday, June 22, before his departure for Washington, Sullivan granted an audience in his offices to the Managing Committee of the League. J.L. Lisak spoke in behalf of the Committee, describing the Polish voter situation in Chicago, Cook County, and Illinois. Sullivan gave Lisak's arguments close attention and promised that he would endeavor to satisfy the Polish voters in the coming campaign. Sullivan took this occasion to say that some committee had already conferred with him, but that the Polish Democratic League of Illinois and its members are well known to him from their loyal support of Democratic candidates in past elections and that the League will soon achieve its aims. Other members of the committee took the floor on Polish voter problems, and Sullivan admitted that their claims were just. The Committee left Sullivan's office after a conference of almost an hour, satisfied that the Polish claims had been placed before Sullivan properly, for each member of the Managing Committee of the Polish Democratic League of Illinois has the good of the Polish voters at heart rather than personal ambition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1143.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On this occasion, it should be mentioned that the Polish Democratic League of Illinois is incorporated under the laws of the State. Meetings of the League are held every month at the Hotel Sherman, and every Polish citizen is welcome to attend. Delegates from the Polish wards present their reports, always with the idea of strengthening Polish influence in the political field here in the land of Washington rather than for personal advancement. Delegates from outside Chicago, from Danville, Momence, LaSalle, Dwight, Bradley, Westville, Streator, and Springfield, also attend.</p>
   <p>The Polish Democratic League of Illinois accepted unanimously a resolution calling for unity and harmony among the Poles on June 23, which resolution appeared in the Polish Press. The League and its members know that with unity, harmony, and co-operation, the Poles can achieve the best results in the political field. The League was the first Polish political organization to be prepared for harmony. A committee was delegated to work for co-operation among the various Polish factions, the better to serve the Polish cause and Polish candidates, but the Cook County League and certain others, so-called neutrals, presented demands which the Polish Democratic League might have regarded as just; however, its representatives were never again <pb facs="5423968_3_1144.jpg" n="6"/>notified of the Cook County League's meetings. Today, the Polish Democratic League is still ready for harmony because this is necessary for the good of the Polish cause. The sooner we unite together toward one common goal, the greater the benefits the Poles will derive from the coming campaign.</p>
   <p>Joseph L. Lisak, president,</p>
   <p>John A. Koziczynski, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
