<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-04">Nov. 4, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Political Mass Meeting Held at Polish Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-04">Nov. 4, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MASS MEETING HELD AT POLISH HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Democratic mass meeting was staged yesterday afternoon at the new Polish Hall, Bradley and Noble Streets. The meeting started about 3 P. M. after all those that had taken part in the parade had entered the Hall.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Jacob Mucha, president of the Polish Democratic Club of the Sixteenth Ward. Mr. Mucha called upon Frank Bieszke to preside as chairman and Stanislaus Czajka to act as recording secretary.</p>
   <p>In a few words Mr. Bieszke explained to the large audience the purpose of the gathering, and then presented Thomas A. Smyth, candidate for trustee of the Sanitary District.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smyth, in a long speech, pointed out the changes and improvements he would strive for if elected to this office. In conclusion he urged everyone to support <pb facs="5423968_3_0946.jpg" n="2"/>the Democratic ticket, for this is an important election. It is the duty of everyone not to forget to vote because there is great concern over the honest administration of public funds.</p>
   <p>Joseph J. Duffy, another candidate for trustee of the Sanitary District, spoke in the same vein.</p>
   <p>A speech by Judge M. A. LaBuy caught the fancy of the audience because he reminded them of the promises of Mr. Swift [Republican Mayor of Chicago] and his attitude toward the Poles after he was elected to office. Judge LaBuy asserted that only the Democrats have been favorable to the Poles. In closing he explained how to mark the ballot in tomorrow's [Tuesday's] election.</p>
   <p>A third speech was presented by Alexander J. Jones, another candidate for trustee of the Sanitary District. Mr. Jones urged everyone to vote a straight Democratic ticket, for there is a policy at stake. He also said that it is our duty to <pb facs="5423968_3_0947.jpg" n="3"/>show the Republicans that the Democrats can stay on top. The offices that are to be voted on are of vital concern. Before he left the platform he asked the audience to vote for the Torrens Land Title System.</p>
   <p>At this point A. J. Kowalski took the stand and delivered an address in Polish. He stressed the point that the Polish people should vote the straight Democratic ticket because it is the only party that respects the Poles. His words brought a warm response from the gathering.</p>
   <p>Other speakers who spoke in Polish were Stanislaus H. Kunz and Jacob Mucha.</p>
   <p>The meeting was staged in grand style and the audience was very enthusiastic. After the meeting was over Frank Wenter, another candidate for trustee of the Sanitary District, arrived. Although he was too late for the meeting, he was welcomed by those that tarried.</p>
   <p>There was one occurrence at the meeting, however, that was displeasing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0948.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Placards had been printed by some kind of Jewish concern which publicized the mass meeting. These placards contained several statements in Polish that broke every rule in grammar and spelling--the terminology was scandalous. It will be sufficient to reprint a few of these errors, such as "Wielke (Great) Mass-Meeting," "W Stanislow Skol Hall," and "Sunde 3 November".</p>
   <p>No one could determine who and for what purpose these cards were printed and publicized, although Mr. Mucha brought this subject up at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Some claimed that this was a "mistake" made by someone on the mass-meeting committee. It would be a good thing if such "mistakes" were not made again. The Poles have many Polish print shops and they should be given the work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
