<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26">Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From the Field of Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26">Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE FIELD OF POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Daily, chairman of the Democratic organization, held a conference with the Polish delegation January 24 about adding one more Pole to the committee of fifteen. The committee of fifteen is, as you know, a body that selects candidates for the Democratic ticket, for whom later the people are asked to vote. The Polish delegation was composed of Aldermen [B.S.] Adamowski, S. Walkowiak, and Rutkowski, Mr. Kasperski, County Commissioner [A.] Nowak, former Judge [Edmund K.] Jarecki, Judge [Joseph] LaBuy, and Messrs. P. Szwaba, Prystalski, [Joseph] Ruszkiewicz, Budzban, Frank P. Danisch, Mindak, Landmesser, and Gorski.</p>
   <p>Mr. Daily selected a committee from the Polish delegation composed of Messrs. Danisch and Nowak and Alderman Adamowski with whom to discuss this matter. He assured them that he would see to it that some one resigned from the nominatings committee, and that in his place he would nominate a Pole, Mr. <pb facs="5423968_3_1442.jpg" n="2"/>Ruszkiewicz, in accordance with the wishes of the Polish delegation. Congressman Stanislas H. Kunz was already a member of the committee of fifteen. And indeed, Mr. Henry Stuckart, former city treasurer, resigned from the committee to make room for Mr. Ruszkiewicz, but Mr. Daily did not keep his promise, and instead of appointing a Pole he appointed the fourteenth Irishman, Mr. Witty of the Seventh Ward.</p>
   <p>Polish Democrats, to work! Work for Polish representation by those who are willing to grant to Poles what they justly deserve! The action of Mr. Daily should be branded with severe condemnation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
