<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-24">Feb. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Strange Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-24">Feb. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A STRANGE SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The economic situation in the United States is becoming paradoxical. In the full current of unheard-of prosperity, which America is supposed to owe to its pacifistic restraint, the great metropolitan centers are beginning to be shaken by sudden convulsions of hunger riots. For the past three years one has heard here a continuous stream of speeches on the subject of good times, the splendid condition of commerce and industry, the constant increase in the wage scale, and the growth of fortunes and riches without end or measure.</p>
   <p>Then suddenly the people, despite the golden manna which the war in Europe is supposed to be bringing them, are beginning to riot and demonstrate in America, because they have nothing to eat and the price of food is out of reach of their pocketbooks.</p>
   <p>And the United States today is in the same situation in which a certain gentleman <pb facs="5423968_3_0322.jpg" n="2"/>of Greek mythology found himself, who, as punishment, was compelled to feed himself with gold. For many months, for several years in fact, ship after ship has been bringing whole carloads of European gold to America, and Uncle Sam is now the greatest possessor of wealth in the world, and has the greatest amount of gold in his treasury. But gold cannot be eaten and no one can make shoes or clothing of gold.</p>
   <p>European gold, with its bloody sheen of war, did not find its way into the pockets of the masses but wandered into the safes of the great powers of the world, the stock market, commerce, and industry. European gold, to which it seems that the curse of speculating on the hunger of the belligerent nations across the sea has stuck, had in the first place the effect of lowering the value of money in America. The more of this gold that came into American ports, the cheaper money--that is, those pennies which serve the great masses of people as the means of purchasing articles indispensable to life--became here. This phenomenon is quite a normal occurrence, in accordance with the unvarying laws of economics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0323.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Money as such, even if it be made of the finest gold, represents no real value. It is only a means of exchange, through which one can exchange the value of one type of work for that of another.</p>
   <p>Europe, enveloped by the hurricane of war, stopped working for others and works for itself only for the purpose of continuing the war. America, by avoiding declaration of support of either side of warring Europe, has made money on the European war, prolonging it--with its food and armament supplies--in return for European gold.</p>
   <p>Therefore, Europe did not pay America for the produce of its farm labor as it formerly did, by an equal exchange of the products of its labor, but with gold, which is a symbol of its former or future work, work which can be resumed only after the war is over and which only then can actually begin to bear fruit. Therefore, in exchange for mass export of foodstuffs and industrial products to Europe, the American people do not receive a true equivalent, which would supply the needs of livelihood of the people here, but only gold-a sort of gold <pb facs="5423968_3_0324.jpg" n="4"/>demon which only feeds the speculative fever of the rich capitalists and lowers the value of the money of the poorer classes.</p>
   <p>Industry and agriculture in the United States today are not functioning normally. Agricultural and industrial products are not being produced primarily to supply the needs of our people, with only the surplus used for export, but export bringing in gold in exchange has now become the main purpose of our productiveness. Our productiveness has greatly increased, quite naturally doubling the wages of our people and increasing the demand for laborers, but since this work is destined, in the main part, for export, it must bring with it a continual, endless increase in prices. And it is the most indispensable articles of existence which most greatly increase in price.</p>
   <p>The result of this situation in the home economics not only of the poorer classes but even of the middle classes must be most unfortunate. When anyone burns a candle at both ends, pretty soon the flame of the last remnants of the burning wick burns his fingers. The people here are experiencing this unpleasant <pb facs="5423968_3_0325.jpg" n="5"/>situation from both sides simultaneously. On the one side, the same articles are constantly increasing in price; on the other, for the same money one can constantly purchase less and less. It is true that American products are now cheaper in the European markets than in the [United] States, but for this the European nations are fighting not only for their own future, but for the future of the entire world, while the United States "enjoys" peace and, through someone else's war, amasses mountains of gold.</p>
   <p>The internal situation of the United States is beginning to resemble, in some respects, the situation of Greece, which in her "neutrality" is constantly experiencing ever greater war blows on her own skin. By making every effort to keep out of the world war, America may find herself embroiled in a domestic war in her own country with her own hungry people.</p>
   <p>Since the first hunger demonstrations occurred on Washington's birthday, it is difficult to push away the thought that the "business-minded" American people <pb facs="5423968_3_0326.jpg" n="6"/>have finally recalled the advice of one of their greatest men, who prophetically warned the nation against shutting itself up in the narrow sphere of its own backyard interests, visible for only a short distance. It seems as though Washington had foreseen the present epoch of the great war when he pointed out to the Americans that their stand and actions not only could decide their own fate, the fate of their own country, but could also decide the future of coming generations and centuries.</p>
   <p>Americans can no longer shut themselves up in their own country when the war in Europe is causing riots of the hungry people in American cities. The past few decades have brought about such a far-reaching union and interdependence of economical, cultural, and political conditions that today America dares not be indifferent to what is going on or what will happen in Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
