<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-12">April 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Communistic Experiments in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-12">April 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTIC EXPERIMENTS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Up to this time American historians have shown very little interest in the communistic experiments which were made in the United States during the cycle of the economic crisis from the year 1830 to 1850. In the book by Don Seitz "Horace Greeley" there can be found a very amusing chapter devoted to Mr. Greeley's interesting experiments; during the years when unemployment and misery at its worst, culminated in the financial panic, of the year of 1837.</p>
   <p>Greeley published many articles in the New Yorker, under the title "What will be done for labor?", which attracted the attention of Arthur Brisbane, father of the Hearst publications. During his tour of Europe, Arthur Brisbane adopted the ideas of Fourier, and upon his return to America, with the aid of Greeley, endeavored to realize them in the United States. As a result, a series of communistic settlements arose, supported by the convictions, that there will be more good fortune, less misery and evil, if, in the place of the present system of individualism and stubborn rivalry, society would be reorganized in united effort. Past experiments indicate that industry can be place on an honor merit system. One of the communistic settlements is situated in Indiana, in the County of Warren, and bears the name of the "Grand Prairie Harmonical Association" Greeley was one of its trustees.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0230.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Promoters of this new economic experiment, were convinced that humanity is at a complete loss as to how to prevent a seemingly inevitable catastrophe, unless it check existing economic temperament, and agree in the undertaking of honest harmony, united effort and just distribution of the profit earned by labor.</p>
   <p>However, in spite of the opposition to the leaders of communism and Greeley, and because of their understanding of the principles of morale, they cooperated in opposing liberal trends.</p>
   <p>This experiment, nevertheless, proved to be a disappointment because, people are only human, therefore, not without fault. Harmony was short lived; the brilliant and cultured refused to associate and agree with the masses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
