<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-01-07">Jan. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Child Labor Must End</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1929-01-07">Jan. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHILD LABOR MUST END</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Chronic unemployment is an unnecessary evil and we do not have to be its victims," stated Dr. I. A. Lapp, professor of Marquette University. In his opinion, this problem can be solved, if not completely, at least in part.</p>
   <p>At present employment is being given to a vast army of young workers under sixteen years of age. This should be forbidden by federal law. By so doing, in a short time wider fields would be open to the unemployed who have to support families. This law would give these youngsters a better opportunity to prepare themselves for their work by attending school.</p>
   <p>"We do not have to have child labor," declared Professor Lapp. "The idle hands of the laboring classes are increasing daily. It should be considered a crime to employ children under the age of sixteen. This would eliminate the fruitless search for work of many men. Unemployment is becoming a chronic condition. Several statistical reports indicate that this is gradually becoming <pb facs="5423968_3_0177.jpg" n="2"/>a serious problem. From the years 1923 to 1925, 400,000 people were added to the unemployed. And yet production increased a billion dollars.</p>
   <p>"The railroads help increase unemployment. During the past eight years ever two million workers have left farms to find employment in the large cities. The time is becoming ripe for us to get together and solve this menacing problem before a catastrophe arises," contended Professor Lapp.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lapp shares the same opinion of other experts in economics, who claim that this condition will result in great damage to posterity. There is no reason why children should work whose parents are unemployed and in perfect condition to work for the support of their families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
