<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 67,
<date when="1922-03-21">March 21, 1922</date><title level="a">Black Sheep in Politics or the Breaking Up of Unity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 67,
<date when="1922-03-21">March 21, 1922</date><title level="a">BLACK SHEEP IN POLITICS OR THE BREAKING UP OF UNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a practice in every primary for some candidate who runs for office, to break up a bloc, and so "steal" votes from an opposing candidate. Politicians know these candidates as "dark horses", by which name they are universally called throughout America. We have often witnessed in previous elections how a Pole was put against a Pole. The Poles appeal to the voters for support in the primaries, which naturally, they receive out of patriotism. Both candidates receive the Polish votes, but neither of them have enough votes together to defeat the opponent, one of another nationality. The one who was put forward for the same office and on the same ticket has been well paid, because he has broken up the Polish votes and one of another nationality has been elected. This applies only to a "candidate" who is not well known in politics, but who, among his own fellow-countrymen, can find some support and take away perhaps several hundred votes from his countryman. In the coming primary this will not happen, because neither on the Democratic nor the Republican ticket are there two candidates for one and the same office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0613.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is nevertheless possible, that some candiates will remove themselves before the primaries, admitting that they have no chance of election. By stepping aside they are asking their fellow-countrymen to vote for the "regular candidate". Those who take this course will awaken the suspicion of the voters that they were paid by the political machines and have cheated the voters. We believe that all the present Polish candidates who are running for the more important positions, as for example the State offices, will not withdraw their candidacy. It will be best for all Democratic voters to make a cross at the top of the ballot. Let those who must vote the Republican ticket do likewise.</p>
   <p>In the primaries one cannot vote a "split" ticket. This practice is only permissable in the fall election.</p>
   <p>During the election we can vote for all Poles from one or the other party, but in the primaries only on one "ticket".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0614.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>POLES AGAINST POLES</p>
   <p>Once for all we should demand from the leaders of the political parties that they should put up for nomination only one Pole for each office. If, however two names are suggested one of them should positively withdraw. If a Pole is a candidate against one of another nationality then he should not withdraw. If he does that, then it will become known that he had some sort of hidden motive.</p>
   <p>Men and women voters have a powerful weapon in their hands, and they can use this weapon with good results in the primaries and election, when they vote on the party ticket for which they have today registered. Newly registered citizens can vote for example, the Democrats' ticket, if they will register as Democrats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
