<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 45
<date when="1921-10-01">Oct. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Equal Rights in Law</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 45<date when="1921-10-01">Oct. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EQUAL RIGHTS IN LAW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The outstanding mark of a modern state is equality for all citizens provided by lw, and the conducting of the government by the representatives of the majority.</p>
   <p>In the United States, Poland, and other democratic countries, all citizens are equal in the eyes of the law.</p>
   <p>It is very unfortunate that not all citizens understand this equality which the law provides for everyone, and the equal right to hold a high office.</p>
   <p>Many people maintain very stubbornly that such equality does not exist, for instance, in the United States. They base this statement on the fact that in spite of their endeavors they did not attain their objective</p>
   <p>The unenlightened masses, who do not know very much about social order, <pb facs="5423968_3_0269.jpg" n="2"/>think that equality means that all people should be equally rich and have equal success in life and other matters.</p>
   <p>These people do not realize that such equality cannot be created by any state, nation or community, because man is not provided with power to change the natural law given to the world by the Creator.</p>
   <p>The equality of all citizens in regard to the laws of the country is a different matter; it depends on the right of every citizen to have one vote, a right to run for office and all other privileges provided by law, but there are also obligations and responsibilities to the nation for the fate and welfare of the country which every citizen must bear.</p>
   <p>This is a brief view of the "equality" of citizens as regards law.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0270.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This does not mean that all citizens are equal to each other, although all of them have equal rights as far as the laws of the country are concerned.</p>
   <p>There are o two persons who would be equal to each other in every respect, no two individuals of the same character, no two men equally wise. Independent of the will of society, some people are smarter than others; some have great abilities, others haven't.</p>
   <p>Although there is no perfect man in the world and all of us have faults and virtues, not all of us have them in the same degree. The people are more or less perfect, more or less good and more or less bad.</p>
   <p>Some people have pleasant, others violent characters; some are industrious, others are lazy; some are thrifty, others are spendthrifts; some are honest, others dishonest and so on.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0271.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In other words, nature didi not create man equally.</p>
   <p>The Socialists' assertion that every educated, wise and industrial man came into possession of his wealth or high position by exploiting the poor is not true.</p>
   <p>The lazy and spendthrift can blame only himself for not getting rich.</p>
   <p>Society would place a rope around its neck if it did not reward industrious people. Society must choose for its leaders and high offices the very best and most able people, otherwise it will perish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
