<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 248,
<date when="1922-10-23">Oct. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Proper Thing to Do</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 248,
<date when="1922-10-23">Oct. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROPER THING TO DO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish voters know well what is the proper thing for them to do on the day of election, November 7. They all found out very well, at the expense of their own pockets, how much they have been weighed down by taxes; they have become convinced how the public funds have been wasted, always and everywhere. In the present campaign for election the Democrats have put up a watch-ward for the purpose of removing grafters from the city hall and to change completely the system of taxation. This watch-ward is sounded in all of the new wards.</p>
   <p>The Republicans, on the other hand, say, that the whole of today's high cost of living and high taxes is the fault mainly of the Democrats, but they do not render sufficient proof. "These are empty claims," said to us one of the prominent leaders of the Democratic Party.</p>
   <p>The most heavily taxed are the owners of small real estate, to which class belong the Poles. In order to prevent real estate appraised from rising too high in the future it is necessary to choose for members of taking bodies, honest people from the Democratic Party, says the aforementioned leader.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0603.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Poles should remember that their victory lies only with the Democratic Party. The Poles cannot vote for the Republican Party, because they do not have a single Pole for any important office on their ballot. On the Democratic ticket, however, they have three, of which, one of the most important is the County Judge.</p>
   <p>On the Republican Party ballot can be seen the names of two Poles, who are candidates for representatives to the legislature and senate.</p>
   <p>These two offices do not mean much--remarked our informant. You need a county judge and city judges to protect you in some of the police courts, and that poor families will get the proper care from the county department. A representative in the legislation, who wants to plead for the Poles, is isolated.</p>
   <p>That is why I advise the Polish voters not to split their ballots, but vote for the candidates of the Democratic Party. Voting for the entire Democratic Party is best, because the support in politics is mutual. In previous elections I happened to notice how voters voted only for the candidates of their own nationality and passed up the others entirely. That is a bad system. We go with the Poles hand in hand, <pb facs="5423968_3_0604.jpg" n="3"/>but we also desire that others go along with us.</p>
   <p>Let all Polish voters make only one cross in the circle at the head of the ballot. Such voting is the most simple, because it only takes about two minutes of your time. Splitting the ballot is very dangerous. All do not know, especially the new citizens, now to do this, and that is why their votes are invalidated. So that the Polish candidates will not lose one vote, I advise you to make one cross at the top of the large ballot, on which the candidates for the county offices are listed.</p>
   <p>The same kind of cross should be put in the circle at the head of the judicial ballot, on which are the nominees for Municipal Judges--Frank P. Danisch and John Prystalski.</p>
   <p>So advises our good friend, one of the leaders of the Democratic Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
