<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 114,
<date when="1923-05-15">May 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Pole Should Be Nominated as Health Commissioner Town Hall Promises to Poles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 114,
<date when="1923-05-15">May 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A POLE SHOULD BE NOMINATED AS HEALTH COMMISSIONER TOWN HALL PROMISES TO POLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish citizens are reminding Mayor Dever to execute those promises which he made before the election.</p>
   <p>We first demand that he admit to his cabinet a citizen of Polish extraction. As to nomination for Health Commissioner, this office is of great importance for the Poles, especially if it were held by one who is well known to us, Dr. J. Pietrowicz. He knows perfectly the needs of our fellow-citizens and also feels that he would be of great benefit to us. Experienced politicians have come to understand this and are exerting pressure on the Mayor that he name Dr.Pietrowicz as Commissioner of the Health Department.</p>
   <p>Judge E. K. Jarecki, Jos. Ruszkiewicz, Max Adamowski, and several other influential politicians have taken this affair into consideration. Mayor Dever must understand that he can not merely make promises to the Poles, but that he must also fulfill them by giving appointments to us Poles in the various departments under his guidance. We shall then remain quiet as a mouse beneath a broom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mayor Dever is quite familiar with politics, he knows the Poles and their needs; because for many years he has held the office of Alderman in the 17th Ward, a section which is densely populated by the Poles. It might be that the Mayor is not informed of the fact that the Poles possess over 100,000 votes, and for this reason he has no intention of considering us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
