<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 36, 
<date when="1919-09-03">Sept. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Socialism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 36, 
<date when="1919-09-03">Sept. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the aim of Socialism? The aim of Socialism in the expropriation of citizen capitalists in the political and economic field.</p>
   <p>In what way can that expropriation allow itself to be carried through? In this respect the Socialists themselves are not in accord: some, like Julius, Guesde, want to use superior force and violence and due to this they are called Marxists (after their leader, Karl Marx, a German Jew); others, like Juares, desire to go the legal way, based on agreement, and they are known as Parliamentary Socialists.</p>
   <p>What is the program of the Marxists? The community should embrace all means of production; capitalists should disappear altogether; competition and over-production should be stifled. Equitable statistics would show how much should be produced for general use. The worker should work an average of three hours daily, and with an increase in machinery the working day should be shortened to one hour daily.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0303.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Personal property is not done away with entirely, but is concentrated and applied to that which is strictly personal.</p>
   <p>What is the program of the Parliamentary Socialists? The Parliamentary Socialists are making towards collectivism with every means, but for the most part through legal methods or reform based on agreement; the most imperative matter in their eyes is the taking over by the government of all enterprises, industrial and commercial, such as railroads, mines, banks, gas plants, sugar refineries, monopolies, etc., so as to gradually abolish payments for service, vesting private wealth into state ownership.</p>
   <p>What do the Socialists promise? The Socialists promise perfect happiness, a true paradise on earth. There will be no poor or rich people, master employers or workers; there will be no capitalists or proletariat, but there will be united workers. From then on they will not have to buy bread, pay rent, etc. The inhabitants will be maintained and lodged at the expense of the state. There will be no care about <pb facs="5423968_3_0304.jpg" n="3"/>bringing up children, maintaining of the aged and those not able to work; the state will attend to the matter of the sick, the bringing up of children, the lodging of the aged and crippled. Beyond the hour of light work a person will enjoy happiness and peace.</p>
   <p>What benefits will result from such compliance to the community question?</p>
   <p>This system will lead a worker slavery and poverty under the tyranny of socialistic government! The country or state which does not know how to produce good matches, will be burdened with the preparing of good food, homes and clothing for the entire world. The state as the only spreader, the only guardian, will appoint to everyone a quarter, for which he will have to work very hard. Every person will be a mechanical part in a large machine operated by the hand of a tyrant. The Socialists are jeering at us because such a paradise will be a virtual hell, where one will not understand the other, indeed, where <pb facs="5423968_3_0305.jpg" n="4"/>one grabs something belonging to another, tearing it out, so as to return to the law of private ownership.</p>
   <p>What is the true definition of Socialism? It is a community alliance, where no one will work as long as he is not forced by his enemies, where everything is only received by way of graces of those who are governing. The Socialists are fighting for power, so as to introduce their own order of things, which would divide the community into (1) those working forcibly, (2) those in charge of the surveyance. One group and the other in constant variation with each other.</p>
   <p>What is the greatest crime in Socialism? The greatest crime of Socialistic principles is the doing away with personal property, family, and religion, those first fundamentals of society.</p>
   <p>What is personal property? By the word "personal property" we understand it is everything that a man rightfully and justly possesses, that is, money, chattels, clothes, houses, factories, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0306.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Did the law of possession always exist and was it recognized? Yes, all civilized nations recognize the law of personal ownership, and countries which have stopped upon this law have fallen anew into barbarism.</p>
   <p>In what way does Socialism consider personal property? Socialism recognizes personal property as robbery; it would like to bear from all individuals their property and give them to the "chosen" (Jews?! - Compositor). In one word, Socialism desires a general confiscation of personal property.</p>
   <p>Does Socialism recognize the family? No, Socialism does not recognize marriage, but is for free love.</p>
   <p>What will become of the children brought up under the Socialistic system? The children will not know either father or mother; they will be foster children of the state.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0307.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Does Socialism recognize religion? No, Socialism recognizes neither God nor religion.</p>
   <p>Is it possible to be a good Catholic and confess at the same to Socialism? No, because we have no Catholic Socialism; it is even a gross absurdity to say "Catholic Socialist." The principles of one and the other are so contradictory and exclusive that a good Catholic cannot be a Socialist, and a rea Socialist is in the same way not a Catholic. A Catholic can be social, this means he can support the community movement only on the principles of the holy Catholic faith; taking then the abstract form of this expression, we cannot talk about Catholic Socialism or about Socialistic Catholicism, but only about social catholicism.</p>
   <p>According to his conscience, can a workingman join and take part in the Socialistic Party? No, because the Socialistic Party, which is revolutionary, could possibly push a workingman into an act not conforming with <pb facs="5423968_3_0308.jpg" n="7"/>his conscience. He would sell his freedom for the benefits of the revolutionists and they would tear from him his faith. The women, most of all should guard their children against Socialism?</p>
   <p>(Signed) X</p>
   <p></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
