<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-08-17">Aug. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Jews Are the Spreaders of Bolshevism in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-08-17">Aug. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS ARE THE SPREADERS OF BOLSHEVISM IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The only brave man in America who is not afraid to tell the truth to the Jews is Mr. Henry Ford, a millionaire of Detroit. His revelations about Jewish machinations has aroused the world. He proved by facts what a dangerous element the Jews are among the Christian nations. Recently he began to unearth and print [articles about] some of the nefarious work of the Jews in America. Here is one of the revelations:</p>
   <p>Mr. Martens, so-called Soviet Ambassador, who was deported by the United States government, before departing for Russia, appointed Mr. Karol Recht, a Jew, as acting ambassador of the Soviets to the United States. Mr. Recht is a lawyer, with offices in New York. His office is used as a rendezvous for all Jewish union leaders of New York, also for some union leaders of the United States, and occasionally even for some federal officials who are under Jewish influence and sympathize with the radical movement. The situation in New York is very grave, because radical activities are spread from that city <pb facs="5423968_3_0279.jpg" n="2"/>over the whole country. New York is a laboratory in which revolutionary emissaries propound the principles of radicalism. Some are learning the lessons and their [knowledge of] Bolshevistic doctrine is increased daily by lectures, given by all kinds of Bolshevik Jewish agents and advisors who come here directly from Russia.</p>
   <p>America does not realize that all the disturbances and uproars, about which we read every day, are not accidental, but are the well--prepared activities of Bolshevik agents. They are the planned activities of Bolshevik Jewish leaders, who fully realize what they are doing.</p>
   <p>There is always an element among the masses which is easily influenced and becomes enthusiastic over insignificant matters. All revolutions, namely: The French, German, and Russian were instigated by the people who were chosen for that task a long time ago. And up to the present time, the afore mentioned countries have been governed by groups of such people who have been <pb facs="5423968_3_0280.jpg" n="3"/>selected for that purpose, and are composed mostly of Jews. Russia and France are governed mostly by the Jews. Germany also, in spite of its anti-Semitic attitude is controlled by the Jews. New York is in the clutches of just such a situation; the Jews are organizing in the same manner that they did in Russia, France and Germany when they organized revolutions. For the American revolution they are choosing and appointing their people in New York.</p>
   <p>The majority of New Workers still remember the movement "Save Fifth Avenue." Fifth Avenue extends from Fourth Street to Thirty-fourth Street including a part of Broadway and is an historic avenue. Fifteen years ago the homes of old families, publishing establishments, and shops, and famous trading centers were located here. It was a location known throughout the United States as a center of "good taste" and "American substance." But now the Americans, who thought that they were safe in their own city have been disillusioned. A strange element has moved into that district: The buildings which [formerly] contained collections of art and masterpieces, now house factories where <pb facs="5423968_3_0281.jpg" n="4"/>foreigners are employed. Those newcomers do not work gladly, or with smiling faces; they are not satisfied with the work which they are doing and with the peace which they are enjoying; they are always gloomy, sad--angry at someone or something. These newcomers are Russian and Polish Jews. They invaded that district for the purpose of contaminating it. There were protests, but all in vain. Organized Jews were getting stronger and stronger every day. Finally they bought large properties in that neighborhood for almost nothing.</p>
   <p>Today the whole of Fifth Avenue is filled with dark unsatisfied faces.</p>
   <p>Still worse are the statements published by the newspapers that the Jews are such good and peace--loving citizens, that they work only for the happiness of their families. The falsehood is too apparent. It is made for the purpose of creating public sympathy and averting government watchfulness. The Jews tell us that they brought a high culture to America and that no other immigrants are as welcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
