<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-04-04">April 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Last Shot</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, (Zgoda)</title>,
<date when="1910-04-04">April 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAST SHOT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most important obligations of every Polish-American citizen to his adopted country, a country which is so kind and hospitable, and which accepted him so graciously is to willingly take active part in its government. Those who do not take an interest in their adopted country's politics are not very grateful to the host who has been very kind and gracious.</p>
   <p>It is an established fact, that American politics are foul, corrupt, and dishonest, and it is also supposed that for that reason the honest and decent folks, in order to not become sullied themselves, avoid getting mixed up in politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0808.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0809.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0810.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Up to the present time the Poles were lax in making full use of their citizenship rights. Many procrastinated in obtaining their citizenship, thereby injuring their own political strength, and as individuals were useless to the country.</p>
   <p>Blind adherence to one party or to the other, and continually contending among themselves, proved harmful to the Poles as a whole. We know that both parties have their good and bad points, and good and bad individuals, among their adherents. Individuals of other nationalities, also adhere to one party or to the other, and usually give it their full support at election time; but if the candidate, for instance, is a Germen, and is running for mayor, or governor, then the Germans discard their party loyalty, and give full support to their countrymen. The Irish, the Swedes, the Czecho-Slovaks and others do likewise, but not the Poles; they remain loyal to their party. The other national groups, even though they are in the minority, are able to elect their candidate, but not the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0811.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0812.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Now it seems, that we have suddenly become conscious of the injustice that we are perpetrating against ourselves by our indifference, and we have put up six Polish candidates into the political arena; these candidates should be elected by us. Our Dziennik Zwiazkowy is not obligated to either of the two parties, and it will not sell out for a few paltry dollars; but we will always support our candidates wherever they may be running for office. In helping them up the ladder, we are helping our Poles as a whole. Nevertheless, we have in our midst so-called Polish, national, and Catholic newspapers, These papers are a hindrance to our Polish cause, and we are sure that they would support the devil himself if there was a dollar in it for them. The success or failure of a Pole means nothing to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0813.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Our Dziennik Zwiazkowy fortunately is beyond bribery; we do not have to sell out our own brothers; we are here, and always will be here, to defend, support, and promote Poles and their cause. We will give our support to Polish candidates irrespective of party. It is our natural obligation.</p>
   <p>We are firing the last shot in the present aldermanic campaign. We have from the beginning supported Polish candidates irrespective of their party affiliations, and we still think that we are justified in doing so. The results of tomorrow's election, will give us the answer. Our Poles either have become conscious of their obligation, or they will require many more years of learning in order to become fully conscious.</p>
   <p>Therefore, today, for the last time before the election, we are making our final plea to all our Polish citizens to go to the polls tomorrow, and place your crosses before all the names of Polish candidates on the ballot.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0814.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
