<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-20">June 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting of Polish Citizens</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-20">June 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MEETING OF POLISH CITIZENS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish citizens of the Sixteenth Ward had convened in large numbers yesterday, in the school hall in order to take measures in organizing the club of "Polish-American Democratic Citizens of the 16th Ward". (sic) The meeting was called to order by citizen John Arkuszewski, afterwards, Anthony Rudnicki was elected chairman, and Stanley Szwajkart secretary.</p>
   <p>New members enrolled in the club whose membership list has increased to forty. Besides the citizens mentioned last Monday, the following members have joined: Peter Kiolbassa, Vincent Peszczynski, Theodor Buczkowski, Valentine Szewc, Anthony Wojciechowski, Bernard Lieske, John Kwasigroch, Joseph Chelminiak, Lorenc Majewski, Corneli Murkowski, Louis Biadaszkiewicz, Constantine Malinski, Andrew Kwasigroch, Walter Chojnacki, and Adalbert Matuszak.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1325.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was resolved to accept only citizens of the Sixteenth Ward into this club and only those who already have the right to vote on the basis of their second citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>Many citizens spoke of matters pertinent to the club, among these were: citizens Arkuszewski, Rudnicki, Kiolbassa, Kunz, John Kwasigroch, Roland, Fuhl, Tomasik, Mucha, Krolik and others.</p>
   <p>The motion of citizen Roland was beneficial to the club. In the future, arrangements will be made in the nature of recitals or educational talks, primarily on parliamentary rules and then about the duties and task of the various national, state, country and municipal officials, beginning with the President of the United States to the city aldermen. Naturally, only then will these matters be discussed when the club will become finally organized.</p>
   <p>The club administration was also elected, that is, the officials of the club and an executive committee composed of seven members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1326.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following citizens were elected as officials: Anthony Rudnicki, president; Francis Wleklinski, vice-president; Francis Fuhl, recording secretary; Thomas Krolik, financial secretary; John Kortas, treasurer.</p>
   <p>For the executive committee the following citizens were elected: Peter Kiolbassa, A. J. Kowalski, John Kwasigroch, Stanley Kunz, Adalbert Tomasik, Jacob Mucha and Joseph Chelminiak.</p>
   <p>The next meeting of the club will be held on Sunday, July 3.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
