<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-14">Sept. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Local News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-14">Sept. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow, September 15, 19<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, is the day of the primaries in Chicago. Although in accordance with its principles the Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy does not show any particular preference for any political party in this country, nevertheless, it is its right, and even its duty to support Poles when these aspire to public office. Regardless of the political faction to which a Pole belongs, we support him because duty and national feeling impel us to do so. A Pole can perform official duties as capably as those of many other nationalities, if not more capably. Conseauently, why should our people not did him and increase the number of honest officials? The following Poles are candidates for nomination for various public offices in tomorrow's primary election:</p>
   <p>For county assessor: Mr. Frank <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> a well-<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, at present <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0799.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For sanitary commissioner: Mr. Stanley Adamkiewicz, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>For county commissioner: Messrs. S. Kuflewski and Robert Lenard.</p>
   <p>For State senator: Mr. Peter Jezierny, Ninth Senatorial District, and Mr. John Prystalski, Thirteenth Senatorial District.</p>
   <p>For State representative: Messrs. John Reimer and W. J. Laskowski, Fifteenth Senatorial District; Joseph Lisack and Fran Landmesser, Twenty-fifth Senatorial District; Theophilus Weyna, a member of the Polish National Alliance, Joseph Pitlack, Anthony J. Onecki, also a member of the Alliance, and Max Lewandowski, Twenty-seventh Senatorial District.</p>
   <p>For sanitary commissioner: Dr. E. T. Napieralski, a member of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>For State senator: Mr. J. M. Sienkiewicz, Fifteenth Senatorial District.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0800.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For State representative: Messrs. John W. Fruzyna, Ninth Senatorial District; Frank J. Karch, a member of the Alliance, Fifteenth Senatorial District; and Albert Rostenkowski, a member of the Alliance, Twenty-seventh Senatorial District.</p>
   <p>The Poles, therefore, have an opportunity to select candidates of their own race, and they should exert every effort to make certain that the worthiest of these shall be placed upon the regular ballot. The Polish people are therefore urged to vote for their brethern.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
