<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 44,
<date when="1898-11-02">Nov. 2, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0902</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0902.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 44,
<date when="1898-11-02">Nov. 2, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a few days we will have an election. In many cities there are Poles as candidates for office. Up to the present time we have been convinced that even in politics the Poles have not been properly organized, and even when there is a Polish candidate for office, they do not know how to work hand in hand and do not know how to forget their squables and jealousies, and as a result, the Poles are very often the losers.</p>
   <p>If anything happens to the Jew, all the Jews, as many as there are, shout Oi'. Oi! Gevalt! Robbery! - as if it hurt all of them. In business the Jews act the same way. One will not hurt the other's business; especially, if there is a larger capital needed, they join together, lay down the money, and together do business with combined efforts; they cheat the sucker and divide up the profits. For that reason a Jew will never be lost because where Polish business goes bankrupt the Jews are making money. They Build stone mansions and carry on as a well-to-do-class.</p>
   <p>In this respect we should take a lesson from the Jews and, whereever it concerns a Pole, stand as one man. We will never lose by this, because today I stand for the other one, but I know that tomorrow he will stand up in my defense.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0903.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us try and understand better what concerns us - and support ourselves together in every field and benefit by doing same. The Jews, Germans and Irish have left us far behind them. They do not ask whether it is a friend, or a pal, and if he is one of 'their own' they support him as much as they can, and they themselves benefit by doing it.</p>
   <p>Just take a look and see how many political offices they hold, and how much of large business is in their hands, and you will have to admit that the above statements are true.</p>
   <p>Are we to go thru life as if we were blind? Shall we, seeing what others do - not profit by it? Shall we always remain the last?</p>
   <p>No, brothers! It is time to awaken, organize, work together and help one another.</p>
   <p>Let us try and remember now, during election time, that the more offices held by Poles, the greater will be our importance in this country, and the greater the respect for us. So for our own good, whenever any Pole is running for office let us not look to see if he belongs to the Democratic party or the Republican, but remember that he belongs to the Polish Party, that he is a Pole and give him a vote.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0904.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Oh! if it could only come that we Poles could establish our own Polish Party. If we could only learn how to unite and vote as one, then in many cities and even in Chicago where we have tens of thousands Polish votes, we would also hold office. Then the mayors and even the President of the United States would have to take our number into consideration and would not toss to us only scraps but would have to give us higher offices and fulfil our just demands.</p>
   <p>We are still far from it, but the task is not as difficult as it seems? If all the societies in each parish would form together one political club and the presidents of such clubs come to a mutual understanding and called themselves the "Polish Party, oh! how important we would be considered.</p>
   <p>Then the representatives of these clubs of this "Polish Party" could boldly tell the candidate for president, "We demand such offices and in return we give you so many thousand Polish votes."</p>
   <p>Every candidate and every party would have to take us in to consideration and we would have some "fat morsels" in politics; besides that, the American people would cease to hold us lightly.</p>
   <p>Today we are divided into different camps and groups, unorganized, amounting to nothing or very little.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0905.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Before this "Polish Party" is organized let us at least remember that we are Poles and wherever a Pole is running, vote for him in union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
