<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-23">Dec. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">"In What Manner the Classes More Liberally Endowed Mentally, Morally, or Financially Must Exert Their Influence to Raise the Classes Less Educated, with a Lower Moral Outlook, and Possessing no Material Resources"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An article read by Reverend Eugene Siedlaczek at an entertainment given by the Polish Patriotic Organization on Sunday, December 17.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-23">Dec. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">"IN WHAT MANNER THE CLASSES MORE LIBERALLY ENDOWED MENTALLY, MORALLY, OR FINANCIALLY MUST EXERT THEIR INFLUENCE TO RAISE THE CLASSES LESS EDUCATED, WITH A LOWER MORAL OUTLOOK, AND POSSESSING NO MATERIAL RESOURCES"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An article read by Reverend Eugene Siedlaczek at an entertainment given by the Polish Patriotic Organization on Sunday, December 17.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The entertainment given Sunday by the Polish Patriotic Organization was more than a mere charitable function--during it a speech was delivered and a treatise was read, both of which represent permanent and important values. Of the former we have already given a lengthy review, so that now we will limit ourselves to the latter. Mr. S. Zahajkiewicz's speech has been already published.</p>
   <p>Herewith we are publishing a synopsis of the article read by Reverend Eugene Siedlaczek. We regret that the limited space at our disposal does not permit <pb facs="5423968_3_0527.jpg" n="2"/>us to publish the complete text of the article, which begins with an exposition of the unhealthy condition of modern living. This condition has been eloquently described by Reverend Siedlaczek in these words:</p>
   <p>"The history of the world shows a continuous battle, a fight for survival, bitter in the extreme, sorrowful, desperate. For some time past, particularly the last two decades, this desire to destroy one another has led the modern world into a strange state of unrest. This is evidenced by the convulsive tremors that shake governments and institutions, and by the persistent evil work which undermines and destroys all of the precepts of religion, morals, good order--in a word, everything that civilization has depended on for ages.</p>
   <p>"Rottenness, unheard-of demoralization, has stolen into the highest spheres among those who consider themselves superior and to whom the masses look for help and relief, and in whom the nations place all their confidence. Foreign ministries are falling one after the other. The government will follow them, and then, what will happen This question is a great puzzle to all who participate in political activities. Everybody peers into the future with <pb facs="5423968_3_0528.jpg" n="3"/>fear, because before his eyes he sees a horrible vision with blood-stained hands, on whose forehead the word 'crime' is written, on whose face egoism has engraved its mark--egoism which sacrifices everything standing in its way.</p>
   <p>"This vision is coming ever nearer and cries: 'My name is Revolution!' Who created it? The moral reaction of two classes--one superior, the other lower. The first one bears greater responsibility, because although it possesses a store of moral strength, it has made no effort to extinguish to extinguish the evil in its infancy..</p>
   <p>"Moral evil--the mutinty of man against moral order and law, had existed  undoubtedly from the day of the fall of our first parents, and this same mutiny appears in various forms nowadays. A war to the death against religion, a war against righteousness-that is its motto.</p>
   <p>"Who is, I ask, the fundamental foe of today's criminal revolution? The Catholic religion. Thus the Catholic Church is primarily exposed to its <pb facs="5423968_3_0529.jpg" n="4"/>hatred. The anarchists and socialists are attacking it with all the strength at their command. The servants of the church, nicknamed by them the 'black internationals', are marked for destruction. The first object of the revolution is to confiscate all church property, which, so to say, is an heirloom of the poor; the second object is to eliminate the salutary influence it exerts over our everyday affairs.</p>
   <p>"The revolution discards the family as an entity, endeavors to eliminate its religious character, wants to transform the marriage act into a civil function.</p>
   <p>"The present revolution says to the working man: 'You are as good as your employer'; to the employer: 'You are a free man and need not recognize any responsibilities toward the workingman'. In this manner it preaches its so-called 'universal brotherhood' while in reality it fans the flames of hatred and civil war among the poorest. Such is today's revolution, today's socialism.</p>
   <p>"One must look deeper for the sources of this revolution. The world of today, the present decade, throwing aside Christian doctrines which interfere with <pb facs="5423968_3_0530.jpg" n="5"/>its evil habits, vainly seeks a solution for infernal doubts by discovering new systems of philosophy and reaches in the and a state of paganism that clothes nature with a raiment of deity and preaches a voluptuous freedom of conscience--freedom in evil habits, a base paganism which destroys all humane feelings and all truth.</p>
   <p>"What is the cause of this It is lack of that moral strength which energizes our entire human structure and can only be derived from belief in the one God and certainty of a higher destiny."</p>
   <p>And so, normal living and civilization, according to the author of this articles, lie in genuine Christianism; the cause of their downfall, in evading Christian ideas. He further considers the composition of the human being: the body, the soul, and the grace. In proportion to which of these prevails, human beings are either materialistic, learned, or spiritual. In the last one, the author recognizes the real Christians--the chosen people, and commands them to become the leaders of humanity, for the have greater educational, moral, and material attributes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0531.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The author's beautiful words to the effect that the human soul is endowed with grace, we are quoting at length. They will best explain this thesis.</p>
   <p>"A spiritual person, truly Christian, sees in a stranger a brother. He does not look askance at him even if the latter does not share his ideas and beliefs but gives him a friendly handshake and supplies him with the things he needs. He looks at a stranger as a human being, a co-worker in praising God and for the benefit of all. His heart is filled with love form God and exclude all love of himself.</p>
   <p>"A spiritual person endowed with this third life, that is, grace of living, will sacrifice himself for another individual, and for humanity. According to the thought of God, he who blesses his brethren is an apostle.</p>
   <p>"This person not only understands that he is burdened with his own private duties, performed around his home fire or in private circles, but he also recognized his duty to his country. Patriotism follows the love of God, and <pb facs="5423968_3_0532.jpg" n="7"/>is his ideal; he knows that such Christian patriotism, sincere and genuine, naturally cannot be idle, lifeless."</p>
   <p>This is how Reverend Siedlaczek would like everyone to be, especially those who are in any way superior and who, endowed with exceptional graces, are in a position to influence of lead others. As to the proper use of this influence, he says:</p>
   <p>"Just as in a Christian family enlightened with the grace of life, the older brother or sister gives a helping hand and brings up, leads, guards, and helps his younger brothers or sister, just so in our national life, those clases more liberally endowed should continually endeavor-if their hearts are filled with genuine patriotism, godly patriotism--to exert their influence on the lower classes and raise them mentally, and materially. No doubt such action would demand much sacrifice and self-denial on the part of these superior beings, but these sacrifices are only their direct duty as considered in the light of Christian spirit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0533.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"Every nation is composed of old and young people, of watchers and workers, of lawmakers and law enforcers, of teachers and students. There are millions on the one side and on the other. And these millions of people in a nation are more or less obligated to improve other millions morally, spiritually, mentally, and materially."</p>
   <p>As necessary adjuncts for properly undertaking these tasks, the author demands: similarity, if not in methods, at least in the objects desired; sacrifices and self-denial, and the elimination of egoism, whose daughter is this infamous liberal freedom leading to disorder and crime; finally, sincere patriotism. Once more we regret that lack of space does not permit us to quote the complete passages of the article relating to the foremost two conditions. Nevertheless, we quote, without any change, what Reverend Siedlaczek says about patriotism.</p>
   <p>"Sincere patriotism--not the kind that depends on gold or honors but the one inspired by a true love for our Country--places upon us the tremendous, holy, and public duty of working and sacrificing ourselves for our younger and <pb facs="5423968_3_0534.jpg" n="9"/>weaker countrymen, not in proportion to any earthly reward but according to one's strength and ability. Sincere patriotism does not exclude the recognition of personal meritorious acts, and it does not deny the right of suitable rewards to those who, while sacrificing themselves for their follow men, bring credit to their country by helping others. But as a basis, as a fundamental law true patriotism demands sacrifices for one's fellow men merely because they are sacrifices for the public good, without thought of remuneration, without thinking of any personal benefit. On the contrary, if necessary, even against our own interests.</p>
   <p>"Whenever this spirit of national patriotism disappears, or when it is used only as a mask to disguise personal views and intentions, then from the highest official to the lowliest public servant, from the general to the private in the ranks, from the minister of education to the plain teacher--all will betray their country in the name of such false patriotism and take unfair advantage of the public, in the end betraying their own country. These things have happened and still happen. We can expect such things, if the souls of patriots are false.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0535.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"And there is still another sort of patriotism, alas! among us. Stubborn, and crooked, unfruitful and selfish. This sort of patriotism is temporary, exclusive, jealous. Many would give all they possess for their country, but would demand exclusive control over it. They will give and serve, provided they be allowed to direct and control things their way.</p>
   <p>"This kind of patriotism is false. Every faithful son of a nation should love it in God. We will then be faithful and great in his sacrifices for the benefit of all everywhere and at all times."</p>
   <p>Such patriotism, according to the author this article is an indispensable condition for wholesome and beneficial influnence over the younger folk. One more pointing out the necessity for such action, Reverend Siedlaczek makes a very accurate comparison between the public as a whole and the family in which the older brothers neglect the younger ones and forget to guard them against danger. In the family circle, much neglect is the cause of death, crippling, or otherwise injuring the younger. The same applies to the public as a whole. Left without help or supervision of older brothers over their <pb facs="5423968_3_0536.jpg" n="11"/>moral, mental, and material life, the younger brothers become moral cripples, follow blindly the road to ruin and lawlessness, become burdens on the community, and perhaps turn their evil thoughts against it, sowing rottenness and preaching false doctrines. The damage done to all is great.</p>
   <p>In conclusion the author, addressing himself to the readers, says that it is only rarely that those in higher positions work according to God's will for the benefit of the younger generation. He warmly urges the readers to change for the better. Here are his words:</p>
   <p>"We find very little of sincere sacrificing for the sake of our weaker brothers. It would seem at times as if we did not wish to acknowledge them. Their troubles and their poverty does not seem to affect us; and we seldom agree that it is our duty to counteract this poverty, whether it is moral or material. Too literally do we believe in the words, 'As you make your bed, so you shall sleep.' Let us return to this sense of obligation. Let us not spare pleas and reminders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0537.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>"Today we realize that the spirit of love and charity live within us. Let us continue this way, always in the name of God and patriotism! Let us not give the younger generation cause to condemn us. Let us continue to educate them and to improve their morals, and finally, speaking of the moment, et us first dry their tears--the tears of poor mothers and children--so that they also can be happy with us during the Christmas holidays</p>
   <p>"To make sacrifices like that for your brothers is expressed in the words of our poet Sigismund Krasinski:</p>
   <p>'In the form of word or deed,</p>
   <p>Give of ourself to your brethren</p>
   <p>Multiply yourself through your good deeds</p>
   <p>And from you alone, there will be thousands!</p>
   <p>Be not fatigued even though shackled.</p>
   <p>The pain although it hurts, it does not hurt!</p>
   <p>In your own being be your entire nation,</p>
   <p>Be heaven and earth a miracle of cohesion!</p>
   <p>Holiness in servitude!'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
