<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 120,
<date when="1921-12-31">Dec. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">To Work! to Action! Poles!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 120,
<date when="1921-12-31">Dec. 31, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TO WORK! TO ACTION! POLES!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It's high time that we prepare ourselves for work because weeds, and more weeds, multiply terribly fast.</p>
   <p>The public is not mentally ill but individuals are, to whom "riches" are every-thing without regard for which way they will be obtained. They are able to sacrifice their Fatherland, Faith, and their own father, just to bring forth their own big "I" or to accumulate riches.</p>
   <p>Not pausing to reflect upon the fact that they are sowing the seed of discord among us, they are plainly retarding the development of our nation. They spread moral filth among our society, these leaders whose intentions are of nominating themselves - - taking advantage of people, who have difficulty in orientating themselves in the present-day world-wide turmoils. Whether <pb facs="5423968_3_0258.jpg" n="2"/>with bad intentions, or through political short-sightedness, they are laying thorns in their path and are preparing the way for Bolshevism in the entire sense of the word.</p>
   <p>What is this and toward what does the installation of class among us lead to? The constitution of our nation gave such great freedom to each member of our nation, that no other nation in the world can boast in giving equal liberty. In return for this freedom we should learn the spirit of giving and do every thing humanly possible for our society.</p>
   <p>Our enemies will see that when we come to an understanding, we then will establish one of the best and the strongest constituent parts of humanity.</p>
   <p>Saviors of the nation, attention. Contribute toward the salvation of our country. Awaken you Poles, and thresh out the weeds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
