<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-14">Dec. 14, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Democratic Young Men's Club Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-14">Dec. 14, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMOCRATIC YOUNG MEN'S CLUB HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Polish Democratic Young Men's Club held their first meeting in Wiza's hall, Noble and Sloan Streets, on Tuesday, December 12, for the purpose of making the club a permanent political organization. An unexpectedly large attendance filled the small hall to capacity long before eight o'clock.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stanley Czajka was selected as chairman and Mr. Andrew Szultz as secretary.</p>
   <p>Mr. John Kondziorski, the first speaker of the evening, reasoned clearly as to the necessity for forming a club for Polish young men and explained the benefits that can be derived therefrom. He next spoke about the two candidates for mayor of Chicago and gave a brief sketch of their biographies.</p>
   <p>The second speaker was Mr. Frank Bieszki. In his lengthy talk, he acquainted those present with the political history of the last few years. He proved that the Republicans' claim that the Democrats are responsible for this depression is absolutely false, because even during the Republican administration <pb facs="5423968_3_1262.jpg" n="2"/>conditions were just as bad, if not worse. He spoke of the year of 1873, when Grant was president, when misery, more terrible than it is to-day, stalked the country. Speaking of the election, he said that the Republicans cannot accuse Mr. Hopkins of anything bad, but print and distribute pamphlets in which they describe him as a Papist, so as to convince the non-Catholics that they should not vote for him. This is another reason why we Poles, who are proud of the fact that we are Catholics, should work all the harder for him. This speech was applauded enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>Then a member of the House of Representatives, Mr. John Kwasigroch, spoke of our candidate as a young man full of energy and rightful aims. In very fervent words, he urged the citizens to exert all efforts in order in order to make the influence of the Polish young men felt.</p>
   <p>After a few other short speeches, on these same topics, on the motion of Mr. Julian S. Szczepanski, those assembled proceeded to organize the club.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1263.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was unanimously decided to name it"The Polish Democratic Club of Young Men of the Sixteenth Ward."</p>
   <p>The administration was then elected as follows: John Mondziorski, president; J. S. Szczepanski, vice-president; Vincent J. Jorwiakowski, secretary; Joseph Grabowiecki, treasurer; John Konwinski, marshal.</p>
   <p>A few important motions were then passed, including the following: that every young Polish citizen from 21 to 35 years of age can become a member; that the young men may attend the meetings and listen to the debates, and that the Club should be shortly incorporated.</p>
   <p>It was decided to hold the next meeting Saturday evening in Mr. Wiza's hall.</p>
   <p>Finally, new members were listed and over one hundred were enrolled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
