<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-26">June 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Contest in the Election of Mr. Peter Kiolbassa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-06-26">June 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A CONTEST IN THE ELECTION OF MR. PETER KIOLBASSA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some of our readers know already, that Mr. John F. Smulski, defeated by Mr. Peter Kiolbassa for the office of alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, has filed a complaint with the city council as to the legality of Mr. Kiolbassa's election.</p>
   <p>According to the official recount Mr. Kiolbassa's majority was only seventy-two votes, so the opposition hoped that somehow this majority would be cut down.</p>
   <p>But this hope is not being realized.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, after many legal skirmishes, in the presence of election officers and a committee of the city council, a recount was begun.</p>
   <p>The first fourteen precincts were recounted. And what was the result?....Mr. Kiolbassa not only did not lose a vote in these precincts (in spite of the many <pb facs="5423968_3_1703.jpg" n="2"/>attempts) but he actually gained three votes.</p>
   <p>So he has a majority of seventy-five, not seventy-two votes.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow the other fourteen precincts will be canvassed, and we are convinced the results will be the same.</p>
   <p>At any rate the contest will prove a fizzle.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smulski began it, we understand, mainly on the demand of the Republican city machine, whose members supported him with a vigor worthy of a nobler cause. These gentlemen hoped something unforeseen might happen so that, by trickery, enough votes might be thrown out to change the result; they have miscalculated.</p>
   <p>That a Pole should permit himself to be used for such a purpose is very incomprehensible to us....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
