<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-16">June 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Tragic Results of Labor Clash in Lemont</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-16">June 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TRAGIC RESULTS OF LABOR CLASH IN LEMONT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have just received the latest news from Lemont, Illinois, where a clash occurred a week ago in which a number of our unfortunate countrymen fell. We learn from Mr. E., who has just returned from Lemont, of the death of the second victim, the seventeen-year-old boy Kluga. Among those who have little chance for recovery are the Poles Jaskulski (bullet in side, not yet removed), Kolarz (bullet in thigh, also not removed), Wesolowski, Wojtanowski, and others. The medical attention they have had has been entirely inadequate. Great poverty reigns in the homes of the victims; for instance, the aged parents of Kluga are now without any means of support; others fare as badly.</p>
   <p>John C. Willand, a Pole, Sergeant in Company E, Second Batallion, Second Regiment of the Illinois National Guard, who was in Lemont with his Company from Tuesday to Friday, assures us that the Poles were victims of a wanton attack by the contractor. He had at first exploited them in the worst possible way and finally had imported Negroes from Georgia to replace them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Sergeant Willand also assures us that the Poles of Lemont are a hard-working, peaceful people....held in good repute by the town of Lemont.</p>
   <p>The unfortunate victims are very much in need of aid, and it is our duty to give it to them. Two of our local physicians, Doctors Janczewski and Kodis, will leave for Lemont within the next few days to administer medical aid.</p>
   <p>This is not enough, however. At least a small sum of money ought to be sent to Lemont to satisfy the victims' immediate needs. We appeal to the Polish workingmen--our duty to national brotherhood and labor unity calls for offerings!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
