<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-08-24">Aug. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Poles Complain</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1019</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1019.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-08-24">Aug. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLES COMPLAIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A reader of the Staats Zeitung, the German-Pole, Mr. I. H. Kominski, of no. 607 Noble St., sends us the following communication:</p>
   <p>"The Poles bitterly resent the indifference of the Democrats, since the latter neglected to nominate Polish candidates for the office of County Commissioner." This resulted in the publication of an article, yesterday, in the Dziennik Chicagoski, which created a sensation among the Poles, and is likely to seriously effect the Fall-elections.</p>
   <p>The proposition provides, that all Polish voters of the entire county (a total of at least 8,000 - 10,000) support the Democratic National and State ticket in exchange for six or seven Democratic and three or four Republican candidates for county commissioners, all must be men of recognized standing. The Polish-Democratic League of the state, an alliance of all Polish Democratic clubs throughout the state, shall be entrusted with the affair and bring the plan to a successful conclusion. In this manner the Poles intend to prove to the Democrats, that their voices are a decisive element.</p>
   <p>That the Poles are justified in demanding representation on the Democratic platform,as they are party members with only few exceptions, and that they are not inclined to look at this affront with indifference, was to be expected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1020.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The executives should not regard these expressions of discontent lightly, as the Poles control nearly 10,000 votes and their requests are legitimate, and should be heeded.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
