<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol.17. No.247.
<date when="1906-10-26">October 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Politics.</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Woman's Comment on Politics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0855</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0855.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol.17. No.247.
<date when="1906-10-26">October 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Politics.</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Woman's Comment on Politics.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>October 26, 1906.</p>
   <p>Dear Editors of the Dziennik Chicagoski:</p>
   <p>They say a woman's work is to tend to her home and kitchen, and not to mess in politics. According to my estimation the home and kitchen should come first for the average woman, but if it were not for politics existing in this country, the kitchen would be very miserable because instead of beef steaks, roast beef, pies, etc. the working class of people, especially the Poles, would then have to surely eat potatoes without meat, or served with a bowl of dried noodles, and, maybe, just a glass of milk. This probably would be the daily food devoured by nearly every family.</p>
   <p>Why do I write like this?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0856.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I am in the midst of gentlemen arguing about politics, or the election.</p>
   <p>One cries out: "Look what kind of a record Smulski Has?" Another answers: "And what good has he done the Poles? Many others have such records, but you hear nothing about them."</p>
   <p>Another says: "Piotrowski is as good as Smulski and maybe even better. He isn't guided by any political machine as Smulski who was and is." Then he pulls out a printed paper from his pocket and asks me me to read it.</p>
   <p>Seeing this paper, I recognize it to be a sample ballot to be used for electing officials at the election, November 6th.</p>
   <p>I read off the first column: "Republican". At the end of this column it also reads: "You also have two Poles, one Lithuanian, the rest Jews, Germans, Irish, and two Negroes: about these the Polish National Daily paper raves.</p>
   <p>I then proceeded to read the other column "Democratic". Towards the end it commented to the other party: "See, Piotrowski did not change his name, neither <pb facs="5423968_3_0857.jpg" n="3"/>did Jozwiakowski, or Chileski, and so if you shall elect a Republican, you will not have a Polish Judge, but a Negro. Then if an incident occurred where you would be arrested, say at a wedding or a picnic, the patrol wagon would present you to a Negro court."</p>
   <p>There were many more discussions, or arguments, as you might say, about which I would not care to write. It may be that I have taken too much liberty already in writing this much.</p>
   <p>I do want to say this, that the Polish women folks should call the attention of their husbands, brothers, and friends to the fact that the tongue was victorians in this case, and not fists, as is usually the case. A woman's tact should lead them on the right road.</p>
   <p>I remain,</p>
   <p>Mary Olszewska,</p>
   <p>1171 N. Irving Ave.,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
