<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1923-03-31">March 31, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Joseph Ruszkiewicz, an Active Citizen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Jednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1923-03-31">March 31, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">JOSEPH RUSZKIEWICZ, AN ACTIVE CITIZEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The one person who has been and who is energetically working continually for the benefit of Poles in Chicago is Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz. In spite of the fact that he was born in America he is a sincere Pole, which rarely is the case.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz was born March 19, 1880, in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. At the age of ten years he came with his parents to Chicago and has permanently resided here ever since. He has been in the real estate business for the past sixteen years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz has been very active not only in national affairs but also in politics. He has held office as city treasurer for six years, having under his control local funds exceeding thirty million dollars. Clayton F. Smith appointed him to this office to serve a period of two terms.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1631.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the years 1911 to 1915 Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz was a director of the Polish Roman-Catholic Organization; later he was appointed treasurer of this organization for two years. He was a member of the Illinois State Tax Commission for a period of four years, during which time our taxes were much lower than at any other time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz is known to everyone as a man possessed of extraordinary ability, the qualifications which are demanded of a financier, and because of his ability and honesty he reached the rank of president in the Polish National Alliance Bank, a bank which has in circulation the vast sum of three million dollars.</p>
   <p>As we previously mentioned, Mr. Joseph Ruszkiewicz is also active in politics. He is the first vice-president of the Central Democratic Organization of Chicago, to which belong all Democratic committees in the city. Many times during the past, through efforts of Mr. Ruszkiewicz, the Democratic Party has <pb facs="5423968_3_1632.jpg" n="3"/>given the Poles many positions in the various offices. Mr. Ruszkiewicz continually fights on, so that the Poles may be placed on the same plane with citizens of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ruszkiewicz was the first Pole who filled the office of sanitary trustee in the Cook County Commission. In 1916 he performed these duties for six months.</p>
   <p>In spite of the fact that much of his time is taken up with political affairs and business, he likewise endeavors to take interest in many organizations of which he is a member. He is a member of the known and popular Iroquois Club in Chicago, a member of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, and the Polish National Alliance. Besides these, Mr. Ruszkiewicz also belongs to the Knights of Columbus (Lafayette Council), and to many other benevolent societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1633.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Although being active in so many affairs, Mr. Jos. Ruszkiewicz does not evade giving any necessary help, when it is needed by anyone.</p>
   <p>He gained the recognition and respect of the Poles for his kindness, being one of their prominent representatives.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
