<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, 
<date when="1928-02-20">Mar. 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Woman Nominated for Cook County Recorder</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mrs. Salomea Jaranowska to Complete the Term of the Late J.F. Haas</title>
</bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1411</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1411.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, 
<date when="1928-02-20">Mar. 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMAN NOMINATED FOR COOK COUNTY RECORDER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mrs. Salomea Jaranowska to Complete the Term of the Late J.F. Haas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Salomea Szczypinska-Jaranowska was nominated yesterday to fill the vacancy left by the death of the Cook County Recorder, Joseph F. Haas, who died last week. She promised to fulfill her duties to the best of her abilities and for the betterment of the county.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, Mrs Jaranowska occupied herself with domestic affairs and made a pleasant home for her husband and three children. Her decision to take such a responsible position came at a surprise.</p>
   <p>"My policy and program will be to fulfill the requirements of my position for the good of the country. I will not deviate from this program one instant," stated Mrs. Jaranowska.</p>
   <p>At the beginning John Jaranowska tried to get this position, but the Cook County <pb facs="5423968_3_1412.jpg" n="2"/>Commissioners voted for his wife. It was the commissioner's contention that since he already holds the position of Cook County Commissioner, he could not possibly perform the duties of both offices with the best of efficiency. Mr. Jaranowska will run for this office in the next election.</p>
   <p>"I will not ask anyone to do the things for me that I know how," averred Mrs. Jaranowska. "I will be diligent and punctual with all my work."</p>
   <p>She was asked whether she will make any changes in her office. There was no reply. She only looked in the direction of her husband. He came to her rescue by stating that she must given time to adjust herself to her new position. To a query of whether she would be punctual at her office, her husband emphatically answered in the affirmative. He further stated that although they will attend the funeral of John Smulski tomorrow he will escort her to her office after the services.</p>
   <p>Born in Chicago</p>
   <p>Mrs. Jaranowska was born in Chicago in 1891. Her parents came to America from <pb facs="5423968_3_1413.jpg" n="3"/>Poland. She lived with her parents until her 18th birthday. Then she married. Up to the present time this Polish woman never took active part in politics, never interferring with her husband's associations.</p>
   <p>Her salary as Cook County Recorder will be 9,000 dollars a year.</p>
   <p>Immediately after accepting the nomination, Mrs Jaranowska took oath of office. Her duties began this morning at 8 o'clock.</p>
   <p>The commissioners of Cook County that voted for her were: F.L. Boutell, J.P. Carolan, J.W. Gibson, J. Jaranowski, F.A. Kriz, A.C. Metzger, L. Nettelhorst, M. Newby, C.S. Peterson, and O. W. Schmidt; M.F. Kavanaugh, C. Smith and F. Wilson did not vote.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
