<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 82,
<date when="1908-04-08">April 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Polish Brothers of the 16th Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0833</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0833.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 82,
<date when="1908-04-08">April 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR POLISH BROTHERS OF THE 16TH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Election tomorrow. That is why we want to throw more light on the political affairs of the 16th ward with regard to us Poles, so that every one will know just how they should vote.</p>
   <p>Alderman John Schermann is at present seeking the support of all Polish voters. Do you, fellow citizens, know who was among the politicians last spring who was working against us Poles, so that our brother Anthony Czarnecki, editor of the Daily News, would not receive the nomination of the Republican party? Do you know who told John Devine, a member of the central committee, that the Poles in the 16th ward would be insulted if Czarnecki would have received the nomination for county clerk?</p>
   <p>Alderman Schermann was one of these persons who were working against Mr. Czarnecki, although all the people in the 16th ward and the surrounding wards pledged him their support, they placed an Irishman in <pb facs="5423968_3_0834.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Czarnecki's place.</p>
   <p>If the Poles think that this is not true, go to Alderman Schermann and ask him, or ask Mr. Czarnecki. Go and ask Walter Schrojdy, a commissioner. Ask John Devine, who through a protest by Alderman Schermann and others, did not allow Mr. Ozarnecki to receive the nomination.</p>
   <p>Do you, Polish citizens, consider this working in behalf of a Pole? All the English newspapers were supporting Mr. Czarnecki. If Mr. Czarnecki was unworthy, wouldn't all the newspapers state it as such? Didn't Alderman Schermann want a Pole for this office, or was he afraid that once in office Mr. Czarnecki would expose Alderman Schermann's crooked deals toward the Poles, or was he afraid that if Mr. Czarnecki was nominated and won in the election, he would have the support of the Polish and English papers in any of his future political campaigns?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0835.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Andrew J. Schultz was working earnestly with Alderman Schermann in this case. Maybe Alderman Schermann thinks now that Mr. Czarnecki did not receive the nomination, all the Poles will support and re-elect him to the aldermanic office for the second term.</p>
   <p>Don't the Polish people want any of their nation's sons to be victorious in this political world and work their way to the top? This question is up to the Polish people to decide.</p>
   <p>After the mayor's election, what did the Poles get? What did Alderman Schermann do for them? In place of Nikodema Budabana, who occupies his office? Anybody but a Pole. In place of Dr. W. A. Kuflewski, who occupies his office? Anybody but a Pole.</p>
   <p>Is this not enough evidence to convince you Poles? Alderman Schermann, if re-elected, will dispose of John Devine, an Irishman, and take <pb facs="5423968_3_0836.jpg" n="4"/>over his office. The only time the Poles get any consideration from Schermann is when he is running for office and is seeking the support of the Polish voters.</p>
   <p>It is a true fact that not one of our state high officials or any of our county officials were present at the meeting held in the 16th ward on behalf of Alderman Schermann. At the meetings held for other Republican candidates, these high officials took an active part and gave speeches.</p>
   <p>Were these officials ashamed to come and speak before the Polish people of the 16th ward becaue of the scandalous paper propaganda against Alderman Schermann?</p>
   <p>The Polish people should not accept money to cast their vote for Alderman Schermann, but to go to the polls and support their own fellow <pb facs="5423968_3_0837.jpg" n="5"/>citizen. Split your ticket if you so desire, but do it of your own accord.</p>
   <p>No one could shame the name of F. W. Koralewski. The greatest Republican newspaper, The Tribune, refused to support Alderman Schermann, but gave its support instead to Mr. Koralewski, whom they specifically claimed was a man of honesty, of integrity, and trustworthy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koralewski was raised since childhood in the 16th ward, always among his own people: the Poles, helping them to the best of his ability and seeking to better their aims and views towards the Constitution of the United States.</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
