<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1930-02-01">Feb. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">President of Sport Commission Is a Candidate for State Office</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1930-02-01">Feb. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT OF SPORT COMMISSION IS A CANDIDATE FOR STATE OFFICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Rostenkowski, popular sportsman, very well known among the hardworking promoters of sports in the Polish Roman Catholic Union, has secured the endorsement of the Democratic party to run for the office of State Representative of the 27th Senatorial District. To date he has been endorsed by many outstanding business and political leaders throughout the city. He is considered as the right man for this responsible position and he hopes that the Poles of his district will rally around him when the primaries come around in the first week of April.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Rostenkowski is known to the Polish Roman Catholic Union members and sportsmen as one of the most energetic men connected with the organization. He is a supporter of the Polish youth movement and was appointed as the first president of the present Polish Roman Catholic Union Sport Commission, a position that holds great responsibility. His efforts made the Commission a successful body which has promoted the spirit of sport and responsibility among the Polish youth of the present day in the organization to no small extent. Mr. Joseph Rostenkowski has been actively engaged in matters concerning the welfare of his community, city, state, and his organization for a great many years. Although he has seen service of lengthy <pb facs="5423968_3_1626.jpg" n="2"/>duration in important matters, he is still a young and energetic man, whose sole purpose is to help the people of the 27th Senatorial District. He surely does qualify for the position for which he seeks the nomination as a Democratic candidate.</p>
   <p>To Mr. Joseph Rostenkowski, the sport bodies of the organization wish the best of luck in his worthy and commendable pursuit of an office that demands the responsibility of a man that will do all in his power to aid the cause of those who cast their ballots for him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
