<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 280
<date when="1908-11-30">Nov. 30, 1908</date>.<title level="a">Local Chronicle - Best Candidate from the Republican Party</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 280<date when="1908-11-30">Nov. 30, 1908</date><title level="a">LOCAL CHRONICLE - BEST CONDIDATE FROM THE REPUBLICAN PARTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In today's Polish newspaper will be found a portrait of Mr. John F. Smulski as a likely candidate of the Republican party for the office of treasurer of the city of Chicago. With the greatest pleasure we offer his portrait to the public.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smulski has for quite a while in the past thought of running for the office of city treasurer on the Republican ticket as soon as his term as state treasurer expired, but there has been so much propaganda in this matter than it is doubtful as to what steps Mr. Smulski sill take. If Mr. Smulski does not show any interest in this important office, then this office will seek him, because he is the man best suited for a position of so great a responsibility. The Republicans in Chicago know that the popularity of this candidate will no doubt win for him this office and carry our candidate to victory where others would fail. The office of treasurer for the city or state has drawn so much interest that it is the talk of every nationality, mainly the Poles as to who is the best fitted for this position.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1508.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish citizens have shown more interest about casting their votes at the coming election than ever before. Why shouldn't they? Mr. Smulski is state treasurer while Mr. Kolbassa is city treasurer; they both have refused great fortunes which they could have had from their respective positions, but they thought more of their political parties and the good record and respect of the Polish people than they did of their own interest.</p>
   <p>At present, the Republican party cannot see any candidate that is as popular as Mr. Smulski and, if he accepts, it will be for the good of all us Poles.</p>
   <p>As is known, Mr. Smulski is still the president of the South Park Board, a reliable position that calls for a man of honesty, integrity and trust.</p>
	<pb facs="5423968_3_1509.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are reminding you, people, that it was Mr. Smulski who started the movement for the erection of a new Polish college. Let us Poles remember that in unity we have strength.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
