<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-16">Sept. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Policy in American Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-09-16">Sept. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLICY IN AMERICAN POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent primary election held in Chicago on Wednesday, September 13, 1915, has shown our political weakness only too clearly. To be more specific, we should say that it manifested our political discord, which has always been injurious to our people and continues to be so. We have had our own people as candidates for various political positions, federal, state, and city. All the Polish candidates were respectable and well qualified for the positions which they sought, and nevertheless candidates of other nationalities were able to defeat the Poles through their ingenuity, solidarity, and co-operation.</p>
   <p>While the Polish citizens of Milwaukee combined their strength and have nominated Mr. Szczerbinski as representative to Congress, and they will, undoubtedly, also elect him at the regular election, the Polish electors of Chicago have failed miserably. Of eight Polish candidates in three Congressional districts only one received the nomination, namely, Mr. John Golombiewski, in the Fourth District. The question remains whether or not the Poles there know how to <pb facs="5423968_3_0722.jpg" n="2"/>combine their strength and elect him, thus saving the honor of the Poles in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Eighth District presented the best opportunity to nominate a Pole for Congress. Three Poles have campaigned in that District: Z. H. Kadow, N. L. Piotrowski, both on the Democratic ballot, and P. M. Ksycki, on the Republican. In view of the fact that this has always been a predominantly Democratic District, a Republican would have little chance of being elected. And so a Polish Democrat would undoubtedly have been elected had it not been for Mr. Z. H. Kadow. Although he did not have the slightest chance of winning, yet he ran for the office as if he purposely intended to defeat a Polish candidate. If he has even the slightest conception of politics, and as an attorney and a person taking an active part in political life he should have, then he was aware that if two Polish candidates [were on the ticket], both might be defeated. Since he was the less popular of the two, he should have stepped aside.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0723.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He broke an agreement of honor entered into by him and Mr. N. L. Piotrowski that whoever received the majority of votes at the political mass meeting of the regular Sixteenth Ward Democratic organization should be the candidate, and the other should not only withdraw but should work in behalf of his opponent. At that mass meeting Mr. Kadow received an insignificant minority of the votes, and yet he did not prove himself to be a man of honor. He did not keep the agreement solemnized by his own signature, and he flouted the Polish citizens by continuing to be a candidate for the office of Congressman.</p>
   <p>And what happened? In spite of Mr. M. Kruszka's assistance, who, instead of working in behalf of the Polish candidates in his own city, Milwaukee, has thrust his nose into the political affairs of Chicago, he failed to win. As the result of his efforts Mr. Kadow received a total of 980 votes in the whole District, whereas Mr. Piotrowski received 2962 votes. An Irishman, Gallagher, received 3679 votes and won the nomination. Had the votes cast for Mr. Kadow been combined with those cast for Mr. Piotrowski, the latter would <pb facs="5423968_3_0724.jpg" n="4"/>have been nominated, since he would then have had 3942 votes, approximately 300 more than Gallagher. We may therefore thank Mr. Kadow and his conceit for the fact that the Poles will not have their own Congressman at Washington. The Poles will undoubtedly remember this in the future.</p>
   <p>But not only Mr. Kadow is to blame in this instance. The blame should be shared by those who aided him in the evil work. They fought Mr. Piotrowski as if the salvation of the nation depended on his defeat. There were several Polish Democratic "leaders" who fought Mr. Piotrowski with a determination worthy of a better cause, and who would rather vote for an Irishman than for a Pole.</p>
   <p>Mr. N. L. Piotrowski has forwarded to the Dziennik Zwiazkowy a letter of appreciation addressed to all those voters who sincerely supported his candidacy. At the same time he utters his remonstrance against those who opposed him so bitterly. He writes as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0725.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Since I did not aspire to this position of my own volition or because of personal ambition, I therefore cherish no personal grievance. I cannot, however, remain indifferent when I pause to think that the Poles did not take advantage of their apportunity to send a Polish representative to the Congress of the United States, who could render priceless service to the Polish cause in these uncertain times. To judge by the small vote cast, I have no alternative but to think that this matter is of little interest to our people; they did not understand or appreciate the importance of the matter, just as they failed to understand the importance of primary elections. It is for this reason that they do not vote at the primaries unless they are persuaded to do so by some political pollworker.</p>
   <p>"Both political machines, Sullivan's faction as well as Harrison's, were against me. One as well as the other worked against me through their precinct workers and forced people to vote for Gallagher or Devine or Kadow simply to defeat me.</p>
   <p>"In the precinct of Alderman W....., in which only Poles reside, I, a Pole, <pb facs="5423968_3_0726.jpg" n="6"/>received forty votes; Kadow, also a Pole, received only five votes; and Gallagher, an Irishman, received thirty-eight. Would it be possible for an Irish candidate to receive so many votes in a predominantly Polish precinct if Alderman W....and his precinct workers had not compelled the Poles to vote thus? This proves that some Polish "leaders" are only tools in the hands of Irish politicians and do not hesitate to betray Polish causes. Identically the same procedure was followed by the Polish leaders in the Sixteenth Ward.</p>
   <p>"Yes, our Polish politicians have sold Polish votes to candidates of other nationalities. Let us, on the other hand, look at the way in which the Irish conduct themselves. Whereas Mr. Gallagher received nearly 1400 votes in the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Wards, mostly from Poles, I, in the predominantly Irish populated Eighteenth and Nineteenth Wards, received only thirty votes, and Kadow received twenty. And what, may I ask, has Mr. Gallagher done to benefit the Poles? What has he accomplished for the Polish cause that the Poles should cast their votes in his favor against a candidate of their own nationality, who has for years worked to the best of his ability in behalf of the Polish cause? The <pb facs="5423968_3_0727.jpg" n="7"/>indifference of our people, jealousy, the underhand work of Polish politicians, and the money of non-Polish candidates, all these have brought it about that again an Irishman and not a Pole will represent the Polish people at Washington, and that the Polish cause will not have its spokesman there.</p>
   <p>"Finally, I take advantage of this occasion to thank all my fellow Poles who were kind enough to support me with their votes. I shall forever be grateful to them for this. In like manner I wish to extend my appreciation to the Dziennik Zwiazkowy and to the entire Polish press, which with extraordinary effort and sacrifice has disinterestedly supported my candidacy for the good of the cause.</p>
   <p>"To one and all I wish to extend my heartfelt appreciation.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"N. L. Piotrowski."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0728.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Mr. Piotrowski's grievance against the Polish Democratic leaders is well founded because they, in the main, have been responsible for a Pole's defeat. By their efforts they have succeeded in letting a person not Polish represent our people in Congress. This is miserable politics, of which we should feel ashamed. Evidently we have not become equal to the political task of promoting our own welfare.</p>
   <p>The same holds true in regard to the Fourth Congressional District. The Democratic Poles failed adequately to support the candidacy of Mrs. S. J. Kuflewski. Similar conditions prevailed in the Seventh District, where Mr. L. Mallek and Mr. M. Dominowski failed to gain the nomination to Congress. And so all the Polish candidates lost.</p>
   <p>In so far as other public offices are concerned, we see that very little support was given to Polish candidates because underhand political tactics prevailed over our own Polish interests. By acting thus the Poles have proved themselves nil in politics in the presence of other nationalities, for the other nationalities <pb facs="5423968_3_0729.jpg" n="9"/>always succeed in downing us for a miserably small pittance.</p>
   <p>When, therefore, will our Polish people prove themselves better politicians than during the last campaign? Our primary interest was to have a Pole as a member of Congress, and you, Polish voters of Chicago, did not give him to us! Has our Polish spirit fallen so low that we can remain passive to all this? Is it not time that we should awaken from our lethargic indifference and become more active and more united, so making possible the election of Polish candidates to public office? It might be worth while for us to ponder a bit over these questions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
