<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-12">Sept. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Sixteenth Ward Polish Democratic Club Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-09-12">Sept. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">SIXTEENTH WARD POLISH DEMOCRATIC CLUB HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Poles of the Sixteenth Ward held a meeting last Sunday afternoon at M. Derengowski's Hall, Dickson and Blackhawk Streets, for the purpose of organizing a new branch of the Polish Democratic Club. Jacob Mucha, president of the Sixteenth Ward Polish Democratic Club, said that the purpose of the meeting was to help the Polish Democrats of the Sixteenth Ward organize themselves better than they had been up to then. The Poles, he said, had been led long enough by some politicians, and it was time to stop it. The Sixteenth Ward Polish Democratic Club has decided to organize the Polish Democrats into four branches. These four branches combined would constitute a strong Polish political club.</p>
   <p>There were many good speakers, among them Francis Bieszka, L. Roland, and W. Tomasik.</p>
   <p>The branches will be located as follows: one on Carpenter Street, another on <pb facs="5423968_3_1584.jpg" n="2"/>Blackhawk and Dickson Streets, the third on Fry Street, and the fourth on Fox Place.</p>
   <p>After the speeches were over and a number of members had been enrolled, the meeting proceeded to elect a president and a secretary.</p>
   <p>Matthew Derengowski and Francis Jankowski were chosen as president and secretary respectively.</p>
   <p>The name of the club will be Klub Polsko Amerykanski Demokratyczny 16 et Wardy-Odzial Nr. 2.</p>
   <p>[Sixteenth Ward Polish-American Democratic Club, Branch No. 2.]</p>
   <p>Meetings will be held every second Sunday of the month.</p>
   <p>Those who desire to become members, pleaseapply at any time to M. Derengowski, president, 650 Dickson Street, or to Francis Jankowski, secretary, 134 Cleaver Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
