<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16. No.216.
<date when="1905-09-16">September 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Candidate for Judge.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Julius F. Smietanka Democratic Candidate for Judge of the Superior Court.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0873</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0873.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16. No.216.
<date when="1905-09-16">September 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Candidate for Judge.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Julius F. Smietanka Democratic Candidate for Judge of the Superior Court.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Julius F. Smietanka, Democratic Candidate for Judge, was born in Chicago in, 1871. He received his education at the Polish parochial school of St.Adalbert, 17th and Paulina St.</p>
   <p>After graduating from St.Adalbert's, he attended publi high school in Chicago. On completion of his four years at high school, he enrolled in the law school, Kent College, from which he was graduated with distinction in June 1894. In this same month he was admitted to the Bar in Illinois for the practice of law in Illinois.</p>
   <p>He resided in South Chicago, where he engaged in work dealing with the citizenship of Polish people. During this period he built up so efficient and reputable a name he was considered one of the best Polish lawyers in Chicago. Today, he has the largest list of Polish clients of anyone in active practice.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0874.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He had so many Polish clients on his list in a few years, that he persuaded Warren Pease, and Samuel W. Polkey, to form a partnership and after a few months of hard work, they organized a firm under the name of Smietanka, Pease, and Polkey, with offices, 120 E. Randolph St. Up to this time, Mr. Smietanka had never held any political office.</p>
   <p>Our candidate comes from a family that was one of the first Polish families to migrate west and settle. He also is a member of many Polish and American organizations, some of the most important of them being the Federation of Polish Roman Catholics; Dembinski Singing Society; Polish Sokol and Polish National Alliance. He is a member of the parish of Immaculate Conception of St.Mary, South Chicago, and resides with his parents, 9024 Escanaba Ave.</p>
   <p>When informed of his selection as candidate for Judge, he was the happiest, as well as the most talked about and respected man in his vicinity. The Society of Lawyers in Hyde Park, one of the first professional organizations to acknowledge this selection, passed the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"This Society is presenting in the case of Mr.Smietanka, all his qualifications, which make him distinguished as honest and impartial-an ideal judge. We see in him <pb facs="5423968_3_0875.jpg" n="3"/>a man sedate, right, conscientious in his obligations, and one who understands the law.</p>
   <p>After checking his qualifications, this Society, wholeheartedly supports Mr. Smietanka as Candidate for Judge of the Superior Court, and hopes that the people of Cook County can see that he is the best man for the office."</p>
   <p>Mr.Smietanka is the first Pole in Chicago to be selected for the high office of Judge of the Superior Court. His nomination, in this coming election, will be a stepping stone for future Polish candidates, and we urge all you Poles who have any respect for your native brother's welfare, as well as your own, to vote for Mr. Smietanka.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
