<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-21">June 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Poles of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-21">June 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE POLES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received the following appeal from the executive committee in charge of rendering aid to the unfortunate Polish strike victims in Lemont, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Countrymen! On the ninth of June, an awful crime was perpetrated in Lemont, Illinois, the principal victims of which were our brethren, Polish strikers. These people, unarmed workingmen, were barbarously attacked by the contractors and their hirelings,armed white men and negroes, on no provocation and without any reason whatsoever. Not only did the murderers attack our brethren, who stood by peacefully some distance away, but they pursued them for almost a mile, killing and wounding many. Two Poles have already died of their wounds, and a great many more lie suffering between life and death. They and their families, meantime, are living in great poverty. Justice not only failed to be meted out, but the murderers are still free <pb facs="5423968_3_0134.jpg" n="2"/>while a number of strikers were arrested immediately after the shooting. In the name of national solidarity and mutual good, in the name of Christianity, American Polonia of Illinois, already something of a political power, is in duty bound to hasten to the aid of the unfortunate strike victims in Lemont. Besides giving them material aid in their poverty, it must use its influence in bringing the criminals to justice, and it must protest as loudly as possible against such violence and lawlessness. With this end in view, a meeting was held on June 19, at which a group of Chicago Poles decided that we in Chicago must come to the support of our brothers in Lemont. An executive committee has been formed to take charge of the matter. A collection taken up at the last meeting yielded a considerable sum, which will be used to relieve the poverty of the strikers. It was decided also that a great mass meeting be held, at which we can decide upon appropriate resolutions that will voice our feelings on such distressing occurrences as that of Lemont. The mass meeting will be held on Sunday, June 25, at the School Hall near Bradley Street. In accordance with the decision made at <pb facs="5423968_3_0135.jpg" n="3"/>the last meeting, we invite all of our countrymen to attend. The presence of each and every one of us is imperative; the greater our gathering, the mightier our protest. So we repeat: Every Pole should attend the mass meeting on next Sunday for his own good and for the good of his brethren."</p>
   <p>E. Z. Brodowski, T. Krolik, and J. Mucha, who have been delegated by the executive committee to investigate the strikers' situation, went to Lemont this morning. Results of their trip will appear in tomorrow's issue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
