<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">Mar. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1025</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1025.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4 (German)</item>
     <item>I F 1 (German)</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-07">Mar. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again we have been defeated. Last year we were beaten by a split in the Democratic ranks, but this year we have been defeated by a division within our own ranks. In the preceding year, we at least were rewarded by having our own candidate elected to the office of city treasurer. This year, we find no such consolation.</p>
   <p>Last year, as well as this year, we can blame no one but ourselves for our sad showing in the election returns. The same individual was responsible for the results each time. Will this be a lesson to us?</p>
   <p>Let us ponder over these two elections. Last year, as it is known, there was a split in the Democratic party. Heavy clouds of doubt shrowded its ranks. It was feared that the Republican candidate for mayor would get into office, <pb facs="5423968_3_1026.jpg" n="2"/>although there was a slight <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the Republican ranks also. But this break in the Republican ranks was not as severe as the break on the opposing side.</p>
   <p>In the many public mass meetings and in some of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the failure to agree upon a Democratic candidate for mayor was blamed upon the Poles. It was pointed out that the good of the party depended upon a solid vote for the regular Democratic candidates by the Polish citizens of Chicago. Only this solid support would avert the crisis in the Democratic ranks. It was emphatically pointed out to the Polish citizenry that the fate of the party lay in their hands, that if they divided their votes defeat was inevitable, and would be followed by heavy losses to the party and to their group.</p>
   <p>Yet, persons were found who favored a split in the regular Democratic party. They expended untiring effort in creating friction in the party ranks, especially in the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> It was in this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that great pressure was put on the Polish citizens to vote for a German candidate. At the head of <pb facs="5423968_3_1027.jpg" n="3"/>this faction was the former alderman, who called himself a Pole, but worked for the benefit of the Germans at the expense of the Polish people.</p>
   <p>What were the results? It is true that a polish candidate for city treasurer was elected, truly a proud victory for the Poles. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Kunz was victorious, despite the intrigue. However, a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Republican candidate for mayor, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, was elected by a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of a little over two hundred votes. This in itself was an example to our people. It definitely proved that if the Polish people had voted as they were told, and had not listened to the agitators, a Democratic mayor would have been elected by an undisputed majority. As a result, a score or even a few hundred Poles would have benefited by being placed in the various vacancies that come with a change of government in the city hall. Instead, many lost their positions.</p>
   <p>What happened this year? We tried to assure the victory of one of our own candidates for west Town collector. This was no easy task. Not merely one ward <pb facs="5423968_3_1028.jpg" n="4"/>was concerned, but fourteen. In most of these wards, the Polish population was small. But the support of the Democratic party, plus that of the Labor party, gave August Kowalski a splendid opportunity to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. What made us concerned was the entrance of an independent <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the Sixteenth Ward. The same individual who could not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> votes in the primaries to be nominated, and who last year and responsible for the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in our ranks, again tried the same <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>The Germans in the West Side <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> insulted. They had just reasons. They had been promised a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the victory of the Democratic party if a Polish candidate for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> collector were elected; because of this, the Poles of the Sixteenth Ward wanted to work for the regular German aldermanic candidate. Besides, they had the promise of the before-mentioned "Independent" that the would drop out of the race as soon as the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> showed that the votes were against him. But, instead, this person stepped out and tried to wrench victory from a German candidate. The Germans had a right to feel offended.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1029.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>They said, "If this is the way the Poles are going to cooperate with us, then we will not support them." The German population <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the Polish in these fourteen West Side <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> The Poles could <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> beast of a strong Sixteenth Ward, and it was there that the split in the vote occurred.</p>
   <p>The outcome of the election was as <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and clerk were chosen, the collector's <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and, as a result of the Democratic party split, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> office was virtually given to the Republican candidate. All the German <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> were elected.</p>
   <p>The Germans have been <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> saw the danger and sounded a warning that the Polish candidate's <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of election as West Town collector were <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> issued a last <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to the Polish people. We <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> than not to listen to the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who had already caused enough harm during the last election. But what <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> This paper was severely criticized for supporting <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the <pb facs="5423968_3_1030.jpg" n="6"/>Sixteenth Ward, The was called <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. The vituperations were so load that the Germans who were going to support the regular Democratic ticket decided to get revenge by voting for a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> candidate for collector.</p>
   <p>Therefore, Kowalski lost a position that would have been his had it not been for the split in our ranks. We are indebted for this to a few score self-made "ardent" political patriots and their <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, men who last year used patriotism as an excuse for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> instead of a Pole, and this year used the same idea to oppose a German. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> As a result, neither side made a gain. Will this be a lasting lesson to us? We have some doubts, for last year's lesson did not do us any good in this year's election. The political agitators again <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> important office to further their small <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> ambitions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
