<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-06">Feb. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Poles and Political Patromage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-06">Feb. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLES AND POLITICAL PATROMAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is absolutely not a sufficient number of Poles holding office in the administration of the City of Chicago, and likewise of Cook County. Recently, during the campaign for the primary elections, at several of the meetings the speakers emphasized the credit due Mayor Harrison for placing Poles in responsible administrative positions. And furthermore it was stated that it is a duty of the Poles to express their loyalty and gratitude by casting a vote in his favor. Let us see whether the Poles are in debt or owe gratitude to any one. In all similar discussions and arguments statistics play an important role. Therefore, in this instance we shall present statistical data which will determine our position in regard to this question. We must remind the speakers who brought the issue of gratitude to the surface that at the last election a total of 400,000 votes was cast; 250,000 of these were Democratic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1477.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are not in a position to determine definitely the number of Polish Democratic votes, but we can safely assume that at least 30,000 of the total were Polish Democratic votes. This constitutes at least one tenth of all the votes cast for the party.</p>
   <p>Statistical figures are facts which are consulted by candidates after each election, and are used as basic information in distributing patronage. Without a doubt Mayor Harrison consulted these election returns prior to the appointment of worthy workers to various administrative positions in city government. We likewise know that he would not be mayor of the city were it not for the Polish votes. Thus he should be guided by the law of proportion in allotting these positions, and make his selection to conform in number to the percentage of votes each national group has cast.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1478.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Poles, on this basis, are entitled to 10% of all positions alloted by the Mayor. Should the figure exceed 10% then we should express gratitude, but not until then. As a fact the number of Poles holding administrative office is far below the 10% quota which is due. Thus, statistical data do not testify in favor of those speakers who, in behalf of the Mayor, appeal to the Polish voters in Chicago for expression of loyalty and gratitude. The Polish people are very appreciative for any special favors that may be extended them, but certainly in the case mentioned above we see no reason why they should express gratitude for things which were not received. Thus, until such time as our list shall reach and exceed the 10%, we have nothing to be grateful for. Ten per cent represent a quota which our Mayor is bound by duty and spirit of fairness to fill. As the situation stands at present, the appreciation and gratitude should come from the office of the Mayor and should be extended to the Polish people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
