<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
	<bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy Zgoda</title>,
	<date when="1910-03-22">Mar. 22, 1910</date>.
	<title level="a">Labor Questions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
     <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy (Zgoda)</title>,
	<date when="1910-03-22">Mar. 22, 1910</date>.
	<title level="a">LABOR QUESTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our ao-called social problem is too broad and general to be solved by a struggle between capital and labor. Labor's problems are often considered as the whole social problem, because labor's cries are the loudest.</p>
   <p>Labor was first to condemn our present social organization, and most determinedly demanded a change. Therefore it is small wonder, that it has become an important social problem. Two reasons can be advanced for this: first, the technical development of big business; and second, the agitation of labor organizations.</p>
   <p>The creation of new industries requiring great concentration of capital and men, has resulted in a heretofore unknown struggle between the <pb facs="5423968_3_0379.jpg" n="2"/>powerful and rich industrialists, and labor, living for the most part in want or in almost complete misery.</p>
   <p>Nowhere has social inequality stood out so prominently, and the enemies of society appeared before our eyes so blazingly, as in the concentration of capital and human beings in large factories.</p>
   <p>Here neb are subjected to hard labor, at poor pay. Here the capitalists are milking stupendous profits from industry.</p>
   <p>The worker, who grieved daily, over this injustice, and was personally conscious of the overbalancing of human sweat and hard labor, by lifeless wealth, voiced his discontent, and hoped for a change.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0380.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The worker who is fighting against the present system was the first to observe these injustices, and immediately set himself to the task of correcting them.</p>
   <p>Theoretically, he fought by bringing to light the errors of our social organizations; by picturing the existing miseries, and the struggle to overcome them; by imploring aid from the selfish owners of undeserved wealth. Or, practically, by carrying on a clearly defined agitation among the disgruntled, emphasizing the many injustices, and by instilling into them a feeling or consciousness of the necessity of organization, a faith in the future, and hope for ultimate victory.</p>
   <p>Constantly pointing out the large number of the abused, the agitators endeavored to form a powerful labor organization. In such an organization <pb facs="5423968_3_0381.jpg" n="4"/>numbers would compensate for the lack of material wealth, and this would enable the workers to wage a war against the existing usurpations.</p>
   <p>The whole aim of this movement, should be to improve the economic welfare of the working classes, by the enactment of favorable legislation. It is evident that the workers' organizations, must strive for social equality, not only by appealing to the nobler and more human instincts, but also by immediately placing themselves in a position to take advantage of any favorable conditions arising in the business world.</p>
   <p>It is said that the undervaluation of the workers is the outgrowth of the selfishness of powerful social groups in the upper strata of society. There exists a natural conflict between the interests of the employers and those of the workers. The employer, having politics as his ally, has for centuries exploited labor, and labor cannot free itself from this plague, until it becomes big and strong enough, so that when it speaks its voice will be heard.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0382.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Finally the labor movement should aim to better the material welfare of the worker by creating for him the possibility of honest sharing in the income of the community.</p>
   <p>The one sure way of accomplishing this is by gaining influence and political power. Then the labor movement will appear in theory, as aiming at many radical changes and reforms in our social structures, but practically, as a struggle for political influence.</p>
   <p>This dual role of organized labor will react very favorably upon all labor groups, because it appeals to the honesty of the general public, and particularly to business.</p>
   <p>Those in favor of honest government, and equal rights for all classes, also favor reforms aimed at the many mistakes and abuses of our social <pb facs="5423968_3_0383.jpg" n="6"/>system, such as the exploitation of our fellow human beings on a large scale.</p>
   <p>In its far reaching demands, this labor movement has brought about some changes in the working conditions of today, and it probably has affected all classes of labor.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in the interest of self-preservation, the exploiters found it wise to quickly remove labors' leading agitators and liberators, also some of the most outstanding grievances, hoping that in making some insignificant concessions they would avert a major calamity.</p>
   <p>So under the pressure of this movement, the cause of the workers began to attract attention so rapidly, that in the last twenty or twenty-two years it became a chief topic of conversation and discussion. Now we must admit, that, as a result of this movement, much has been accomplished, and <pb facs="5423968_3_0384.jpg" n="7"/>in the past few years working conditions really have been improved.</p>
   <p>Now we have many laws safeguarding the worker against injury and exploitation. A complete system of insurance has been established, entitling the worker to a compensation in case of accident or injury. Laws have been enacted, safeguarding women and children in d=industry.</p>
   <p>A workman is not considered as a piece of machinery any longer; the law specifies the number of working hours, and assures him a day of rest during the week. They cannot exploit a man to the last ounce of his physical strength. The employer must adhere to a set of rules and regulations. Government inspectors (everywhere except in the United States) do not tolerate violations, of these rules, especially of those pertaining to sanitation and hygiene.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0385.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Industry is not permitted to prey upon the workers, because their organizations and the courts are willing to serve the in all their demands. Now the working hours have been reduced. The work has been made easier. In fact, whole existence of the worker has been ade more tolerable, and his problems have captured the interest and sympathy of the general public.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, discontent among the working classes, i not diminishing but is spreading and gaining greater momentum daily. Labor organizations demand a complete overthrow of our present system, and assure their members that in the future, labor will be fully compensated for its creative activity. Furthermore labor leaders affirm that all real values, are the result of human labor, exerted on lifeless matter.</p>
   <p>Of course this is a picture of a distant future, but, labor today is <pb facs="5423968_3_0386.jpg" n="9"/>not et satisfied with its present gains. The working class claims that many of the abuses from which it suffers have not as yet been abolished. The demands of labor are very important, but, they meet with a stubborn opposition on the part of capitalists.</p>
   <p>Labor organizations have loaded capital and industry with many burdens, and they are tolerating them only, because they hope that their differences will finally be adjusted; but these differences remain solved only for a short time, and soon agitation is started again. Such has been of late the relationship between capital and labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
