<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>. Vol. 15. No. 52.
<date when="1921-12-22">December 22, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Constitution of the United States - Is your Protection against Injustice.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>. Vol. 15. No.52.
<date when="1921-12-22">December 22, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Constitution of the United States - Is your Protection Against Injustice.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You should study the Constitution of the United States, in order to acquaint yourselves with the laws and duties of this country. The Constitution is the highest law of the country, observed by all states and cities of the Union. Learn some of the most important points of the Constitution.</p>
   <p>It establishes a permanent government which is responsible to the people for your safety and welfare.</p>
   <p>It gives the alien the privilege to become a citizen of the United States and a right to vote.</p>
   <p>It gives the voters the right of participation in government through the officials elected by them. It gives every one who is qualified, a right to hold an office. (Presidency is the only office than an alien is not allowed to hold in the United States.)</p>
   <p>It guarantees the freedom of religion, the freedom of the press and the freedom <pb facs="5423968_3_0262.jpg" n="2"/>of speech, also the right to assemble peacefully....</p>
   <p>It protects the right of possession, either personal or real estate, and prohibits (or forbids) the government from confiscating any property without proper court procedure.</p>
   <p>It considers all citizens equal in the eyes of the law. It also provides the following privileges for further protection of its citizens from injustice.</p>
   <p>It does not allow any one to be arrested without proper court order, and the arrested one has a right to know the reason for his arrest.</p>
   <p>It gives every one the right to be judged by the jury and to have the assistance of a council for his defense. It does not allow that you should be judged twice for the same offense. It also gives the right to the offender to be judged there where the offense was committed. It gives you the right to compel the witnesses to appear in court for your defense. It frees you from becoming a witness against yourself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
