<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 116,
<date when="1921-12-24">Dec. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Socialists and Communists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 116,
<date when="1921-12-24">Dec. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISTS AND COMMUNISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time our socialists have been yelping at the communists in return barking at the socialists; perhaps they desired to soap each others' eyes. There were those who believed this nonsense, but we know them well and know that their aim is to abolish everything which is not tainted with the rot of "radicalism". They could, therefore, no longer endure their own nonsense and so they came face to face with each other.</p>
   <p>The socialist party and the communist party decided to unite as one group, and have invited the presence of all "reds" in New York, with the aim of organizing the "Labor Party in America".</p>
   <p>The group selected for this "red" festivity was composed mostly of Jews, communists and socialists, also - The American Labor Organization, The Jewish Federal Socialistic Party, The German Labor Society, The Jewish Workers' Federation, The Scandinavian Federation of Workers, The Socialist Greek Union, The Irish-American Workers, and socialists of all nationalities.</p>
   <p>They will use "crafty" means of every type to wipe out everything that is not tainted with socialism; and so we can expect that our socialists who hide beneath <pb facs="5423968_3_0260.jpg" n="2"/>the cloak of a Polish origin, will pretend to favor everything that is Polish. It can not be understood how those socialists can lie so shamelessly, calling themselves Poles, and unite themselves with the greatest enemy of the Polish nation - that is, the Jews. If we glance over the statistics of the P.P.S., we will beconvinced that an enormous percentage of Jews and socialists are attempting to bring about in Poland a union with discordant interests. But their end is nearing; their reign is losing its grip, because in Poland the workingman has lost faith in them, and in many countries these "liars" are strewn about to the four winds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
