<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 67,
<date when="1908-03-19">March 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Working Classes Should Be Refresented in City Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 67,
<date when="1908-03-19">March 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WORKING CLASSES SHOULD BE REFRESENTED IN CITY HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago we called the attention of our readers to the necessity of electing socialists as representatives of the working classes to the City Council, because they as members of one great proletariat family will protect it against the crafty capitalists and will conduct the city's business only in the interest of the working people. We also pointed to the various city departments and stated that proper and honest management of these departments would help to abolish, or perhaps relieve the terrible bondage in which we are kept by the capitalistic monster.</p>
   <p>At the present time, the whole city management is a privilege of the capitalists; they take advantage of their economic preponderance, especially of our low social and political level, and by means of the most degrading bribery and cheating, they manage the city's business not for the city, but for themselves.</p>
   <p>The Polish national-clerical pipers are already "blowing their horns" with all their might in favor of some candidates, which is the best proof that they are either already bribed, or that their pockets will be filled with <pb facs="5423968_3_0440.jpg" n="2"/>jingling coins in the very near future.</p>
   <p>The workingman, however, should not be fooled by that kind of paid propaganda, but should be supported by facts. He should form his own opinion regarding the candidates for alderman. It is obvious that the candidates for aldermen were not made guardians of the city over-night by a magic wand, but are the same business men they were before.</p>
   <p>If any of the candidates running again for office had "slipped with one foot" before, we must not take it for granted that they have acquired more agility in their old age; and that in the future not only one but both feet will slip and the workingman will be obliged to pay for it with his skin.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that every business man is an enemy of the workingman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
