<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-06">Oct. 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">New Polish Democratic Headquarters in the Sixteenth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-10-06">Oct. 6, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLISH DEMOCRATIC HEADQUARTERS IN THE SIXTEENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>New Polish Democratic headquarters have been opened at 587 Milwaukee Avenue for the convenience of those residing in the Sixteenth Ward. Democrats can meet here freely. Naturalization classes are open to all those desiring to become citizens. Those wishing to take advantage at this service should call any day at 12:30 P. M. and every evening, except Monday, at 7 P. M. Citizenship papers may be obtained free of charge. The Polish Democratic organization also pays for the transportation of the applicant and witness, and the latter's fee, if any. There is no charge for any of these services.</p>
   <p>The office is open daily from 9 A. M. to 10 P. M. During these hours questions of all kinds will be answered.</p>
   <p>Naturalization Committee, 587 Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>Joseph S. Geshkewich.</p>
   <p>Louis Roland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These Democratic headquarters were opened for the convenience of the citizens of the Sixteenth Ward by the president of the Sixteenth Ward Polish Democratic Club. All expenses were borne by him.</p>
   <p>The president of the Club is Peter Kiolbassa, city treasurer. Credit is due him for this generous contribution to the Polish people. He also arranged to have the office and hall decorated with American flags; a large banner with the name of the organization has been placed in a conspicuous place on the outside of the building.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kiolbassa is leaving today for San Antonio, Texas, where he will stay eight days. The vice-president, Mr. Buxbaum, will take charge of the duties of the Club during his superior's absence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
