<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-11">June 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Newly Organized Democratic Club]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-11">June 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[NEWLY ORGANIZED DEMOCRATIC CLUB]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An important meeting of the newly organized Democratic club of the Sixteenth Ward will be held on June 12, 1892, in meeting hall no. 1 of the Polish school building, on Bradley Street. It is presumed that it is not necessary to encourage the citizens too emphatically in taking part in this meeting. We hope that the hall will be filled.</p>
   <p>Thus far, somehow, we have had no success with our political organizations. There were several trials, none had borne the desired fruits. Perhaps at this time it will be more favorable; we have learned a great deal, especially during the past year. The Poles have gained much experience and all the nationalities acknowledged that the Poles would be capable of occupying positions in municipal politics, if they were better organized.</p>
   <p>In the spring of last year we were most vitally interested in political affairs; a great deal was said and written about us here. In the fall <pb facs="5423968_3_1022.jpg" n="2"/>nearly nothing was heard of us; in the spring of the following year, however, we suffered an enormous defeat, and it was shown here most conclusively how much we are in need of a good organization.</p>
   <p>During the spring of last year we have combined our whole strength, because, personally, we were most interested. It pertained to our candidates and we have solidly worked for their benefit. Then, everyone was interested in politics, everyone who was a citizen was proud of the fact that his vote amounted to something. In the fall we had no candidates; great was our indifference during the election as a result of this.</p>
   <p>In the spring of that year a controversy existed amongst us. Consequently, we were ignobly defeated.</p>
   <p>All this proves that we do not know how to participate in politics properly. When it pertains to our personal matters then we are temporarily excited but, when we are not interested personally, we do not speak. Is this proper?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1023.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We should comprehend that our interest does not merely consist in electing a few of our candidates to some office. We make part of the city, part of a community, part of a state, part of the American nation, and for that reason municipal, county, state, and national politics should always concern us. Our general welfare depends upon the returns of these elections, upon the statutes that are being enacted, and upon the gains or losses that result from the victory or defeat of the party in which we have always participated However, we do not know how to do that; we are only concerned with how some Poles will receive some position.</p>
   <p>For this reason a permanent policy necessary for us. By simply belonging to a political organization, we will learn to understand national politics and to take wise action in it. Then it will become easier to place our own candidates and assist in their election; then, the other nationalities would have to take us seriously.</p>
   <p>When a political club is organized it is our opinion that it would be well <pb facs="5423968_3_1024.jpg" n="4"/>to hold most frequent meetings, called by this club, in order to clarify particular [issues] of national, state, county, and municipal politics by means of addresses, orations, and readings. Debates could also be conducted which would greatly help in clarifying the frequently involved and difficult questions. A more political club, whose members at a certain time would perhaps proceed in unity, but do not themselves know why they are doing so will not help. It is necessary to create a thorough understanding of the situation and make sure that every citizen gains a most adequate knowledge of various political questions.</p>
   <p>Let us, therefore, meet in council tomorrow afternoon, and let us gather in as great numbers as possible. Before this takes place, let us also give thought to what motions and propositions we are to present so that the organizers will meet with more success this time than previously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
