<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 88,
<date when="1908-04-13">April 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"The Club Is Mightier Than the Constitution"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 88,
<date when="1908-04-13">April 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">"THE CLUB IS MIGHTIER THAN THE CONSTITUTION"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>These words were uttered by a certain captain of New York City Police to the committee sent by the conference representing working-men's societies, complaining that the police acted unlawfully at the meeting for the unemployed on March 28th. As we know, the American Constitution guarantees very plainly the right of the citizens to assemble publicly and discuss anything they please.</p>
   <p>The purpose of that conference for the unemployed, which took place at Union Souare in New York, was to discuss peacefully the situation caused by business depression. The speakers to explain to the assembled workers what to do in order to get work which they need so much. Therefore, this meeting was neither anarchistic nor socialistic. The signs announcing the meeting did not indicate that it was going to be revolutionary propaganda. The police of New York are aware that the organizations which help the unemployed in that city do respect the laws of the country and the city, and were able to keep good order in the past years.</p>
   <p>Why is it that the police attacked the innocent pedestrians with the brutality of the Russian Cossacks about two hours before the explosion of Silverstein's bomb.? The authorities stated that the police had a right to disperse the crowds, because they had no permit to hold a meeting and on that account had gathered unlawfully.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0213.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true that they did not get the permit when they applied for it at the police station and the park commissioner's office. But it is also true that according to the Constitution of the United States, neither the police nor the park commissioner has any right to refuse a meeting to be held at a public place by the working-people. Furthermore, that there were such meetings held at Union Square for the same purpose by the same people who were also the organizers of the Unemployed Aid Conference. The authorities in this case acted despotically; they deprived the American citizens of the great right which was handed down to us by the Fathers of the Nation, the right to assemble in public places for discussion.</p>
   <p>If anyone is guilty of violating the Constitution of the United States, it is the park commissioner and the police; not less guilty is the Mayor of New York who sided with these authorities. If any one is to be punished, it should be these public servants and not the participants in the meeting who had a right to gather in Union Square, and this right was denied to them.</p>
   <p>Had they submitted to the despotic prohibition of city authorities then, they would have given the authorities an excuse for similar refusals in the future, and endanger the right of citizens to assemble in public places. Indeed, we all know how easy it is to lose personal liberty if we allow someone unpunished to deprive us men of a very small part of that liberty; and that concerns the whole nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0214.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The proverb says: "Give only a finger to a dog and he will want the whole hand". Let the American working-men allow their capitalistic government to deprive them of only one right guaranteed by the Constitution - than, in a very short time, they will lose a second had a third right. Today they will forbid the working-men to hold a meeting; tomorrow they will forbid them to organize for their protection; and on the third day they will forbid them to publish a paper which serves the interests of the working-man. For such is the nature of the people who want to dominate their fellow-man, whether in Russia or America.</p>
   <p>Therefore, our brothers in New York City were justified in what they did. They were not afraid of the police and held their meeting in spite of the prohibition by the police authorities. In this case they acted as any patriotic and liberty loving American citizen would. We are positive that it was not the lack of a permit to hold a meeting at Union Square which caused the police to fall down upon the participators of the meeting, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> anyone with whom they came in contact. We are quite positive that the police would not have acted differently even if the workers had a permit to hold the meeting. The police desired to discourage the unemployed of New York City from holding such meetings in the future. It was for the purpose of scaring the socialists and preventing them from teaching the workingmen about their rights.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0215.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The dominating class in America is responsible for the poverty of a million and a half of the working people. It knows how poorly the affairs of the country are managed; it knows that the people are indignant because of greed, brutality, and the autocracy of the capitalistic government. Therefore, it hates the sight of the working people.</p>
   <p>The Chicago and New York City police know very well the attitude of the dominating class toward the army of hungry and despairing working-men. The police also know that the capitalists and their servants, the politicians, will look on peacefully when they, the police, attack the working-men with their clubs. The police know that the capitalists ignore the Constitution, and this is the reason why the police play the role of the Cossack in respect to the American working-men. For that they are praised by the capitalistic press and their hirelings, the politicians, from Roosevelt down to the common alderman. They always forgive the heroes in blue uniforms for being very closely allied with the crooks.</p>
   <p>The police captain knew what he was talking about when he said: "The club is mightier than the Constitution".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
