<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 20,
<date when="1921-05-19">May 19, 1921</date><title level="a">The Week</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 20,
<date when="1921-05-19">May 19, 1921</date><title level="a">THE WEEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is by no means an innovation in a Polish-American periodical, or for that matter, in any foreign language American paper. The introduction of this weekly comment on things in general was prompted by the duty we owe to our younger generation of Polish-American readers, who are well versed in both the American and Polish languages, and if you wish to have it, for the enlightenment of a wider class of readers on American matters, inasmuch as they are co-related with affairs and events foreign to the average American mind.</p>
   <p>There is being spread widely in the industrial regions of this country propaganda tending to upset the great American slogan "One Flag, one country!" Now and again we will hear of "red literature" circulated in a foreign language among the foreign born. The "reds" among the foreign-born workers are practically nil. The red leaders must be looked for among the Big Bill Haywood and Scott Nearing type of man. It may seem amiss to many that a periodical published in the Polish language, and a local paper like the Polonia, should take up the work, yet we believe sincerely that if all foreign language American papers followed suit, the "glad hand" of the truly patriotic American would lend unanimous support in furthering the good work. We ask nothing but a clear understanding of the Polish-American. We feel assured that our work will be well received and we shall try our utmost to fulfill the duty to the best of our ability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
