<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 55,
    <date when="1922-03-07">March 7, 1922</date>.
    <title level="a">A Pole at the Head of the Ballot</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 55,<date when="1922-03-07">March 7, 1922</date>.
    <title level="a">A POLE AT THE HEAD OF THE BALLOT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During this current year it occurs for the first time that a Polish candidate stands at the head of the Democratic ballot in Cook county. There never was an instance in the past where a candidacy of this kind had been given to a Pole. Smaller offices were always given to us - but never before has a Pole been endorsed for the office of county judge.</p>
   <p>Toward the end of last week the list of candidates which the Democratic committee endorsed for office was completed. In reality, the county ballot has been prepared for nearly two weeks, but there was still lacking the list of candidates for municipal judges.</p>
   <p>Today, therefore, we can give in its entirety the whole regular Democratic ballot, just as we received it from Democratic headquarters in the Hotel Sherman.</p>
   <p>Who are the candidates?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A Pole, Judge Edmund K. Jarecki, stands at the head of the above mentioned ballot. We repeat once more that this is the first time in Cook county that a Pole has been offered the candidacy for the highest office in the county. Now the Poles will be able to show their strength. The Poles can elect Judge Jarecki for this office, but only if they take action in the primaries and the election. THe primary election will be very important because an Irishman is also endeavoring to receive the nomination for that office on the Democratic ticket. The regular Democratic organization is not supporting this Irishman. The Democrats in Cook county have endorsedJudge Jarecki and if they fulfill their duty properly, Jerecki will be nominated in the primaries and will be a Democratic candidate in the fall. We can expect a colossal victory of the Democrats. The reasons for this are many; in Chicago and Cook county there are more reasons for a Democratic victory than anywhere else. in the first <pb facs="5423968_3_0621.jpg" n="3"/>place there is the present standstill in work, lack of well-being, because millions of people are unemployed.</p>
   <p>Three Poles are candidates for municipal judges, all of the three have this year received the support of the Democratic party. one of the candidates is Attorney Peter H. Schwaba, the second is Attorney John Prystalski, the third is Frank Danisch.</p>
   <p>The Poles know all three candidates because all three of them have already held public office. Attorney Schwaba was an official in the State Health Commission during the administration of Governor Dunne; Attorney John Prystlski served a number of years as assistant state's attorney, and in this office he demonstrated extraordinary ability. Attorney Frank Danisch was clerk of the Municipal court and everyone knows him well.</p>
   <p>The Polish candidate for county commissioner is Mr. Albert Nowak, <pb facs="5423968_3_0622.jpg" n="4"/>who for many years has held this office.</p>
   <p>Remember about registration. The Poles will be able to elect their candidates only if they take a combined interest in the primaries. He who wants to vote must register, and the registration in Chicago is on March 21st. Th primaries fall on April 11th.</p>
   <p>Women are allowed to vote this year for all offices. The Polish women this year will have an opportunity to demonstrate their strength in voting.</p>
   <p>The committee engaging in the candidacy of Judge Jarecki for the office of county judge is at present collecting funds for the campaign. At the head of the finance committee stands Mr. Paul Drymalski.</p>
   <p>The headquarters of Judge Jarecki are in the Hotel Sherman, Room 202.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0623.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Beginning today the headquarters will be open daily for all who during this campaign desire to contribute toward the victory of Judge Jarecki and all of the other Polish candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
