<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-19">Dec. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Report from the Political Club of the Fourteenth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-19">Dec. 19, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A REPORT FROM THE POLITICAL CLUB OF THE FOURTEENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The political club of Polish citizens of the Fourteenth Ward at its last meeting considered in detail the matter of the striking tailors who in Chicago are struggling for better wages for themselves as well as for their fellow workers. There are 45,000 striking tailors, of whom 15,000 are Poles. This struggle has already been marked by three deaths, and these three dead, unfortunately, were Poles. Three Poles were deprived of life by the brutal police whom the officals of the city, by order of the Mayor, placed at the disposal of unscrupulous exploiters. By so doing they have left the city devoid of police protection, at the mercy of criminals. Such behavior of our city officals deserves reproof. The police assist the scabs to and from work, attack innocent women and children, and degrade themselves by doing yeoman work for capitalists, which is unbecoming to the dignity of police. Thus far no one has made any protest against the behavior of our police department.</p>
   <p>We have, nevertheless, four Polish aldermen in the city council, sent there by <pb facs="5423968_3_1177.jpg" n="2"/>Polish votes, but did even one of these gentlemen have sufficient courage to pretest against such behavior of the police? Did any one of them raise his voice in the city council? No. They cannot be found where they ought to be, where they ought to stand, in defense of their compatriots, of their brethren.</p>
   <p>The club has adopted a proper resolution in this matter. It will be presented to the alderman of the Fourteenth Ward, Mr. Lawler, that it may be brought before the meeting of the city council.</p>
   <p>W. Belinski, president</p>
   <p>M. Przybylski, vice-president</p>
   <p>Z. Cichanski, treasurer</p>
   <p>A. Mazylewski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
