<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol.9. No.20.
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">- Do Miners Desire Smaller Wages -</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol.9. No.20.
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">- Do Miners Desire Smaller Wages -</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Throughout Pennsylvania is heard the report that the mining companies are contemplating a lower wage scale in April of the coming year, that is at the time of the expiration of the present agreement. It is true that we still have eleven months before that time, but it is never too early for preparedness.</p>
   <p>Do the miners desire a lowering of pay?</p>
   <p>From all probability no. On the contrary they think, that they are entitled to an increase. But in what way can they prevent the capitalists from carrying out their aims and what way can they try to better their welfare?</p>
   <p>In those districts, where most of the miners belong to a union, there is not even any talk about that whether there can be a cut in the wage scale, and their demands for an increase will be taken into consideration. The owners of the mines acknowledge the strength of the Union, and there only they decide to negotiate in case of a strike, eventually agreeing to the terms of the miners, where there are not and if so very few non-union miners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0472.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In what way does the question present itself in districts, where just a few members belong to the Union? What will they do? They ought to know, what they should do. The only one way of bettering their conditions is to sign up for a membership in the Union.</p>
   <p>(We call your attention to the article: How much does a ton of coal cost the capitalists.) Editorial column.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
