<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-09">July 9, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Poles in Chicago and the Incedents of the Last Few Days</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-09">July 9, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLES IN CHICAGO AND THE INCEDENTS OF THE LAST FEW DAYS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The deplorable incidents of the last few days seriously affected the Poles of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the columns of this newspaper, our readers will find the details about our countrymen's participation in the incidents which occurred last Saturday. One Pole was killed, six Polish men and one Polish woman were seriously wounded, and many Poles were injured. This is the sum total of the profits which we gained by taking part in the great railroad strike in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Many people are already condemning us for our part in that affray and there <pb facs="5423968_3_0119.jpg" n="2"/>will be still more newspapers, individuals, and political parties which will draw from this circumstance wrong conclusions, which will be harmful to us.</p>
   <p>The question therefore arises: Are these conclusions justified by our acts? Or have they been arrived at through malice and falsehood? Will it not be necessary for the Polish people to protest against these conclusions? We will comment on this later.</p>
   <p>Today we feel that it is our duty to make at least this short statement: Contrary to the assertions made by some newspapers, we do not see any such terrible criminals among the Chicago Polish people as they would wish to make them appear. On the contrary, we are the victims of this unfortunate trouble. We see heedlessness for which many persons pay with their blood. After men have plundered and burned railroad cars, and have escaped, a crowd of Polish gaspers gathers and receives the bullets intended for the guilty persons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0120.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, we appeal once more to our countrymen: Compatriots! Be careful. Do not be misled either by the instigator or by your own passion. Do not participate in disturbances. Do not gather thoughtlessly, from curiosity, at places where there have been disturbances. The bullets which penetrated the breasts of your countrymen yesterday might be aimed at your breast.</p>
   <p>You will find a similar warning in the telegram sent by our Archbishop, which appears on the front page of this paper.</p>
   <p>Once more, we beg and beseech you, please avoid mobs. This concerns not only the present, not only your health and life, but also your future. We ask you to stay out of these troubles so that you will not be considered as disturbers and anarchists, and under this pretext be denied this American land and deprived of the right to gain a livelihood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
