<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-31">July 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Anglo-Saxon Editor Foreigners for Strikes in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-31">July 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ANGLO-SAXON EDITOR FOREIGNERS FOR STRIKES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the Anglo-Saxon publications, when discussing in an editorial the strikes that are very often breaking out in various branches of industry, sharply attacks the workers who came to the United States from some foreign countries. He writes of the outbreaks, agitation and disrespect for the laws of America and puts the blame for all this on the immigrants.</p>
   <p>Slinging mud at the workers of foreign origin, and especially at those of Slavic extraction, the editor in his editorial gives the following advice: "very apparent is the necessity of teaching and Americanizing these violent foreigners. It is very surprising, how rapidly these foreigners ascertain the value of the American dollar, how prompt they are in demanding higher <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> how alert they are in organizing themselves for concerted action, and how rapid they are in understanding the meaning of an American strike of considering a job. It is necessary to teach them the meaning of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Laws, the extent of their authority and the <pb facs="5423968_3_0055.jpg" n="2"/>jurisdiction of the constitution. Union leaders, on many occasions in the past, appealed to all the union locals in the coal mining regions exhorting them to calm down, and it was expected that this would be accomplished peacefully; however, the succeeding outbursts became so violent, that they surpassed all former outbreaks.</p>
   <p>It is a great misfortune, that capitalists and unions do not energetically endeavor to Americanize these foreigners. They come to this country in hordes, colonize and work according to their own plans, being subjected strictly to police regulations and court discipline only when they commit a crime. The important coal mining industry of this country is at their mercy, since these foreigners rebel against the coal companies whenever they please. Because society does not fulfil its obligations towards them, they in return have little respect and understanding for the general welfare; therefore, this condition exists during periods of unrest and catastrophe."</p>
   <p>So much from the Anglo-Saxon editor. He forgets or may be does not know that strikes bring to the front labor leaders belonging to unions, men <pb facs="5423968_3_0056.jpg" n="3"/>who were born in this country, and brought up as American citizens. He forgets that the Slavic element is doing hard and dangerous work, which pays small wages. If these <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> on strike, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> a time when they realize that they <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> by the capitalists, or killing themselves by hard labor, which no American, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>or Swede would care to undertake. Criticizing only the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for these outbreaks, is, to say the least impudence, because everybody knows that Americans and foreigners of other than Slavic extraction also <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in strikes. Americans are the first to rouse the others; then they put the blame on the foreign element. In regard to the Anglo-Saxon editor, we want to point out that he does not mention that the dynamiting McNamara brothers, are not Poles.</p>
   <p>Further, the very intelligent editor, suggests the Americanization of the foreign element, so that they may quicker become familiar with the American laws and respect them. He believes that, when Americaninzed, they become angels; he does not see that the highest percentage of the various crimes, scandals and vice is committed by Americans. Instead of converting and civilizing foreigners, let the Anglo-Saxon editors and missionaries convert and civilize those American born persons who manifest criminal <pb facs="5423968_3_0057.jpg" n="4"/>tendencies by committing such acts as lynching and killing innocent negroes; slaying government officials and judges in courts; abducting and beating women; dynamiting buildings and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> shooting and killing their own families during family quarrels; holding up railroad trains and robbing the passengers, and many more crimes that are too numerous to mention, since they are taking place at all times. Let the Americans civilize these people, teach them to respect the American laws, because the European immigrants respect this law and are not as apt to commit various crimes, as is the element which has been living in America for several generations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
