<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 137,
<date when="1908-06-12">June 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Socialist Party Is the Only Party of the Working Class</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 137,
<date when="1908-06-12">June 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIALIST PARTY IS THE ONLY PARTY OF THE WORKING CLASS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist party is the only party of the working class; the only party of the disinherited; the only party of the enslaved and despised; the only party which stands honestly on the platform that liberates the people from misery and exploitation; the only party which endeavors to obtain equality and freedom for all people, men, women, and children.</p>
   <p>A real Socialist not only believes in the future brotherhood of men, but also knows how to bring this belief to realization. As the brotherhood of men is the aim towards which a Socialist strives, so enlightenment and struggle of the classes are the means by which this aim is attained. The brotherhood of men is the crowning masterpiece and struggle of the classes is the foundation of our work.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the socialistic movement is the brotherhood of man, as public ownership is its destination. That elegant, rich, old patriot, <pb facs="5423968_3_0419.jpg" n="2"/>Grover Cleveland, could preach the philosophy of brotherhood while he was sending federal troops to Chicago for the purpose of defeating the striking workingmen in Pullman.</p>
   <p>Full of talk about morality, Theodore Roosevelt could speak about brotherhood, while at the same time he branded some of the best people of this country with the name of undesirable citizens. Finally, that "high style" Christian gentleman, a man who can love his country well because it actually belongs to him, Mr. John D. Rockefeller, who mentions the love of God in almost every word and who proves by every action that he loves money, could just as well only declare that he dedicated himself to the cause of the brotherhood of men. But his efforts in realizing the ideal of the brotherhood of men depends on this: all possession of this world should belong to him and to him only; the existence of other brothers will depend on Mr. Rockefeller, whether he will allow to let them exist on earth or not.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
