<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-19">May 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Unions and Strikes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-19">May 19, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">UNIONS AND STRIKES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the field of building in Chicago a misunderstanding has arisen between labor and the contractors. This has grown to such an extent that operations are practically at a standstill. This condition has stopped the building industry from making any profit and has halted employment for the workers. The contractors are protesting against the sympathetic strikes called by the central labor union board. The workers, however, dispute the claims of the contractors on the ground that they are trying to split the control of the unions, especially the carpenters, masons, roofers, and others of the building trade.</p>
   <p>Which side is right is not for us to say at present, for the courts are going to pass judgment. But we cannot help but say that sympathetic strikes should not be permissable. They interfere with the principles of justice and righteousness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0100.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When a contractor of carpentry takes over the work on a building and makes an agreement with the workers which coincides with the demands of the union, then, if he fulfills his promises to the workers, the carpenters' union has not the right to make trouble, or to call a strike just because another contractor, for example a sheet metal contractor, is at odds with the sheet metal union.</p>
   <p>A contractor's agreement with his workers has the same value as any other agreement. No one will feel secure, after closing a bargain in business, if one party is going to have the privilege of breaking faith to the detriment of the other party.</p>
   <p>Let the masons strike whenever they wish. Let the plasterers take a holiday whenever they consider this necessary, because of the unjust behavior of the contractor. But no other contractor should suffer from sympathetic strikes if he has treated his workers according to agreement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0101.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The union leaders conduct themselves in these affairs with their first thoughts for their fellow union men. Although this is true, they forget that other conditions and obligations exist which should be considered, especially the feeling of duty and honor.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, however, one must consider it wrong on the part of the contractors when they attempt to block the efforts of the central union board which is striving to unite all labor unions of the building trades into a co-operative group. Such workers, whether they are tinsmiths, roofers, or masons, have a common interest.</p>
   <p>If the sympathetic strikes are called for no just reason they must be considered evil, but if it is a matter of life or death for the central union board then it is another matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
