<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-26">Mar. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">St. John Cantius Parish Endorses Adamkiewicz for Alderman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-26">Mar. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ST. JOHN CANTIUS PARISH ENDORSES ADAMKIEWICZ FOR ALDERMAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening a big rally to support the candidacy of Stanley Adamkiewicz for alderman of the Seventeenth Ward was held in the parish hall of St. John Cantius Parish. This district does not remember ever having such a big political rally. More than seven hundred people were present. Judge Joseph LaBuy was made chairman. He called upon Stanley Pitera to act as secretary. Speeches were made by Judge J. LaBuy, T. Weyna, Attorney John Jankowski, Attorney J. Young, Alderman Stanley Walkowiak, Joseph Ruszkiewicz (commissioner of the Seventeenth Ward), John Sobota, Mrs. Sophia Malkowski, Michael Kolassa, Michael Wojtecki, Stanley Kielczynski, and Attorney A. Bisek.</p>
   <p>The speakers explained to the audience that the Seventeenth Ward was a Polish ward and as such should have two Polish aldermen. Since Mr. S. Adamkiewicz has the best qualifications for this post, all the Poles should stand squarely behind him on April 3 and cast their votes for him. If Mr. S. Adamkiewicz should fail to get elected, it would prove that there are traitors in the <pb facs="5423968_3_1461.jpg" n="2"/>Seventeenth Ward, which is almost entirely Polish.</p>
   <p>The last speaker was candidate Adamkiewicz himself, who, in his sincere speech, promised the people that he would work earnestly for the good of the Seventeenth Ward, and that his doors would be open day and night to all citizens.</p>
   <p>Pretty moving pictures were shown between speeches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
