<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-16">Mar. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Political Mass Meeting Held in Bradley Street Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-16">Mar. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MASS MEETING HELD IN BRADLEY STREET HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Democratic mass meeting was held yesterday, Sunday, March 15, in the great St. Stanislaus Kostka Hall on Bradley Street.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Mr. Jacob Mucha, president of the Sixteenth Ward Polish-American Democratic Club. Mr. Mucha explained the purpose of the meeting, and called on Judge [M. A.] LaBuy to act as Chairman and the undersigned to act as secretary.</p>
   <p>Judge LaBuy told the audience that now is the time for action in the Sixteenth Ward, and for the Polish-Americans to remember how they have lost within one year all they had gained in the previous years of hard work, by foolishly supporting the Republicans.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Peter Kiolbassa, the candidate for alderman of the <pb facs="5423968_3_1228.jpg" n="2"/>Sixteenth Ward. He was greeted with thunderous applause. Briefly, but clearly, he explained that he had no intention of becoming a candidate for alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, until the citizens of the Ward, representing various nationalities, demanded that he become a candidate, and at a meeting, held for that purpose, had unanimously endorsed him. Mr. Kiolbassa explained that on seeing such unanimity, he decided to accede to their demands.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Stanley H. Kunz spoke. He said that some Poles claim that Mr. Kiolbassa should not accept the nomination for such a low office as that of alderman, but that those gentlemen are mistaken. He further stated that an alderman's duty is to protect the welfare of the citizens of the ward which he represents, and that a great deal is expected of him.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. August J. Kowalski spoke. He urged everyone to vote the Democratic ticket, and pointed out the queer actions of the Republicans controlling the civil service. A few Poles applied for city jobs to the authorities in charge, <pb facs="5423968_3_1229.jpg" n="3"/>and were told to fill out an application and answer a number of foolish questions, such as, for example: Where were you born? How old are you? Where did you attend school? What college did you attend, and if you completed the course where and at what college? How much do you weigh? But this was not all. After answering all the questions, the applicants were sent to a doctor who ordered them to strip naked. Here they were examined from all sides; they were ordered to bend, to straighten up, to walk, jump, and perform all kinds of twists. They were felt over, pinched and punched to the limit of their patience.</p>
   <p>After this strange and comic examination, these poor fellows were told that not one of them was able to handle a pick or a shovel, because they either did not walk straight enough, or were cross-eyed, or too fat or too skinny....They were forced to undergo many other such insults. And these are the tactics employed by the Republicans in their treatment of the poor workingmen, and these Republican politicians cannot, or do not want to improve themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1230.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This speech brought gales of laughter from the audience and was applauded vigorously.</p>
   <p>By a standing vote, Mr. Kiolbassa was then endorsed for alderman of the Sixteenth Ward. Everyone in the hall arose as one man.</p>
   <p>Mr. F. Bieszki made the final speech. He reminded all in the audience that they must not forget to register a week from Tuesday, and heartily supported the candidacy of Mr. Kiolbassa.</p>
   <p>The Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
