<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-04">Feb. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Our Local Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-02-04">Feb. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LOCAL POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>So far things look pretty well for us in this year's political campaign. We were afraid that we should encounter greater difficulties and meet with less success. Above all we were afraid that our two main groups of local Democratic politicians would begin to fight each other in their keen competition for jobs and public office, and then the whole political business, would result in a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> loss to us, just as surely as two and two are four ! And it already <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to look as if that was going to happen because of the intrigues of certain individuals known only too well by our past experience with them, but fortunately the majority of our clear-thinking and well-informed fellow countrymen exerted their best efforts to bring about an understanding and a compromise which immediately produced the favorable results desired.</p>
   <p>Whoever is familiar with our city politics knows only too well how the Irishmen, <pb facs="5423968_3_1435.jpg" n="2"/>The most <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> political <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the entire country <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the divergent <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> nationalities <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> anything because they do not constitute comes around, they either put up an Irish candidate, as long as the Poles could not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> on one of their own, or <pb facs="5423968_3_1436.jpg" n="3"/>they put up both these contending Poles on the ticket to split the Polish vote so that the third candidate, who is always an Irishman, a German, or a Jew, is elected.</p>
   <p>This is an old story and a familiar political trick. Had the Poles become aware in time of how this game is being played here, and had they not fallen for empty husks, had they understood that two candidates cannot be elected to the same office and having come to some agreement among themselve had supported one whom they had chosen as the better man of the two, we should hold today many of even the most important city and county offices. When our fellow countrymen, having so many votes behind them and working closely with the Democratic party, would have every chance to control Chicago politics.</p>
   <p>So far, unfortunately, it has not been thus, and for this reason aliens have been bossing us. Besides, some of the leaders whom we have had in our political life have been of the lowest and worst type: liars of all degrees, intriguers, and those called here "doublecrossers" [English word used]; they have always <pb facs="5423968_3_1437.jpg" n="4"/>followed and helped people of their nationalities, ready to betray their own people, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> their closest friends. Fortunately matter are improving, and an intelligent civic <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> among us. And that is exactly what we see this year.</p>
   <p>In this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the Poles have succeeded in large measure in achieving their aims, at least at this stage of the campaign. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> service has been rendered in this respect by the Polish leader of Chicago Democrats, Congress-man Stanley <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who, experiences in local politics as few other men are, submitted our just claims with such force and defended them so courageously that we received what we demanded. In large measure it now depends on us whether we win the final victory. For this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> work congressman Kunz deserves the most sincere appreciation, which we most willing accord to him. We are sure that the Polish community will remember <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> much we <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to him and will repay him when the opportunity offers.</p>
   <p>Above all we have <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> this, that we have a Pole at the head of the list</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1438.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1439.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1440.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>We repeat, therefore, that to a certain degree everything is coming along all right. Keep it up, Polish Democrats! Together in solidarity, in agreement, and understanding, without intrigues, without trying to harm one another, without sniping! Remain on active duty to the end of this campaign, and we shall succeed in putting our men into important county and city offices.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
