<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-06">Feb. 6, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">What the So-Called Polish Socialists Think of Polish Nationalism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-06">Feb. 6, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE SO-CALLED POLISH SOCIALISTS THINK OF POLISH NATIONALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish-American Socialists, of whom, unfortunately, there are quite a number, are resorting to extreme measures in order to bewilder our poor and uneducated people. They cheat and lie about everything. One of their most popular lies, which they use to blind the eyes of the masses, and which they invariably offer whenever there is any effort made to exclude them from the ranks of the Polish national organizations, is the following: the fact that we are Socialists does not mean that we are any the less Poles or Polish nationalists; we are always ready to work for the welfare of Poland.</p>
   <p>This argument finally persuaded the Polish National Alliance to accept them [into its ranks]. Our Socialists, making a great fuss about their nationalism, point to the fact that even in Europe there exists a Polska Partya Socyalistyczna, P. P. S. (Polish Socialist party), and therefore, it is very easy to <pb facs="5423968_3_0497.jpg" n="2"/>reconcile socialism with nationalism. These arguments have convinced a number of ignorant persons who are, to this day, being misled.</p>
   <p>We have always realized that this claim to Polish extraction of the Polish Socialists was merely a subterfuge, designed to attract simple-minded Poles into their net. We have spoken and written about this situation, and have been insulted for our pains.</p>
   <p>Now, fortunately, we are able to submit conclusive proof that their "Polish ardor" is only a sham, and that Socialists of Polish descent have as much in common with the ideal of Polish nationalism, as the Zulus or Hottentots of Africa. The proof is given in the official organ of the Polish Socialist party, called Przedswit (Before Dawn), which is published in London.</p>
   <p>The last issue of Przedswit fell into our hands accidentally. It contains a lively debate between two or three congenial souls on the theme: Can the Socialists of Polish descent and their party (P. P. S.) have anything in common with <pb facs="5423968_3_0498.jpg" n="3"/>Polish nationalists, and have they any interest in such national affairs as, for example, the Rappershwyl fund? In the final analysis, the answer is--no. The answer is given in an introductory article by the editors of the official organ of the Polish Socialist party.</p>
   <p>So that we may not be accused of exaggerating, we quote here a number of passages from the article in Przedswit. In the introductory editorial, we read first that "nationalism" could be, at best only an "introduction to socialism"; that it was very unimportant. Furthermore, P. P. S. has officially announced that it has no intention of dividing its strength to further some kind of nationalist activity. Finally we read the following paragraph: "....In all European countries, we see the phenomenon that with the growth of the Socialist party, all progressive, democratic, and radical tendencies weaken, lose ground and die out."</p>
   <p>That is clear. Nationalism is included among the tendencies that will die out. A few lines further on we read:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0499.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"....Every political action is an opportunity for us to unfurl our Socialist flag and to broaden our contact among the masses for the dissemination of Socialist thought; this is synonymous with weakening the nationalist party. We know that this will be a bitter pill for some to swallow, but the logic of history is often cruel."</p>
   <p>At last, P. P. S. has taken its stand. If this is not sufficient, we read further:</p>
   <p>"....Our attitude toward the nationalist party should, therefore, be one of indifference to its activity. We are Socialists; we believe only in socialism, and we refuse to support any other cause."</p>
   <p>So it is to be indifference"! But the P. P. S. goes even further. A few lines further on, Przedswit says:</p>
   <p>"....Although we would be glad to back a party opposed to Russian rule, nevertheless, <pb facs="5423968_3_0500.jpg" n="5"/>we cannot afford to dissipate our strength in order to support that party, even in the event that we did not foresee the trend of events. The policy of the Socialists and of the nationalists must necessarily conflict.....Such instances have occurred and will occur again; at that time, we will undoubtedly have to assume an inimical attitude in place of one of indifference.</p>
   <p>"....If, for example, the nationalists try to raise the declining, fortunately, influence of the Church, then it is our duty to attack such an action severely. Or if the nationalists try to transfer their activities to groups which may be more or less accessible to our influence, then we will have to declare, 'Hands off'."</p>
   <p>So that's how it is! "Hands off"--that is the advice of the Socialists to the Polish nationalists. This is surely clear and understandable! Their opinion of, and attitude toward the Rapperschwyl fund is even clearer. Przedswit <pb facs="5423968_3_0501.jpg" n="6"/>compares it with the Irish fund and with the work of Irish revolutionists, and says: "The unnerving, stifling atmosphere surrounding our fund, with Milkowski, Lewakowski, and all the other political hangers-on at its head, is a far cry from the Irish project. That is real revolutionary action directed against the enemies, while here we have a few political grandfathers, who, having laboriously collected a comparatively small sum [of money], now wish to sacrifice themselves in order to keep the fund intact for some future revolutionists. In the meantime, they dole out a little of it for some imaginary party."</p>
   <p>In another article, Przedswit writes of the Rapperschwyl fund as follows: "....This entire undertaking is highly characteristic; it is sufficient to prove that the party which [is supposed to have] started the fund, actually does not exist.</p>
   <p>In general, P. P. S. treats all nationalist activity with very little ceremony. Here is another quotation from Przedswit: "....Socialism alone can save Poland, <pb facs="5423968_3_0502.jpg" n="7"/>because nationalism is a corpse which no miracle can bring back to life. Therefore, anyone who wishes to see an independent Poland, must join us, but without any conditions, without any 'buts,' and he must agree to follow our entire program from A to Z."</p>
   <p>So "nationalism" is a "corpse". Judgment is rendered, signed, and sealed. And yet socialism is willing to take unfair advantage of this "corpse," if the opportunity should arise.</p>
   <p>"We have spoken only of the attitude to be taken toward nationalists today. Of course, in the event of a revolution, or during the period immediately preceding one, we would have to change our attitude completely. Then we will not forget that we are Socialists, that we must not hide our beliefs; however, we will think primarily of fighting the enemy, and we will gladly accept every person who is willing to become our ally. But because we know all about this potential ally, because we know that he cannot be as consistent in his radicalism as we are, because we know that he will at times falter, whereas we will go forward boldly, <pb facs="5423968_3_0503.jpg" n="8"/>it is therefore, natural that we watch him carefully because he will very likely, repay us in like manner."</p>
   <p>That is a peculiar attitude to adopt toward an ally--"to watch him carefully". The idea is indeed diabolic. These quotations should be sufficient. They should convince everyone that the Socialists who call themselves Poles, are the enemies of Polish ideals. In addition they are creatures who take advantage of the Polish people in a most contemptible manner. All that they have said in a moment of frankness, should eventually open the eyes of our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
