<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 69,
<date when="1908-03-21">March 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Constitution of the United States of America and the President</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 69,
<date when="1908-03-21">March 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND THE PRESIDENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Constitution of the United States has placed a great power in the hands of the President. He appoints the higher officials, such as cabinet members and judges of the Supreme Court. He conducts the foreign affairs, although it is not without the consent of the Senate. The President of the United States also has the power to use the U. S. Army for the purpose of repelling an enemy or suppressing insurrections.</p>
   <p>It can not be taken for granted that vesting such great powers in the President constitutes great merit; the character of allegedly the most democratic constitution in the world should be different. It is quite natural that the more power is placed in the hands of the President, the heavier burdens must be borne by the man who assumes such responsibility. It is not enough to have an unblemished character and possess great love for his country; it is necessary that his social and political convictions agree with the majority of society. Otherwise the President might do a great injustice to society.</p>
   <p>We could verify that the present republican President does not represent the majority of the American people. This majority is composed of the working class whose interests are entirely different, conflicting with those of the capitalists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Indeed, every working man understands very well that there can not be concord between the exploiters and the exploited; the same as fire and water. If a candidate for the presidency of the United States is not himself a working man, or a defender and representative of the working class interests, then how can a working-man vote for him without selling his own interests? A wolf will never be a brother to a sheep. How then can a capitalist or a political grafter be a brother and protector of a working-man?</p>
   <p>This matter seems so simple that we should not waste our breath on it; yet a majority of the American proletariat do not understand it and cast their votes for a career hunting servant and offspring of capital. This happens because very poorly enlightened working-men can not pick out the quintessence of the beautiful words which silver-tongued orators, like Mr. Bryan, who used to charm his audiences with his eloquent speeches. Can we believe anything that he says?</p>
   <p>The only difference between the two political parties fighting each other is this; one of them protects the interests of the big capitalists and the other one, the small ones. The first is devouring the second, accumulating colossal fortunes and combat is the result. But their enmity toward each other is nothing in comparison to the hatred that they feel toward the American proletariat. They know that either one of them lives by exploiting the working-man and it is <pb facs="5423968_3_0434.jpg" n="3"/>much easier to agree among themselves than with the working class, with which there will not be any agreement until they, the exploiters, cease to exist.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bryan feels this as well as Mr. Roosevelt or Taft; therefore, their programs are never clear; they use only beautiful phraseology or find a "convenient horse on which they ride".</p>
   <p>Mr. Bryan, called a democrat, refers continually to the will of the people, but he is silent about the fact that the American people have no will of their own; for the source of their will is hunger and misery which forces them to submit to the will of the capitalists. A man who has no assurance of tomorrow, has only the will of his so-called "work and life giver".</p>
   <p>Under the capitalistic system, the election of either republican Taft or democratic Bryan will never be the expression of the people's will, who are in capitalistic slavery. Let Mr. Bryan insure the working-man's due prosperity. Then if we elect him, he may boast that he became a president by the will of the people. In the meantime, let him not make fun of the working-man.</p>
   <p>Politics like any other kind of exploitation in America, became a business. Whole regiments and companies of politicians roam through the country, considering it their own. Those who will not surrender can not expect to hold any office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0435.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is the reason why we see only a few socialists holding office in the U. S., as they oppose all graft, oppression and injustice. They have very few followers in the world of free competition or free cheating.</p>
   <p>But the ranks of the socialists are growing very rapidly, which proves that the people are opening their eyes and are turning away from this disgusting life, where it is impossible to accomplish anything honestly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
