<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-06">Apr. 6, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Comments on Ninth Ward Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-06">Apr. 6, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">COMMENTS ON NINTH WARD POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Poles of the Northwest Side gained a little at the last election, proving that the Poles in that part of the city know how to work.</p>
   <p>If we Poles, citizens of the Ninth Ward, would take them as an example, we could in a short time raise ourselves to the level which belongs to us in proportion to the number of votes we command. But conditions [in the Ninth Ward] are just the opposite at the present time. As a political unit we are almost unrecognized, and the politicians remember us only before elections. At such times they become cosmopolites and promise to treat every nationality equally, but as soon as elections are over they act contrarily. A German politician fills vacant jobs, such as he has at his disposal, with Germans; the Irish fill them with the Irish; and it is something unusual for them to offer anything to a Pole.</p>
   <p>The Poles in the Ninth Ward have more than twelve hundred votes, and the Irish <pb facs="5423968_3_1587.jpg" n="2"/>have less than nine hundred, yet the Irish control eighty per cent of the jobs, while the Poles get only three per cent, which they get just before the election and lose immediately afterward.</p>
   <p>Why is it that we Poles, who represent one-fifth of the votes in the Ninth Ward, are almost ignored when the positions are given?</p>
   <p>A few Polish professional politicians are responsible for this. These gentlemen, not taking under consideration their own interests and the interests of Chicago Poles, simply sell their votes and the votes of other Poles who do not understand these matters to the one who pays them most. These gentlemen wear the cloak of this or that political party, use beautiful phraseology, and for a few dollars sell their honor and work to a German or an Irishman with a zeal worthy of a better cause.</p>
   <p>There are individuals who act secretly. These are perhaps the worst, for they declare openly that they work for a Pole and yet they instruct those Poles who <pb facs="5423968_3_1588.jpg" n="3"/>do not know how to vote in such a manner that their ballots are invalid or given to the opponent. A certain German politician told me once: "We can buy Polish votes; the Irish would rather vote for a German than for a Pole; and the Germans have enough common sense to vote for themselves."</p>
   <p>It would be hard to contradict this. At the last elections, the well-known Cullerton used all his influence and the Irish spent large sums of money in order to keep a Ninth Ward Pole out of the city hall. Seeing that they could not elect their man, they chose a Bohemian Jew for their candidate. If he were elected by their money, he would dance to the tune of their fiddle. They were paying for Polish votes, for they desired to show that the number of Polish votes in this ward is very small. This is a very important consideration. Only those votes will be counted as Polish which were cast for a Polish candidate when he was running. And now, instead of twelve hundred Polish votes, we have only three hundred. And the fewer votes the Poles have, the less right to city jobs and any kind of consideration in the ward they will possess.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1589.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the other hand, the German candidate also paid well for Polish votes and was not disappointed on account of their zeal, for we could hear how they praised him in Polish districts on election day. It is painful to write about this, but if we remain silent our professional politicians will always mislead our countrymen.</p>
   <p>And what happened? A Polish candidate who should have had 1,200 or more Polish votes, and had a splendid chance to be elected on account of the general splitting of the ballot, was defeated.</p>
   <p>Moreover, it was proven once more that the Poles amount to nothing in the ward. Not so with the Germans, for they voted for their candidate despite the fact that he was branded a boodler by the American newspapers. They preferred to vote for the worst kind of a German, regardless of political affiliations, than for the best kind of a Pole, and this is the secret of their success.</p>
   <p>However, credit should be given to a number of honest Poles who understood the <pb facs="5423968_3_1590.jpg" n="5"/>situation, and devoted their time and spent their money in order to uphold the honor of the Poles of the Ninth Ward, but their efforts were shattered by the money of our opponents and our lack of good judgment. The Bohemians made the following remarks about us: "How can we help the Poles when they vote for a German or a Jew?"</p>
   <p>The situation is rather bad in our ward, and the last election taught us a good lesson. Let us hope that it will be effective. Let us reform in the future. If American citizens of other nationalities spend hundreds and thousands of dollars to get our votes and are benefited by them--these votes are surely of great advantage to us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
