<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 5,
<date when="1903-01-07">Jan. 7, 1903</date><title level="a">Poles in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIV, No. 5,
<date when="1903-01-07">Jan. 7, 1903</date><title level="a">POLES IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Kurjer Polski states:</p>
   <p>"Some persons enjoy themselves joyfully in elaborate places, while others are dying on the streets from hunger and sufferings. This very incident occurred on one of our streets, here in the city. An unidentified Pole dying from hunger.</p>
   <p>"Who he was and where he comes from no on knows and naturally no one will find out. He was seen on the street shivering from the cold, also hungry but still no one cared or could imagine what he needed because this poor soul, not knowing how to speak English, could not explain to others that he was hungry.</p>
   <p>"He was met by policeman Stephenson. Pointing his finger toward his stomach said in a feeble voice, "I am hungry." The policeman not knowing what he was talking about went on his way. While he stood there, and when he started to walk on further his legs gave in, his eyes got misty, his head was in a whirl; hunger had gotten the best of him. A stranger passing by put the dying man's hands on his chest and placed him near the <pb facs="5423968_3_0220.jpg" n="2"/>street curb on Elm street. Policeman Stephenson with his associates thinking they had a drunken man to deal with took him into a pig-sty. As they held him in their arms he muttered feebly, "I am hungry," gasped deeply and died.</p>
   <p>So a Pole starved to death probably away from his family and friends who may live in Poland. Leaving his country, seeking wealth and happiness over here, and to his misfortune finding hunger and death."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
