<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-05">Apr. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Elections</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0997</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0997.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 4 (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-05">Apr. 5, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S ELECTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We foretold the election of Carter H. Harrison to the mayoralty of Chicago by a large majority, and with him the entire Democratic ticket. Even the "beloved" City Clerk, Van Cleave, who received many more votes than any other Republican candidate, was defeated.</p>
   <p>We hardly need mention that we are overjoyed at the results of the election. Since the Poles supported Harrison's candidacy with all their weight (which is not inconsiderable), they have reason to expect special consideration. The fact that Carter H. Harrison is a personal friend of Peter Kiolbassa and other important Polish-American politicians, assures us that the expected consideration will be forthcoming.</p>
   <p>We are pleased also that the results of yesterday's election will be a lesson <pb facs="5423968_3_0998.jpg" n="2"/>to the Germans, who have been much too insolent lately. Last autumn we helped to elect a German to the governorship of Illinois. We had not expected then that the Germans, victorious once, would attempt to force themselves into all high offices. We did not suppose that the Germans would be willing to sacrifice the interests of Chicago, of the Democratic party, and of labor solely to satisfy their own overbearing pride. They wanted to say: "We Germans rule the City of Chicago and the State of Illinois." What means did they not use! How they reviled everyone who dared disagree with them! How much money they spent in promoting a conspiracy with other Chicago papers against a candidate who dared to defeat their man for the nomination! They betrayed both democratic principles and the workers by supporting the Republican candidate. With all their strength they supported a man who is known to be incompetent, whom they themselves opposed not long ago as an enemy of labor. And all this because Harrison proved himself more popular than their candidate, Washington Hesing!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0999.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Germans have received their just deserts. Their influence in Chicago is broken for a long time to come; they cannot expect consideration from Harrison after their scurrilous attacks upon him. We the Poles have every reason to rejoice over this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
