<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-12">Feb. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Warning to the Poles</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. K.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-12">Feb. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">WARNING TO THE POLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. K.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Taking advantage of the poor economic conditions in the United States, the socialists have since recently been spreading their propaganda among the American Poles. This means that a few Polish apostles of socialism or anarchism have decided that right now the time is ripe for getting supporters. Fortunately, among the Poles there are very few supporters of socialism or anarchism.</p>
   <p>These leaders are trying to catch the less intelligent people with the bait of the "workingmen's cause". Our countrymen should be warned against such bait.</p>
   <p>I have no desire to impede the progress of the Polish people or to deprive <pb facs="5423968_3_0523.jpg" n="2"/>them of the right to organize for the purpose of bettering themselves. Indeed, I am very glad that the workingmen are organizing, and I believe that it is a good thing to keep up with the progress of other nationalities. We all have the right to live, and we should protect and defend this right. But we should defend this right by lawful means and common sense. We should not mix with socialists or anarchists; neither should we accept and follow their doctrines, which lead straight to doom. The object of these ignorant instigators who try to ensnare the Polish working people is not to improve their condition--for they are not interested in the welfare of the workingmen--but to mislead them, deprive them of their faith, supply them with bombs of dynamite and incendiary torches, and use them as tools of crime for overthrowing our social order.</p>
   <p>Poles should stay away from these leaders. In the first place, a person who accepts socialistic idealogy cannot be a Polish patriot. The principle of socialism is cosmopolitanism. A socialist does not work for the cause of <pb facs="5423968_3_0524.jpg" n="3"/>any nation; he works for the "international cause," or "for all," as they say. But these are only empty phrases. This can be proved by their attitude toward the oppression of the Poles. We had a good opportunity to prove this at their many conventions held in Europe in recent times. At these conventions the socialists refused to discuss the Polish question and shouted down those who spoke about Poland. Such is the socialists' general conception of justice.</p>
   <p>As to anarchism, we know its principles. Its aim is destruction of society through murder by bombing. Its basis is gross materialism and bestiality, which cannot see anything noble in life. To associate with something like this is surely a crime.</p>
   <p>From a practical point of view and for patriotic reasons, we American Poles have no right to join the ranks of socialists or anarchists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0525.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We know that no government protects these groups, especially when there are immigrants among them. This also applies to the United States. We have found hospitality here and we should not abuse it. If we desire the Americans to have a good opinion of us so that we may have a refuge here for our oppressed countrymen, we must stay away from socialistic and anarchistic gatherings. The speeches made by certain Poles at the lake front will not benefit us; on the contrary, these speeches will create a false opinion about us, for they will give the impression that we are disturbers of peace and overthrowers of principles. This false opinion causes us great harm, because it provides our oppressors with a basis upon which they may maintain that our charges of oppression against them are products of our imagination.</p>
   <p>Work for the motherland, for the liberation of Poland, should head the program of every Pole. After we are free politically, then we may think about improving our social conditions lawfully, if such improvement is possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
