<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-05-09">May 9, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Kiolbassa on Top the Corn Exchange Bank Withdraws from the Syndicate Contract with 3 Banks Kiolbassa's Security Is Good and Sufficient</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-05-09">May 9, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">KIOLBASSA ON TOP THE CORN EXCHANGE BANK WITHDRAWS FROM THE SYNDICATE CONTRACT WITH 3 BANKS KIOLBASSA'S SECURITY IS GOOD AND SUFFICIENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Treasurer Kiolbassa's actions arouse greater interest at present than those of any other official. Kiolbassa's fight with certain parties concerning the disputed question, who shall decide about the disposals of money," reached a new stage yesterday. With the aid of his lawyer, he succeeded in inflicting a serious blow to the Bank syndicate, composed of six member banks, by inducing the Corn Exchange Bank to withdraw. He made an independent contract with the Corn Exchange Bank, the Union National, and the American Trust and Savings Bank, wherein he agrees to deposit the City's funds with the above institutions, and to pay 2 1/2% for the loaned money, even more, during periods of a money stringency. The three Banks, which now function instead of the original six, selected by the City Council, have subscribed to, and provided 15 million Dollars security for Kiolbassa's bond.</p>
   <p>The treasurer reiterated that he will promptly pay all accruing interest, and at present his promise cannot be doubted. He, his lawyer and his bondsmen realized their wishes. They threw the Dixon ordinance over-board. According to Corporation counsel Miller, some of its stipulations were illegal anyway. He brought the facts to light yesterday, so they helped to dissolve the syndicate and upheld their right to select the Banking houses they desire.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Kiolbassa is master of the situation, his work is done, so he said. But his adversaries, more correctly speaking the aldermen who believe that the City council alone has the right to select the banks, still have some work to perform. They intend to try again, on Monday evening, to reawaken the controversy over the Dixon ordinance but they do not feel certain that they will succeed..... His security amounts to $15,405,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
