<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-16">Mar. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">City Politics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-16">Mar. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CITY POLITICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican Convention took place yesterday at Turner Hall, on the North Side. Probably never before has the weakness of the Republican party in the city of Chicago been more evident than now. They themselves feel incapable of doing anything. They have no one whom they can place at the head of their ticket with any hope of success. They cannot even formulate a platform with which they might impress the voters--even with phrases. They have shown themselves powerless and dependent. They have neither platform nor candidates of their own; the Republicans as a party have ceased to exist.</p>
   <p>The platform accepted by the convention was that of the so-called Citizens' party. The mayoral candidate of this party was also nominated to head the Republican ticket. The only candidate of their own is Van Cleave, for city clerk. For two other high offices, that of city treasurer and city attorney, <pb facs="5423968_3_1006.jpg" n="2"/>they have decided to accept some sort of Democrats and have delayed their nomination until today.</p>
   <p>The address in which S.W. Allerton, of the United Citizens' party, accepted the Republican nomination was as colorless as it was comically sensciess. It's chief virtue lay in the fact that it was short. Its whole import seemed to be that Mr. Allerton's wife desires very much that Mr. Allerton become mayor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
