<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 7, 
<date when="1908-01-09">Jan 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Bryan in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 7, 
<date when="1908-01-09">Jan 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">BRYAN IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twice defeated as a candidate for President of the United States, Democratic leader William Jennings Bryan, arrived here in Chicago, invited to a banquet at the Jefferson club.</p>
   <p>All contenders amongst themselves, the Democratic groups, were present at this banquet, their speakers expressing their views, their criticism of the present Republican administration.</p>
   <p>Senator Kern of Indiana attacked it in his speech about the Republican government building a fleet.</p>
   <p>The Democrats who gathered applauded the speakers' attacks upon the Republican government, which led us into the present panic. (Though it seems they forgot about their Democratic panic in the year of 1893).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0453.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Democrats tried to provide a modest appearance for their banquet. They know very well that while hundreds of thousands of unemployed citizens are hungry and cold on our city streets, they shouldn't have upon their tables champagne or wine and beer. However, modest appearances weren't present, because champagne stood before the wealth, and beer stood by those of lower financial standing. The supper alone cost $5 per plate, which was composed of fried fowl, imported cheese, etc.</p>
   <p>Ward politicians displayed lustrous diamonds in the shirts and upon their fingers.</p>
   <p>Turning our attention back to Bryan who lost twice in his campaigns for the presidency and now hasn't any intention whatsoever to try again, unless the Democratic party nominates him. He says at the present time that he isn't so anxious about the electoral results because he says he'd rather be defeated fighting for what's right than to be a victor on the wrong side.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0454.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He states further that the strength lies in the nation, the public is the ruler of our country, also in the majority of the Democratic party there also is "strength with which they may guide me."</p>
   <p>(We voice our opposition to this active deceiver, because "the growing of our entire nation is not due to the majority of the nation," but to the few possessors of trusts, who governed McKinley and who likewise rule with Roosevelt to their own satisfaction).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
