<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-05-12">May 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Married Women and Unemployment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-05-12">May 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">MARRIED WOMEN AND UNEMPLOYMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the present unemployment situation becoming worse, people are objecting to married women taking the place of men. It is not wrong, if she seeks employment because of dire necessity; when her husband is unemployed or unable to earn enough to support the family. When urgencies of this kind arise, there is no alternative but to leave her domestic duties and seek employment. These abnormal conditions, in many cases, are caused by the high cost of living. We should admire a wife who has the courage to work and carry the financial burden so that her family can exist.</p>
   <p>We are not, however, concerned with women who are forced to work but with the young spouses who feel lonesome at home when their husbands work, while they are unable to find diversion of a domestic nature. A young married woman scans the want-ad section of a newspaper and finds that help is wanted at her former trade. She applies and is hired. She is now, however, working just for extra money an not because the family is in need. Her husband earns a good salary, but he has many installments to pay on the mortgage, radio, furniture, car, and many other luxuries which are superfluous. Then again, many husbands only think of their own comfort.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are not concerned with the mate's happiness and contentment but think their partners must work to help pay unnecessary bills.</p>
   <p>There are, however, thousands of reasons for the ambitions of these women who, instead of working in stores, offices or factories, should remain in their proper place, and that is at home. They should consider the thousands who must shift for themselves, widows with children, young girls, and the many fathers, who are unable to provide for their families because of the unemployment situation.</p>
   <p>We cannot insist that married women renounce their jobs because their husbands are employed at fair wages. But this would solve the present unemployment problem, as vacancies are thereby produced for those who now are wondering if work may be found in the future, so that their beloved ones may not starve.</p>
   <p>When conditions improve, with enough positions for all, then married women can work. At present they should consider the existing situation and help their neighbors who are without means of a livelihood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
