<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-11">April 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Where Is the Wealth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-04-11">April 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE IS THE WEALTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press writes of present wealth in the United States, therefore, one cannot be other than surprised, when a reader of such articles, seeks employment and finds none, but sees before him a very hopeless future. His savings have been reduced to nothing, and he inquires, "Where is the wealth? Where is it concealed? How can it be identified?" Internal Revenue Agents however, have succeeded in locating the hiding place of the wealth and tore away its mask, leaving no doubt as to its existence and character.</p>
   <p>It is shown by the Treasury Department of United States that ninety-five per cent of the income tax was paid by twenty nine one-hundreths of one per cent of the total population of the United States. The remaining balance of five per cent of the income tax was paid by ninety-nine and seventy-one one-hundreths per cent. Other particulars mentioned are: 207 persons paid income tax on incomes of $1,000,000, or more, showing an increase in the millionaire group of 132 over that of the year 1924; seven persons paid an income tax on $5,000,000, or more; forty-eight and one-half per cent paid income tax on $100,000., or more; one person out of every 345 has no reason to complain, because he is in very good circumstances.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0204.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This small portion of the population truly wades in great wealth; but the fact is that some of this wealth has been accumulated by others, however, the truth remains, that the twenty-nine one-hundreths of one percent of the population in this country, has a monopoly on the wealth in their grasp. The United States census shows a population of 115 million people, of which, 333,400, are classified as wealthy.</p>
   <p>In 1926, the United States Steel Co,.showed a net profit of $134,837,957., which was $25,386,172., more than in 1925. Therefore, it is not surprising that, the president of this corporation, Mr. Gary, sees great prosperity in the future.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, there were 6,643 bankruptcies in the first quarter of 1925, or nine percent more than in 1926. The aforementioned facts prove who has control and benefits from this wealth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
