<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-27">Aug. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Political Front</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-27">Aug. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE POLITICAL FRONT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish candidate for Congress, Mr. Francis Koralewski, was born in New York City on January 7, 1874. His parents came from the Posen and Gniezno district of Poland. The late John Koralewski, father of Francis, was an active organizer of Polish societies in America. Through his efforts the Thaddeus Kosciusko Society was formed. The parents of the candidate moved to Chicago in 1876, where their son attended Holy Trinity parochial school. Completing his elementary course, he then attended the Northwestern High School. Thereafter he enrolled in Lake Forest University, in the legal department. He was admitted to the bar in 1895.</p>
   <p>From the beginning of his career Mr. Koralewski manifested a profound interest in public affairs. He took active part in the life of Polish societies. He belongs to the Lodge of the Polish November Uprising, which is Group 348 of the Polish National Alliance; to the Polish Alma Mater; to the Chopin Chorus; <pb facs="5423968_3_0661.jpg" n="2"/>and to many other Polish groups. In addition he is a member of the Chicago Bar Association, the Illinois Bar Association, the Chicago Press Club, and the Iroquois Club. In 1908 he was elected alderman of the Sixteenth Ward. The American newspapers have printed extensive articles on Mr. Koralewski's activities in tax matters. He introduced an ordinance [in the city council] to create an investigating commission for the purpose of achieving a more equable assessment of large corporations and wealthy families. It was because of this action that large corporations and wealthy families [now] render a more accurate report of their incomes. This naturally causes the assessments to be more equably proportioned, so lessening the burden laid on the poorer taxpayers.</p>
   <p>This prominent activity soon attracted the attention of his party, which placed him in the assessor's office, where he remained for a period of six years. In 1912 he was a member of the Electoral College, the only Pole to hold that distinction. He was instrumental in excluding provisions in a <pb facs="5423968_3_0662.jpg" n="3"/>city ordinance which would have given certain privileges to the electric railroad company operating between South Bend, Indiana, and Chicago and would have deprived the city of an income of approximately fifty thousand dollars. In short, he has given priceless and valuable service to the city and has brought honor to the Polish name.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koralewski has conducted numerous court actions for claims against large corporations and has gained many legal battles for his clients. He is well versed in political matters and is a practical Pole. He has given his children a thorough Polish education under the able tutelage of the Reverend Walter Zapala. He has represented the Polish Roman Catholic Union and the Polish National Alliance in many cases at law. After the conclusion of his work for the Polish Central National Committee, to which he had donated his services, only a short time remained for a Pole to file his petition as candidate for Congress. Prominent civic leaders of various circles requested that Mr. Koralewski file his petition. The petition was finally filed after <pb facs="5423968_3_0663.jpg" n="4"/>a general meeting [had been held] of Polish clergy, journalists, and other prominent persons. The meeting occurred in the office of the Reverend Frank Gordon.</p>
   <p>After a sincere exchange of opinions by those present at the meeting the Reverend Mr. Gordon himself came to the conclusion that Mr. Koralewski would be the candidate who would have the best chance of winning. A majority of those present decided to support him wholeheartedly.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koralewski as delegate to the National Democratic Convention touched upon a very important topic, namely, the question of the revision of the Congressional districts in the State of Illinois. Governor Lowden announced publicly some two or three weeks ago that the time is near for the State of Illinois to get busy if it wishes to have its Congressional districts revised.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0664.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If a Pole should fail to be elected to Congress at this time, then we may be certain that members of other races will attempt to have the boundaries so arranged with respect to the Polish district that it will be easy for the other nationalities to win at all times. The Eighth Congressional District is the district most densely populated by Polish-American citizens. It is the only District in the United States in which the Poles can elect a Pole if they are once united. Should it so happen that in the new revision the entire Eighteenth and Nineteenth Wards are annexed to the Eighth Congressional District, then the Poles would be in the minority. But if a Pole was elected from that District, he could see to it that to the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Wards the Polish sections of the Fifteenth and Twenty-eighth Wards should be added. This would assure our people of being perpetually represented in Congress. Politics plays a very important role not only in the small local spheres but also in Washington. Mr. Koralewski is well versed in politics and an authority in political matters. As an attorney he would be a very important factor because Congress is the law-making body of the <pb facs="5423968_3_0665.jpg" n="6"/>nation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Koralewski is now a delegate to the General Polish Convention being held at Detroit, Michigan. He represents the Central Polish Democratic Commission and has gone to the Convention to make certain that a Polish political group shall have its representative there, and that Polish political matters in America shall receive their full share of consideration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
