<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-10-30">Oct. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Vote for Your Own Fellow Countrymen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0783</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0783.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-10-30">Oct. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">VOTE FOR YOUR OWN FELLOW COUNTRYMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, as well as any other newspaper in this country, must take an active part in politics, which millions of our citizens are interested in, and upon which depends our welfare or our stagnation and suffering. Our press is in a fortunate position because it does not have to cater to any one political party, for no party has our press on its payrolls, but is absolutely non-partisan and wishes to serve a good cause.</p>
   <p>The Dziennik Zwiazkowy accepts paid advertisements just as the many other daily weekly or monthly newspapers do because on this revenue a newspaper subsists, but from the political standpoint it stands on neutral ground and recommends for political office only people whom this newspaper believes to be worthy and responsible, without regard for party affiliation, nationality, or creed, just as long as these persons are capable, honest, and respectable.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0784.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In politics Dziennik Zwiazkowy, from the time of its origin, has first of all served all Poles who have aspired for political office, not paying any attention to party connections. We are not concerned with their party connections or platforms, which in politics are all promises that are never fulfilled, but we take care of a person who deserves our support.</p>
   <p>We are very happy to recommend and support our Polish candidates who aspire for political office because the Poles are closest to our hearts, because they create better material for honest and responsible political positions, because we are concerned in elevating the Poles a step higher in society, and because in all government bureaus we should like to be able to find Polish people who knowing how to protect our interests and care enough about us to do so, Polish people who will help, not hinder, those of our nationality.</p>
   <p>Maybe one of our candidates is better or worse than any one else for a particular political office, but to our press he is always a better candidate than a person of another nationality. Other nationalities also send forth persons who <pb facs="5423968_3_0785.jpg" n="3"/>are not fitted for politics; then why should we Poles vote for such unfit candidates when we are able to put up our own Polish candidates for these offices, bettor fit and more responsible than these others?</p>
   <p>We do not as yet have Polish candidates for presidents, governors, and other big political offices; therefore our press finds it its duty to support candidates of other nationalities, but we do not give to any one candidate special support, and we oppose those who affront people of our nationality, especially the Polish immigrants.</p>
   <p>For any political advertisement, [however,] that any newspaper publishes neither the editor nor the publication is held responsible, since this is only a business matter, like a soap, liniment, or toothpaste advertisement. Journals are morally responsible only for what they write in their articles and their editorials, in which their tendencies and their aims are reflected.</p>
   <p>Therefore we can assert that the Dziennik Zwiazkowy has never stood for any <pb facs="5423968_3_0786.jpg" n="4"/>particular political party and never will, but will always serve the Polish candidates who are aspiring for political office with its influence and its reputation. That is why we pay no attention to paid political advertisements, but with all our hearts support our own Poles, wish them good luck, and ask our Polish citizens to cast their votes for them.</p>
   <p>In the present political campaign, many of our Polish people are aspiring for political offices in various cities and on all political party tickets; that is why we are asking our Polish voters to remember these Polish nominees, and not to miss any, just as the Irish, the Germans, the Swedes, the Jews, and others remember their own.</p>
   <p>Let party affiliations be put to one side, and let us merely concern ourselves with our Polish candidates. Vote for any one whom you choose to vote for in the case of offices to which no Polish candidate aspires, but if there is a Polish candidate, do not let your arm weaken! Vote for him regardless of whether the other man is better or worse than the Polish candidate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0787.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In Chicago this year we have a few Polish candidates seeking various political offices on three of the largest political party ballots; forget these parties and cast your vote for all these Poles.</p>
   <p>Election is just a few days away; therefore do all you Poles unite, and victory will be on our side. By electing our fellow countrymen you will make the others take notice of our strength and solidarity. This is necessary for the good of all us Poles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
