<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-16">July 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is to Blame?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-16">July 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS TO BLAME?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several days ago we raised the question why the Poles had been ignored in the recent appointments made by the Mayor despite the fact that they had supported him. We also indicated that the Mayor had not treated the Poles fair, since he made many promises and kept none.</p>
   <p>We also added that the entire blame was not the Mayor's, that part of it was ours, and that we would discuss the matter some other time.</p>
   <p>Our behavior in many respects was not befitting us and is still worse than it is supposed to be. We are going to say a few words in this connection, for this is very important, as it is high time that we change our attitude. It is only with a definite change for the better that conditions will change in our favor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1523.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today we will consider a few facts that are familiar to us. One of these is that not a single Pole has received a major appointment in the city administration.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly, the Mayor had a sincere desire to place a Pole in some important office and, besides, to appoint some of them to the Board of Education and the Public Library. The Mayor announced his intention and informed the Polish political leaders to present candidates for these offices.</p>
   <p>And what happened? There were not enough Polish candidates for the offices in question at the time. This alone made it look bad for the Poles. We have capable and responsible persons, but we seem not to agree as to which of us should be appointed.</p>
   <p>Finally, candidates were found and presented to the Mayor. And these candidates were without question capable and true Democrats.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1524.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Unfortunately, they had enemies. And what happened then? Why, we are ashamed to admit some of the details, for all kinds of intrigues developed not to permit this or that candidate get this or that office. All kinds of committees were formed and grievances were presented to the Mayor, each trying to convince him as to whom the appointments should really go. It is even a greater shame to admit that some committees resorted to lies in order that the proposed candidates lose out on their appointments.</p>
   <p>This is how the Poles behaved toward their fellow-men. So many candidates were presented that in the end not a single one of them received an appointment.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to claim that the Mayor acted justly. Having the recommendations of several persons who could be trusted, having easy access to places where he could find out whether the prospects were capable of handling their positions, the Mayor should not have succumbed to the <pb facs="5423968_3_1525.jpg" n="4"/>intrigues but gone on with his appointments. However, there is no doubt that our attitude discouraged all possible plans in behalf of the Poles on the part of the Mayor.</p>
   <p>The same thing happened day before yesterday when news was spread that Edmund Z. Brodowski had been appointed consul by the President. Several persons sent telegrams of protest to Washington in order to have the Senate oppose this appointment.</p>
   <p>A counter protest was telegraphed yesterday to the Senate, and it is anticipated that the latter will pass on the President's recommendation. But it remains to be said that there was enough evidence to indicate that a Pole was again opposing a Pole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
