<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-21">Oct. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Democrats of Chicago Hold Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-10-21">Oct. 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DEMOCRATS OF CHICAGO HOLD MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>W. Tomasik informs us that a meeting of Polish Democrats from all parts of Chicago was held at the Central Democratic Committee's headquarters, 137 Monroe Street, last Thursday [October 19] evening. The meeting was opened by Stanley Kunz, alderman of the Sixteenth Ward, who told the gathering that it was absolutely indispensable that the Poles of Chicago unite into one central Democratic organization. His proposal was accepted enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>S. F. A. Satalecki, of the Ninth Ward, was named chairman of the meeting, and W. Tomasik, of the Sixteenth Ward, secretary.</p>
   <p>Alderman Kunz also urged the Poles to register in the greatest possible numbers for the coming elections; he asked that in giving their place of birth, Poles stress the fact that they were born in Poland, not Prussia, Austria, or Russia, and that they protest if the judges do not record <pb facs="5423968_3_1276.jpg" n="2"/>their place of birth properly. He encouraged Poles to take out citizenship papers, which will be given free on Monday, October 23. Tuesday, October 24, is Registration Day.</p>
   <p>After Alderman Kunz had finished his address, it was decided that the next meeting of the Polish Central Democratic Organization would be held on October 22.</p>
   <p>At the same time, the following citizens were named to head the Organization in their respective wards: M. Wojtalewicz, Sixth Ward; W. Lewandowski, Seventh Ward; G. Kozlowski, Ninth Ward; J. Kozlowski, Tenth Ward; Park Commissioner E. Z. Brodowski and B. Rozanski, Fourteenth Ward; S. J. Fruzyna, Fifteenth Ward; A. W. Rudnicki, Sixteenth Ward; L. Kalisz, Seventeenth Ward; J. Balk, Twenty-sixth Ward; F. Malkowski, Twenty-eighth Ward; M. Gryszczynski, Twenty-ninth Ward; G. Lauferski, Twenty-seventh Ward; M. Wiora and J. Koziczynski, Thirty-third Ward; and J. Miller, Thirty-fourth Ward. The <pb facs="5423968_3_1277.jpg" n="3"/>meeting was adjourned after these appointments had been made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
