<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-23">Nov. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Thanksgiving Day - a Day of Twofold Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-23">Nov. 23, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THANKSGIVING DAY - A DAY OF TWOFOLD DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thanksgiving Day, which is being observed tomorrow is a splendid American traditional custom.</p>
   <p>The average American business man who is occupied with the problems and duties of trade and commerce, becomes truly idealistic on this holiday by observing and giving thanks to the Creator for the many gifts received throughout the year. The festivities in the American home are crowned with an excellent repast consisting usually of a turkey and all the trimmings, not simply to satisfy an appetite, but because it is the prevailing spirit of thankfulness to our Almighty God for all blessings bestowed upon us, and it also portrays the real meaning and importance of the day.</p>
   <p>This traditional meal, most unfortunately, will not be enjoyed by all, because there are hundreds of thousands who cannot have a turkey dinner; they are destitute and many not even have a piece of bread. It is the latter who will and should, on this day, pray to God that He remember them in the future by bestowing upon them a small portion of worldly gifts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0210.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hidden under a glittering shell of wealth, we have an abyss of misery, want and suffering among the great masses of the destitute who are affilicted with the scourge of disease, unemployment, strikes, and the battle with organized trusts who seek to deprive the majority of the very essentials of life. The charitable societies, while doing their best to alleviate human poverty, find themselves helpless before the dire needs of these surging masses.</p>
   <p>Investigators reveal several instances of these terrible conditions which are especially tragic in homes where disease and unemployment prevail. There we can see sick parents and under - nourished, barefoot children living in heatless, damp cellars or attics, surrounded by a few pieces of furniture which should be thrown away as scrap.</p>
   <p>In many instances these people die as paupers and of starvation rather, than ask alms. Tomorrow's joyful occasion has nothing to offer them and they will no doubt shed bitter tears of despair and suffer from the pangs of hunger, while those more blessed, who tomorrow will be filled with such joys as the day may provide, should not forget their less fortunate brothers who have nothing over which to rejoice; they should lend a helping hand not only on Thanksgiving Day but they should share their abundance throughout the year <pb facs="5423968_3_0211.jpg" n="3"/>by renouncing some of the surplus splendor and luxury and presenting it to the other side thereby eliminating famine and destitution in this world of plenty. Our twofold duty should therefore be an expression of thanksgiving towards the Creator and the spirit of good will towards our neighbor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
