<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-08">Oct. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">In the Vicious Circle</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-08">Oct. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE VICIOUS CIRCLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the question; "What is the foundation of the American juridical system?" The only correct answer, and a very short one, is: None whoever had an opportunity to get in touch with the courts, will agree that this answer is correct.</p>
   <p>The best illustration of this fact, that all our courts' procedure is hanging in the thin air and has no solid foundation of the statute, is the Thaw affair.</p>
   <p>The crime committed by Thaw is not interesting at all; it was just a common case of jealousy of male for a female, which was settled with the murder of Stanford White. Naturally the most guilty person in this crime was Mrs. Thaw, who by animal emotion of sex appeal, caused the fight between two males, rivals for the favor of a female, which was sanctioned by the law of nature. Such things are of common occurence, and in the majority of cases the female is guilty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0337.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In this particular case, not common people, but millionaires, were involved. We are sure that it would have been different, if Mrs. Evelyn Thaw would have cast her eyes on a chauffeur or on some other poor man. That happens often too, because in natural sex appeal, the social status of the subject is no barrier for a female. In that case the whole affair would have been suppressed.</p>
   <p>But both sides had a great deal of money; so a legion of lawyers, knowing all tricks and formulas, hard to understand - formulas called "the law" - did their tricks; the millionaire-murderer was sent to an insane asylum.</p>
   <p>Lawyers were victorious, and justice went to sleep; only the pocketbooks of both rivals suffered terribly. The case would have been forgotten, but Thaw still had a lot of money left; so in some mysterious way Thaw escaped from the institution. The poor wretch thought that he would catch a boat in Canada to Asia or Africa, but this plan was not in the interest of his legal guardians, and Thaw was forced to come back to the United States. The lawyers started another court procedure, only a more costly and more confusing one. Today, as this case stands, the most brilliant brain would have a hard job to untangle it. The final decision probably will be reached when <pb facs="5423968_3_0338.jpg" n="3"/>the whole Thaw's fortune will vanish and lawyers will have deserted him.</p>
   <p>This is the regular course of a court procedure when a defendant is a rich man and is an easy prey for unscrupulous lawyers. Not the law or court statute is the deciding factor in such cases, but money.</p>
   <p>The most interesting, part of it is that money can be used in two ways: for acquitting a guilty person, but also for condemning one that is innocent; that depends on the lawyer's opinion, because the defendant is entirely at the lawyer's mercy.</p>
   <p>Some of the more honest lawyers are fleecing their clients, but they give them an honest service; while others simply rob their clients of the last nickel, and in the end throw them on the court's mercy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
