<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-13">July 13, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is at Fault</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-13">July 13, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS AT FAULT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mayor Carter Harrison has completed giving appointments recently, of which he had many.</p>
   <p>From this large number did the Poles get any? How many did receive appointments?</p>
   <p>The Poles form one-tenth of the population of Chicago: one-tenth of city offices and other employment should go to them, especially when the party they supported is in office.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, we must admit that thus far not one important office was given to a Pole. The minor insignificant appointments are of no value. There is no complaint about this, but there is just cause to demand what is our <pb facs="5423968_3_1527.jpg" n="2"/>just due.</p>
   <p>Who is at fault?</p>
   <p>Without doubt the Mayor is responsible. He promised before he was elected to office and reaffirmed his promises when he took office. Only two months ago he publicly announced that he was going to appoint a Pole to head one of the important city departments and begged that candidates be presented to him. This was fulfilled immediately, and everyone was certain that the promise was going to be kept. But afterwards the Mayor denied what he had previously said. When candidates were presented to him he offered one an insignificant post that the applicant refused on the grounds that it was below his station.</p>
   <p>After protests were made, Mayor Harrison promised (countless such promises were made to various groups of Chicago) that he was going to appoint a Pole to the Board of Education and another to the Public Library. Again he <pb facs="5423968_3_1528.jpg" n="3"/>requested that candidates be presented to him.</p>
   <p>This again was done. These offices do not offer any salaries, but these positions are such as to enable their holders to get positions for others, and this would give a chance for other Poles to get minor offices and positions.</p>
   <p>Polish representatives were again presented to the Mayor, and all indications pointed to the fulfillment of his promises.</p>
   <p>But again they were broken--and yesterday he presented the names of appointees for the Board of Education and Public Library before the City Council. This list did not contain one Polish name.</p>
   <p>To the Poles at large who have supported the Mayor in force, this attitude is strange. After Mr. Harrison took office the Polish press spoke highly of him. It is apparent that all this praise must be taken back--for he who desires to rule justly cannot break any promises.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1529.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It was demanded of him that he revoke the order of the Chief of Police, who wronged one of our compatriots. This demand was immediately complied with, but a few days later the Chief ignored the Mayor's decision. The Poles remained silent because at the same time another received a promotion. But now we have all the reason in the world to complain, because the Mayor has completely ignored us.</p>
   <p>Despite the fact that the Mayor is at fault for not recognizing the Poles for city appointments, we are a little at fault too, and we should admit it if we want to have our conditions to change for the better.</p>
   <p>More of this later.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
