<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-06">June 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Present Unemployment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-06-06">June 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">PRESENT UNEMPLOYMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past several years we have been sympathizing with England, because of her unemployment situation, we discover however, in an address by the English Minister of Labor in the House of Commons, the claim that unemployment in England is not as great as that in United States. At present 78,000 who are unemployed, have registered in England; that is the smallest number since 1921. Thus, in answer to the question regarding the existing situation in the United States, the Minister of Labor replied, that these figures are not official and not the authentic statistics, however, individuals who are in a position to issue a correct and reliable statement, regarding the unemployment census, say that United States, at the date of this writing has 500,000 unemployed.</p>
   <p>Should the issue concerning these statistics be authentic, America is in a fairly good status. From time to time statistics are released in a publication issued by the Department of Labor in Washington. It is evident, that in the past, the people in general did not concern themselves with statistics of this nature. However, it is very probable, that the figure submitted by England is correct. According to an audit submitted by Mr. Hoover, secretary of commerce of the United States, the United States has at all times 1,000,000, persons who are unemployed; many of this group are classified as unemployed, and work only during a seasonal rush.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0202.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To this figure we must also add the miners, who are now striking, also those who were laid off, because of the slump in business and other reasons.</p>
   <p>The total number of unemployed is much greater than the figure submitted by the English Minister of Labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
