<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-12">Sept. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Aftermath of the Recent Primary Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0649</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0649.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV [Bohemian]</item>
     <item>IV [Jewish]</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-09-12">Sept. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AFTERMATH OF THE RECENT PRIMARY ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While the results of the primary election of September, 1918, are evidence of the sincere desire of the people to bring the World War to a victorious end, nevertheless they failed to fulfill the expectations of the Poles. Our people have failed to gain the very thing that they so earnestly desired. They did not gain what Polish honor required of them. Ambitions and petty local and personal differences disrupted our national unity. Our people have failed to achieve the necessary political solidarity, and in their blindness they have buried their chances for representation in Congress. The Polish element, embittered by such base conduct, will ultimately take energetic steps to expose the dissenters from Polish solidarity who abuse their authority. They will be deprived of their powers once their nefarious and underhand activities are brought before the bar of public opinion.</p>
   <p>Enough of this disgraceful abuse of our national honor! The betrayal of Mr. F. Koralewski as an individual would be insignificant were it not for the fact that his candidacy embodied the hopes of the Polish people to express <pb facs="5423968_3_0650.jpg" n="2"/>themselves in Congress through their own Representative. Let th<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>se gentlemen who are responsible for this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>etrayal ask their own consciences whether they still have the right to expect the confidence of Polish voters. They had better retire from public life lest the embittered Polish voters <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the political scene once and for all. Thanks to these gentlemen, the Polish voters of a purely Polish district are entirely <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> upon the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Mr. Thomas <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. He is unfamiliar with our interests <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in the least concerned with our Polish national cause.</p>
   <p>Just words of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are also due to Polish Republican voters. They allowed an almost certain nomination to be torn from their grasp. It was unpardenable carelessness. They might easily have foreseen that the intrigues in the Democratic camp, which for the last several years have acquired an almost chronic character, would make impossible the nomination of a Polish candidate. They had an extremely well-qualified candidate who enjoyed general respect, and whose name carries no little weight in authoritative circles. With Mr. <pb facs="5423968_3_0651.jpg" n="3"/><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the Poles could easily have won the nomination and have saved the Polish national cause. Unfortunately, the Republican leaders were entirely indifferent to this matter. Their indifference allowed the nomination of Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the disloyal Thompson faction, in a Polish Republican district. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Polish Republicans, this does not reflect great credit <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> you.</p>
   <p>The generally popular Republican candidate for clerk of the municipal court, Mr. John <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to gain the nomination despite the fact that his victory was said to be assured. It would have been better to boast less and to work more, and victory would not have been snatched from us. Luckily for us Mr. Frank <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> gained the Democratic nomination for this office and in that way maintains our prestige.</p>
   <p>Among Poles, besides Mr. Rydzewski, the following have their victory assured on the Democratic ticket: Messrs <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. Nowak and Thomas <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> candidates for country commissioner, Joseph La Buy and S. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> candidates for judge <pb facs="5423968_3_0652.jpg" n="4"/>of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Joseph Petlak, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> representative. Other results of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are as yet uncertain, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> is not complete. Mr. Albert <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> nomination for State senator from the twenty-seventh <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> district.</p>
   <p>Among our <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> more received by Thomas Scully for the county court bench <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Anthony <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for sheriff. Adolph Sabath [Jewish-<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> true <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the Poles, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the Democratic nomination for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to Congress from the Fifth District.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
