<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-07">Apr. 7, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Election Aftermath in the Sixteenth Ward</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-07">Apr. 7, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION AFTERMATH IN THE SIXTEENTH WARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The elections are over. We have good reason to be proud not only because Harrison was victorious as Democratic Candidate for the office of mayor but because all the candidates supported by the Dziennik Chicagoski were elected.</p>
   <p>We also have in mind the Sixteenth Ward, where the political ballyhoo practically nullified the voice of reason and prevented concentration.</p>
   <p>Our position was difficult in view of the two Polish candidates. The friends of one of them not only recruited followers at various meetings but interfered with regular Democratic Ward meetings and with the important speakers who were urging the people to vote straight Democratic.</p>
   <p>Where the voice of the political barkers did not reach, the soft voice of <pb facs="5423968_3_1532.jpg" n="2"/>the Dziennik Chicagoski found its way, and credit should be given to it by the reader.</p>
   <p>Our rejoicing is not prompted by the defeat of Alderman Stanley Kunz. On the contrary, we are sorry for him because he exposed himself unnecessarily, for he did not consider the influence of our newspaper.</p>
   <p>We are happy over the victory of Henry Ludolph because we have rescued the honor of the Poles in the Sixteenth Ward from the politicians of the city. By the victory of Kunz we should have gained nothing, whereas today we are receiving recognition as a nationality uniting solidly with others in case of need. Because of this solidarity our two aldermen are going to work hand in hand, assuring us recognition in politics and consideration for our claims which we have a perfect right to make and to expect [to find acknowledged].</p>
   <p>We also have other reasons to be proud of the citizens of the Sixteenth Ward. An anarchistic Jewish newspaper Kropiolo has arisen among us. The result of <pb facs="5423968_3_1533.jpg" n="3"/>the election definitely shows the kind of influence which this Jewish rag has on our people. None! We are certain that the two hundred votes received by the Hesing ticket were cast by sympathisers of the Germans. This enemy of the Poles and of Catholicism did not gain one vote from the Polish citizens of this ward.</p>
   <p>This gives us sufficient evidence that the Kropiolo [Sprinkler] or "Sabath Courier" is a meaningless rag as far as we are concerned. We shall continue to march forward for the people in religion as well as in politics: true people, pious people, and above all--Polish people.</p>
   <p>We do not expect any reward for this, since we are accomplishing only one of our duties and feel that we have the right to exclaim joyously:</p>
   <p>"Hail to the Polish citizens of the Sixteenth Ward! May the Poles in other wards follow their example!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
