<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 8,
<date when="1898-02-23">February 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Lattimer Murder Case</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 8,
<date when="1898-02-23">February 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">LATTIMER MURDER CASE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cold blooded murder of striking miners in Lattimer county, has caught the reading eye of all Polish American citizens in the United States.</p>
   <p>The eyes of America are focused on the outcome in this case. Most of the murdered miners were Polish.</p>
   <p>It is a written law that all people committing crimes such as in this case, regardless of their standing socially or politically, are to be tried in court for murder.</p>
   <p>We, the Polish American citizens should take it upon ourselves, to see that the blood of our comrades, who so gallantly gave their lives so that others may profit, will not be forgotten; their widows who are suffering and shedding tears, their children left fatherless to the mercy of the town and county, helpless, defenseless, what is to become of these poor people; will their pleas go unheard and unanswered?</p>
   <p>The Committee for prosecution, will seek to collect damages as well as seeing them prosecuted to the fullest extent of the law.</p>
   <p>The committee has the best lawyers obtainable to face the lawyers and the wealth of the coal company who are fighting to have the sheriff and his deputies freed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0085.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee has sent out letters to all Polish societies, churches, cooperative societies also to all Polish people living in the United States to send in donations to continue the case against this wealthy coal company. Any amount, regardless how large or small, will be accepted and we give our heartiest thanks for your kind contributions. Send all money to Mr. John Nemeth,</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Luz Co.,</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, Penn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
