<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-16">Nov. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1599</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1599.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-16">Nov. 16, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican mayor pro tem, Mr. Swift, has begun to rule with a vengeance, in spite of his promises that he would make no important changes and that he would probably leave everything as it is until the next mayoral elections.</p>
   <p>A number of building inspectors named by the Harrison administration fell victims to his political "broom" yesterday, and among them, naturally, two Poles. These were Julius Stasiewski and Jacob Fruzyna. When he received the order from Mayor Swift to discharge all building inspectors who had not taken examinations, Building Commissioner Toolen thought that he had misunderstood. Two conferences with the mayor were necessary before Toolen decided to take this summary action. But the order was definite; there was no appeal.</p>
   <p>Toolen plainly stated that he refused to accept responsibility for the action. Several weeks will elapse before new inspectors can be appointed and examined, and everyone who has had anything to do with politics knows how these examinations <pb facs="5423968_3_1600.jpg" n="2"/>will be conducted. A candidate will pass even if he can neither read nor write, provided he pleases his politician-examiners; if he does not, no matter how capable he may be, he will fail. Let this be a lesson to the Poles who deserted the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>It is only with the greatest difficulty that we can attain any sort of influence in politics; by helping a certain party to victory, we gain a few positions or offices. But if we allow ourselves to be misled by political trouble-makers, we immediately lose all that we have gained, and not only does the party to which we have passed fail to recognize us but it holds us in contempt.</p>
   <p>Indifference [to politics] also harms us. It is definitely harmful to our political status if we neglect our civic duty by failing to vote, or by failing to register in time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1601.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As yet it is not known whether or not another registration will be held before the mayoral election. If there is another registration day, however, let all those who have moved, or become citizens recently, or who failed to register the last time, attend to their duty. Let everyone of us register; those who believe they are now registered should verify their registration for themselves in order to be certain that their names are on the voters' lists. On election day, let us all, without exception, go to the polls and support the one party from which we can expect any benefits: the Democratic party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
