<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-31">Mar. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Voters, Attention!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-31">Mar. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH VOTERS, ATTENTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This coming Tuesday, April 3, elections for aldermen will be held in Chicago. Among the aldermanic candidates there are some Poles whom it is our duty to support with all our power for the simple reason that their election will be beneficial to us all.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy has never served any political party, but it has always supported all Polish candidates, regardless of their party affiliations.</p>
   <p>This newspaper accepts the political advertisements of all parties because this is business and every newspaper does it in order to keep on running. Therefore, the editorial staff is not responsible for statements made in advertisements. Our sympathies are with the Poles, and that is why we have always recommended and will continue to recommend our brothers for whatever offices they may seek, because by electing a Pole the city will gain an honest public servant and we <pb facs="5423968_3_1455.jpg" n="2"/>will gain honor and greater representation.</p>
   <p>The greater the number of Poles in high office, the more will people of other nationalities respect us and the more of our people there will be on the city's pay roll.</p>
   <p>The office of alderman in such a large city as Chicago is a very important and responsible post. Chicago's population is larger than that of some small countries in Europe, and its annual budget is larger than that of many countries in Europe, Asia, and Africa. There are about 400,000 Poles in Chicago, which, with the exception of Warsaw, is the city with the largest Polish population in the world.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we are entitled to hold all kinds of political offices here. To begin with, we should have an appropriate number of aldermen in the City Council, as there are in the city about 60,000 Polish male voters and several thousand women voters.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1456.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, it depends solely on us whether we have our own officers or whether men of other nationalities rule Polish wards.</p>
   <p>This coming Tuesday, April 3, is election day, and the names of three Polish candidates for aldermen appear on the ballots, namely:</p>
   <p>Stephen Thieda, Republican candidate, Twelfth Ward; Stanley Kunz, Democratic candidate, Sixteenth Ward; and Stanley Adamkiewicz, Democratic candidate, Seventeenth Ward.</p>
   <p>These men are well known and respected. They are all members of the Polish National Alliance and other Polish organizations. They are all capable, energetic, and honest, and therefore will represent us honorably in the City Council and will always defend our interests. Therefore, it is the duty of all citizens of Polish descent, both men and women, to vote for them because our collective needs demand this. Let all of us stand squarely behind our <pb facs="5423968_3_1457.jpg" n="4"/>candidate at the polls on Tuesday and cast our votes for Adamkiewics, Thieda, and Kunz!</p>
   <p>Besides these Polish candidates, there are men of other nationalities running for aldermen who are our friends and will work hand in hand with our aldermen when we elect them. They are Harry Listler, Republican candidate for alderman of the Twenty-eighth Ward, and Jan Hrubec, Democratic candidate for alderman of the Twenty-ninth Ward. Mr. Hrubec, a Czech, is a brother Slav worthy of our support.</p>
   <p>Another brother Slav worthy of our support is Joseph Simon, a Czech, a good friend of the Poles and a capable man, who is running for the office of city clerk.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
