<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-03">June 3, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Masonry and the Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-03">June 3, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">MASONRY AND THE CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a known fact that the French Parliament is antagonistic to Catholics. It purposely does not term this enmity as anti-ecclesiastical, but rather as anti-clerical. Whoever has had the opportunity of giving this matter more serious consideration will verify the fact that this hatred of the government circle of France toward religion has destroyed all the principles of justice and freedom.</p>
   <p>This unjust attitude has been passed on to the communal administrations, in accordance with a previously designed plan which originated with the members of the higher strata of society. The whole conservative press of every nation, including the moderate Republican-French press, lament this sad state of affairs that has brought only a twofold harm. In the first place, it incites the sincere elements within the nation to voice openly their complaints, and <pb facs="5423968_3_0560.jpg" n="2"/>secondly, it has thrown a burden upon the nation's shoulders by an increase of expenditure of some two hundred thousand francs. The French Masonic press emits a voice of triumph in support of this increase. This feeling of elation is also expressed in the newspapers of similar type in other countries. One of the Italian Masonic newspapers--and some of the Polish papers in America that echo this Italian newspaper--make a statement to the effect that people should cast off the yoke of the Church, blaming it for all the present social upheavals and the suppression of intellectual peace.</p>
   <p>The reason for these impertinent expressions of the Masons is easily seen. The influence of this group is so great that it has gained political control over a large part of Europe. It has therefore decided to advance its battle against the Church to a final point. This it hoped to accomplish by tearing out the Christian character from the world. Had it but the slightest iota of shame, it would admit that a destruction of the salutary influence of the Church would permanently hinder the introduction of social peace. It should admit sincerely that the hostile action taken by the Masons in France <pb facs="5423968_3_0561.jpg" n="3"/>and other nations aroused public opinion against them, and resulted in their own condemnation. Let them openly admit that their detrimental reign is endangered because the Church and the Catholics have been successful in repudiating numerous charges raised against them by the Masons. Let them also concede that the people have seen that the much desired social reform is impossible without the active participation of the Church. An admission such as this would at least vindicate actions. It should remain sane and should refrain from presenting its political and social plans or views because it sees that the people are becoming isolated from it.</p>
   <p>What influence has the Church had in the creation of the present international turmoil and in the diplomatic situation in Europe? Evidently none. Masonry has deprived her (the Church) of all influence in these matters. It is responsible for the Church's present state and for the insults she receives. The Triple Alliance was, for a long time, considered to be the best basis for European peace. The Church, however, saw that this foundation was weak. The international complications increased while the preparations for war were <pb facs="5423968_3_0562.jpg" n="4"/>acquiring greater proportions each day. At least an indirect provocation [for war] was given rise by this alliance which placed the whole world in a turmoil.</p>
   <p>It is not difficult to prove that any attempt to abuse the Church and any effort to harm it only resulted in a depression and a straining of natural laws. This conviction will rouse the Catholic conscience to an awakening to which no political force can remain opposed. This feeling has gradually grown in strength until an opportunity presented itself in the official statements of the parliamentary protests. Thus it was proven that it is impossible to have world peace without the aid of the Church, whose sons are found in all countries. It was shown that depriving the Church of freedom brings not peace but a constant state of turmoil, just as it is a state of war against the Holy See.</p>
   <p>No one would be so unreasonable as to blame the Church for the general dissatisfaction and for the unstable economic condition in Italy, in German <pb facs="5423968_3_0563.jpg" n="5"/>socialism, in Russian nihilism, in the bombing attempts in France. Nor could it justly be said that the Church caused an eastward movement in the Russian government. The difficulties between Russia and Austria as well as Germany, or the hostile attitude existing between France and Germany together with the other sources of conflict which destroy the bonds of European nations, cannot be blamed on the Church. All these misunderstandings and antagonistic attitudes were born with the masonic system or were increased through it. The Church, on the other hand, not only discouraged this but also endeavored to suppress every outburst of that nature. The fault does not lie in the Church because it was unsuccessful, but rather in the hatred which masonry bears toward it and which permeated the governing circles. It is useless to speak here of Socialism, which continues to acquire an uncontrollable form, awakening fear in all nations. Those who least acknowledge religious principles, even they are compelled to admit, in the face of the present situation, that without the aid of the Church, peace is impossible. It is an undeniable fact. It is equally true that an expansion of masonic influence over Europe will cause the downfall of the entire social structure. Civilization, as a whole, <pb facs="5423968_3_0564.jpg" n="6"/>can expect its salvation only through the Church and through the return to Christian principle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
