<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 213
<date when="1922-09-12">Sept. 12, 1922</date><title level="a">Mrs. Anna Nowak Selected for County Commissioner.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 213,<date when="1922-09-12">Sept. 12, 1922</date><title level="a">MRS. ANNA NOWAK SELECTED FOR COUNTY COMMISSIONER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time two political factions of the Democratic Party have been making endeavors to insure for their candidates the selection of a county commissioner to fill the vacancy of the late Albert Nowak, the Polish politicians and the assistant to the City's Treasurer, Clayton F. Smith, have been making efforts to give the vacancy of the late Mr. Nowak to his wife, which was promised by the administration committee of the Democratic Party. Meantime it happened otherwise. In the place of Albert Nowak there was nominated Mrs. E.W. Bemis, ignoring all the demands of the Poles. Generally it was thought that the matter was buried and Mrs. Anna Nowak will not have a chance to obtain the office of County Commissioner.</p>
   <p>This matter was taken up at the convention of the Polish Fellowship at St. Stanislaus Parish Hall last Sunday. It had been even forcibly mentioned in an adapted resolution, and the result was spontaneous. The politicians from the Irish camp became convinced that we already have organized ourselves, and that at present we cannot be trifled with. Mrs E.W. Bemis resigned yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1430.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Evidently they need Polish votes and are beginning to submit to us. Mrs. E. W. Bemis is likewise a smart politician. She came to understand that it would be better to step aside and make place for Mrs. Nowak, and gain for herself a good name among the Poles, so as to receive their votes in the fall election. Therefore, she stepped side and will be a candidate for that office in the Falls.</p>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
