<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">Mar. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Zbigniew Brodowski Appointed Park Commissioner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">Mar. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ZBIGNIEW BRODOWSKI APPOINTED PARK COMMISSIONER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few weeks ago, we intimated that the newly elected governor of Illinois, Mr. Altgeld, would probably name a Pole to the office of Commissioner on the West Park Board. We said that this Pole would probably be Mr. Zbigniew Brodowski, former editor of Zgoda, a partner of Mr. Peter Kiolbassa and a highly respected Polish businessman. A telegram from Springfield brought the news yesterday that Mr. Brodowski has been formally appointed to the West Park Board. This is very heartening news to the Poles in Chicago, for a park commissioner is one of the important officials in the State's administration. This position is ordinarily sought by men of high standing, and in truth the competition at this time was unusually keen. The Bohemians did what they could to gain the appointment for one of their own countrymen; there had been three Bohemian candidates for the office.</p>
   <p>In appointing a Pole, Governor Altgeld proved that he is guided by a sense of right and justice and that he recognizes the value of Polish service in <pb facs="5423968_3_1730.jpg" n="2"/>the Democratic Party. Finally, Governor Altgeld's appointment is entirely proper. Mr. Brodowski is well known as an intelligent, capable, and honest Pole. His willingness to lend assistance, as well as his kindness, has won him a large circle of friends and well-wishers. Undoubtedly, his new office will place him in a position to render important services to his countrymen. Since the parks employ a great number of people, and since the Board takes charge of employment, we know that Mr. Brodowski will see to the employment of as many Poles as possible. At any rate, the appointment of Mr. Brodowski to so important a position is as much an honor to the Poles in Chicago as it is to himself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
