<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-02-28">Feb. 28, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Our Neighboring Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-02-28">Feb. 28, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">OUR NEIGHBORING COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>North of us lies a vast expanse of land belonging to England, called the Dominion of Canada. It is quite natural for the United States to have acquired a taste for this piece of land, and there is hope that in time the Canadian party which favors a union with the United States, will become strong enough to win. Then, in a short time, the United States would occupy the entire North American continent, with the exception of Mexico, and would undoubtedly become the greatest power on the face of the earth.</p>
   <p>With almost every year, the possibility of forming such a union is greater, and especially today, the prognosis in this respect is very favorable. It is true that this union is not as near as some enthusiastic optimists expect; yet, it cannot be denied that the possibility for its realization is greater now that it was, for instance, a year ago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1405.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For this good outlook, we are indebted to Mr. Blaine, the Secretary of State, who endeavored to establish a pact of trade reciprocity between the United States and Canada, which would do away with high tariffs. Such agreements are authorized by McKinley's Bill, and Mr. Blaine has already taken advantage of the provision of the bill to make a reciprocal trade agreement with Brazil. However, his attempt to make a similar agreement with Canada was unsuccessful.</p>
   <p>There are two parties in Canada, a pro-government, or Tory party, which is against such agreement, and a Liberal Party, which favors it because its adherents are of the opinion that such agreement helps develop Canadian commerce.</p>
   <p>The Canadian Prime Minister, Sir John MacDonald, leader of the conservatives, opposes this proposed agreement impetuously. The combat between the two parties is very stubborn, and as it usually happens in such factional fights, both parties are throwing calumnies at each other. In order to deliver a decisive blow to the Liberal Party, Sir John MacDonald broadcast that if the entire Liberal Party favors a union with the United States, it is equivalent to treason, and he called every one who favors this trade reciprocity agreement a traitor to the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1406.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This aggravated many liberals, who are faithful to their government, and also opened the eyes of those who never thought of that "treason," with the result that many of them became supporters of the plan.</p>
   <p>In this manner, Sir John MacDonald, instead of delivering a staggering blow to the Liberal Party, strengthened it and in reality augmented the "treason", of which he accused the party.</p>
   <p>Recently, primary elections for nomination of government officials were held in Canada, and they showed a great gain by the Liberal Party.</p>
   <p>In the near future, we will know the results of this crisis and these struggles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
