<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-03">Apr. 3, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Whom Should We Vote For?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-04-03">Apr. 3, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">WHOM SHOULD WE VOTE FOR?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election will take place in a few days. In publishing today's paper we are publishing one of our last issues before the election.</p>
   <p>It is time, therefore, to discuss with our readers what candidates we should vote for. However, in our opinion, there is only one course open for the Poles; they should vote for the Democratic candidates.</p>
   <p>This course is demanded of us not only as good sense, but for practical and selfish reasons also.</p>
   <p>The Democratic party, the true people's party, the party with a high regard for religion, ought to be our party. There is no room for us in the Republican party, for its irreligious tendencies threaten everybody professing the Catholic <pb facs="5423968_3_0925.jpg" n="2"/>religion, and it also belittles all foreign-born citizens who, as we did, have settled here from Europe. It was from the mouths of Republicans that scurrilous remarks about the Poles issued.</p>
   <p>Should we, then, support such Republicans? It would be absolutely contrary to our own interests.</p>
   <p>So, to every person suggesting that we go along with the Republicans, we say publicly, "They are ordering us to braid a whip with which to beat our own backs!"</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the Republican ranks consist practically entirely of rich monopolists, who are robbing the poor people. Shall we then, plain workingmen, entrust offices to them and in this manner help them to continue to oppress us? We feel that we should do just the opposite. All practical arguments favor our supporting the Democrats.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0926.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Here in Chicago we have paid dearly for turning over a part of the Polish votes to the Republicans. This has been going on for two years. At one time, thanks to the Democrats, we were respected. We had influence, high offices, work, and were looked up to by the politicians. Today all of this is practically destroyed. The Democrats, convinced that we are not supporting them wholeheartedly, are turning away from us. The Republicans treat us always as voters who can be herded like cattle, one way or the other.</p>
   <p>The "gratitude" shown by Swift and his comrades for the Polish Republican votes is well known.</p>
   <p>Turn away from the Republicans once and for all, and go hand in hand with our old friends, the Democrats; that is our only salvation. Our own interests demand that we do this.</p>
   <p>Barely one year of Republican government in Chicago and West Town gave us--what?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_0927.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It gave us filthy streets, losses in business, prodigality in expending public money, a raise in taxes on an average of thirty per cent, etc.</p>
   <p>That is the result of voting for the Republicans. It is surely sufficient. The party, which, aside from many other inconsequential acts, has plunged its hands so deeply into the pockets of our citizens, is either not fit to govern, or it does so dishonestly.</p>
   <p>In view of this state of affairs, it is impossible that we should support the Republican party. There is only one thing left for us to do: Vote for the Democratic candidates!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
