<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-14">May 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Republican Delegation's Audience with Mayor Swift</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contribution)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_3_1558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-14">May 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH REPUBLICAN DELEGATION'S AUDIENCE WITH MAYOR SWIFT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contribution)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican promises prior to the election have come to naught, for, with the exception of J. Dahlman, no one has received an appointment.</p>
   <p>All the positions that were occupied by Polish Democrats have been filled by Jews, Bohemians, Italians, Scandinavians, and people of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Although it is true that two Poles received appointments from J. M. Horn, assessor of West Town, the positions are only temporary--for only two weeks.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday, May 11, a delegation made up of Polish Republicans, representing all the wards populated by the Poles, called upon Mayor Swift to find out why Polish Republicans were overlooked during the distribution of city positions controlled by the Mayor (it must be added that these approximate 15,000).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1559.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mayor Swift received the delegation not only coolly, but rudely, and loosed an abusive stream of words. According to past and present custom, the Mayor receives all delegations behind closed doors. When the Polish delegation approached his office, Mayor Swift purposely, for the humiliation of this group before a crowd of politicians, representing a variety of nationalities, which was found in his chambers, permitted it to enter. This body numbered about seventy persons, including several women who are active in Republican political affairs.</p>
   <p>As soon as some of the Polish delegates began to speak, the Mayor quickly broke in and said: "It is not true; I know better."</p>
   <p>One of the delegates said that he represented the Republican club. Mayor Swift replied to this: "You represent nobody; you are nothing."</p>
   <p>The Polish Republican delegate replied thus to the Mayor, "For the past eighteen years I have been a staunch Republican, but from today on I am a Democrat."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_3_1560.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To this the Mayor replied, "I don't care for you Polacks, I can get along well without you."</p>
   <p>In conclusion Mayor George B. Swift told the delegates that city positions are for Americans; that the Poles are fit only for the shovel and pick.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lorimer, an outstanding Republican political leader, who was present and heard everything, laughed heartily at all this, and pointed a finger at the crowd, saying, "Look at the Polacks, they want city offices." Then the entire Republican clique that was present burst into laughter that could be heard on La Salle Street; meantime they repeated loudly: "See the Polacks!"</p>
   <p>Mayor G. B. Swift, feeling content with his present victory, bade the delegation farewell with a triumphant voice and yelled: "Get out of here you Polacks!"</p>
   <p>All of this is written as it occurred, without any further comments; let everyone judge for himself and reach his own conclusions.</p>
   <p>R. I., Republican</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
