<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1919-03-08">Mar. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Dovre Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1919-03-08">Mar. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE DOVRE CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a former issue of Scandia "O. C. P." unjustly attacked certain members of the Dovre Club and in the same breath applied abuse to certain persons outside the Club.</p>
   <p>The Dovre Club always did and does now consist of the highest type of citizen. The fact that its program and its activities do not conform to the notions and the ideas of O. C. P. in no way alters its complexion. Are we not pledged to the American form of government, election by ballot, the sovereign prerogative of every person entitled to vote? And besides this are we not, according to American law, obliged to abide by the will of the majority?</p>
   <p>The entire membership had notice of the call and the purpose of the general meeting. Its proceedings were usual and regular, with much discussion and oratory. We proceeded to the balloting, and the result [was the will of] <pb facs="5423969_1_0988.jpg" n="2"/>the majority. I know of nothing tricky or shady about it; and the fact that we have since had the city-wide primary election, in which the Dovre Club's endorsement was ratified, Mayor Thompson receiving nearly 25,000 more votes than Olson and Merriam combined, quite satisfies the average unbiased, fair-minded citizen that the wisdom of the members of the Dovre Club, like good whiskey, improves with age.</p>
   <p>Mayor Thompson confines his campaign speeches to the masterful achievements of his administration. Great deeds are imperishable; they need no explanation. The Mayor made 196 speeches; the common unbiased people well understood him, and they have answered.</p>
   <p>It is the hurt bird that flutters. It is in very poor taste for O. C. P. to cast aspersions on Mayor Thompson and the Dovre Club member who happens to occupy a position in the city Law Department under the Thompson administration; and for O. C. P. to insinuate that because of his holding such a position the said member has become the controlling factor in the Dovre <pb facs="5423969_1_0989.jpg" n="3"/>Club's affairs is, in our opinion, to insult the intelligence of all the members not in accord with the critic's way of thinking.</p>
   <p>I should welcome the presence of O. C. P. at the deliberations of the Dovre Club so that we might take his measure in ready repartee and retort. I think that it would inspire him with keener spiritual vision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
