<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-04">Dec. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Reunion of Temperance Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-04">Dec. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">REUNION OF TEMPERANCE WORKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday was perhaps the day of the most brilliant event in the history of the Scandinavian temperance movement in Chicago. On that day occurred an impressive reunion of old veterans, men who were in the thick of the fight; who shouldered the heavy load and helped to overcome prejudices and prepare the minds of the people. It was a reunion of men to whom it is due that the Chicago Scandinavians may today review with pride a period of achievement, a propaganda for "the great reform" of today, in which we have much reason to rejoice--a propaganda which promises great results in the future.</p>
   <p>They met, these valiant fighters of the past and the present, many of them for the first time in years, for the purpose of honoring the man who has stood for years as a leader in the fight, in fair weather and foul, early and late, on Sundays and weekdays, without rest; ever in arms, the giant, topping them all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0304.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only were the old men in the fight present, but regiment upon regiment of the young, the recruits came marching up to pay their respect and give their thanks for a struggle extending over a quarter of a century, for sacrifices, for a good example set.</p>
   <p>The occasion was the twenty-fifth anniversary of Mr. Hans Larsen as total abstainer from intoxicants. Some of his abstainer friends had, on the occasion, arranged for a surprise for Mr. Larsen, and a surprise it did become, not only for Mr. Larsen but for the committee on arrangements; friends came in multitudes from near and far--many more than the committee had expected.</p>
   <p>The place designated for the gathering was Bowes Hall, corner of Erie and Noble Streets, and here at 8:30 P.M. between two and three hundred people gathered. The committee went to Mr. Larsen's home....to bring him to the place of the meeting, and...after a while Mr. Larsen appeared with the members of the committee. Under great enthusiasm he was introduced by Mr. Harveland. In a few fiery words Mr. Larsen expressed his thanks for the <pb facs="5423969_1_0305.jpg" n="3"/>ovation. He emphasized the difference, in his own mental and physical condition, between the present time and twenty-five years ago. He had come to the conclusion, he said, that it pays to "go crazy" as people said of him when first he became an abstainer.</p>
   <p>Afterward the aged Mr. Tollak Ellingson from Arkansas was introduced. Mr. Ellingson became a total abstainer in 1860; he signed as an abstainer in the first total abstinence society in Norway, Stavanger Abstinence Society for Young People, organized by the father of the temperance movement in Norway, Asbjorn Kloster....In 1873 Mr. Ellingson came to Chicago where he organized the first Norwegian temperance society. In 1875 he prevailed upon Mr. Hans Larsen to sign the pledge....so that the evening's celebration actually was the indirect fruit of his endeavor of many years ago....</p>
   <p>An oration was given by Mr. Odelins, after which the assembly....marched to Harmony Hall where the tables had been loaded with good things to eat. During the banquet the orchestra played Norwegian numbers, and a state of great <pb facs="5423969_1_0306.jpg" n="4"/>enthusiasm prevailed.</p>
   <p>At twelve o'clock, midnight, Mr. Ole Johnson gave a speech in honor of the guest of honor. He surveyed the history of Mr. Larsen during the past twenty-five years, which in effect is the history of the Norwegian temperance movement in Chicago during the same period.....Mr. Larsen, during the period mentioned, has been connected, more or less, with practically all the Scandinavian temperance organizations in the city. He concluded by presenting Mr. Larsen with a medal of gold, made from a drawing by Mr. Ben Blessum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
