<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-06-30">June 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Prohibition Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-06-30">June 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROHIBITION CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The national platform of the Prohibition party, presented in outline elsewhere in the paper, is a "narrow-gauge" platform in the basic sense of that term. The platform is quite lengthy, having a number of subsections, but it has only one plank, the liquor question. Everything else is disregarded.</p>
   <p>There are two tendencies within the Prohibition party, the "broad-gauge" tendency and the "narrow-gauge" tendency. According to the former, the party ought to step forth with a complete program, i. e., a program to include all the political issues of the day. According to the latter, the party platform is to be limited to the one issue which for all Prohibitionists is the main issue.</p>
   <p>In the past the "broad-gauge" group constituted the majority, and the <pb facs="5423969_1_0359.jpg" n="2"/>program of the party was then as broad as was the political field of the country. In those days the platform of the party demanded, for example, votes for women, postal savings banks, public ownership of railroads and telegraph systems, etc. The party, however, did not make much progress, and many sought the cause of this in the radical platform. So the issues of votes for women and all the other "reforms" were eliminated from the platform, the only issue remaining being that of prohibition of intoxicating liquors.</p>
   <p>The platform adopted by the convention in Chicago this year is of this "narrow-gauge" type. It considers only the question of drinking. The presentation of the party's attitude on this point is clear and to the point. But it is being spoiled through a reckless and nasty attack against the government and President McKinley personally.</p>
   <p>The question of the Army Canteen, especially, added fuel to the flame of fanaticism. Reports and statements from officers who know army life agree <pb facs="5423969_1_0360.jpg" n="3"/>that the Army Canteen has been of benefit to the soldiers because it has eliminated the private liquor dispenser with the connected evils, which otherwise surround the army camps. The declaration is unanimous that the discipline in the army and the morals of the soldiers have been improved since the institution of the Army Canteen, and that its discontinuation would lead to increased drinking and immorality on the part of the soldiers, and to a slackening of discipline in the army.</p>
   <p>The convention, however, did not take these facts into account. Of course it was objectionable in the eyes of the Prohibitionists that the President referred to the statement of the Attorney General concerning the law on the Army Canteen. To be sure, the Attorney General is the legal advisor of the President in just such questions as the one at issue, and the presupposition is that the President is to follow his advice.....But the Constitution and constitutional practice do not carry weight against the cry of fanaticism. To the fanatic, the methods of constitutional government are immaterial, if <pb facs="5423969_1_0361.jpg" n="4"/>indeed they are known by him.</p>
   <p>In the Navy conditions are different. There the Canteen would be a temptation to the men, without protecting them against worse temptations. President McKinley, therefore, ordered Secretary of War Long to prohibit the sale of intoxicating liquors on board the ships. Thus he has removed the sale of intoxicants among our warriors where such is possible. One could not, of course, expect the convention to acknowledge this. The blindness of fanaticism is proverbial.</p>
   <p>The personal attack upon the President of our country, however, exceeds altogether the limits of the proper. There is no man in the country whose life is purer than that of President McKinley. He himself is a total abstainer; his life has ever been exemplary, and he always did enjoy the undivided respect of those who knew him. To have the private life of this man attacked by a group of fanatics, several of whom are former drunkards, is disgraceful and will be judged according to its merit by every unbiased man or woman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0362.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Through this attack on the President, the Prohibitionists' convention has invited a comparison between President McKinley and the candidate for President of the Prohibition party. Skandinaven, however, does not approve of the Prohibitionists' method of compaigning, and for that reason will not take up the matter of comparison between the two. The delegates to the convention were highly enthusiastic at their selection of a standard bearer and acclaimed him in the following inspired verse which they gleefully shouted:</p>
   <p>"Have you seen our nominee?</p>
   <p>He's the man they call John G.</p>
   <p>President Woolley! Woolley!</p>
   <p>Who is he?</p>
   <p>He's the man they call John G.</p>
   <p>He's to be our nominee.</p>
   <p>We'll elect him, don't you see?</p>
   <p>Whoopee!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
