<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-14">Aug. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Politics in the Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Olaf E. Ray</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-08-14">Aug. 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS IN THE SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Olaf E. Ray</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The intention in my former article on the present topic was to be of advantage to Dr. Doe as well as others who, in my opinion are wasting the years of their youth and their abilities without any practical thought for the possible attainments by themselves or by our nationality as a whole of preferments in our political life. Even if one considers all our political societies in the aggregate one finds that their political weight is exceedingly slight. Mr. L. E. Olsen of the Leif Ericson Lodge holds an insignificant political post, gained, probably, on account of his activity as a member of the Lodge. Our turners and singers, on the other hand, are, as far as I know, not represented <pb facs="5423969_1_1157.jpg" n="2"/>in any political position important or unimportant, thus complying with the rules laid down by Dr. Doe.</p>
   <p>The other day our Governor appointed Mr. Gustaf Lundquist, president of the Swedish Glee Club, to be a member of the Lincoln Park Board, and practically all the Swedes who now are holding high public positions are prominent members of some Swedish society or other not connected with the churches. Why are not Norwegians such as Messrs. Olaf F. Severson, Sivert T. Gunderson, Lauritz Thoen, Harry Anderson, C. A. Clemetsen, Edward Willman, Edward Williams, Alderman Johnson, John Olson, and many others of political inclinations members of our Norwegian societies? Is it not because the societies, as such, are lacking in political significance? Have we not carried on our work of banning politics from our societies to such extent that the membership lists of these societies now include practically only such organizations as will remain lifelong newcomers in the field of politics, in accord with the example given by Dr. Doe?</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1158.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fact is that now, a Norwegian with political ambitions and qualifications is compelled to seek connections outside of his national group if he is to be considered, and the candidate has no time to lose in anything as fruitless as to join our secular organizations. These various societies have pulled many a vigorous youth away from our church organizations and to such extent impoverished our Norwegian church so that it is no more a political factor to be counted with. Our young people must return to their church connections so that we may be able to gain political influence in that manner, or the secular societies must undertake the political obligations which must rest upon the leaders of the nation. I am ashamed of our weakness in organization... We must gather together the forces now scattered about.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
