<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-25">March 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-25">March 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4..............The Norwegian National League recently decided to accept the invitation of the Union League Club to take part in a series of meetings and lectures whose aim is to instruct "new comers" (immigrants) as to the duties and privileges of American citizens.</p>
   <p>This sounds like a brilliant idea and only one of the National League's delegates had the courage to voice his skepticism regarding the practicality of the idea.</p>
   <p>Let us look more closely into the matter. What is the Union League; who and what are its members? The league is a social and political organization whose members are drawn from the city's wholesalers, merchants and manufacturers, all prominent in capitalistic circles, all (but a vanishing minority of Democrats) are Republicans. We can not condemn these men on the grounds of wealth, but when this same capitalistic club machinery is put into motion to inculcate the ideals of capitalism and machine politics into the minds of Norwegians and other so-called foreigners, it is high time to register a strong protest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0584.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Norwegian National League is far more capable of instructing our new arrivals in Americanism than the Union League and when meetings and lectures are deemed advisable and practical we will readily find, among our own people, far better and conscientiously clean instructors than any of the Union League's capitalistic demagogues. As far as high ideals of citizenship are concerned these self styled teachers have much to learn from our Norwegian immigrants and we, who already are citizens, should wake up and protect our fellow countrymen from the rotten intrigue of the money hungry teachers and parasites of the capitalistic system.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
