<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-29">June 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Hiding Like a Thief</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-29">June 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">HIDING LIKE A THIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John D. Rockefeller and others of the leading men of the Standard Oil Company have been summoned by Judge Landis to make explanations in the Federal Court in Chicago. As the readers know, a case against Standard Oil Company of Indiana has been under consideration in Judge Landis' Court resulting in judgement against the company. It has been claimed, however, that the Indiana Company is merely a branch of the great trust, Standard Oil of New Jersey, and before Judge Landis determines the amount of the fine, he wishes to be informed on this point. Nobody can give better information here than the leading men in the New Jersey Company, and Judge Landis had them summoned to testify in the case.</p>
   <p>What, now does John D. Rockefeller do, this good man who preaches about the sinfulness <pb facs="5423969_1_0626.jpg" n="2"/>of the world, and who gives much money to churches and schools? Does he take the first train to Chicago to save the court the trouble of summoning him? As a law-obedient citizen, will he do his best to get the needed information before the court? Not at all! John D. Rockefeller, the richest man in the world sneaks away so that the sheriff and his men shall not be able to find him.</p>
   <p>When a law criminal has broken a law he will usually try to escape the consequences of his act by running into hiding. The servants of law hunt him and he flees from place to place like a hunted beast, seeking refuge in any place seeming to give promise.</p>
   <p>John D. Rockefeller and many of the rich men of this country class themselves among the lowest of criminals in this respect. Claiming that they are running their business for the good of the people they insist, when some law interferes with their activity, that the law is unconstitutional or anyway so foolish that it cannot be <pb facs="5423969_1_0627.jpg" n="3"/>executed without doing enormous damage. It might be imagined that they would gladly appear, then in the courts in order to prove that they are right. Instead, they flee as common criminals, and if caught they seek refuge in every possible subterfuge in the witness chair.</p>
   <p>Our greatest money lords are playing a miserable role in these matters. Their infractions of law may call forth a kind of admiration on account of the magnitude of the actions involved. But when the rich law-defjers slink from place to place like common thieves, in order to escape from the process server, then they cannot escape the general contempt of the people. As President Roosevelt said, "they are undesirable citizens."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
