<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-30">Mar. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Arbitration in the Coal Industry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-30">Mar. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ARBITRATION IN THE COAL INDUSTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The commission appointed by President Roosevelt to arbitrate the great coal strike recommended, among other things, that a permanent board of arbitration be established to settle the differences which might arise between the mine operators and their employees. This board, known as the Anthracite Conciliation Board, consists of three representatives for the miners and three for the operators.</p>
   <p>Before this Board, any miner or operator may bring in his complaint, if any. The Board listens to both parties in the dispute, and in many cases it has succeeded in settling the dispute without further difficulties. If necessary, however, the Board takes further steps; testimony is heard and each side in the case presents full particulars as to the cause of the conflict. Then the Board gives its decision. If no agreement can be reached--if the division in the Board is three against three--an arbitrator is selected by the judge of the Third Federal District Court, and the decision of the arbitrator is binding.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0807.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the first three years of the Board's activity it dealt with one hundred and fifty cases; in this three-year period the number of complaints was only twenty-two. This shows how much has been done to improve conditions between the mine operators and their workers.</p>
   <p>Curiously enough, the workers demanded the abolition of the Board at the and of the first three-year period. They wanted three arbitration boards to replace the original board--one for each of the three federal districts. They had to drop the demand, however, and the arrangement, including the arbitration board, was renewed for three years. The new three-year period expires on April 1 of this year.</p>
   <p>As previously mentioned, the workers have presented a number of demands as conditions for continuing to work, and among these demands is the abolition of the arbitration board.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0808.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The attitude of the workers on this point is inexplicable, unless one presupposes that they are being ruled by a handful of leaders who want to have the Board abolished because the latter has proved that the highly paid leaders constitute an unnecessary expense for the workers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
