<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-12-31">Dec. 31, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[An Enormous Gift]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-12-31">Dec. 31, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[AN ENORMOUS GIFT]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.col.1....John D. Rockefeller has made the University of Chicago a Christmas present of ten million dollars. Accompanying the gift was the statement that this would be his final donation to increase the capital of the university and that he was withdrawing his representatives from the Board of Trustees. The university is to be taken over by the City of Chicago on condition that the sum of $34,426,049 be contributed for its continuance.</p>
   <p>What a vast donation from one man! Many are of the impression that there would not have been a U. of C. were it not for John D. Rockefeller. But the fact is that this school was founded at the time of Lincoln and Douglas long before the reign of John D., and before he had bought or speculated with his first oil well.</p>
   <p>It was only with his advancing years that Rockefeller, after piling up his <pb facs="5423969_1_0174.jpg" n="2"/>vast fortune by the process of throttling all competition, began considering the question of what to do with all his ill-gotten millions. In view of the methods used in gaining this vast amount of money the idea of becoming a philanthropist was the natural way out; a good deed to counteract the evil. So much for the method and countermethod of John D. Rockefeller. He was a true product of the existing economic system that even now is developing into its own Frankenstein. One fact holds good - that while the system that produced John D. Rockefeller continues, the majority of Chicago's youth will be deprived of an opportunity to obtain the higher education that a university offers and will be doomed to slavery in the struggle to build up colossal fortunes for the coming generations of John D's and others like him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
