<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-06-29">June 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[They Are All Alike]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-06-29">June 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[THEY ARE ALL ALIKE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new era in American politics is at our door. The conservative Old Guard, consisting of Wall Street vampires, trusts, and other leeches, is dominating the old parties more and more, while Roosevelt, Bryan, and other so-called progressives are howling to high Heaven to get the idea across that nothing can be accomplished for the common welfare by continuing the old trust-saturated political setup.</p>
   <p>The eyes of our citizens have at last been opened. They now readily see that both the Republican and the Democratic parties are owned (hide, hoofs, and horns) by Wall Street and the trusts. The Republican convention was concrete evidence that "the people," in particular the working class, can expect exactly nothing from that party. The election of Root as chairman of the convention was <pb facs="5423969_1_0578.jpg" n="2"/>equivalent to raising the black flag of piracy over the meeting, since Senator Root is the attorney for the Wall Street vampires. President Taft was renominated, and there cannot be the slightest question, in any intelligent mind, as to who owns Taft.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt, contrary to tradition, wants a third term, and is starting his third party of which he will be the head and the tail (and all in between), so that he can play his self-created role as the Bismarck of the United States.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt's cry of "wolf, wolf!" means in effect, "those who oppose me and--socialism". In spite of Roosevelt's so-called radical humbug, we can see in the background Wall Street, the trusts, big business, and other parasites, with their hands deep in their pockets ready to supply the "pork" wherever and whenever Roosevelt needs the votes. The only difference between Taft and Roosevelt is in plain avoirdupois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
