<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-11-14">Nov. 14, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Learn English</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-11-14">Nov. 14, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">LEARN ENGLISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>Knowledge of the English language, it seems to me, is a prerequisite for true loyalty and patriotism. A person cannot rightly be expected to take an interest in the affairs of a country whose language he does not master. Some may say: Cannot a person imbibe that spirit through any other language just as well? To some extent, but not so well. Where in any language will you find examples of Webster, Adams, Clay, Everett, Henry, and many others? You may take their speeches and translate them, but in that act their true mission has lost its power, strength, and beauty. What other language abounds as plentifully in gems of thought as that of the English. Take the words of Shakespeare, Milton, Gray, Longfellow, Bryant, <pb facs="5423969_1_0166.jpg" n="2"/>and Whittier, and compare them with others in their respective fields of labor.</p>
   <p>Many young men have I seen who are unable to read the English language intelligently and fluently, and these have been born and reared amidst the free institutions of our land. Now, these will become leaders some years hence. They will be the principal actors in life's drama in years to come. They will be the heads of the families of our land. The offices of the township, county, and state must be filled by some of them. The laws, forms of government, and social questions will be presented to them. Will these men fill their places of trust and honor and distinction without knowing English?</p>
   <p>Some maintain that we should not neglect our mother tongue, but use it as much as we can. To do that we must educate the children in our own language, which is foreign. We must make them familiar with our habits and customs, which are alien to our country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0167.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us have English pure and simple. We cannot so easily get both, and get them well. Let us have the essential one, and have it well. I look forward to the day when thought, feelings, and nationality shall be unified, and a language spoken which shall be understood by all.</p>
   <p>Forget your national background, become Americans, become good citizens, in thought and action. This is your country, treat it as such.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
