<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[The Trend Toward Democracy]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-11-04">Nov. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[THE TREND TOWARD DEMOCRACY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The trend and development of the times are noticeably alike all over the world; in fact the whole world seems to be enveloped in a haze of radicalism and liberalism. Greater personal liberty and more democratic forms of government are demanded in America, Europe, and Asia alike.</p>
   <p>Turning our thoughts to China, where the sons of Heaven have grown under the yoke of oppression placed upon them by a corrupt alien power for the last four hundred years, we find people in the throes of revolution, striving to overthrow the oppressor, to regain personal liberty, and to establish a constitutional form of government patterned after the ideals and informed with the spirit of western governments. The spirit of the Occident has penetrated deeply into the Orient, and China, long a closed book of oriental <pb facs="5423969_1_0890.jpg" n="2"/>mystery, is gradually being opened to modern people whose ideas are the subject of intense study among the great thinkers of China.</p>
   <p>We have not been able to work up any degree of enthusiasm for the cause of missionaries to China and their Christian (?) teachings, but if their presence in China has in any way stimulated the awakening which brought on the political upheaval, we are strongly in favor of them. The Manchu dynasty seems to be on the verge of extinction.</p>
   <p>Persia also is having its radical upheaval, and a parliamentary form of government is being demanded. Turkey, in a bloody revolution, has been taken over by the Young Turks, who have banished the old reactionary Sultan, with eleven of his wives, to a place of safe-keeping and have established a government along more modern lines.</p>
   <p>Throughout Europe, the radical element is gaining in power. King Manuel of <pb facs="5423969_1_0891.jpg" n="3"/>Portugal has fled to London, and his former kingdom is now a thriving little republic. Spain is a seething volcano ready to erupt any minute.</p>
   <p>In France, radicalism has turned its guns on Catholicism and has made education a public responsibility instead of a Catholic institution. Radicals have won important victories in recent elections in England, Sweden, and Switzerland. Because of hard times in Germany, the Socialists will double their strength at the next election and increase their representation in the governmental body. Ireland is still fighting to get home rule, such as Canada and other British colonies enjoy. In the United States, we also note the spread of radicalism. In the Republican party, the insurgents are fighting for a change that will bring about greater personal liberty, limit the powers of capital and the trusts, and annihilate the supporters of these things, i.e., the "standpatters". On the other hand, Democratic forces are active. Democratic victories all along the line, in city, county, and state elections, indicate the possibility of a Democratic national victory in 1912.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0892.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Greater personal liberty, more economic freedom and justice, more systematic and intelligent direction in government, a higher standard of living and better working conditions for the working class, woman suffrage, and job security, are demanded by our American radicals, if these demands can properly be called radical. In our humble opinion the word rational would be more truly descriptive of them; they are demands which are just and humanitarian in every way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
