<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-25">Sept. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Manly Speech</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0675</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0675.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-25">Sept. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MANLY SPEECH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Theodore Roosevelt spoke on September 24 to a large audience at Rawlins, Utah. Among other things he said:</p>
   <p>"Without a doubt there are evils in our mighty, intricate, and wonderful industrial system. The large fortunes which have been accumulated by individuals and by corporations have no doubt, frequently been gained through tactics that were not altogether proper. There is every reason why we ought to strive fearlessly and intelligently to abolish such evils; but there is also every reason to go at this work carefully, so that we may not kill the patient while trying to cure the evil.</p>
   <p>"Let us approach the work with courage! Never shall I advise timid action.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0676.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But let us give this question careful consideration. And remember: what men in public position are saying must be weighed on the scale of their actions. A pledge made to the people ought to be just as sacred as a pledge made to an individual, and ought to be kept just as faithfully.</p>
   <p>"On the other hand,the people ought to demand no more in the way of a promise which cannot be kept from a man in public life, than they would demand from a man in private life. When the people demand pledges or promises of a public man, then they ought to demand that the man in public life explain in what way he will keep those pledges or promises. The people should never demand of their public servants any more than they know those servants can do." These are manly words and sound political morals. There is no attempt to flatter the people in this speech.</p>
   <p>Let the reader compare the statements by Roosevelt with the resounding phrases <pb facs="5423969_1_0677.jpg" n="3"/>of Colonel Bryan, with his eternal acrobatics, and his promises of everything between earth and sky; and he will at once realize the basic difference between these two men. Roosevelt does not flatter; he uses the whip, and right-fully so. He tells the people that they are demanding promises of their public men which cannot be fulfilled. This is true. In doing so the people are tempting weak men to take a false stand. Lies may flatter, and the people try to imagine that they believe the lie, and they reward the eloquent liar with votes and applause. This may continue so long that the people may forget they are dealing with humbug of the most dangerous type.</p>
   <p>The cure advocated by Roosevelt is simple: never demand any more in the way of promises of men in public life than you know they are able to keep. Then you may and must demand that they fulfill their promises.</p>
   <p>Here is a reform which is much needed, and for which all of us should work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0678.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is the paramount issue in this and every other election, and will be until humbug is weeded out by its roots.</p>
   <p>A hurrah for Theodore Roosevelt; the man without guile or humbug! He is a man the nation cannot afford to push aside or to lose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
