<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-10-10">Oct. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Middle Class</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-10">Oct. 10, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE MIDDLE CLASS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For more than a third of a century the world has been waiting to see some definite indication of the fulfillment of the prophecy by Karl Marx that the middle class would disappear. On the basis of facts now in evidence it seems that the fulfillment of the prophecy must be postponed indefinitely.</p>
   <p>By the "middle class," Marx means the independent minor producers, and also the small dealers who are distributors on a small scale of the produced goods.</p>
   <p>It is true that many of these have, during the past few years, been driven out of business by the large industrial combinations, yet one has to admit that the class maintains its position remarkably well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0735.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as agriculture is concerned, we find a decided tendency toward the small farms,and this tendency is being felt by the Bonanza farms of the west, and in time they will have to give in.</p>
   <p>In the sphere of industry, as professor Ely has shown us, the small manufacturer is multiplying, and it is also a fact that the number of small retail dealers is not increasing.</p>
   <p>The definition of the term, "middle class" implied in the above discussion is not sufficient, however; the people referred to comprise only a part of the middle class. The changes in production method which have made innumerable small dealers and manufacturers competitors of large corporations have not changed the economic position of the class. The members of the class are still only producers and distributors within the limits of the capital they have invested; they are still members of the middle class, a term which also ought to include all the public office holders whose salaries runs from $1,500. to $8,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0736.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no more striking proof of the increase in the middle class than the increase in the number of middle-class homes in all our cities. While these homes are generally erected and owned by big companies, the undisputable fact is that an increasing number of families are able to pay a rent of from $300 to $2,000 per year for their living accommodations.</p>
   <p>If the middle class is about to disappear, the rich people must be getting richer in proportion to the total increase in property, but it will be difficult to prove that such has been the case.</p>
   <p>Cases indicating an opposite tendency may be found.</p>
   <p>In 1821 the fifty-six richest men in Boston possessed 19.90 per cent of the total capital in the city, while in 1888 a similar number merely possessed 10.08 per cent of the total capital then in the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0737.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the city of New York....in 1840 there were, according to Freeman O. Willey's statistical information, twenty-five persons who together possessed 18 per cent of the total property in the city. In 1894 it required one hundred eighty-three of the largest private fortunes to cover 18 per cent of the total property then in the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
