<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-01-21">Jan. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Call Off Garment Strike]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0786</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0786.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-01-21">Jan. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[CALL OFF GARMENT STRIKE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.5.........The 10,000 striking Garment workers and Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx have called off hostilities. An agreement has been reached whereby all strikers are to be re-employed, with no discrimination and their demands regarding closed shop, pay rates and hours are to be settled by arbitration.</p>
   <p>There are still 18,000 garment workers out on strike at other plants (those forming the trust) and these strikers have declared a boycott against their former employers and are doing all in their power to turn all business to the Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx Co. plant, this now being known as the "plant friendly to the union." The arbitration committee in the Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marx agreement consists of one representative of the firm and one from the union, the third to be selected by these two. Clarence Darrow, (radical philosopher, author) defender of Haywood was chosen by the strikers though the employers have not announced their appointee. The points are to be arbitrated are - 30% increase in rates, shorter hours and the elimination of the so-called finalties or so-called prison regulations.</p>
   <p>The strike was called in September 1910, and was the worst labor conflict in the history of Chicago. It was a bitterly fought battle on both sides; five were killed <pb facs="5423969_1_0787.jpg" n="2"/>in street riots and hundreds were injured. More than five-hundred strikers had been arrested, disorderly conduct being the charge in most cases, though they were discharged immediately when brought into court. John F. Sonsteby (Norwegian) was a busy man during the strike. Being the attorney for the Garment workers union, it was Mr. Sonsteby's lot to defend those arrested.</p>
   <p>Another Norwegian who had quite a lot to do with the arrested strikers was Judge Torrison, whose method of handling such cases is to be commended. Other judges could well profit by following the example set by Judge Torrison during these hectic months.</p>
   <p>We cite one instance: - twenty-four strikers were arrested when they started a demonstration in front of one of the plants where the strike was in sesssion, and they were charged with disorderly conduct though little or no evidence was submitted in proof. Judge Torrison, instead of fining the hungry men, they requested and were given their promises to go to their homes and refrain from further demonstration and to report to him in thirty days with evidence of faithful compliance. The promise was unanimous and when the thiry-days were up they appeared, to a man, before <pb facs="5423969_1_0788.jpg" n="3"/>Judge Torrison and on the strength of having kept faith with the court, all charges dismissed and they were allowed to go their way. Needles to say, Judge Torrison has won a host of friends both in the union and outside.</p>
   <p>Credit must be given Hart, Schaffner and Marx for their attitude in the conflict. This concern has at all times stood ready and willing to arbitrate with their employees in contrast to the attitude of the "trust" plants whose motto has been (and is)"We have nothing to arbitrate. "</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
