<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This country of ours is a Republic. The majority rules. Officers elected by the people manage the Government. It is therefore one of the most important duties of the citizens to vote. Under the laws of Illinois the citizens not only vote on election day to elect their officers, but on primary day they vote for their choice of party candidates.</p>
   <p>This spring Chicago has a very important election for mayor and other city officials; both women and men have the right to cast their ballots.</p>
   <p>The selection of candidates will take place on Tuesday, February 25. But under the law, to be able to vote in the selection of party candidates on February 25, it is absolutely necessary to be registered. If you are not registered now, you must register at your precinct polling place on Tuesday, February 4. Unless you register on that day, you will have no snare in <pb facs="5423969_1_1050.jpg" n="2"/>selecting your party candidates.</p>
   <p>Americans of Danish, Norwegian, or Swedish descent, have shown, especially in Chicago, their splendid patriotic feelings in regard to the Red Cross and the Liberty Loan subscriptions. How let us show our full appreciation of our citizenship by doing our duty in regard to voting. All of us who are not registered should be sure to register on Tuesday, February 4.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
