<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-07-07">July 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The New Board of Education</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-07-07">July 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW BOARD OF EDUCATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the eight members of the Chicago Board of Education named by Mayor Busse, seven are new men. Dr. Guerin retains his place, while all the rest of the so-called Dunne men have been retired. Most of the Dunne men were of purely theoretical bent; they meant well but were lacking in practical insight. Mr. John J. Sonsteby was fully as capable as any of the other Dunne men, and in several ways Mayor Busse would have made a better choice if he had kept Mr. Sonsteby on the board and let Dr. Guerin go.</p>
   <p>Mayor Busse does not seem to have much faith in women as members of the Board of Education. There is not one woman among the members of the Board whom he has named. We admit that there are altogether too many women teachers, but it would undoubtedly be of benefit to the children if mothers had some voice in the Board of Education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1146.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As usual, the Germans and the Irish are well represented on the Board. The Poles and the Bohemians have not been forgotten either. The Jews have their men on the Board, Dr. Guerin is considered representative of the handful of Frenchmen in Chicago. Yet the Scandinavians, who are about as numberous as the Irish in this city, do not have even one representative on the new Board of Education. Possibly, the Scandinavians have not been working hard enough, or have not been sufficiently united, to get their men appointed. Yet there were Scandinavian candidates who were fully as able as any of the men who have been appointed. Consequently, the Mayor has no excuse for disregarding the Scandinavians.</p>
   <p>Whether the new Board will be better than the old one, the future alone can tell.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
