<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Illinois Good Templars</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-09-12">Sept. 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ILLINOIS GOOD TEMPLARS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Illinois Grand Lodge of the Scandinavian Good Templars held a three-day convention, September 4 to 6. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> delegates were present representing forty lodges. It was resolved to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to the Juvenile Templar, a paper published by the Grand lodge. The death benefit was increased to $200. The Grand lodge has <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>235 members; the Juvenile Templars have 335 members and seven lodges.</p>
   <p>Financial Report</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand from last year</cell>
     <cell>$ 880.81</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Income this year to date</cell>
     <cell>2,560.68</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$3,441.49</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses this year to date</cell>
     <cell>$2,591.68</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0248.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand, July 1, 1915</cell>
     <cell>$1,049.81</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Thirteen Chicago members were elected to the Illinois executive board.</p>
   <p>The following resolution was passed by the membership:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, There is now in force in the State of Illinois an act popularly known as the 'Local Option Laws," and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Many of the cities and towns of this state, by referendum vote of their Citizens in accordance with the terms of said act, have been declared to be 'Anti-Saloon Territory,' and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, In many of these cities and towns there are, and have been for some time past, open and notorious violations of the words and spirit of said law, <pb facs="5423969_1_0249.jpg" n="3"/>principally by clubs and social organizations, and so called blind pigs, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, It is the sworn duty of our mayors and police officials, states attorneys, and sheriffs to enforce this law, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Many of these officials for political purposes are in connivance with these violators, thereby defeating the will of the citizens, the spirit and purpose of the law; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, By the Scandinavian Grand Lodge of Illinois, I. O. G. T., in Convention assembled, September 4, 5, and 6, 1915, that every official under whose regime these lawless institutions flourish, be he mayor, councilman, states attorney, chief of police, or sheriff, is hereby censured for his neglect of duty; and be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we urge every member of the Good Templars and all citizens <pb facs="5423969_1_0250.jpg" n="4"/>who favor the enforcement of said law to remonstrate with the officials of their respective localities in order that the will of the majority may be supreme. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That any official, city, state, or county, who fails to enforce existing laws, should be recalled from his official capacity.</p>
   <p>"<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Nelson,</p>
   <p>Acting Grand Chief Templar,</p>
   <p>"Eric J. Ericson,</p>
   <p>Acting Grand Secretary"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
