<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-22">Nov. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Saloon?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-22">Nov. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE SALOON?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All patriots, whether prohibitionists or not, are agreed that the fight against the liquor evil is one of the burning questions of the day; the disagreement in the matter concerns the methods and the means, not the goal.</p>
   <p>Some time ago a committee of noted men was formed in New York for the purpose of making the saloon problem the object of a thorough and impartial investigation. The committee consisted chiefly of people who are considered as belonging among the country's reform forces, and who in many ways have been fighting evils and working for better conditions. The chief reason for their undertaking the task was the scant results achieved by the prohibition movement. They felt that a thorough and impartial investigation of the problem might lead to the finding of more effective means for overcoming the liquor evil.</p>
   <p>One of the members of this committee is Reverend Royal L. Melendy, who is connected with the Reform Settlement, Chicago Commons, located in the Seventeenth Ward of <pb facs="5423969_1_0308.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago. Reverend Melendy has devoted six months to the study of the saloons in this Ward. Since a large number of Norwegians are living in this part of the city, Skandinaven believes that it ought to publish the results of this investigation of the saloons in the Norwegian neighborhood. A summary of Reverend Melendy's report is presented elsewhere in this issue of Skandinaven.</p>
   <p>As our readers will notice, Reverend Melendy's opinions concerning the saloon differ in several respects from those generally held. Some of his statements are surprising. Thus he asserts that the saloon, as it has developed in Chicago and in most of the large cities in our country, is something very different from what most people consider it to be. The saloon is not simply a place which people enter for the purpose of drinking intoxicating liquors; it is an institution which, to use Reverend Melendy's words, constitutes a phase of the neighborhood in which it is located, and it cannot be taken away except through the substitution of some other institution which could carry on the many social functions which at present are undertaken by the saloon.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0309.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Undoubtedly there is some truth in this; at the same time, Reverend Meverend Melendy has been misled in his investigations on several points. Thus it is completely incorrect to say that as a rule one may eat as much as one pleases in a saloon whether liquor is bought or not; also the description he presents of the serving of a hot "free lunch" in a saloon has but faint relation to the true situation in the average Chicago saloon. Cases in which the saloonkeeper "lends money to people from whom he does not have much hope of repayment" and finds work for unemployed people are undoubtedly so rare that it is completely misleading to refer to them as representing the rule.</p>
   <p>And while Reverend Melendy has found the good sides of the saloon, which most people have been unable to detect, he has overlooked many dark sides which are clearly apparent to anyone who wants to see.</p>
   <p>But even though, in the opinion of Skandinaven, Reverend Melendy's report on the saloon evil is misleading in many ways, there are elements in the report which the advocates of temperance may well keep in mind. At least it explains in part why the work for abstinence has not made greater progress. The fight against <pb facs="5423969_1_0310.jpg" n="4"/>the saloon evil has not sufficiently considered the "social functions" of the saloon. All of those one hundred and one different needs, the satisfaction of which the saloon, as matters are, has monopolized, have usually been completely overlooked or at least greatly underestimated. As a result, the temperance movement has suffered the opposition not only of those who manufacture and sell liquor and those who consume it, but also of many who are neither the slaves of liquor nor its admirers. In other words, it is not to be expected that the fight against the saloon will attain its goal until the opponents of liquor have undertaken the task of replacing the saloon with something better, or until conditions have become so changed that the saloon becomes superfluous as a social institution in a neighborhood.</p>
   <p>The investigation by Reverend Melendy leads to this conclusion. To what extent it is justified we are not able to say at present. Even though the opinion held by the minister is fully justified with reference to some places, it is by no means certain that his views are valid with respect to all saloons.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0311.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The problem of the saloon is a large one and has many sides. Under no circumstances would it hurt the friends of temperance or abstinence, or other people as well, to take up for study the opinions and arguments presented by Reverend Melendy in the report here discussed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
