<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-09-27">Sept. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter from Niels Gron</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-09-27">Sept. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER FROM NIELS GRON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of Skandinaven:</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>On my return to Chicago, I find that youresteemed paper has done me the honor of mentioning my name in two leading articles in the issues of September 13 and 22.</p>
   <p>I herewith kindly request you to publish in just as prominent a place in your paper, the following corrections of a few misstatements which appear in the articles in question.</p>
   <p>1. Nowhere in the article mentioned by you, do you find me explaining that I had been requested by Major McKinley to transmit this "message of good will," <pb facs="5423969_1_0521.jpg" n="2"/>as you prefer to call it. Neither is there anything that "purports to convey greetings from him to the Scandinavians." What was related in the article in question, was simply the contents of a conversation that I held with Major McKinley at his home on the 16th of July, 1896.</p>
   <p>2. I was not removed from my position as chairman of the Scandinavian department of the Republican National committee, but simply turned the department over to Mr. Julius Goldschmidt, chairman of the foreign bureau, when there was demand for my services on the platform.</p>
   <p>I never stated that I was a graduate of Pennsylvania University, but you will find my name on the register of Pennsylvania College (between the years 1885-1886). Also on the graduating roster of Harvard University for 1894.</p>
   <p>Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>Niels Gron.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0522.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Gron's corrections fail to be true. This paper has found nothing in his article which had not already been found there by many other Skandinavian papers. He ought to know that the Scandinavian "Popocratic" press is still at it ridiculing the ex-head of the Scandinavian bureau, and charging him up to Major McKinley and Mr. Hanna, together with his luggage of cheek, overweening self-importance and bad breaks. Mr. Gron would better abstain from writing for the press until he shall have learned how to say his say.</p>
   <p>His denial of having ever stated that he is a graduate of the University of Pennsylvania should have been addressed to the Pioneer Press, where the statement was originally made in a manner suggesting that Mr. Gron himself was the direct source of information. But although he is known to have made extensive use of the puff published by a western paper, he is not known to have troubled himself about a correction of the false statement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0523.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What Mr. Gron says about "simply turning the department over to Mr. Julius Goldschmidt" is amusing, if it isn't true. Taking him at his word, Mr. Gron must have been a part of an autocrat at the Republican headquarters, and Mr. Hanna and the other members of the national committee are evidently very grateful to this young man, because he has graciously refrained from kicking them all downstairs, and turning their respective departments over to somebody else.</p>
   <p>The fact of the matter is Mr. Gron was removed as chairman of the Scandinavian department after his arrogance and incompetency had become unbearable. In order to let him down easy, he was sent out to make a few speeches in these parts. That's the long and short of the "demand for his services on the platform," to which he alludes.</p>
   <p>Should Mr. Gron be sent East never to return, the Scandinavians of the West will endeavor to get along without him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
