<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-10-22">Oct. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Typographists Celebrate</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian-Danish Union Celebrates Eleventh Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0749</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0749.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2) (Danish)</item>
     <item>II A 2 (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-10-22">Oct. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE TYPOGRAPHISTS CELEBRATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Norwegian-Danish Union Celebrates Eleventh Anniversary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian-Danish Typographical Union celebrated its eleventh anniversary last Sunday evening with a banquet at Humboldt Park House. In the newly renovated concert hall Mr. Hans Finstad had prepared an excellent dinner, and after the guests had been seated, Mr. Finstad and his assistants were busily engaged in the task of providing for every guest promptly and adequately.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bernhard Svendsen, chairman of the committee on arrangements, acted as toast-master; he welcomed the guests, reminding them that the Union had been organized eleven years ago; that it had weathered many a storm; that at present it was sturdier and in better condition than ever before.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Ariansen, the president, spoke in honor of the day and expressed his satisfaction at seeing so many of the members present..... He gave a brief survey of the history of the Union and concluded by toasting the united typographists, who eleven years ago started their activity as Local 272 of the International <pb facs="5423969_1_0750.jpg" n="2"/>Typographical Union of America.</p>
   <p>A song for the occasion, written by Mr. August B. Holm, was sung and applauded. The author of the song then spoke in honor of Norway. A speech in verse, delivered in honor of Denmark by Mr. Thales Borgeson, was received with enthusiasm. Mr. P. J. N. Petersen spoke in honor of America, and this was followed by the singing of the national anthem. [Translator's note: Reference is made at this point to several additional speeches.]</p>
   <p>Afterwards, the punch bowl was placed on the table, and the time was passed in conversation, speeches, singing, and music. Vocal solos were given by Messrs. Severin Arnesen and O. Osmundsen, and a piano solo was played by Albert Olsen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
