<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-04">May 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[The Newspaper Strike]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-05-04">May 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[THE NEWSPAPER STRIKE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our big evening paper did not appear on Thursday on account of striking mechanics, or more properly speaking, because of the lock-out by the Newspaper Publishers' Association.</p>
   <p>Friday's morning paper appeared though somewhat shrunken in size because the publishers did not have sufficient time to train a required number of strike-breakers to a stage of efficiency that would enable them to print the regular-sized newspaper. The giant electrical presses are not mastered in a day.</p>
   <p>The present conflict started in the shops of the Hearst papers, where the mechanics had been working under an exceptionally beneficial contract with Hearst. Mr. Hearst has publicized this contract, using it as a bait to get organized labor patronage, and has been successful beyond all expectations. The contract has been the weapon with which he fought the Publishers
    <pb facs="5423969_1_0785.jpg" n="2"/> Association to a standstill, and it is this contract which he now tries to annul so as to seek shelter under the protecting wing of the Association contract.</p>
    <p>Until about two years ago, Hearst was notoriously "independent," and defied the Association constantly, thereby gaining the confidence and support of organized labor. Now that he has obtained his objective the human(?) chameleon changes from yellow journalism to the conventional color, and the publishers in the Association stand shoulder to shoulder in defense of their erstwhile yellow peril. The change of front on the part of Hearst was brought about by the American Federation of Labor, when it tore away the mask of deception worn so long by Hearst, and left him in the stark nakedness of his ill-concealed enmity toward labor.</p>
    <p>The Publishers' Association is here showing an example of solidarity that could profitably be emulated by organized labor.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
