<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-12-20">Dec. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Norwegian American People in Chicago and Suburbs:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-12-20">Dec. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE NORWEGIAN AMERICAN PEOPLE IN CHICAGO AND SUBURBS:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On behalf of the American Red Cross I beg to recommend its brilliant undertaking for the welfare of humanity.</p>
   <p>The Red Cross has started a campaign, the objective of which, is to add 15,000,000 new names to its membership list, and Chicago will undoubtedly do its share in regard to this increase. Our Norwegian American people are known to be among the most loyal and patriotic of American citizens and they do certainly wish to contribute their mite toward making the Red Cross membership campaign in Chicago a brilliant success. This will be gained if everybody joins this great benevolent society, taking part in the society's work for alleviating loss and need a pain among our valiant soldiers who are fighting for the security of our country.</p>
   <p>Do not forget the many hundreds of young Norwegian American men who were <pb facs="5423969_1_0883.jpg" n="2"/>called to the colors.</p>
   <p>Do not forget, either, that nobody obeyed the call to military duties more willingly and promptly than the Norwegian-Americans in Chicago.</p>
   <p>There men are fighting your fight for liberty and democracy, and they are looking to you for support and encouragement, and this you can render them through your support of the American Red Cross, which is the society that is best adapted to send help to the soldiers in camp, in the trenches, on the battlefield, at sea, in the hospitals.</p>
   <p>The objective of the campaign is to gain new members for the Red Cross, to renew the memberships, which have expired, to increase the interest for the work by getting at least one "magazine" reading member in every home, to prevail upon every member, old or new, to raise the Red Cross Service Flag, and also get every home to include Red Cross in its Christmas program by means of lights placed in the Service Flag hanging in the window on Christmas Eve; and seeing to it that every member of the family be also a member of the Red Cross.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0884.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee for the campaign has planned an intensive program of work to be executed through ward and precinct committees, the members of which will visit every home in Chicago and suburbs.</p>
   <p>When the Red Cross workers appear, you will be cordially invited to join the society and if possible to have every member of your family join. To do this is your patriotic duty.</p>
   <p>I feel assured that the Norwegian-Amerian people will respond to the call of the American Red Cross with great readiness and zeal.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>Oscar H. Haugan</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
