<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-11">Mar. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Representation Wanted]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-03-11">Mar. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[REPRESENTATION WANTED]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4. - A great many Norsemen are taking an active part in the present city election. We have politically minded countrymen in the Republican and Democratic parties and in the Socialist as well. To those of our compatriots in the ranks of the Socialist party we have nothing to say at this time. To those in the other parties we would direct the following questions: What reward or prospect is offered by the party leaders as to placing Norsemen on school, park or library boards? What, if anything, is done to recognize our influence in the city hall or county building? Have the political leaders intimated the least willingness to arrange for proper representation (according to population) in city council and county board of super visors?</p>
   <p>At the present time there is not one Norwegian on the School Board: considering the thousands of Norwegian school children in Chicago this is a slap in the face to our people. One of the first duties of the winner in the coming race for the mayor's chair will be the appointment of several <pb facs="5423969_1_1131.jpg" n="2"/>new members to the School Board, and in the interest of our Norwegian-American voters and their children, Scandia does not hesitate to say that at least one, if not more, of the board members should be chosen from the Norwegian group. We urge our campaigning Norwegian to make this demand in no uncertain terms. The consideration is our just due.</p>
   <p>We should insist on representation in the park commission and the library board; even though these positions involve no salary it would open an opportunity to advance the interest of our people both old and young.</p>
   <p>What are our politicians doing in such practical matters? It is to be hoped that our best interests are not lost sight of because of zeal in job hunting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
