<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-08-30">Aug. 30, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Be Ourselves</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0483</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0483.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-08-30">Aug. 30, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">LET US BE OURSELVES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Paul Du Chaillu, the famous traveler and author of The Viking Age and many other well-known books on Norse topics and travels, was one of the Americans who attended the banquet given in honor of Dr. Nansen in Chicago last fall. Mr. Du Chaillu is proud of the "old North" and the people who hail from those lands, and is not afraid of saying so, even in the teeth of haughty prejudice. He thinks that the Scandinavians in this country ought to cherish the land of their fathers and the tongue of their mothers. These sentiments find eloquent expression in a letter recently received by the publisher of this paper concerning the Nansen banquet. As it may be suggestive to many of our young men and women who are inclined to discard their paternal heritage of nationality and language tradition, Mr. Du Chaillu's letter is published here, in English. It reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"John Anderson, Publisher of Skandinaven.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0484.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>I write to thank you and the Nansen committee for the great honor you have done me in inviting me to attend the banquet given in honor of Dr. Fridgof Nansen by the Norwegians of Chicago and the Northwest.</p>
   <p>"It is a memorable occasion. The demonstration was a success. I felt quite proud to meet not only Dr. Nansen but also many distinguished Norwegians and other guests of the three other Scandinavian nationalities who had been, like myself, invited to meet him. Many of those seated round the festive board had come from different states and travelled a long distance to be present and testify our admiration and great appreciation of the scientific value of his exploration and of his indomitable courage. Well may Norway be proud of such a son. Let the children of Norwegians born in the States be ever proud of the land of their fathers-- for it is a glorious land with a grand history-- let them remember that the Vikings of the Scandinavian lands conquered and settled in Britain, Ireland, and Gaul, overran Germania, <pb facs="5423969_1_0485.jpg" n="3"/>Spain, Italy, Greece, Sicily, the Black Sea countries, Palestine, North Africa, and that finally some of their ships crossed the broad Atlantic and discovered America. Let them remember that we owe today a great part of our civilization, laws, and energy to those grand Vikings of old.</p>
   <p>"Let every Scandinavian never change a single letter of his name, and still less transform the name of their fathers into English or Scotch. It is beyond my comprehension that any Scandinavian fails to be proud of the land of his ancestors."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
