<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-08-16">Aug. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Socialists and Silver</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-08-16">Aug. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISTS AND SILVER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the Republican spellbinders is in the habit of stigmatizing the fifty-cent dollar as the "socialist dollar." The term is improper and foolish. People in this country have as much right to be Socialists as they have to be Republicans or Democrats. "Socialists" and "socialistic" are no longer used as epithets or as terms of opprobrium except by people who are devoid alike of culture, common sense, and good breeding. As a matter of fact, the Republican platform is somewhat tainted with socialistic notions. Nor is the Democratic platform, despite its strong anarchistic coloring, entirely free from socialism.</p>
   <p>The expression is foolish because the Socialist party does not believe in free silver. Far from supporting the Bryan ticket, it has a Presidential ticket of its own in the field, and has condemned the sixteen-to-one fallacy in strong and emphatic language. The Socialists may be mistaken <pb facs="5423969_1_0923.jpg" n="2"/>in some of their views. But many able men are found in their ranks. Nor can it be denied that they are sincere in their efforts to better the condition of the workers. But they do not believe in free silver because they know that free silver will rob the worker of part of his wages and cripple his power to support his family and educate his children. Spell-binders had better be careful.</p>
   <p>We know that the Scandinavians are not easily fooled, but they should think twice before they vote for any kind of legislation that may be opposed to the best interests of the majority.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
