<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-02-15">Feb. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[A Worthy Work]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-02-15">Feb. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[A WORTHY WORK]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian-American Foundation was founded for the purpose of aiding deserving Scandinavian and American students to extend their education beyond the confines of their own countries. The idea appealed strongly to all our prominent Scand-Americans; the founder of the great Hector Iron Works, the Danish-born Nils Paulsen, immediately donated $100,000, and at his death in 1911, his will disclosed a bequest of $400,000 to the same fund. During 1912 and 1913, scholarships, in the amount of $300 were granted, beginning Jan. 1, 1914, the amount will be increased to $750.</p>
   <p>In view of these scholarships, the best universities of the U.S.A. award free tuition to the winners. Two scholarships will be awarded each year to each of the Scandinavian countries. The winners will be chosen by a committee from his own country, to be appointed annually by the American Ambassador to that country. At present, we have two Norwegian students here: Bernard Berger at Harvard; and Martha Dahl at the University of <pb facs="5423969_1_0172.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago, in the department of the Domestic Sciences. At the Christiania University in Norway, there are two American students, Martin B. Rund, and Henning Larson, both from the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The foundation publishes the American-Scandinavian Review, wherein all important subjects of mutual interest are discussed and brought to the notice of the entire world. At the same time, it creates and maintains greater co-operation along all lines between the Scandinavian countries and the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
