<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-07-09">July 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Milk Trust Is at it Again]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1910-07-09">July 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[MILK TRUST IS AT IT AGAIN]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.2..........Anent trusts:- Chicago has a very real and efficient "trust," the milk trust (Bowman Dairy Co. and the Borden Dairy Co). Every summer they manage to boost the price of their milk products thus giving them a price consistently one cent higher than that charged by the smaller independent dealers. The trust claim this privilege because of asserted higher standards in quality and sanitary production and handling methods.</p>
   <p>John Public has been bled to such an anemic condition financially that he can barely exist; he does a lot of roaring about the depredations of the trusts but when an election is held he consistently casts his vote for the candidates that spends the money most freely and snaps his fingers at tomorrow.</p>
   <p>We have come to the painful conclusion that the needed change will come only after the trusts have lowered the living standard of the American worker to a point where <pb facs="5423969_1_0601.jpg" n="2"/>a revolution will be the only way out. We doubt whether anything but constantly worse living conditions will ever bring about a movement for the better.</p>
   <p>Last week our customary two quarts of buttermilk was delivered by a bowman driver. An hour later the contents of the bottles had settled and the top quarter was a sickening, watery liquid of a dirty yellowish color. We shook the bottle remixing the ingredients and drank two glasses of the mixture and promptly threw it all up; it was sour as vinegar. It is our candid opinion that this buttermilk had been "doctored" with formaldehyde or some other dope to artificially preserve its freshness and nourishment.</p>
   <p>Had this doped milk product come from a small dealer he would certainly have been summarily dealt with and severely punished but in the case of the "trust" - endless and meaningless investigation resulting in exactly - nothing.</p>
   <p>A complaint to our Health Department brought a reply that our complaint had been referred to the Bowman Co., for investigation. On Saturday the driver was shown the <pb facs="5423969_1_0602.jpg" n="3"/>untouched second quart in question and, "Those dumb idiots in the country have added to much water." But one does not, as a rule, vomit from fresh water. On Monday an inspector of some sort from Bowman's called. He was extremely courteous but would not admit even a remote possibility that the milk had been doped in any way. His company, he said, was very thankful for our having brought the matter to their attention and assured us that the blame would be properly placed and the guilty properly dealt with.</p>
   <p>This is the super service and quality mothers of Chicago are paying excessive prices for in order to be sure their little ones are getting pure unadulterated milk products that protect the life and health of coming generations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
