<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-15">Sep. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Workers and the Election</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-15">Sep. 15, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKERS AND THE ELECTION</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The attorney of the election commissioners has discovered that the election next Tuesday is really no election, and on account of this, the workers have no right to demand time off so as to be able to vote. And the board of commissioners sustain him.</p>
   <p>He could have found equally good reasons, and better ones, for the opposite conclusion. At best, his statement is one of juridical hairsplitting. Why he should have given such a narrow interpretation of the law is inconceivable unless the intention is to prevent the workers from voting. The election takes place during working hours and if the workers are not given time off for a couple of hours, most of them will be unable to vote.</p>
   <p>It is thought, and for good reasons, that the workers are largely against the new charter. As things have developed, many of them will be deprived of their right to vote, no matter whether or not this was intended.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1080.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In any case the decision is as unjust as it is unfortunate. It will, however, hardly result as intended. It is likely that this act to exclude the workers from participation in the election will arouse the anger of the public, and this will probably react against the charter.</p>
   <p>Thoughtful and just employers will give their workers the chance to vote without loss of wages, in spite of the decision of the election commissioners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
