<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-24">Feb. 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1912-02-24">Feb. 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4...Strange and wonderful, many times ludicrous, statements are found in British books, magazines and newspapers, regarding Norway and things Norwegian. Just at the moment we are thinking of the Englishman, Cecil Forsyth, who in his recent book, "Music and Nationalism," mentions Norway and Russia, as very late entries into the ranks of music producing countries, and under German influence at that. We are not of the musical profession so cannot refute this statement. He may be right as to the early or late entry but when he puts Norway and Scandinavia on the same level as Russia, as far as music and culture are concerned, we can only say that these are unproven and unfounded statements that have been worn threadbare by English mouthings and do not mean anything. We are reminded of an English literary light who pictures Ibsen as a Scotts-Teutonic-Dane. This is truly a new breed unknown in Denmark and impossible in Norway. Any Englishman who lives but a day's journey from Grimstad or Skien, Norway, that can caricature Henrik Ibsen with such a conglomeration of nationalities should either take up ethnology or appear for help at a reputable <pb facs="5423969_1_0457.jpg" n="2"/>psychological institution. Ibsen has always been and forever will be a 100% Norwegian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
