<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-03-14">Mar. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Direct Nominations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-03-14">Mar. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">DIRECT NOMINATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The growing dissatisfaction with the old caucus and convention system is attested by the fact that primary election bills have occupied the attention of several legislatures this winter, especially in Indiana, Wisconsin, Minnesota, and North Dakota. But most of the party leaders look upon the innovation as a menace to their influence and are generally opposed to its adoption. In North Dakota an admirable primary election bill was slowly strangled to death by the cunning old bosses, and in Minnesota, where the plan of direct nominations has had a successful trial in Hennepin County, the extension of the system to the state at large is vigorously opposed by the old guard.</p>
   <p>The winning party of neither of these states had made this reform a leading issue at the last election; hence the adherents of the old system were <pb facs="5423969_1_1109.jpg" n="2"/>in a position to assert that the principle of direct nominations had not received the sanction of the people. In Wisconsin the status of the question is different. The Republicans of Wisconsin have twice in succession incorporated a primary election plank in their platform, and each time the people have put their stamp of approval upon the proposition and thus converted the "demand" of the party into a "command" to the legislators. The reform is part and parcel of the creed of the ruling party, as has been decreed by the supreme authority, the people, in most unmistakable terms. There are Republicans who regard the primary election system as expensive, cumbersome, and unwise, but if they are loyal and true Republicans they will bow to the will of their party and the people. Failure to execute a popular mandate expressed in such an emphatic manner would be an act of treason that would utterly destroy popular confidence in party pledges and seriously weaken the people's faith in the representative system of government.</p>
   <p>Candid criticism of the pending measure is in order and can only be productive of good. The Stevens Bill is probably open to objections in some <pb facs="5423969_1_1110.jpg" n="3"/>particulars and may be improved. It cannot be scrutinized and sifted too thoroughly. It is the duty of every Republican to do his utmost to make it as perfect as possible. But the principle of direct nominations is not open to discussion in Wisconsin. The people have settled that part of the question. All that remains for the legislature to do is to carry out the will of the people in good faith and to the best of its ability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
