<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-09">June 9, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">On the Altar of the Iron Horse</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-06-09">June 9, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE ALTAR OF THE IRON HORSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hardly a day passes without human life being sacrificed at the railroad crossings in Chicago. Frequently several such accidents occur in one day; during the past week six people were killed in one day. A far larger number are being injured. Perhaps most of the maimed persons seen on the streets are people who have been injured at the railroad crossings.</p>
   <p>Accidents at crossings will continue to happen as long as the tracks through the city are not elevated. But most of them could be prevented through a better guarding system by the railroads. Much has been done of late in the direction of elevating the tracks, and at a multitude of crossings it is no longer necessary to keep watch. Why not move the flagmen thus released to other crossings where no watch is kept now?</p>
   <p>The city has the right to compel the roads to keep watch where needed, and if the coroner and the coroner's jury used their wits there would soon be <pb facs="5423969_1_0629.jpg" n="2"/>the necessary number of watchmen at the crossings. No consideration should be given to the railroads' contention that it is too expensive to keep watch. The roads have had a number of good years, and the only complaint of late has been that the traffic has been so enormous that the roads could not cope with it. It is therefore no use trying to argue that the companies cannot afford keeping watch at dangerous crossings.</p>
   <p>But human life is cheap in America, especially the lives of humble people. The life of a workingman is about the cheapest article in the country. Therefore, we will probably for a long time yet continue to read day by day the sad news of people sacrificed on the altar of the Iron Horse in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
