<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (Danish)</item>
     <item>I C (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/><pb facs="5423969_1_0964.jpg" n="2"/>sentiments in order to further the faint and hopeless chances of Abel Osmond as a candidate in his race for Circuit Clerk by airing him as an able man and a typical progeny of the Viking race, whom the Norwegians in particular and the Scandinavians as a unit ought to assist to fame and fortune.</p>
   <p>My Scandinavian friends, I guess the abilities of the man are figments of the imagination of his promoter, whose ax is to be sharpened on the same stone; but, of course, that part needs no looking after, as long as H. L. T. is himself on deck.</p>
   <p>Mr. Osmond is of Norwegian blood, but at the same time it is well known to everybody that he has nothing in common with his so-called people (except that in the campaign for office he may have to nod to Ola and Lars) , neither by association nor marriage. I say that neither he nor any other Scandinavian of his type need look for united Scandinavian support. The Norwegians, Swedes and Danes are so to speak one people, and when they unite in supporting for public office a man of their own nationality, he must be a man who has his national group at heart--who loves to work for their advancement--who is not ashamed to associate and mingle with them--in short, he must have something in common with them, that is <pb facs="5423969_1_0965.jpg" n="3"/>his as well as theirs. A man may combine the learning of Yale and the etiquette of Boston and yet not feel the blood run to his cheek for being known and called a Norwegian, a Swede, or a Dane. A man who speaks with a foreign accent is just as good a patriotic citizen of this union as he who has become one by chance. We have in this political race Mr. Fred Johnson, who is as much a Swede as Osmond is a Norwegian, but he does not appeal to that nationality especially for solid support because he has nothing in common with them, he does not think any more of them and would not do any more for them than he would for a Dutchman, but treats them all with equal respect; and therefore in his scramble with the rest for office, he stands upon his merits before all the people alike in asking support.</p>
   <p>Mr. Johnson is certainly far more entitled to Scandinavian support at this time than is Mr. Osmond,if the preference is to be judged by nationality. The Norwegians have a county office and several town officers as supervisors, assessors and collectors, but Mr. Johnson is not asking for help on the ground of blood relation. If he were, I say again that the Swedes and Danes would now have the first claim on him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0966.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But let us view the two candidates, Mr. Johnson and Mr. Osmond, as two American boys. Whom shall we as citizens and voters of this country support at the caucus on June 12th? I say, let Fred Johnson get your hearty support this time, for he is, as most of you know, experienced in the work, having served a long time as deputy county clerk, besides being an honest, genial young man of excellent reputation. Osmond is a young man with an inherited fortune and can live in ease and luxury without public aid.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
