<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-09-06">Sept. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Army Canteen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-06">Sept. 6, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE ARMY CANTEEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a different place in this issue is published a letter from Adjutant General Corbin in which he presents certain information concerning the so-called Army-Canteen or Post Exchange. This letter is self-explanatory and is recommended to the consideration of our readers.</p>
   <p>Those believing in total abstinence have found much to criticise in this institution, and more particularly about the attitude of the government in regard to the Canteen. We do not doubt that the total abstentionists are moved by good intentions in their stand on this matter, and believe that they are acting and speaking in good faith.</p>
   <p>On the other hand there is good reason to believe that many who know little or nothing about the subject are, nevertheless, criticising this institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0313.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They know that the Canteen is in some way connected with sale of intoxicants, but whether the institution is a house, a bottle, or what not, they have no knowledge. Some seem to believe that the Canteen is a saloon which the government is conducting for the purpose of making drunkards out of all the soldiers.</p>
   <p>These people ought to read General Corbin's letter. He explains that the Post Exchange is a co-operative store where the soldiers may buy at wholesale various articles which the government does not supply, but which are needed by the soldiers; such as tobacco, writing paper, sewing materials, and many other little articles. There is a special section in the Army Canteen, set aside as a club room for the soldiers. Here the soldiers write their letters, read papers and magazines, and play billiards, etc. Here they may also buy beer of light wines, but not brandy or whiskey.</p>
   <p>Mr. Corbin informs us that this institution has been most helpful to the <pb facs="5423969_1_0314.jpg" n="3"/>soldiers, and to the army. It has improved both discipline and temperance. The soldiers drink less and save more; they are more law-abiding, and the general health of the army has improved as a result of the organization of the Canteen. Corbin himself was, to start with, an opponent of the Canteen, but the benefits derived from it have made him change his opinion, and at present he is joining practically all army officers in praising the institution.</p>
   <p>These are matters about which our people ought to know. The great majority of temperance advocates who condemn the Canteen have not investigated the matter thoroughly; they are speaking of the Canteen somewhat as the blind person speaks about colors. The leaders of the total abstinence movement should not plead such ignorance, however, and one feels compelled to assume that some of them are speaking against their better knowledge. This is undoubtedly the case in regards to the editor of The New Voice, the Reverend Mr. Dickie of Michigan. He speaks and writes like a crazy man, or as a man who is not interested in truth. The candidate for president of the Prohibition party, who otherwise is <pb facs="5423969_1_0315.jpg" n="4"/>a gifted and eloquent man, speaks quite frequently in a way which would seem to indicate that he is not quite normal.</p>
   <p>Our Norwegian temperance believers are on the whole more liberal in their views, although many of those who speak for the people in general seem blinded by sheer fanaticism; the fanaticism which is spoiling and delaying the temperance movement in our country. The great majority of the Norwegian temperance advocates do not believe in the practice of advancing the cause by false statements. They do not believe in hiding essential facts, and they do not believe in misrepresenting the facts. They will value the letter by General Corbin as it is a weighty and illuminating statement of facts concerning the Army Canteen.</p>
   <p>The Norwegian papers which desire to promote the cause of temperance will publish General Corbin's letter if they are interested in having truth prevail. These papers have found much to criticise in the institution and have been using strong expressions against it, but they have not informed their readers <pb facs="5423969_1_0316.jpg" n="5"/>of the real nature of the Canteen nor presented the real facts concerning it and why it is maintained.</p>
   <p>If these papers have any regard for the truth, they will bring this needed information to the attention of their readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
