<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-04-06">Apr. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Primary Legislation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1091.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-04-06">Apr. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">PRIMARY LEGISLATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Minnesota the adoption of a primary election law is now assured. The opposition in the Senate, which it was feared would be strong enough to defeat or mutilate the measure, crumbled before the strong pressure of public sentiment and the bill passed the upper house by a majority that was even more decisive than the vote in the House of Representatives. The bill as it now stands follows in the main the lines of the Hennepin County law which has been tried with satisfactory results. It does not satisfy the demands of the advanced spokesman of direct nominations, but it is regarded as a good beginning. The principle which established the law will be amended and improved as time and experience may suggest.</p>
   <p>A very different spectacle is presented at Madison. While Minnesota is to have a primary law, though it has not been expressly demanded by the people, this <pb facs="5423969_1_1092.jpg" n="2"/>all-important reform may be defeated in Wisconsin, even though a large majority of the members of the legislature are pledged to its support. In the West (including Chicago) the Republican majority complied with the wishes of the people, not deeming it necessary to wait for the formal instruction of a platform pledge. In Wisconsin a minority of the Republican majority defies a popular mandate expressed and affirmed by overwhelming majorities in two successive state elections.</p>
   <p>The recalcitrant Republicans do not waste any time on argument. The primary election bill is "populistic legislation," and that is sufficient to condemn it in their eyes. This reform has been the chief plank of their own platform in two general elections; it is opposed by nearly every Democrat in the legislature; the combined forces of the Democrats and populists have been arrayed against it. Yet it is "populistic legislation"!</p>
   <p>The primary election law is the Republican legislation that has emanated from the present legislature. As a matter of fact it was opposed by the Democrats and <pb facs="5423969_1_1093.jpg" n="3"/>populists because they realized that such a measure would be a feather in the cap of the Republican party. Their plan was to defeat the bill and steal the Republican thunder for use in the next campaign. A similar motive is undoubtedly in a large measure responsible for the Democratic opposition. Primary elections are inevitable. The people demand the right to choose their own candidates for public offices, and they will have their way. If one party shall prove faithless, another will be chosen as the instrument of the people. Unless it is enacted as Republican legislation this year, a primary election law may be placed upon the statute books by the Democrats in 1903.</p>
   <p>Let the minority Republicans heed the signs of the times. The honor and welfare of the party, the will of the people, the loyalty to the principle of representative government demand the enactment of a primary election law by the present legislature. If these Republicans are troubled by political considerations let them remember that it is as poor politics to attempt to thwart the will of the people as it is good politics to give the people what they want, and that if primary legislation is good Republican politics in Minnesota and Wisconsin, it <pb facs="5423969_1_1094.jpg" n="4"/>is equally good Republican politics in Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
