<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Judicial Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE JUDICIAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the six new circuit judgeships created by the recent act of the legislature, there will be twenty circuit judges to be elected in June. The whole West Side of Chicago has but one circuit judge and the Northwest Side has long felt that it has not had its proportionate share of representation upon the bench.</p>
   <p>The coming election presents a fine opportunity to give that part of the city its proper representation. The twenty-eighth Ward Republicans have endorsed Oscar M. Torrison for one of the new judgeships. The Dovre Club, which has done great service to the community in the cause of good citizenship and in the election of good men to public offices, has seconded the endorsement of Mr. Torrison. The Skandinaven heartily joins with hosts of others on the Northwest Side in the movement for the nomination of Mr. Torrison.</p>
   <p>Mr. Torrison has had many years of experience as a judge of the Municipal Court, <pb facs="5423969_1_1060.jpg" n="2"/>and has established a splendid record and a reputation throughout the city as an able, fair, and humane judge. His character is above reproach; his education and legal attainments are well known. He has always, in a marked degree, received the endorsement of the [Chicago] Bar Association, which is really the best criterion of a judge's qualifications. As a public-spirited citizen he has for years been identified with the best public movements. His strength and following as a vote getter has recently been demonstrated in a way that attracted attention through the whole city. His nomination by the Republicans would add strength to their ticket and at the same time please the people of the Northwest Side where he is so well and favorably known among all classes and all nationalities. His nomination would be particularly pleasing to that large body of Norwegian citizens who are justly proud of his record and standing in the community, and who at this time are not represented in any public position in either our city or county governments, although they have been for years one of the main sources of strength to the Republican party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
