<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-07">Mar. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Norwegian Republicans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-07">Mar. 7, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORWEGIAN REPUBLICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Norwegian-American Republican Club was well attended and was very representative. The meeting was held at Björgvin Hall. The Hall was decorated with Norwegian and American flags. On the stage a number of palms added to the festive air.</p>
   <p>After Mr. A. Larsen, Jr. had played a piano solo, Adolph Larsen, Sr., the president, called the meeting to order, and the annual report was read by the secretary.</p>
   <p>The report evoked strong applause from the audience; it presented a clear picture of the Club's activities during the past year. The president gave a speech outlining the organization's objective and its work during the ten years of its existence.</p>
   <p>Among other things, he stated that the aim of the Club is to promote clean politics and to aid the Republican party in advancing this purpose, while at <pb facs="5423969_1_1006.jpg" n="2"/>the same time it strives to weed out unhealthy growths within the party. The members of the Club, he said, are peaceful people, but as true Republicans and loyal Norwegians they are both ready and able to take up the cudgel against disruptive influences whether these be found in one party or in the other. Such had been the program, he said, during the years of existence of the Club, and such, he hoped, would be the program as long as the Club should continue to exist.</p>
   <p>After the speech, election of officers was held, and it was evident that the unity and friendly feeling which had governed the Club last year was still prevailing. On nomination, the men named for the various offices were elected by acclamation.</p>
   <p>The new officers were elected as follows: president, Mr. Edwin S. A. Lahlum; vice-presidents, Messrs. Olaf E. Ray, Berthens Hansen, and Otto Benzon; secretary, Mr. Adolph Larsen, Jr.; treasurer, Mr. [Julius] Jaeger; doormen, Messrs. H. Syvertson and John T. Olsen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1007.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The date of the annual meeting, determined by the bylaws to be held in December, was changed through alteration of the laws to be held in February. The political executive committee was given an added membership of ten, increasing the total membership of the committee from fifteen to twenty-five. The retiring president was given a rising vote of thanks for his good work for the Club.</p>
   <p>The new president delivered a brief speech thanking the members for the honor and confidence shown him.</p>
   <p>The floor was then given to States Attorney Ben Short, who delivered an excellent speech for which he reaped much applause. Mr. Short knew the Norwegian history thoroughly, from the days of Leif Ericson's visit to America and onward; he was familiar with the beautiful nature of the country, the honesty, hospitality, and love of liberty of the Norwegain people. He stated among other things, that of the many thousands of criminal cases which year after year the States Attorney's office had to deal with, only a minute fraction was Norwegian; that of the more than nine hundred criminal cases <pb facs="5423969_1_1008.jpg" n="4"/>which he personally had had to prosecute during the past year not a single one had been Norwegian.</p>
   <p>There are no better people among us, he continued, either in politics or in business, and a party which has a club like the present as its supporter has reason to consider itself fortunate and may well hope for victory at the polls.</p>
   <p>Finally, he stated that he was convinced that the regular Republican organization in the Twenty-eighth Ward was proud of having the Norwegian-American Republican Club as its assistant; and this he said as a resident of the Ward and as a member of the aforementioned organization.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry Littler, the Republican candidate for alderman for the Twenty-eighth Ward, was the next speaker. He said among other things, that in the twenty years during which he had lived in the Ward he had never sought or held any political office, although he had at all times taken an active part in the political life of the Ward. He had not sought the nomination <pb facs="5423969_1_1009.jpg" n="5"/>for alderman now, he said; in fact he had declined when his friends first requested of him that he run for the office. Only after much pressure had he consented to become a candidate. If elected, and he felt certain of election by the aid of the Norwegian-American Republican Club, his aim and his work would be for the best interests of the Ward and the city. He was anxious to make good so that he, on leaving the city's service could have as honorable and clean a record as had the former president of the Club, Mr. A. Larson, when he left the City Council.</p>
   <p>After this speech it was unanimously decided that the Club apply all its forces for the election of Mr. Littler as alderman.</p>
   <p>Between speeches, and during the following festivities, the Bjorgvin Singing Society gave some splendid numbers, and Mr. E. C. Bye, the well-known banker who is one of the organizers of the Club, gave an equally excellent solo. Mr. Bye's voice would be an honored addition in an opera company. Mr. Gustav Eriksen, one of the members of the Bjorgvin Society, gave some lusty farm stories for which he received well-deserved applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1010.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The long tables decorated with flowers, etc., were loaded with genuine Norwegian sandwiches, but in spite of heavy attacks on the food...there was plenty left to feed at least fifty more men.</p>
   <p>As the combined meeting and festival drew to a close, there was unanimity of opinion that meetings such as the one sponsored here by the Norwegian-American Republican Club of the Twenty-eighth Ward do not occur often in our city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
