<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-04-13">Apr. 13, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Education Is the Word</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-04-13">Apr. 13, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION IS THE WORD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Is it right to argue for the uneducated against the enlightened? Most emphatically no! We would commit two wrongs. First, we would be giving the hundreds of thousands of uneducated an excuse for their negligence and thoughtlessness, when they should have been fitting themselves for the requirements of an educated and virtuous life. Second, we would reward the labors and struggles of the more educated with base ingratitude and thereby discourage them.</p>
   <p>A certain contributor in this paper who signs himself "X", apparently needs the artificial aid of the wonderful "X-rays" to help him pick his weary footsteps out of the past and to come up with the requirements of today.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No one has tried to take any of the well-earned laurels from the "pioneer", for we owe to them, our strong morals, force of energy, and spotless character. Their character was created by circumstances. The religious controversies in the Old World and subsequent immigration to the wilds of North America made the pioneer what he was. But in those days the problem of education had not been acknowledged. The common laborer was not educated, much less the common woman. But now we have solved the problem of a complete educational system. The necessity of such a system was and is apparent to everyone. Our pioneer mothers have done their duty; their mission died with them. The wilderness is conquered and we turn our thoughts to the only power that insures future prosperity: education.</p>
   <p>People who struggle for an education should not be daunted! They deserve the admiration of everyone who wants to see the spotless banner of "education and progress" planted against a transparent background where not a speck of ignorance lingers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
