<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-21">July 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Taxing Bachelors and Bachelors Maids</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial under "Women and the Home")</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-21">July 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TAXING BACHELORS AND BACHELORS MAIDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial under "Women and the Home")</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A serious proposal for taxing bachelors and women not married has been brought forward in the German press.</p>
   <p>That the bachelors ought to pay for their freedom and pay dearly, that is a proposition to which women will agree immediately. But to compel the lonely self-maintaining women to pay an extra tax and even place them on a level with the despicable bachelors - that is an idea which could only arise in a society governed by the miserable males. Because, the self-maintaining woman says, I do not at all object to getting married. But since, it is with the man - except on that poor day of the leap-year - and none of these detestables have looked me up, prefering to live the gay life of the single rather than to settle down to home and family, and so, there I am! And am I now to pay taxes - because nobody proposes to me! The injustice of such a proposal is too glaring; only men could think of anything as cruel as this!</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0383.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Berlin press has been quick to reduce the whole story to practically nothing, whether to avoid riot within the circles of women or whether other reasons have been determining factors we do not know. The papers now assure us that no steps in the direction mentioned will be taken until the war is over,anyway. Till then the unmarried men and women may feel at ease.</p>
   <p>So there we are. The men may enjoy their liberty, and if so why should they not pay? But the great majority of women would feel that they were paying for a condition which they did not at all desire, and which they did not bring about.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
