<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-04">Nov. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Drift to Debs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0914</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0914.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-04">Nov. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE DRIFT TO DEBS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the more noteworthy features of the present campaign is the strong drift towards Debs among voters of radical views. The Bryan leaders had relied upon this element to support the Nebraskan. They scoffed at the Social Democrats and took it for granted that all who disbelieve in the present social order would fall an easy prey to the demagogic eloquence of Colonel Bryan. They have discovered their mistake. They have learned that a Social Democrat has nothing in common with a Democrat of the Bryan stripe--that Social Democracy represents a well-defined social system and is made up of men who have principles and believe in them. Such men will have nothing to do with a party that is devoid of principles and only tries to prolong its existence and grab power by raising false issues. It is very evident that the Social Democrats will draw to itself all that is respectable among men and women of pronounced radical views, leaving all <pb facs="5423969_1_0915.jpg" n="2"/>the human debris of society to the aggregation led by such men as Richard Croker. As between the Republican and Democratic parties a Social Democrat has no choice; he believes in neither. Yet many Social Democrats will vote for McKinley because he represents a prosperity that is essential to the welfare of their families. But all Social Democrats who think they can afford it, and that they can accomplish anything by voting their real convictions at this time, will support Debs.</p>
   <p>The shameful attack by a Bryan-Carter Harrison mob upon three of the speakers of the Social Democratic party is the best evidence of the desperation which has seized the Bryan forces upon their discovery of the drift to Debs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
