<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-05-09">May 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Debating Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-05-09">May 9, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">DEBATING SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor Skandinaven, Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>In a recent issue of Skandinaven, I read the following, written by G.F.:</p>
   <p>"Debating societies should not exist. They are many times worse than drinking because those who drink also want to be members of these societies."</p>
   <p>This is altogether against public sentiment and the teaching of our youth. To think as the author of the letter does is bad enough; to say it is much worse. What was it that make such men as Clay, Lincoln, etc? Were not these men enthusiastic debaters and speakers while they were treading the "flowery path of knowledge"? Do not all great men of today recommend debating societies? If you trace the lives of our great men of the past and present you will find that the majority of them used of the tongues in their youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0320.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Intoxicating drinks at debating societies are a nuisance. A society with a good leader never needs such drinks. Most probably G.F. belongs to a society using such drinks. If so, I would advise him to introduce to the society this question for debate: Resolved that intoxicating drinks need not and should not be used in this debating society.</p>
   <p>What does G.F. mean by "other things" and "such gatherings"? He cannot mean that debating societies are to be compared with dances or such.</p>
   <p>There is much to say in regard to this article, but space is limited and I must stop. Only this: Young people! invest a couple of dollars in good books on discussion and debate; and the good that they will do will remain a part of you all through life, and you will be better able to defend yourself in the future--not physically but mentally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
