<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-07-02">July 2, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Suggestion, Mr. Spaulding</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1899-07-02">July 2, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A SUGGESTION, MR. SPAULDING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning the Chicago Union Traction Company assumed the actual management of the West Side and the North Side street railway systems, and Mr. Jesse Spaulding succeeded to the position so long occupied by Mr. Charles T. Yerkes.</p>
   <p>The transfer of these large properties will rank as a transaction of great magnitude, even in these days of gigantic deals. Every detail had been carefully arranged by a few men representing the moneyed interests involved on either side, while the community at large was afforded only occasional glimpses into the pending negotiations. And yet, important as was this transfer considered merely as a business transaction, its public importance was of still greater moment. The shareholders whose capital is invested are vitally interested in the welfare and earning power of these traction systems; but the noninvesting, franchise-granting public, the city, and the people, have greater things at <pb facs="5423969_1_0699.jpg" n="2"/>stake; for the growth and development of the city and the prosperity and happiness of the people depend in a large measure upon the character and adequacy of the street railway service.</p>
   <p>Considering the double character of the valuable properties that have changed hands, it is to be hoped that the change may prove to be advantageous alike to the people and the new owners. The realization of this hope depends mainly upon the company. The people are patient and reasonable in their demands, and if they are met in the same spirit there need be no apprehension of impatience or unfairness on their part. But their rights should be respected and their wishes receive proper consideration.</p>
   <p>Let Mr. Spaulding ascertain the needs and consult the wishes of the different sections of the territory tributary to these systems, and he will strike the path that leads straight to success. There is no disposition at this time to rehearse complaints of conditions in the past. It is admitted that great things have been accomplished; on the other hand, it is not to be denied that greater <pb facs="5423969_1_0700.jpg" n="3"/>things remain to be done.</p>
   <p>Mr. Spaulding has been so closely identified with the late management that his conception of the existing need of improvements of the service may not be entirely unbiased. If he were to inaugurate his management by a personal inspection of the various lines at all hours of the day he would acquire a vast fund of useful information. The work, if thoroughly performed, would not be one of unmixed pleasure. If the president of the Union Traction Company should find himself attempting to hang onto a car by his fingernails, the object lesson of the experiment would be all the more valuable. On the Halsted Street line, for instance, he would discover that not even such meager accommodations always are to be enjoyed during the busy morning hours, and he would often be compelled to wait fifteen, twenty, or thirty minutes, or even longer, on a street corner, unless he should decide to walk. Pressing business might be waiting for him at the office, but that would not increase the number or capacity of the cars. Should he want to try the line during the rush of the evening hours he would better limit the cash in his pockets to a nickel, <pb facs="5423969_1_0701.jpg" n="4"/>otherwise some of the gangs of pickpockets, who do business with the patrons of this line whenever the crush on the cars offers opportunities, would be likely to get it. If he is a good listener he would find the conversation of the passengers on the overcrowded cars very instructive, if not particularly edifying. Among other things, he would discover that the people wonder why it is that trailers may be run on Sundays, but not on weekdays on this line; why the time of a businessman or a worker going to his place of work, is considered less valuable than the time of people who are going somewhere to do nothing except to breathe the free air. He would probably find some-what similar conditions prevailing on other lines also. On the whole, a thorough personal investigation could not fail to be instructive in many ways.</p>
   <p>The great majority of the people of Chicago believe in private management of our street railways, as affording the best guaranties of a safe, efficient, and progressive service. By pursuing a broad, liberal, and progressive policy the company will justify and strengthen this belief. But public opinion is <pb facs="5423969_1_0702.jpg" n="5"/>quick to change nowadays, and it may be set down as a certainty that a manifest disregard of the reasonable demands of the people will result in an irresistible demand for public ownership and management. The shareholders have a good thing in their investment and naturally desire to keep it. No one will be disposed to begrudge them even liberal dividends if they understand that they are not the masters, but the servants of the community, and act accordingly. A wise policy will gain for the company the good will of the people--the surest guaranty of the safety of capital invested and of the stability and profitableness of the investment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
