<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-15">Dec. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Dance about the Golden Calf</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-15">Dec. 15, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANCE ABOUT THE GOLDEN CALF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known Episcopal Bishop Potter of New York, in a lecture the other day on the topic "Property and Society," said among other things:</p>
   <p>"Divorces, crime, and corruption in all our cities develop from the same root--the lust for money. Look wherever you will in our complex political and social life, and you will find behind it all the question of profits. Listen to whichever scandal you will among politicians, in the camps of the soldier, or in the halls where the socialites gather--everywhere it is the dollar, in the final analysis, by which everything is measured.</p>
   <p>"Listen to the talk of the children as they compare their parents; listen to groups of young girls of whom one might imagine that where their finest, most sacred sentiments are concerned, they would be free from the thoughts of <pb facs="5423969_1_0911.jpg" n="2"/>filthy lucre--you will find that they have their price and that they are not to be had for less.</p>
   <p>"Go wherever you will; converse with whomever you will: with ministers or priests who are calculating the income from their spiritual field of labor; with the loaders of great universities who are paralyzed with the fear that some honest, straightforward professor may happen to tell the people the truth at a time when it would be well that truth be heard, and thereby lessen the income of the university--at the base of it all is the question of money, and that question usually supplies the answer to all the rest.</p>
   <p>"The situation, threatening as it is to all that which is best in the life of a nation, is the result of causes which are not too far to seek. These causes are to be found in the spirit of the time; in the conditions of our national life; in the goal according to which the value of our personal life is measured.</p>
   <p>"I see no prospect that any legislation, any socialistic system, any system <pb facs="5423969_1_0912.jpg" n="3"/>of land division or taxation can free us from the dangers which threaten our society. Only Christianity, the Church of God, can do it."</p>
   <p>The Bishop's charge is serious, yet true in the main. His accusations may be leveled, with practically the same force, against life in every country. The quest for gold may be more intense in one country than in another; but the power of money is one of the cornerstones in every one of the countries that we call civilized. This condition is inseparable from the principles of private property and free competition. Bishop Potter has emphasized the dark side of the situation--the consequence of property's being considered the goal instead of the means. He is right in his statement that there is no remedy against this misconception except in Christianity; only the religion of brotherly love can teach man the right use of property.</p>
   <p>Yet the socialists do not agree with the Bishop. They teach that as long as private property and free competition prevail, society inevitably rests upon <pb facs="5423969_1_0913.jpg" n="4"/>the basis of selfishness; that the worship of the dollar is inseparable from the principles of private property and of free competition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
