<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-04-05">Apr. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-04-05">Apr. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pierpont Morgan, the grandiose manipulator of values, is dead. It is suggested that he could not face the really intimate inquiry of the Pujo Committee. Morgan dominated over enormous business enterprises to a greater extent than any other living being.</p>
   <p>Not alone was this true of American industry, but nearly every country in the world felt his power, banks in London and Paris, railroads in China, saltpeter mines in Chile. Insurance companies such as the New York Life and the Equitable, and no less than fifty-nine gigantic trusts and other financial giants were controlled, if not entirely owned, by Morgan. Of the combined wealth of the United States he had absorbed $15,000,000,000.</p>
   <p>Morgan's death naturally brings to mind other financial giants, - Carnegie, Bessemer, Nobel, Crupp, Cunard, Vanderbilt and others whose manipulations not only accumulated their individual fortunes but were, to a greater or <pb facs="5423969_1_0573.jpg" n="2"/>lesser extent, beneficial to the country as a whole. They pioneered and built-up big industries that supplied work and profit for thousands. While these men were capitalists in the strictest sense of the word, they must be given due credit for their share in making possible the development of our vast resources and territory.</p>
   <p>Morgan cannot be placed in the same class as these men. To the best of our knowledge, Morgan did not once lend a hand in the development of anything productive; he was a speculator (polite phraseology for gambler) whose specialty was not to create wealth but to accumulate it by any and all means. Some years ago he had a vision of a universal ocean-shipping monopoly to be controlled by himself, but in this he failed, not even getting a start. His idea was not to increase and improve transoceanic service, but to monopolize it. As a speculator he desired to concentrate values with himself in control and possible ownership later on. So great was this one man's influence that panics happened at his will with resultant loss to others and gain to Morgan. Here is one man whose demise will not be mourned, by those who created his wealth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
