<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-09-23">Sept. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Root of Anarchism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0916</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0916.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-23">Sept. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE ROOT OF ANARCHISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anarchism in present-day Europe and nihilism in Russia of twenty years ago present similarities as well as dissimilarities. While nihilism was an expression of local and temporary conditions, a period of transition effecting only Russia, the present eruptions, and the forces they represent, are the results of those conditions which are now being considered normal and not at all of a passing character.</p>
   <p>Nihilism was a result of the emancipation of slaves in Russia in 1861 and the subsequent speedy increase in popular education. The Russian society was in a state of dissolution, and the people were being made familiar with the doctrines of materialism, and aided by various intellectual stimulants. At the same time the former slaves were made to feel that there was no place for <pb facs="5423969_1_0917.jpg" n="2"/>them in the empire. They learned how to make bombs, and were sent out into the world to starve. The tyrannical acts by the nobility and the clergy, and excessive taxes are contributory causes for the growth of anarchism. These causes are, in part, remnants from the Middle Ages, but modern conditions abolish the old evils merely to supplant them with new ones.</p>
   <p>The basic cause for anarchism is injustice. Injustice is to be found everywhere in the relationship between capital and labor, between the craftsman and the manufacturer. Under the influence of competition the European worker is compelled to sell his labor for just enough wages to keep him alive. If the worker refuses these low wages another worker, who is poorer than he, will enter and take his job.</p>
   <p>The competitive system, according to men who have studied the situation in Europe, is the cause of the growth of anarchism in countries such as Germany and France, as well as in Austria, Italy, and Spain. There is no other means <pb facs="5423969_1_0918.jpg" n="3"/>of overcoming this system than by justice. "By whatever measure you measure, will be measured again to you."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
