<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-11-17">Nov. 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Not Nurseries of Anarchism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-11-17">Nov. 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NOT NURSERIES OF ANARCHISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anarchism was the subject of a discussion at a "free floor" meeting at the Chicago Commons the other night. Abram Isaaks, Jr. attacked government as "a self-constituted arrangement for the well-being of plutocracy" and represented "anarchy as the cure for all ills". Stung by a vigorous arraignment of anarchy by Charles 0. Brown, the two Isaaks (senior and junior), Mr. Enricho Travaglio, and half a dozen other anarchists sprang to their feet when the presiding officer, Professor Graham Taylor, prevented further discussion by adjourning the meeting.</p>
   <p>"While we believe in and stand for freedom of speech," Mr. Taylor said, "this gavel will never permit a meeting of this character to be turned into a gathering bent upon using the torch and championing a deed of blood."</p>
   <p>The public at large will welcome this assurance from the leader of the Chicago Commons; and it would have been still more welcome if it had been made and enforced long ago. There is a general impression that the so-called social settlements <pb facs="5423969_1_0896.jpg" n="2"/>, the Commons among them, have shown a lack of discretion and good judgment in giving altogether too free rein to immature people with economic and political vagaries and grievances of all sorts and descriptions.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. Abram Isaaks, Sr., "the practical anarchist does not conceive these deeds that prove so great a shock to society. Your philosophical anarchist is responsible. He broods over a condition of humanity that demands redress, and proceeds according to his own notions."</p>
   <p>This is probably true; at least, Mr. Isaaks ought to know, as he is one of the representative men of anarchy. Our social settlements have accorded the floor to these brooding philosophical anarchists and have thus enabled them to sow the seeds of discontent in the minds of people they could not have reached in any other way--audiences made up of men and women stronger in book learning than in common sense, and of honest toilers needing and seeking recreation and useful knowledge. It is not doubted that the settlements were intended to benefit their respective neighborhoods and that their work has been conducted with this end in view. But their work has at times been anything but practical, and they have been too ready to accord every absurd hobby a hearing. That a great deal of harm has <pb facs="5423969_1_0897.jpg" n="3"/>been done this way is undeniable. Professor Taylor's statement may be taken as an indication that they intend to follow a safer course in the future. It will restore, at least in a measure, public confidence in the social settlements. Their supporters and the same people of the community in general will learn with satisfaction that they are not to be run as nurseries for anarchy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
