<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-06-16">June 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Park Board Appointments</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4 (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-06-16">June 16, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">PARK BOARD APPOINTMENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Yates' long deferred selection of park commissioners has been made at last, but does not appear to have created any extraordinary enthusiasm in any part of the city. Political bosses of various hues, who desired places for their respective followers, seem to think that the Governor has cast their friends aside for the benefit of his own friends.</p>
   <p>If they are right the Governor has not strengthened himself with the machine, or machines. But that is a matter of comparatively small interest to the people at large. All the people care about is that the managements of the parks and boulevards is intrusted to honest and competent hands, and that the various interests are properly represented on the boards.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1150.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From this point of view the West Park Board at least is open to objections as it now stands. The ability of the commissioners, taken individually,may be all that could be desired; yet the board, as now made up, is rather incongruous and, in some respects,not as representative as it ought to be.</p>
   <p>A short time ago the Governor, it is understood, made a field study of the West Park District, but his appointments indicate that his visit was too brief to enable him to master the geography of this magnificent system of parks and boulevards. The Fifteenth Ward, containing Humboldt Park, is not represented at all on the board, and the same is true of the Twenty-eighth Ward, which contains all of Humboldt Park Boulevard. While the chief park and boulevard interests of the district are thus entirely unrepresented, the parkless Fourteenth Ward is favored with not less than two commissioners. Considering the ample time the Governor took to think about the matter, it would seem that he might have evolved a more equitable and reasonable distribution of the members of the board.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1151.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Looking at the matter from the viewpoint of taxpayers and the people directly concerned, the board is equally incongruous and one-sided in its makeup. The Germans are a great and good people who are entitled to have their say; but four German commissioners are too much of a good thing; it is more than fair-minded Germans can or will insist upon. The Norwegians are somewhat of a factor in this part of the city, so much, in fact, that Governor Yates would not have been within hailing distance of his ticket in Chicago if the Norwegians had cut him as did some of the other groups of voters. They are, moreover, a people who build houses and pay taxes and, generally speaking, form one of the strongest and best elements of the district. Their importance as taxpayers and residents entitles them to a place on the West Park Board, and their fairness of this claim was recognized even by the late Governor Tanner. But Governor Yates has thought differently. In administering such a deliberate slight to one of the most representative elements of the district, Governor Yates has exhibited a lack of tact and good judgment and a narrowness of view that has surprised and disappointed many of his best supporters. If he has been playing politics in this matter he may discover that he has struck some false notes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
