<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-12">Sept. 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Foggy Background</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-12">Sept. 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">FOGGY BACKGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fate of the telephone ordinance was to be decided by the City Council this afternoon. When the aldermen about half past one o'clock began to gather in the corridors of the City Hall, it was easy to note that the atmosphere was tense. And when the meeting had got underway, it was not long before the bitterest fight in the Council for many years was in full swing. Accusations were hurled back and forth, and it was not necessary to be a psychologist to realize that some of the aldermen were inclined to think that certain of their fellow members in the Council were not acting merely with the interests of the people in view. Several quite open intimations were heard that the methods used by the telephone company in gaining votes were not above reproach.</p>
   <p>One of the aldermen, a leader in the opposition against the franchise but one <pb facs="5423969_1_0616.jpg" n="2"/>who would prefer not to have his name mentioned, said to a reporter for Skandinaven:</p>
   <p>"The less said about this matter, the better. Anybody can see that things are not on the level. The friends of the ordinance will do everything possible to get the matter through today, and the haste and arbitrariness displayed are cause for thought. The opponents of the ordinance will do their utmost to prevent this franchise steal; anybody can see that if the franchise is granted in its present form, the city will be robbed of many thousands of dollars annually."</p>
   <p>At the time when Skandinaven was going to press, the fight was still at its height, with no definite indications as to who were ahead. The proponents of the ordinance thought, however, that by making a few concessions they could win over the majority of the aldermen to accede to the granting of the franchise. The opponents, under the leadership of Alderman Snow, also fought hard, however. Amendment after amendment was moved and strongly urged by the opponents of the <pb facs="5423969_1_0617.jpg" n="3"/>ordinance. Some of these amendments were significant; the only value of certain others was that they caused delay, the hope of those who made the proposals being that the City Council might become weary of the whole matter, and at such time the opponents of the franchise would unite in a motion to postpone further consideration till after the election, when the fate of the charter is to be voted on. At least twenty-five of the aldermen present spoke determinedly against the granting of a franchise at the present time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
