<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1892-12-26">Dec. 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Young People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1892-12-26">Dec. 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO YOUNG PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor, Skandinaven</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>One of your contributors writes "What greater and nobler cause can we work for than temperance!" I ask, Is there any greater cause to work for? How many homes would be happier, how many lives would be saved, if all would say the same! How often we read in the papers about people committing suicide and murder while in a fit of delirium tremens! The last piece of furniture is taken out of the house, and the best clothes sold, and that money is spent for liquor! To think such things are permitted in a civilized country like America! Oh, such shame to our country. I do not mean to say that it is only in this country. No, it is in most, if not all other countries. It is a puzzle to me why so many people drink that poisonous brew. I do not see any good in it; besides, a man knows before he begins drinking it what will follow. He knows <pb facs="5423969_1_0327.jpg" n="2"/>it will ruin his life, character, business, home, and everything else. Where he once had a place in good society, he now is found in a saloon or a gambling house. Boy, do not let the first glass fool you; do not touch it. If you do, you are sure to take the second, then the third, and so on, until at last it is too late.</p>
   <p>Now, a word to the girls: Do not marry a man who drinks liquor and do not drink liquor yourselves. Take your health, your honor, and your place in society into consideration. Another thing: do not play cards. That may not be ruinous to the health, but we all know it is to the soul. As many dollars are spent on one evening's gambling, as a person could live on for a long time. Rather buy good books for that money or give it to the poor young friends, do not drop the subject of temperance and books. Let us hear from you again, youngsters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
