<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavians for Carter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0954</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0954.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIANS FOR CARTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavians of Ward Seventeen held a meeting last Wednesday evening at 219 Grand Avenue, concerning today's primary election. The intention is to try to break the present Republican political machine, and the general opinion was that the only way to do this is to work for the election of Judge Orrin N. Carter as governor of Illinois. In the second district of Ward Seventeen, where the majority are Scandinavians, it is felt that there is no doubt the Judge Carter will get a majority of the votes cast. It was decided that the Scandinavians choose their own committeeman in order to deprive the Republican machine of its power. The Republican machine has ruled the Ward for many years. Appeal was made to all Scandinavians to vote today, and to mark their ballots for Judge Carter.</p>
   <p>The ballot for delegates show the following well-known names of Scandinavians: James Jensen, Thomas B. Fogelstad, Walter Olson, M. Paulsen, Ole P. Nordley, E. C. Christensen, F. P. Sandler, Thomas Johnson, S. Henrickson, Charles <pb facs="5423969_1_0955.jpg" n="2"/>Risberg, H. Schow, H. B. Olson, L. Carlson, M. Erickson, J. Jorgenson, Ole Amundsen, Louis Thorson, C. T. Olson, Peter O. Ellefson, J. B. Norland, M. C. Knudson, Henry Halverson, W. H. Olson, Anton Hanson, Dr. Lawson, E. Malam, August Nelson, and Chas. Gulifson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
