<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1918-03-05">Mar. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavian Voters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1918-03-05">Mar. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIAN VOTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten per cent of the population of Chicago are of Scandinavian origin. The Chicago citizens of Sweden, Denmark, and Norway are among the most prominent in all movements for civic righteousness. Some of the most active and intelligent workers for the "Dry Chicago" petition were Scandinavians. The campaign for a dry Chicago is now on. On election day, April 2, opportunity will be given to all voters to express their opinion about the saloon. Only votes will be counted; promises, resolutions, and sentiments will be of on value on election day. Only the ballot will count. A cross after "Yes" will be the only real indication of a voter's interest in the cause. It is not too much to say that this vote will be the most valuable which any man or woman can cast in his life. It will be of immense value in the movement for a dry nation.</p>
   <p>No one will be able to vote unless he is registered, and the only opportunity <pb facs="5423969_1_0337.jpg" n="2"/>to register before election day is on March 12. On that day all precinct polling places will be open for registration. Scandinavian-American citizens, both men and women, who have been in the state one year, in the county ninety days, and in the precinct thirty days, may register. Those who registered at the last general registration and who have not moved will not have to register again. As the Central Registration Law has been declared null and void by the Supreme Court, we are advising all voters who registered in the City Mall or in the district in February, to register again on March 12. Many names have been stricken off the registration lists. Examine the list of your precinct and make sure your name is on it. Many drys will be disappointed on election day because their names have been left off.</p>
   <p>It is estimated that there are thousands of unregistered dry Scandinavian women in the city, and you can readily see that these women can carry the <pb facs="5423969_1_0338.jpg" n="3"/>election. In a time when our boys are willing to die for the preservation of democracy in the world, it is surely the duty of every patriotic Scandinavian-American to be eligible to vote, and vote dry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
