<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-28">Feb. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Prices and Trusts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-28">Feb. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">PRICES AND TRUSTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prices are high and living expenses are difficult to meet. Anyone who has a family to take care of is aware of this situation, and every housewife knows how difficult the situation is, if she is among those who have to try to "stretch" the amounts that are coming in. When times are good, the impact of high prices is felt less, for in good times the income is also higher. In such times all prices rise. Good times and high prices are really but "different names of the same thing". Such, at least, has been the story under normal conditions.</p>
   <p>But the situation has changed. For more than a year now, we have had poor times; yet the prices have remained high, and for many families the matter of making ends meet has been a most difficult one. What explanation is to be found for the present condition?</p>
   <p>Experts explain that a large part of the blame must be placed on trusts-- <pb facs="5423969_1_0606.jpg" n="2"/>capital trusts, and labor trusts as well. Both of these drive the prices up, and the consumer must pay. In the cotton industry the old conditions are still prevailing. There is no trust in the industry.....Cotton prices, therefore, have been reasonable.</p>
   <p>On most other goods prices are unnaturally high because capital and labor, each in its sphere, demand too much. Even many farm products....are being made unnecessarily expensive to the consumer because the market is controlled by trusts which do not pay any too much to the producers, the farmers, but drain the consumer as completely as possible. If, now, the farmers of the country go ahead organizing the contemplated trust in farm products, the result will necessarily be that people will find it next to impossible to raise the money required to pay for the farm products. In other words, living will be made difficult, if not impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
