<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian Instruction in Our Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-08-28">Aug. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN INSTRUCTION IN OUR SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is probably known to the Norwegians in Chicago that the only high school in the city where instruction in Norwegian is given, is the Carl Schurz School on Milwaukee Avenue. In 1913 Norwegian was introduced as an elective course, and since that time nearly four-hundred pupils have studied Norwegian. The instruction in Norwegian is based on a four year course. So far, however, most of the pupils have pursued only part of the course; only a few have completed it.</p>
   <p>During the last term of the past school year there were five classes in Norwegian, with a total pupil number of 156. This exceeds all expectations, but gives no cause for taking things easy now, in the matter, expecting that the Norwegian language be able to take care of itself now, as it were.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0224.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First of all it must be remembered that throughout the high schools, for one reason or other the number of pupils each year dropping out of a course averages twenty-five per cent of the pupil number. Many of the pupils in the Norwegian course were of the graduating class who will, of course, not be members of the school next year. But in addition, the condition brought about by the war will undoubtedly prevent many pupils from continuing their course in Norwegian. It is therefore necessary that all those who are interested in maintaining instruction in Norwegian make as strong an effort as possible to make new pupils take up the study.</p>
   <p>The largest group in America of Norwegian ancestry is in Chicago, 75,000 strong. There are about thirty-five to forty Norwegian congregations and seventy-five to eighty Norwegian societies or lodges. There is a political daily paper, two weeklies, three or four religious weeklies, a magazine for the young people, and several minor papers, all in the Norwegian language. Considering this back-ground something worthwhile ought to be attainable in Norwegian instruction in the schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0225.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At least 2,000 children of Norwegian parentage are frequenting the high schools in Chicago. In them must be awakened the interest for Norwegian language, Norwegian literature, Norwegian culture. The impetus for this interest must be started in the home. Then the ministers and other interested members of the Norwegian congregations can do much to create interest for study of the language. Finally the various lodges and societies within the Norwegian colony can exercise strong influence for the study of the parental tongue.</p>
   <p>We urge all the Norwegians in Chicago who are interested in the instruction in Norwegian language to seek to influence boys and girls intending to enter high school this fall to seek admission at the Carl Schurz high school, and to join the Norwegian classes there. Pupils from any part of the city may be transferred to this school if they intend to study Norwegian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
