<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-08-01">Aug. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Woman at the Helm</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-01">Aug. 1, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A WOMAN AT THE HELM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Board of Education has elected a woman, Ella Young, as superintendent of the public schools in Chicago. Long has the Board been searching for the right man for the job. Many prominent educators in other cities as well as in Chicago were considered.</p>
   <p>The Board first came to the conclusion that it would not be advisable to take an out-of-town man for the job. Chicago has tried men from other cities before, and the results have not been so very good. When this had been decided, it did not take long to come to an agreement. It was soon evident that among the Chicago candidates, Mrs. Ella Young was the strongest; therefore she was unanimously chosen.</p>
   <p>The general opinion in Chicago seems to be that the Board has made a good selection. Ella Young had had long experience in the service of the schools, <pb facs="5423969_1_0053.jpg" n="2"/>and is known in wide circles for her broad knowledge and her ability. The children and youth in the Chicago schools, together with their teachers, constitute a sort of an empire all by itself. To be the leader of this broad realm, with thousands of teachers and hundreds of thousands of children, demands great qualities of leadership. As the principal of the Normal School, Ella Young has shown that she possesses the capacity for leadership to an unusual degree. This woman has quite as much, or more, grit in her make-up as any of the men who were considered for the position.</p>
   <p>The great majority of teachers in our city are, as we know, women. The female teachers have of late created considerable trouble. They have formed a union where radical and immature opinions have only too often held sway. Now and then, one would get the impression that complete anarchy has been ruling among the teachers of our schools. Former superintendents have had their hands full with the task of keeping order among the talkative and aggressive teachers. There is reason to believe that a vigorous woman such as Ella Young will be able to govern them better than any man, for she knows them better.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0054.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In addition, at a time when there is need of constant vigilance against the school-book trust, one may have full confidence in Mrs. Ella Young. She knows that in her appointment the ability of women as administrators is under scrutiny, and one may feel reasonably confident that she will do her best to show that a woman is able to take care of such duties as well as a man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
