<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-10-23">Oct. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Norwegian-Danish Typographical Union</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Anniversary Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2) (Danish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-10-23">Oct. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NORWEGIAN-DANISH TYPOGRAPHICAL UNION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Anniversary Banquet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Norwegian-Danish Typographical Union celebrated its tenth anniversary last Sunday with a banuqet in the rooms of the Union in Nora Hall.</p>
   <p>At about six o'clock in the evening the members began to arrive at the large hall, which was beautifully decorated for the occasion with flags, and with the emblem of the Union over the president's chair. In the dining room Mrs. Harold Larsen had decorated the tables with palms and flowers.</p>
   <p>At seven o'clock, Mr. H. Stockset, chairman of the committee on arrangements, welcomed the assembled union members, and shortly afterwards Mr. J. P. Jacobsen, president of the Union, delivered the speech in honor of the day. He said among other things: "The unions have, during the past few years, accomplished more for the workers in improving their conditions than could have been accomplished by any other method. Through co-operation for their <pb facs="5423969_1_0755.jpg" n="2"/>mutual benefit, the unions have taught their members to understand and feel that selfishness is something to shun and watch out for, because there is nothing which so degrades men as selfishness. The unions teach their members that there must be equal rights for all and no rights without obligations. The unions develop more intelligent workers and real freemen, in that the unions understand that a wrong perpetrated against one member is an insult against all. The members carry in their minds and behavior the insignia of real unionism."</p>
   <p>The speaker concluded with a wish for long life to the Norwegian-Danish Typographical Union, and received warm applause. Mr. Alfred Bjornback spoke in honor of Norway; Mr. James Endresen, in honor of Denmark, and Mr. Bernhard Svendsen in honor of America.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lauritz Eriksen read some poems written by himself and Mr. R. Strom sang a ditty written by Mr. C. Koch, which created general merriment. Then a general <pb facs="5423969_1_0756.jpg" n="3"/>call for speeches was made and many responded.</p>
   <p>Mr. P. C. Pedersen thanked the committee on arrangements for the pleasant banquet.</p>
   <p>Afterwards the punch bowl was brought out, and everybody had a good time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
