<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1879-04-22">Apr. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Compulsory Schooling in Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0105.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1879-04-22">Apr. 22, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">COMPULSORY SCHOOLING IN ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the face of certain ignorant howlers who assert that compulsory schooling is tyranny and a violation of personal liberty, the House of Representatives of the Illinois Legislature has, with 87 to 48 votes, adopted the resolution proposed by Representative Moses Wentworth, making school attendance compulsory in Illinois.</p>
   <p>According to this bill, parents and guardians of a child between 8 and 14 years of age, are compelled to send it to a public or private school for at least twelve weeks a year. An exception is made if the distance from the child's home to the nearest school is more than 1 1/2 miles.</p>
   <p>No person or business firm is permitted to keep a child under 14 years of age working during the school term, and furthermore, it is unlawful to employ such a child for more than fourteen weeks a year. The fine for violation of this latter regulation is from $20 to $50, which is to be collected <pb facs="5423969_1_0106.jpg" n="2"/>by the president or some other member of the school commission, and the fine goes to the treasury of the district schools. If the school commission is notified that a child is unable to procure the necessary text books, it can requisition such books and charge them to the treasury.</p>
   <p>Parents and guardians who fail to send children to school are fined from to $5 to $10, which fine also goes to the treasury of the school district.</p>
   <p>These are the chief provisions of the bill. The proposed term, twelve weeks a year for six years, seventy-two weeks in all, is of course much too short, but in a case of this kind it must certainly be said that something is better than nothing, and we sincerely hope that the Senate will also have the courage to vote for this bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
