<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-02-24">Feb. 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Foreigners and Wife Desertion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-02-24">Feb. 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">FOREIGNERS AND WIFE DESERTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A recent issue of Co-operation, a leaflet published by the Chicago Bureau of Charities, presents some significant facts relating to wife desertion in Chicago and other cities. Upwards of two thousand families in Chicago were deserted by their breadwinners last year, and similar conditions appear to exist in other large cities. Considering the alarming proportions and the distressing consequences of this evil, there should be no hesitancy or delay in adopting effective measures for its abatement.</p>
   <p>As to the causes of the evil, three differing opinions are expressed. One holds that the proportion of desertions to population is not increasing, but that a more thorough study of conditions is bringing the facts into new prominence. Another holds that laxity in marriage and divorce laws is begetting a widespread disregard of family ties and obligations, and that the <pb facs="5423969_1_0386.jpg" n="2"/>remedy lies in stricter laws and their rigid enforcement. The third opinion maintains that the influx of large numbers of ignorant foreigners is responsible for an abnormal increase of the evil. It is asserted that these persons coming from countries in which marriage and divorce laws are extremely restrictive, are subject to a moral reaction which converts liberty into license. The holders of this opinion believe in the enactment of more rigid laws but place their faith chiefly in the educational value of our churches, schools, and other republican institutions.</p>
   <p>The contention of those who hold to the third opinion appears to receive support in the fact that an extremely large proportion of desertions is reported among certain classes of foreigners who have not been long in America and who formerly lived under conditions of great severity.</p>
   <p>The Bureau of Charities is in a position to ascertain the facts in the matter and ought to do it. Legislation cannot provide a remedy that will cure until the disease is fully and reliably diagnosed. It may be a great convenience <pb facs="5423969_1_0387.jpg" n="3"/>to saddle our social ills upon the "ignorant foreigners," but the scapegoat policy is one of doubtful wisdom; it does not go to the root of the evil, and hence, can effect no cure.</p>
   <p>The Bureau says that "an extremely large proportion of desertions is reported among certain classes of foreigners who have not been long in America, and who formerly lived under conditions of great severity". This statement is altogether too general. Who are the "certain classes of foreigners" referred to? Do these classes include immigrants from all lands or only from certain countries? The Bureau ought to furnish a definite and specific statement. As it now stands the charge may be construed to include all foreign-born fellow citizens. All immigrants are "ignorant foreigners," notwithstanding the well-established fact that there is practically no illiteracy in such countries as Norway, Denmark, Sweden, Finland, Germany, Switzerland, and Holland, while we have a great deal more illiteracy than we need even in such states as Illinois and Massachusetts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0388.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In those countries of Europe that are the sources of the greater part of our foreign-born population, desertion is much less common than in the United States, partly because the marriage relations and family ties are held more sacred there than here. When they come to this country the "ignorant foreigners" are astounded and shocked at the formidable grist of our divorce mills. Those of weak moral fiber are undoubtedly influenced to some extent by the general laxity prevailing here in such matters. But the great majority hold fast to their old views and to their wives and children. Moreover, it stands to reason that a husband and father who moves his family across the ocean in quest of a better and more comfortable home in a strange land is not very apt to desert them when he has reached his destination. Of course there are exceptions, especially among "certain classes". Let it be known who constitutes these classes. The Bureau of Charities can supply the information and ought to do it. Full light upon the subject is necessary to guide the steps of the legislature, and may, incidentally, relieve some "ignorant foreigners" of the undeserved odium of a rather sweeping charge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
