<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-02">Dec. 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">President Irwin's Veto</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-12-02">Dec. 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT IRWIN'S VETO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In vetoing the town's appropriation order passed by the County Board, President Irwin forced a clique of taxeaters into a position where they must choose between surrender and open warfare upon the taxpayers. If they submit, about $150,000 will be lost to the fund grabbers but saved for the people. If they decide to fight the veto they will invite the attention of every taxpayer to the following passage in Mr. Irwin's veto message:</p>
   <p>"My reason for this action is a simple one. It is because such allowance by the County Board of any sum of money whatever for town purposes, under existing law, is wilful waste of the people's money and a vicious disregard of the rights of the taxpayers and property owners of this great county. It is an outrage that this community must support numerous crews of legal highwaymen who render no service whatever to the people and whose only claim to <pb facs="5423969_1_1117.jpg" n="2"/>excessive salaries is the one fact that they are efficient workers in the dirty politics that must needs be amply rewarded by fat jobs."</p>
   <p>This is strong language; yet few taxpayers will regard it too strong. There can be no doubt but that the attempted grab would be "a wilful waste of the people's money and a vicious disregard of the rights of the taxpayers and property owners".</p>
   <p>Even if his veto should be set aside President Irwin has performed a valuable service to the community. His action must arouse even the indifferent and sluggish voters to a realization of the outrageous conditions they have permitted to exist, and will thus hasten the final wiping out of a wasteful and vicious system with its brood of public barnacles. The taxeaters of the towns who suddenly find themselves bereft of a lot of handsome Christmas presents in the form of fat rolls of public money may choose to fight; but the best they can hope for is a Pyrrhic victory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
