<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-28">Mar. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The City Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-28">Mar. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the coming city election in Chicago two officials are to be elected on the general ballot--the city treasurer and the city clerk.</p>
   <p>For treasurer the Republicans have nominated one of the best known men in Chicago, Isaac N. Powell. Powell has been the secretary of the board of election commissioners for fourteen years. In this capacity he has taken care of his duties in a manner that has won general appreciation. He is an energetic worker, and he has needed all his energy to deal with the intricacies of the administration of the board of election office.</p>
   <p>As secretary of the board, he also has displayed unusual tact and impartiality, which all parties have been equally ready to acknowledge. The good will he has gained as secretary of the election board will undoubtedly serve him well <pb facs="5423969_1_0939.jpg" n="2"/>at the election. The Republicans will vote for him in solid numbers, and he will undoubtedly win considerable support from voters of other parties. It can hardly be doubted that Isaac N. Powell will become the next city treasurer of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Republican candidate for city clerk, Mr. Jacob H. Marks, was born in Chicago and has always lived here. He resides with his family in the Seventeenth Ward and is well liked by all who know him. During the past four years he has been secretary of the county board, a position which is somewhat similar to that of city clerk. It will thus be observed that he is familiar with the kind of work which he will have to do as city clerk. Skandinaven believes that the voters will do well in voting for Mr. Marks as well as for Mr. Powell.</p>
   <p>The aldermanic election is causing sharp controversies in several wards. In the Seventeenth Ward, Mr. Lewis D. Sitts is sure of being re-elected, and he deserves re-election. In so far as the affairs of the Ward are concerned, Mr. Sitts, ever since he became a member of the City Council, has done the <pb facs="5423969_1_0940.jpg" n="3"/>work of two men--the work Mr. Dever ought to have done as well as his own work. As things are, the Seventeenth Ward simply cannot afford to dismiss Sitts. The voters know this, and Sitts will be elected.</p>
   <p>The Republicans of the Fifteenth Ward have nominated Henry Upatel. The worst his opponent has to say about Mr. Upatel is that he is a Lutheran, and that he opposes Sunday baseball games. There is no comparison between Upatel and Kruger, his opponent. All intelligent voters who do not consider voting a joke, but seek the good of the Ward and the city, will support Upatel.</p>
   <p>In the Thirty-fifth Ward Mr. Race has quite a fight on his hands. He has done a good job, however, and deserves to be re-elected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
