<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-11-18">Nov. 18, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Divorce--A National Sin</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-11-18">Nov. 18, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">DIVORCE--A NATIONAL SIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bishop Samuel Fallows has treated the divorce problem in an article in which, among other things, he shows that the increase in the number of divorces in the United States is twice as large as the increase in population. In seven states, the divorce rate has increased, on the average, from one for every twenty marriages to one for every seven. Illinois heads the list because of the large number of divorces taking place annually in Chicago.</p>
   <p>There are three thousand divorce courts in the United States. In 1890 these courts granted divorces to 35,000 applicants. During the period 1867 to 1886,322,716 people were granted divorces. The number of children whose future was affected by these divorces was given as 267,739. Since, however, there were 140,810 cases in which the applicants made no mention of children, the actual number of children affected by divorce was probably far in excess of that mentioned above.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The main causes of divorce are hasty, slightly considered marriages and inability or unwillingness to realize the seriousness and sacredness of the marriage relation. The fact that divorces are so common also contributes greatly to an increase in their number. Children brought up in an atmosphere of casual acceptance of divorce are not to be blamed much if, when grown up, they have ill-defined conceptions of virtue and morals and the sacredness of marriage.</p>
   <p>The divorce court is the first thought of a dissatisfied man or woman. Only rarely is divorce considered a last resort, after insufferable abuse has been endured. Cases of this kind are few. The public seldom hears of them.</p>
   <p>After careful consideration one is forced to the conclusion that the great majority of this vast number of divorces have their cause in the indifferent attitude of the people. Some couples obtain a divorce only to regret it later on and remarry. This proves that the divorce was ill-considered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0391.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every case of divorce conceals a tale of human suffering and despair. Divorce signifies the abandonment of hope, the disruption of life's most sacred union. Rightly Bishop Fallows exclaims: "Destroy the family and you destroy the state." The mania for divorce is one of our national sins.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
