<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-01-19">Jan. 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">To Scandinavian Mothers, Wives, and Daughters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-01-19">Jan. 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">TO SCANDINAVIAN MOTHERS, WIVES, AND DAUGHTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[An appeal to our Scandinavian women by the Women's Christian Temperance Union.]</p>
   <p>As we cannot talk face to face, this article is written in the hope that we may come to a closer understanding and be mutually helpful in our plans for the welfare of our homes and beloved ones--those for whom we are responsible.</p>
   <p>We are continually anxious for their health, good name, and social standing. We rise early and use all our skill to secure the best of everything for them. Often our self-denial for their sake tends to make them selfish.</p>
   <p>Have we given due thought to the influence of this upon our own spirits and our children's characters?</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0324.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We say that clean cellars, orderly closets, and neatly wrapped bundles in the store chest are better proofs of good housekeeping than lace-trimmed windows or embroidered pillows. Shall we not be just as searching in the care of the thoughts, words, and habits with which our children live?</p>
   <p>What do they talk about in the playground, when they run errands, or when they go to bed at night? What games please them most? What do they do with their pennies? These are not matters that properly take care of themselves. If the ankles are a little weak, we put on a brace; if the eyes are defective we buy carefully fitted glasses. Shall we neglect the little virtues not yet deeply rooted, or the fickle conscience that has little knowledge and less wisdom?</p>
   <p>Let us consider these things, and counsel together on the ways in which we can best do our work and gain the highest reward of motherhood! Some of us have done so for years. The Women's Christian Temperance Union is <pb facs="5423969_1_0325.jpg" n="3"/>organized sisterhood and motherhood. No one, so far, who has lost sight of virture, home, or hope, can say that the W. C. T. U. does not hold out a hand to him. No one seeking to help others can fail to find a method in the W. C. T. U's program of work. Our needs are the same as yours; our conditions the same. Let us unite in planning and working with increased strength.</p>
   <p>This paper will reach many who know of the W. C. T. U. meetings through friends and neighbors. This is written to give such people, and all others who may not know of our work, a cordial invitation to attend any W. C. T. U. meeting you may know of; to add your strength to ours, and ours to yours, in all such work in which women may engage, in the service of humanity, home, and country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
