<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-08">Aug. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">No Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0803</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0803.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-08">Aug. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">NO STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A streetcar strike in a city such as Chicago would be a calamity for the city and for everybody living within the city. Nobody desires that sort of a fight. The companies fear the strike; their workers would by far prefer not to have to strike, and the people of the city are, of course, opposed to any interruption of the regular traffic.</p>
   <p>When, in spite of this, the workers so overwhelmingly voted to go on strike as a last means of obtaining an increase in wages, they no doubt decided that they owed it to their families to make the sacrifice involved, in order to obtain, if possible, somewhat better working conditions. It is significant that the wives of the streetcar workers, according to what we have learned, are supporting their husbands in their attitude. As a rule, the wife of a worker will oppose everything which, even for a brief period, <pb facs="5423969_1_0804.jpg" n="2"/>would deprive her of an income however scanty. When these wives and mothers find that it is better to risk a fight, the reason must be that they cannot get along on the present wages of their providers.</p>
   <p>As everybody knows, prices have risen steadily during the past few years, and this rise in prices has hit the necessities of life hardest. Nor are there any prospects of relief in the near future. It is true that times are good in general, but there is no probability that prices will drop. Meat, milk, butter, and eggs, and nearly all other necessary commodities will remain at the present high price level. And the recent revision of the tariff does not indicate that any noticeable reduction in prices on articles affected by the customs duties is forthcoming.</p>
   <p>These conditions affecting the cost of living lend strength to the demands of the workers. We are facing facts which neither the traction companies nor anybody else can deny or disregard. Fortunately, there are signs that <pb facs="5423969_1_0805.jpg" n="3"/>the dispute may be settled by agreement. The companies prefer such an arrangement, and so do the workers. In addition, the city is a party to the dispute, and the city authorities are doing their utmost to prevent the strike. The state arbitration board has taken steps to get the matter settled through arbitration.</p>
   <p>These various efforts, in addition to the general desire to avoid a disastrous struggle, have, so to speak, paved the way for a peaceable solution of the disagreement, and there is strong reason to believe that the peace negotiations may produce successful results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
