<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-27">Jan. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Inspection of Foods</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-01-27">Jan. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">INSPECTION OF FOODS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the present session of Congress, Senator McCumber and Congressman Gronna of North Dakota have resumed their efforts in behalf of federal inspection of foods. The proposal has been recommended for adoption by the appropriate committee in the Senate.</p>
   <p>As matters are now there is no uniform system of inspection and grading of foods. The gradation scale may be different in different states for the same type of produce, as is the case with wheat, for example. This is a great hindrance to commerce and trade, especially with foreign countries, and the loss as a rule hits our farmers. The proposal by McCumber will correct this evil by assigning the task of inspection to the Federal Government, which would then establish a uniform scale of gradation for the various kinds of produce.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would seem logical for all the dealers in produce to support this proposal since uniform inspection would make buying and selling easier. Yet the National Board of Trade, which recently met in Washington, adopted a resolution opposing the McCumber proposal. It is, however, quite significant that the main arguments against the proposal were of a political nature. It was pointed out that the proposed measure would be unconstitutional, and in addition, the cry of centralization was raised.</p>
   <p>This scarecrow, however, does not frighten people as much as before. The people are no longer afraid that the government will devour individual liberty. If there is anything which the Federal Government can do better than the separate states, it is generally conceded that it is wiser to leave it to the Federal Government; for this is, in any event, better than having the matter taken care of badly or not at all.</p>
   <p>The resolution adopted by the National Board of Trade against the McCumber <pb facs="5423969_1_0609.jpg" n="3"/>proposal is in reality a proof of the value and the timeliness of the McCumber plan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
