<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1900-04-23">Apr. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Mother Tongue</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Halvor Hanson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-23">Apr. 23, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE MOTHER TONGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Halvor Hanson</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the columns for the young people I see an article on more English and less Norwegian. Mr. Thompson says that "the Scandinavians of this country should abandon the habit of speaking in the Scandinavian languages and only speak English".</p>
   <p>I do not agree with Mr. Thompson in this. It would not seem right for us Scandinavians to discard our mother tongue. The young Scandinavians of this country use their own language too little now; in fact, some of them seem ashamed to be a Scandinavian or to talk the language; and many of them will not use their old mother tongue unless they have to.</p>
   <p>I cannot understand why Scandinavians should not speak their own language among themselves, in their homes or in their gatherings, whenever there are none but <pb facs="5423969_1_0472.jpg" n="2"/>Scandinavians present. It is all right to speak English when people are present who cannot understand any other language; but when it comes to being ashamed of speaking our own language among ourselves, then I think matters are going too far.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thompson says that we should not use any language but English in the home, in church, in the parlor, or in the fields. If we could not use the Scandinavian languages in any of those places, I do not quite see where we could use it at all. To most of our young people the home is the only place where they have the chance to learn to speak and read a Scandinavian language, and if the parents do not speak these languages the children cannot learn them.</p>
   <p>I would not say that our young people cannot get along without learning Scandinavian languages, but certainly the knowledge of them will come in handy many a time. Besides, we ought to know something about the language our forefathers used, no matter what language it be.</p>
   <p>I, for one, hold that our young people ought to study the Scandinavian languages in their homes, while they have the opportunity to do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
