<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1901-01-06">Jan. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Mammonizing Education</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-01-06">Jan. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">MAMMONIZING EDUCATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The University of Chicago begins the new year with a substantial addition to its holdings of securities. For some time it has been the happy owner of a goodly slice of Standard Oil stock, and now large blocks of railway stock have been added to the pile. John D. Rockefeller tendered the university a Christmas gift of $1,500,000 to be paid in cash or securities at the option of the board of trustees. After considering the matter the board elected to take $500,000 in cash, $500,000 in stock of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, and $500,000 in stock of the Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railway. A million dollars worth of gilt-edge securities is no mean addition to the fat funds of this school.</p>
   <p>Dr. Harper has established a unique record as a money beggar. Whenever he thinks he needs a few million dollars he beams upon a select circle of millionaires <pb facs="5423969_1_0079.jpg" n="2"/>and multimillionaires and generally gets what he wants. His reputation as a wise and prudent financial manager is likewise well established. The Baltimore and Ohio and the Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railways have no cause to regret that their securities pass into the control of gentlemen like Dr. Harper. His voice and vote will not be used to the prejudice of the properties. A gentleman who has pocketed, without public protest, dividends of eighty per cent on the Standard Oil stock owned by his university, will have no fault to find with stiff railroad tariffs, no matter what common folks may think or say.</p>
   <p>That giant trusts and large railway corporations are benefited when such institutions of learning as the University of Chicago become interested in their welfare admits of no doubt. It is no less plain that our youth and society at large are not benefited by such a close alliance between higher education and corporate wealth. All honor to him who helps to build schools, colleges, and universities, whether he be rich or poor, and whether his offering be large or small. No one will deny that the magnificent gifts for educational purposes of <pb facs="5423969_1_0080.jpg" n="3"/>such men as Rockefeller, Carnegie, and many others, are prompted by a fine public spirit and a most generous liberality. We may even admit that the contributions are made without any desire to influence the teachings of the schools whose coffers they fill, and yet it cannot be denied that they restrict that perfect freedom of thought and teaching which is the very soul of learning and investigation along scientific lines. The subtle influence of wealth will make itself felt in the choice of the presidents and teachers of the millionaire-made universities as well as in arbitrary limitations upon their liberty of economic thought. That this is no idle theorizing, but cold fact, is attested by the dismissal during the latter years of several professors for the alleged socialistic tendencies of their views in economics and social science.</p>
   <p>Nor is this surprising. A trust-made school like the University of Chicago will give a trust flavor to its teaching of every subject bearing upon relations between the people and corporate wealth. But such schools are a doubtful blessing to society. Their tendency is to enlist our brightest young men <pb facs="5423969_1_0081.jpg" n="4"/>and women in the ranks of wealth and equip them for service in the war between wealth and the people.</p>
   <p>In our rejoicings over the rapid growth of our higher institutions of learning we should not forget that liberty is the foundation of all true and wholesome education, nor should we permit corporate wealth to mammonize the higher education of the country. Opinions differ as to the effects of the trusts, but we may all agree that an educational trust would be a curse to the people and a still greater curse to their children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
