<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Vote the Socialist Party Ticket]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[VOTE THE SOCIALIST PARTY TICKET]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign for the coming primary election is in full swing. Candidates are more than busy (especially those desiring the mayor's billet) peddling the usual bombastic jargon of their so-called "platforms." On the Democratic side we have Harrison, Dunne, and Graham, and not one of them has yet made an intelligent statement or advanced a single good reason why he should be nominated. Neither have they advertised their own accomplishments; this modesty is due to the present mistrust of "big politicians" within the party ranks.</p>
   <p>The only Republican candidate worthy of mention is Charles E. Merriam, alderman of the seventh ward and professor of social economics at the University of Chicago. His platform is for "capable administration of the city's affairs in every department," a laudable aim at any time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0462.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Socialist party presents as candidate for mayor a printer named Rodriguez. His platform is that of the Socialist party throughout the world:</p>
   <p>"The powers of government must be placed in the hands of the worker in order that he may enjoy the benefits which result from his efforts."</p>
   <p>Certainly no voter who works for a living can find a legitimate objection to the ideals and the program of the working-man's party. Nor can any voter object to Charles Merriam's platform, since a capable administration of affairs, city state, and national, is the foundation on which government must be built in order that the phrase "government by the people" may regain its original meaning and not continue to be used as a synonym for graft, corruption, and ignorant, inefficent officeholders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
