<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1898-02-01">Feb. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Order of the Crown</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-02-01">Feb. 1, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORDER OF THE CROWN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Order of the Crown, recently established in the heart of American "blue blooddom," is destined to supply a long-felt want. We have in this country a number of people who can trace their pedigrees back to royal mistresses, more or less infamous. Up to the present time, these denizens of noble blood have been compelled to associate with the common herd in this turbulent democracy of ours, and their sensibilities have been most woefully lacerated in consequence. But their patience and forbearance are exhausted at last. They can stand it no longer. They propose to put a stop to a condition of things which compels them to mingle with common folks. From now on, they are going to flock by themselves in a sacred and exclusive fold -- the Order of the Crown, which ordinary mortals will be permitted to admire but not to enter.</p>
   <p>Nothing could be more timely or nice in every way. Of course, to all genuine descendants of royal mistresses, it is a matter of deep regret that they live in a country which presumes to struggle along without kings or nobility, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0490.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But if we cannot have the genuine "crown" article, we can get up an imitation and that is exactly what the knights and ladies of the Order of the Crown have undertaken to do. It would be preposterous to question their success. There can be no doubt that they will get up something that will be as nice as nice can be.</p>
   <p>It may be a surprise to some of these knights and ladies -- but; nevertheless, it is a fact -- that their noble undertaking has aroused the greatest enthusiasm among the Scandinavians, all of whom have royal blood in their veins. In earlier times, the Scandinavian countries were abundantly supplied with kings; in fact, their crop of kings was so large that they were able to furnish rulers to Russia, France, England, Sicily, Ireland, and other countries, and still retain all they needed for home consumption. Norway at one time could boast of no less than some thirty kings, while Sweden and Denmark had in proportion as many more. Every promontory was adorned with a royal castle, and every valley had its own royal court. Those rulers generally were men with large families. Their sons and daughters intermarried with sturdy yeomanry, and in the course of time the whole nation became permeated with royal blood-- became, so to speak <pb facs="5423969_1_0491.jpg" n="3"/>thoroughly royalized in blood. This is true of all the Scandinavian countries. It would be extremely difficult to find a Dane, a Swede, or a Norwegian, either in the old country or in America, who cannot trace his lineage back to some proud king.</p>
   <p>It was, therefore, natural that the founding of the Order of the Crown should be hailed with joy among the Scandinavians here. It is true that there is a difference between them and our knights and ladies of royal blood in the East, inasmuch as the Scandinavians have received their blue blood through the channel of lawful wedlock. However, for the good of the cause and for the sake of unity of action, they will probably refrain from pointing out this difference. It is even probable that they will consent to a special restriction upon their voting power in the new society, lest they may completely engulf the Eastern contingent. This they have no desire to do! they have no disposition whatever to hog all the honors of royal blood in this land. They have enough to spare and hence are perfectly willing to let others enjoy their full share.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0492.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But one thing is inevitable: the Order of the Crown will follow the course of empire; its seat of power must be transferred to the West, where the majority of the Scandinavians live. So what would be more proper than to make Chicago the capitol of the new order? Ah! When will we have the first royal court here?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
