<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-04">Apr. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Refutation of Claim of Superiority of Norwegian Sailors</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor by S. Nelson)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-04-04">Apr. 4, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">REFUTATION OF CLAIM OF SUPERIORITY OF NORWEGIAN SAILORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor by S. Nelson)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the weekly Skandinaven of January 10, I read an article signed A. Evensen. The article appears to be intended as a reply to an earlier article by Mr. Olaf Ray, an article which I have not read.</p>
   <p>I have read considerably, but I do not remember ever to have read anything quite as boastful as the article by Mr. Evensen. He starts by boasting of the Norwegian sailors (himself included). They are the best, the most reliable men on earth, according to him, everywhere preferred, even to the natives of the countries in question.</p>
   <p>It may be that Mr. Evensen has heard statements made, similar to the one above, during his twenty-five years at sea, but I much doubt that he has experienced such preference of the Norwegian sailors. I started as a sailor in 1849, and I have not been aware, in English ships, of any greater preference given to Norwegian sailors than to German sailors, French sailors, etc. The opportunities for the English youth for earning their living ashore are so great that only a <pb facs="5423969_1_0474.jpg" n="2"/>small percentage of the young men choose the sea and sailing for their vocation. Yet the enormous British navy must have men for the ships; for this reason men are accepted from whatever country they may be obtained. As regards the question of gratitude to England one need merely mention that English money built the first railroad in Norway; it built the first plant for illuminating gas; it has opened a number of industries in the country; Englishmen are traveling widely through the country spending money, and so on.</p>
   <p>In Skandinaven for January 24, I find an article by Mr. Olaf Ray, which I would applaud and endorse in every way. He calls attention to the fact that the English have performed the same type of service in Africa as they did in Norway. English capital has buildt railroads, discovered and developed gold mines, brought to the country machinery worth millions of dollars, and from Africa, England is receiving the same type of gratitude as is evidenced by Mr. Evensen.</p>
   <p>Let me refer to the article by Mr. J. M. Johnson, published in the same issue <pb facs="5423969_1_0475.jpg" n="3"/>of the paper. Suppose Mr. Evensen and Mr. Johnson had come to America to take farms; that they were working hard, developing the land and were successful. Suppose now, that the American government were to refuse the settlers the right to citizenship, saying in effect: "It is required of you foreigners that you pay taxes; we, however, will rule the country." Would Messrs, Evensen and Johnson like being treated in such a manner? Would they submit supinely, or would they protest? The situation in South Africa furnishes a parallel to the situation here posited.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
