<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1893-03-25">Mar. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[Harrison for Mayor]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1893-03-25">Mar. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[HARRISON FOR MAYOR]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavians want someone from the west-side for Mayor, a man like Sam Allerton is not fit for the job. People who live on the west-side presume that they too have rights which should be respected. They know that they will receive fair and equitable treatment at the hands of Carter Harrison, but they have precious little confidence in Sam Allerton not that we are inclined to be unreasonable, on the contrary a more patient and long suffering set of people is not to be found anywhere in this broad land. We have suffered wrongs for innumerable years without murmur and have permitted the smallest sections of the city to name the Mayor for several terms in succession. But our patience has reached its limit. We draw the line at Allerton.</p>
   <p>A man who never deigned to put his feet on the west-side until he appeared in these parts as a vote begger and who knows even less about this part of the city than about English grammar, if such a thing be possible, is <pb facs="5423969_1_0969.jpg" n="2"/>not fit to be Mayor of Chicago. The south-side contains all the millionaires, club nobles, union leaguers, silk stockings, the office-holding coterie, and the grand dinners. The brains and brawn are found on the west-side and the bulk of the vote is cast in the northwestern sections of the city. For once they want a man as a Mayor who knows all about the whole city and who has the courage and ability to run the silk-stockings as well as the thugs. They know Sam Allerton is not that kind of a man, while Harrison is.This is the reason the west-side is going to roll up a tremendous vote for Carter Harrison.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
