<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-11">July 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lowden's Difficult Task</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1917-07-11">July 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LOWDEN'S DIFFICULT TASK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Refers to the war time riots at East St. Louis during which more than one-hundred Negroes were killed.)</p>
   <p>Long years will pass before Illinois will be able to obliterate the nasty blot of scandal by which East St. Louis has soiled the good name of our state. The scandal is worse than the one we remember from Springfield a few years ago, and even that is not quite cleared off yet.</p>
   <p>Of course there will be investigations to determine where to put the blame for the disgraceful occurence at East St. Louis. Governor Lowden must see to it that this is done. And he must see to it that the guilty lawless element, be given to feel the full force of the law. He must establish a precedent which will for all time, compel respect for law and for those whose function is to execute the laws. It is quite clear that it will be no easy task, cleaning the political Augias stable which <pb facs="5423969_1_1058.jpg" n="2"/>evidently exists. But the cleaning must be done if we are not to see repetitions of the type we have had to witness these past days, and if our state is to regain the standing and respect which it has lost.</p>
   <p>Governor Lowden's term of office started under the most promising auspices, and the people of the state have reason to expect that he will solve the present difficult problem in a manner which will lend to the closing of his term as governor as satisfactory a shade as that which hailed him when he began in office.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
