<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-04-08">Apr. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Hat an Evening!]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1911-04-08">Apr. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[HAT AN EVENING!]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4. - "Dovre Klub," the 27th Ward Norwegian Republican Club, met at Wicker Park Hall, Saturday, April 1, with Senator A. J. Gronna of North Dakota, as speaker of the evening.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bergersen, the president of the club, presided at the meeting and peculiarly enough in spite of the fact that "Dovre" is a Norwegian club and that the meeting was exclusively for Norwegians, not one word of Norwegian was spoken on the platform during the entire meeting. To complete the incongruity a number of those taking part in the program appeared in the Norwegian national costume. One young man was dressed in what he thought was a national costume though it looked more like a grind-organ monkey's suit, and we wondered what the few non-Norwegians thought of the idea that Norwegians, in the old land, dressed and acted like trained apes in daily life.</p>
   <p>Senator Nelson, also advertised as the speaker of the evening, stated that he was unprepared for the task imposed upon him and he proved conclusively that he had spoken truly. His offer to come again to speak in Chicago, <pb facs="5423969_1_1001.jpg" n="2"/>when he will be "prepared," will hardly be accepted in view of the fact that his display of inanity caused listeners to slip out by twos and threes, throughtout the time he spoke, remarking, "a big man not worth hearing."</p>
   <p>Scandia sincerely hopes that "Dovre" will arrange for further meetings and that these may be more consistent and instructive, in order that our people may derive the benefits intended by such meetings. Among the notables on the platform was an imposing looking, gray-haired man whose identity aroused the curiosity of the audience. The gentleman, here making his first appearance at a Chicago Norwegian gathering was none other than Mr. Grevstad, editor of Skandinaven, whose physical appearance did not belie our mental picture of a typical Norseman as gained by reading his editorials and comments in Skandinaven.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
