<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-08-15">Aug. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Victory for Arbitration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-08-15">Aug. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY FOR ARBITRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dispute between the traction companies and their workers has been settled, and the city will be saved a destructive fight. The workers did not get everything they asked for, but they were granted concessions which their representatives found satisfactory. The agreement is to be submitted to the workers for ratification or rejection through secret vote. It is taken for granted that the agreement will be ratified.</p>
   <p>The outcome of this dispute shows, among other things, what a good organization and good leadership mean for the workers. It is hardly likely that the workers would have attained as good conditions if they had not been so well organized; nor would the organization have been of much use to the workers if the latter had not acted with intelligence and <pb facs="5423969_1_0799.jpg" n="2"/>moderation. Good organization and intelligent leadership form a tower of strength which, as a rule, will secure for the worker his rights. An organization, on the other hand, which is being used arbitrarily by dishonest leaders for their own profit is a detriment to the workers and to society as a whole.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the traction companies also deserve commendation for their reasonable attitude. This is in sharp contrast to the attitude frequently adopted by representatives of capital both in Chicago and in other cities. Once more it has been shown that capital has nothing to fear from the workers if they are willing to meet the latter half way in questions concerning their mutual rights.</p>
   <p>Finally, it has been shown that a dispute between employers and employees can best be settled by the parties themselves. A decision by outsiders (arbitration) may be just, but it may also be unjust to one or the other <pb facs="5423969_1_0800.jpg" n="3"/>of the contending parties, and in such a case the ensuing peace will be of but brief duration. Nobody knows better than the contending parties what the issue concerns, and how much the sides involved may be expected to yield. The problem is to make the parties meet for negotiation in a manner to close the door to disturbing bitterness--to keep the discussion open and free from the appearance of humiliation for either of the parties. A tactful negotiator or go-between may be of considerable value, as was the case during the discussions between the traction companies and their workers.</p>
   <p>The peaceable conclusion of the dispute is a credit to both the parties involved; it is also a new proof that the road to industrial peace does not pass through the morass of arbitration, but through the bright fields of negotiation and discussion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
