<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-01-17">Jan. 17, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Worse</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0961</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0961.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1897-01-17">Jan. 17, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">WORSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If Alderman Madden's enforced withdrawal from the senatorial contest should result in "landing Congressman Lorimer in John M. Palmer's seat," nothing has been gained by the defeat of the Fourth Ward statesman. There is very little difference, if any, between these lights of the Cook County machine. The candidacy of Lorimer is as impudent as was that of Madden, if not more so. Madden is credited with considerable business ability while Lorimer is an untutored, ignorant, wire-pulling ward politician, and nothing else.</p>
   <p>His election would be a blot upon the fair name of the state. It should be prevented. Madden was forced to retire before the wrath of public sentiment and indignation. It looks as though this paper and its readers will have to help defeat this new menace. Well, we can. Madden's machine successor in the race will encounter the same storm and go down before its fury.</p>
   <p>But if they want to make sure of Lorimer's defeat the good republicans must not trust to fate. Let no one think that the machine is shattered. It is still in <pb facs="5423969_1_0962.jpg" n="2"/>good working order and running with a full head of steam. No republican who has the honor of the state and the welfare of his party at heart can afford to relax his efforts until a decent man shall have been duly elected as Palmer's successor.</p>
   <p>The Skandinavian voters will do their part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
