<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1896-01-26">Jan. 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Sorely Vexed Woman</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C (Swedish)</item>
     <item>I C (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1896-01-26">Jan. 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A SORELY VEXED WOMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A woman hiding behind the initials "C.A.J.," tells the readers that this country is preparing trouble for itself in tolerating such foreigners as the Swedes. The danger is near at hand, too, for the politicians of both parties are ready "to raise to power this very undesirable race of whilom serfs of Norway, as well as the descendants of cold-blooded robbers." Is it not terrible? Let the American people awaken before it is too late to rescue the country from the grasp of these foreigners! The fair writer is by no means prejudiced. "A good Swede is one of the finest and most exemplary of men," she says; "but, unfortunately, Swedes of this kind are rare, the majority being cunning, aggressive, narrow-minded, selfish, excitable, rebellious, clannish, and not well-versed in the science of "mine and thine." There are no more aggravating people to live near than these northern people. Force is the only law they recognize."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The dear, sweet thing! How her poor soul must be vexed! It may be suggested, however, that a little elementary instruction will allay her apprehensions and set her fears at rest. The Swedes were never serfs of Norway or any other country. Prisoners captured in war, felons, and defaulting debtors were the only serfs ever found either in Sweden or Norway, and this species of serfdom was abolished about the time America was discovered by Leif Ericson, five hundred years before South America was discovered by Columbus. The institution of slavery never existed in the Scandinavian countries, while thousands of those "aggravating northern people" of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark shed their blood on southern battlefields a generation ago to wipe the infamy off the fair face of this country.</p>
   <p>The Norsemen were "cold-blooded" robbers at a time when the sword was the only arbiter of nations. History has it that they were successful in war. They set up empires in Russia, France, England, Ireland, and in the Mediterranean countries. If the disturbed lady patriot considers herself as <pb facs="5423969_1_0542.jpg" n="3"/>being of pure English stock(?), then she has the great misfortune of having Danish or Norwegian blood coursing through her veins; should there be a French strain in her blood, she may trace it back to some of the Norwegians who conquered England from their stronghold in Normandy. Even if she be a Celt, her blood is likely to contain Norse strains; for, once upon a time, the Danes were established in Ireland for a period of a hundred years, or more, and the result is that a very large number of Irishmen are half-Danes.</p>
   <p>If she desires to know something about her present cousins from the Scandinavian North, she should turn to a compendium of comparative statistics. She will discover that the Scandinavians, including Danes, Swedes, and Norwegians, are the best-educated and the most law-abiding people in the world. Illiteracy is practically unknown in those countries, and in no civilized country is the percentage of crime and pauperism so low as in those very lands. As for the Scandinavians in America, it is a well-known fact, supported by indisputable statistics, that they are the most law-abiding of all our citizens, the native born not excepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0543.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This country is threatened by undesirable immigration. But if she wants to know whence come those who are a menace to our welfare and institutions, the disturbed writer should turn her eyes in a different direction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
