<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-02-10">Feb. 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">An Instructive Lesson</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1901-02-10">Feb. 10, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">AN INSTRUCTIVE LESSON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of mutual concessions, representatives of the building contractors and of the carpenters have reached an agreement which is regarded as fair to both sides. It is confidently expected that it will be ratified by the various unions, and the greatest and most stubbornly fought contest in the building trades of Chicago will then be at an end.</p>
   <p>Building has been practically paralyzed in Chicago while this unnecessary war has been raging, resulting in untold want and suffering among the families of the idle workers, and in enormous loss to the employers and the community at large. Work will now be resumed and Chicago can look forward to an unusually active building season.</p>
   <p>As impartial outsiders consider the agreement, they cannot but wonder why this <pb facs="5423969_1_0813.jpg" n="2"/>simple, common-sense settlement could not have been reached before. The Saturday half holiday and the wage scale now agreed upon are demands that were as fair and reasonable when originally presented as they are conceded to be now. On the other hand, any sensible worker ought to have known one year ago as well as he does today that the building trades council was an organization run by heelers of the Burke-Harrison machine for their own special benefit without any regard whatever for the welfare of the large number of workers whom they managed to get under their control. Nor could it be doubted any more then than now that outsiders have no right or business to interfere with workers during working hours, whether they parade as "walking delegates," "business agents," or by any other title generally assumed by those who do not know how to work or will not work except with their jaws.</p>
   <p>It has cost altogether too much to learn this plain lesson, but if it has been learned thoroughly, it is worth all it has cost. The provision that all disputes hereafter are to be arbitrated, and that work is to proceed while negotiations for adjustments of difficulties are pending, is at least a very hopeful <pb facs="5423969_1_0814.jpg" n="3"/>sign. It indicates that both bosses and workers have come to understand that war does not pay, and that it is the best policy to approach misunderstandings in a spirit of conciliation. That is the main point in the whole range of industrial warfare. Nearly all industrial conflicts may be traced to misunderstandings and prejudices based upon misapprehensions. The time to settle a controversy is before it has aroused the feeling of mutual hostility and has assumed such a definite from that concessions on the part of one side or the other, or both, seem to involve a sacrifice of pride and standing. If the opposing parties promptly take their trouble in hand, approaching each other in a spirit of mutual confidence and with open minds, they are apt to discover that, to use a common expression, "they have nothing to arbitrate," because they have no quarrel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
