<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-21">Feb. 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Primary in the Fifteenth Ward</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0941</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0941.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-02-21">Feb. 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRIMARY IN THE FIFTEENTH WARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Fifteenth Ward there are two candidate for the Republican nomination for alderman. One is a lawyer by the name Upatel; he is the candidate of the Republican machine. The machine is doing its best to get him nominated and, among other things, has ordered the workers of the city to use their time and influence to advance his cause.</p>
   <p>The other candidate is the well-known Norwegian businessman, H. Jorgen Mathiesen. He is a better Republican than is Mr. Upatel, but he is too independent to suit the machine leaders, so they prefer the other man as alderman. Mr. Mathiesen will undoubtedly be a better representative for the Ward in the City Council than a lawyer who is but slightly known. Mr. Mathiesen is absolutely independent of all interests; he has not accepted financial assistance from anybody during his <pb facs="5423969_1_0942.jpg" n="2"/>campaign, and thus, if he be elected, he will stand completely independent in the City Council. Only in such manner can an alderman further in the most vigorous way the welfare of the Ward.</p>
   <p>It seems evident that the political leaders in the Fifteenth Ward seek to push the Scandinavian back. Their plans in this will succeed unless the Norsemen are alert to maintain their influence. They can nominate Mr. Mathiesen if they meet up in force at the primary election--and in doing so they would regain a great deal of the influence they have lost.</p>
   <p>The nomination of Mr. Mathiesen would also be best from the point of view of the interest of the Ward, and in addition, it would strengthen the Republican party. For these reasons the Scandinavians would do a valuable piece of work all around by seeing to it that Mr. Mathiesen wins at the primary election in the Fifteenth Ward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
