<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1920-01-10">Jan. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Would Prussianize the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1920-01-10">Jan. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">WOULD PRUSSIANIZE THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is right to deport trouble-making aliens who come to war upon American institutions. It is well to send them back to their own country. The first duty of a government is to repel a foreign invasion. This duty extends, we think, to the invasion of a foreign disease or of alien germs that menace the welfare of the nation.</p>
   <p>But we do not think the obnoxious aliens are more dangerous to American liberty, security, and happiness than the tendencies of some American statesmen. These officials are trying to change our laws so that any American citizen who disagrees with their ideas or advocates a change in the government may be sent to jail for twenty years. Attorney General Palmer has submitted to Congress a bill defining sedition which would Prussianize the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0871.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We quote from the first section of the proposed act of Congress as drafted by Attorney General Palmer, condensing the section for the sake of clarity, but not changing a word or a comma in the language. We quote:</p>
   <p>"Whoever...to cause the change...of the government or any of the laws or authority thereof....commits or attempts or threatens to commit any act of force against any person or any property, shall be deemed guilty of sedition, and, upon conviction thereof, shall be punished by a fine not exceeding ten thousand dollars or by imprisonment not exceeding twenty years, or by both."</p>
   <p>The second section of the bill as drawn by Attorney General Palmer provides that:</p>
   <p>"Whoever makes, displays, writes, prints, or circulates any sign, word, speech, picture, design, argument, or teaching which advises, advocates, teaches, or justifies any act of sedition, as heretofore defined....shall be punished by <pb facs="5423969_1_0872.jpg" n="3"/>a fine not exceeding ten thousand dollars or by imprisonment not exceeding ten years, or by both."</p>
   <p>Representative Martin L. Davey of Ohio has introduced the Attorney General's bill in Congress. Senator Sterling of South Dakota has introduced substantially the same bill in the Senate. Propaganda has been started throughout the United States to force both bills through Congress.</p>
   <p>If this law had been enacted earlier in our life as a nation it might have been impossible to secure the change in the Government of the United States, effected December 15, 1791, prohibiting any interference by the government with the free exercise of religion or any abridgement by the Government of the freedom of speech or of the press, or the right of the people peaceably to assemble and to petition the government for a redress of grievances.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0873.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It would probably have been impossible under Attorney General Palmer's proposed statute for the people to advocate, as they did, a change in our Constitution so as to</p>
   <p>Forbid secret seizure of persons, houses, or papers; Or to forbid any person to be compelled to testify against himself; Or to forbid any law depriving any citizen of life, liberty, or property without due process of law;</p>
   <p>Or to guarantee to every American citizen the right of trial by jury for any offence;</p>
   <p>Or to change the manner of choosing the President and Vice-President dent of the United States, as was done December 12, 1803; Or to abolish slavery within the Unites States or in any place subject to its jurisdiction, as was done February 1, 1865; Or to forbid discrimination against any citizen of the United States by reason of race,color, or previous condition of servitude, as was done March 30, 1870; <pb facs="5423969_1_0874.jpg" n="5"/>Or to provide for income taxes upon large incomes in the United States, as was done May 31, 1913;</p>
   <p>Or to provide for nation-wide prohibition, effective January 16, 1920;</p>
   <p>Or to adopt woman suffrage.</p>
   <p>Under Attorney General Palmer's act, Andrew Jackson and Thomas Jefferson, both of whom advocated a change in the form of government by changing the method of electing the President and Vice-President, might have been considered guilty of sedition, subject to a ten-thousand-dollar fine and twenty years in the penitentiary.</p>
   <p>Abraham Lincoln, when he wrote the Emancipation Proclamation, would have been guilty of sedition and liable to imprisonment for twenty years.</p>
   <p>Such lovers of liberty as William Lloyd Gerrison and Wendell Phillips would undoubtedly have received the extreme penalty of the law because, when they were most active in forcing a change in the Government of the United States, the rulers then in power were in favor of slavery. Those rulers undoubtedly would have regarded Garrison and Phillips as no better than anarchists, as men who should have been hanged as John Brown was.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0875.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>As for "making, displaying, writing, printing, or circulating any sign, word, speech, picture, design, argument or teaching" which "advises or advocates" a change in our form of government in the manner prohibited, it is not difficult to imagine what a United States judge, of a certain type not unknown to our federal courts at the present time,would have done under that statute to Harriet Beecher Stowe, the author of Uncle Tom's Cabin . She would certainly have gone to the penitentiary for twenty years. And her illustrious brother, Henry Ward Beecher, would undoubtedly have gone too. Any industrial striker who, in a moment of passion, "used or threatened to use force against any person or property," would be liable to twenty years' imprisonment under this statute.</p>
   <p>The state of New Jersey enacted a law much like the bill Attorney General Palmer sent to Congress. We now know how that statute works. Under it, several American citizens have been convicted and sentenced to the state penitentiary, not for forcibly resisting the administration of the law, not for attempting or advocating the forcible overthrow of government (for which a citizen should be sent to prison), but merely "by speech, writing, or printing, inciting or abetting, promoting or encouraging hostility or opposition to the government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0876.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>One of the sections of the New Jersey act would have justified the imprisonment of every member of an anti-slavery society or of every contributor to the Anti-Saloon League.</p>
   <p>We are glad to say that two very able judges of the Court of Errors and Appeals of New Jersey, Judges Minturn and Kalisch, have dissented from the conviction of prisoners under the New Jersey statute. In his very able opinion dissenting from such conviction. Justice Minturn writes:</p>
   <p>"The State Constitution of New Jersey, Article I, Section 5, provides that 'every person may freely speak, write, and publish sentiments on all subjects, being responsible for the abuse, of that right. No law shall be passed to restrain the liberty of speech or of the press'.</p>
   <p>"The principle of free speech and freedom of assembly constitutes the corner-stone of American liberty. When the right to exercise those fundamentals <pb facs="5423969_1_0877.jpg" n="8"/>without the advocacy of force is quiescently suppressed, the lamp which guides our destiny will be as effectually extinguished as the lamp that shone at the shrine of Isis.....</p>
   <p>"The sole prototype of this legislation in American constitutional history is found in the alien and sedition act of John Adams' administration, under the obloquy of which the Federal party went into extinction and oblivion. Speaking of those enactments, the biographer of John Adams reflects the verdict of history when he says: 'No one has ever been able, heartily or successfully, to defend these foolish enactments of ill-considered legislation which have to be abandoned by tacit general consent to condemnation! (More's Life of John Adams, page 283.)</p>
   <p>"If legislation of this character is to pass unchallenged by courts of justice, whose officers are sworn to uphold the Constitution as the very bedrock of our legal system, the time is not inopportune for a revision of the fundamental law and the excision of the guarantees contained in the Bill of Rights and <pb facs="5423969_1_0878.jpg" n="9"/>Magna Charta, which have been the cherished legacy of British and American law since the epochal day at Runnymede.</p>
   <p>"Nor is it perceivable how a party government, which is essentially one of criticism for the avowed purpose of 'promoting opposition to the government', can at all subsist in such an atmosphere of constructive illegality.</p>
   <p>"The presence of such legislation upon the statue books is subversive of personal liberty to speak, write, and publish one's sentiments upon government policies, and any criticism of the Acts of state and national agencies. Its legal recognition would put an end to constitutional and party government, and put in its place a Napoleonic bureaucracy."</p>
   <p>The last sentence was well illustrated by the act of the present administration at Washington two years ago in suppressing the monthly magazine to which Theodore Roosevelt was the principal regular contributor and the most vicious critic of the administration. In another case, in which the present Postmaster <pb facs="5423969_1_0879.jpg" n="10"/>General had excluded a Socialist daily paper from the mail without a trial or even a hearing, the Postmaster General replied to a suit in the Federal Court by declaring that he acted in his uncontrolled discretion, and under the law was not accountable to any one for the justice or effect of his official act. Russia, under the Czar, and France under the gag laws imposed by Napoleon, went no further than this. The terms "reptile press" was coined by Balzac to describe the "editor who daily had to crawl on his belly to some petty official to ask what he would be allowed to say or print".</p>
   <p>We beg Attorney General Palmer to refresh his mind by reading again the history of the ancient alien and sedition laws, whose adoption destroyed the political party that elected George Washington and his successor, John Adams. And then we ask him to read these moving sentences from the first inaugural address of Abraham Lincoln, words of truth which have never been denied:</p>
   <p>"THIS COUNTRY, WITH ITS INSTITUTIONS, BELONGS TO THE PEOPLE WHO INHABIT IT. WHENEVER THEY SHALL GROW WEARY OF THE EXISTING GOVERNMENT THEY CAN EXERCISE <pb facs="5423969_1_0880.jpg" n="11"/>THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT OF AMENDING IT OR THEIR REVOLUTIONARY RIGHT TO DISMEMBER OR OVERTHROW IT....."</p>
   <p>Intelligence, patriotism, Christianity, and a firm reliance on Him who has never yet forsaken this favored land are still competent to adjust in the best way all our difficulties.....We divide upon all questions into majorities and minorities. If the minority will not acquiesce, the majority must, or the government must cease. There is no other alternative, for the continuance of the government depends upon the acquiesence of the one side or the other. If a minority in such case will secede rather than acquiesce, it makes a precedent which in turn will divide and ruin them; for a minority of their own will secede from them whenever a majority refuses to be controlled by such minority. A majority held in restraint by constitutional checks and limitations, and always changing easily with deliberate changes of popular opinions and sentiments, is the only true sovereign of a free people. Whoever rejects it, flies of necessity to anarchy or depotism....</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0881.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Why should there not be a patient confidence in the ultimate justice of the people? Is there any better or equal hope in the world? The new sedition laws proposed by Attorney General Palmer go farther than any British statute. If enacted without modification they would Prussianize the United States. A Patrick Henry, a John Brown, or a Benjamin Franklin would in the future be clapped into jail for twenty years by some petty judge or bureaucrat for lese majeste.</p>
   <p>Attorney General Palmer is a menace to free institutions! What can we do about it?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
