<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-08">Mar. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[A Farce]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1913-03-08">Mar. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[A FARCE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's prohibitionists, under the leadership of the I.O.G.T., are on the war-path. The enemy to be obliterated is the Chicago Norwegian National League. Their offense is serving liquor at the May 17th picnics they sponsor each year. The great struggle was scheduled for Sunday, March and, when the prohibition forces gathered to parade on North Avenue and neighboring streets with banners and bands. Afterwards the main battle was to be fought of words disguised as a discussion and debate.</p>
   <p>The generalissimo of the attacking forces, Mr. Solvesen, evidently forgot about the impending battle, as he did not they up, and Rev. C.W. Hansen assumed command. His opening gun, an appeal to the religious captions of the assembled army, was the only gun fired, as the enemy had ignored the challenge is insignificant, and neglected to send as much as one sniper to represent the sinful hordes of the Norwegian National League. The League, by the way, is the official "board of strategy" for all city-wide Norwegian activity, composed, as it is, of delegates from nearly all the Norwegian organizations in Chicago and Evanston.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0253.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are at a loss to know whether the final decision should read, "League loses battle by default," or "I.O.G.T. loses battle that was not fought." Neither do we know why we have wasted time and material on the whole farce.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
