<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-03-30">Mar. 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Dovre Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1911-03-30">Mar. 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DOVRE CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dovre Club passed the following resolution at its last meeting:</p>
   <p>"To the Honorable Board of Education of the City of Chicago: The Dovre Club of the Twenty-seventh Ward of this City, in special meeting assembled on Monday, have unanimously adopted the following resolution and appointed the undersigned as a committee of five to present the same to your honorable Board:</p>
   <p>"Resolution.</p>
   <p>"Whereas, There has been presented to your honorable Board a petition, signed by a number of representative Norwegian-American citizens of this city, requesting that the Norwegian language be adopted as an elective study in high schools where a sufficient number of pupils may signify their desire to take this study; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We believe that the recognized high standard of character and education <pb facs="5423969_1_0151.jpg" n="2"/>of the Norwegian immigrants to the United States, the splendid history of the Norwegian race, including the first discovery of America, and the rich Norwegian literature in ancient and modern times, amply justify the desire of the Norwegian-Americans of this city to have their children learn Norwegian in our public schools; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The study of the Scandinavian languages has been lately taken up more and more at our universities and in the schools of various important cities of the Northwest, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We believe it to be of the greatest practical utility for our young men to know another language besides English, to perfect and not to forget what they have learned at home of such other language, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We believe that favorable action by your honorable Board upon the said petition would serve immediately to strengthen and popularize our public school system of which the Norwegian-Americans have been the staunchest supporters; be it therefore</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0152.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Resolved, That the Dovre Club of the Twenty-seventh Ward, with an active membership list of more than five hundred citizens, respectfully urge upon your honorable Board to take favorable action upon the petition presented as aforesaid.</p>
   <p>"Louis B. Bergersen, president</p>
   <p>"Chris J. Runden, secretary</p>
   <p>"Committee: Henry Stibolt,</p>
   <p>Victor F. Bendixen,</p>
   <p>A. A. Haarstad,</p>
   <p>Ole Andersen,</p>
   <p>Birger Osland."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
