<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-25">Mar. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">John J. Sonsteby and His Co-Conspirators Leave Meeting of Board of Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-25">Mar. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN J. SONSTEBY AND HIS CO-CONSPIRATORS LEAVE MEETING OF BOARD OF EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The action taken by the Dunne men at the last meeting of the Board of Education was so scandalous that nobody had expected it, even of them. Led by Mr. John J. Sonsteby, they placed all possible obstacles, parliamentary and non-parliamentary, in the way of the majority, and in that manner they succeeded in preventing action by the Board. With their usual nonchalance the radical gentlemen made one accusation after the other against the majority of the Board.</p>
   <p>These Dunne men are proud fellows who do not consider their neighbors except when they are rattling off their usual socialistic phrases in the Chicago Federation of Labor. And thus, when they could not have their way, they left the meeting. In this manner they prevented the Board of Education from taking any action, since there was no quorum left.</p>
   <p>The riot started during the reading of the report of the previous meeting. The <pb facs="5423969_1_0064.jpg" n="2"/>Dunne men called for that part of the report in which the contract with the Commonwealth Edison Company was considered in all its details. The first contract had been sent from the committee on buildings and grounds to the meeting of the Board of Education, where it was discussed by the Board as a committee of the whole. Some changes were made, and the contract was then adopted. It was at this point that Mr. Sonsteby interrupted. He entered a strong protest against the omission of the original contract from the report and demanded that the contract be inserted.</p>
   <p>"Every document used in the report of the committee of the whole has been inserted in the report as it now stands," said Trustee Spiegel. "The report is absolutely correct with respect to what was done at the last meeting."</p>
   <p>"It is evident that an attempt is being made to falsify the report of the Board of Education," said Mr. Sonsteby. "The report is not a correct account of what took place at the meeting, and this is at variance with the statutes of the Board."</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0065.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And now the riot was at its height. Every Dunne man followed the example set by Mr. Sonsteby, each seeking to outdo the other in displaying his impudence and lack of a sense of responsibility. As mentioned before, the upshot was that the Dunne men left, stating that they did not intend to return until the majority acceded to Mr. Sonsteby's demand to have the contract in its original form inserted in the report.</p>
   <p>The majority, however, found it beneath their dignity to defer to these men whose sole purpose as members of the Board seems to be to create anarchy in the teaching force of Chicago. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
   <p>President Schneider and the other members of the Board were, as might be expected, very angry at this arbitrariness on the part of the Dunne men, and they did not keep silent about their feelings. Mr. Schneider had this to say: "We are compelled to adjourn the meeting because there is no quorum present. But this is a sheer injustice to many people to contractors and to workers who desire and need the money which is due them, and which under the circumstances, cannot be paid now. A month has elapsed since our previous meeting, and this [forced <pb facs="5423969_1_0066.jpg" n="4"/>adjournment] nullifies the business of the Board for a whole month."</p>
   <p>"It seems to me that this Board has been weighted down with incriminations," said Mr. Dawes. "As for me, I am quickly fed up with a board of education where such occurences can take place. I strongly protest against the kind of behavior witnessed at our last meeting. It militates against all accepted rules of propriety and parliamentary procedure."</p>
   <p>Other members spoke in the same vein, using even stronger language. Since Mr. Sonsteby and his co-conspirators were reinstated in the Board of Education by the decision of the court, after having been ousted by Major Busse, who found them unworthy of office, they have become more impudent then ever. In some cases, the majority of the people may have agreed with them, but their constant obstructionist tactics are getting tiresome.</p>
   <p>Since the death of Mr. S. T. Gunderson, and especially since he became the president of the Norwegian National Association, Mr. Sonsteby has maintained that <pb facs="5423969_1_0067.jpg" n="5"/>he represents the Norwegians in the city, particularly in his capacity as member of the Board of Education. Even if Mr. Sonsteby did know something about the Norwegians here and at home--and he does not--the Norwegian-Americans would still prefer not to have him considered their representative.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sonsteby represents a radical element in the Chicago Federation of Labor, and nothing else. Several Norwegians have expressed this opinion to reporters for the Skandinaven. "It is bad enough to have him in the Norwegian National Association, without his creating a scandal in the Board of Education," said one well-known Norwegian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
