<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-13">Sept. 13, 1907</date><title level="a">Temporary Defeat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1907-09-13">Sept. 13, 1907</date><title level="a">TEMPORARY DEFEAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The telephone franchise was slated to be forced through at the special meeting of the city council last night, but at the last minute the aldermen lost courage and the plan failed. This seems to indicate that public criticism is carrying some weight even though certain of the aldermen have skin as difficult to penetrate as an elephant's hide.</p>
   <p>It has been said that the foremost advocates of the new charter used their influence to gain postponement. They feared that the acceptance now, of the monstrous ordinance, in spite of the general protest against the "deal", might arouse the public anger to such a degree that it might spell the defeat of the charter also. If the new charter is adopted, the people may have a chance to vote on the telephone franchise, and the strategy was that, by postponing the voting on the <pb facs="5423969_1_0613.jpg" n="2"/>franchise till after the charter vote, support might be gained for the charter.</p>
   <p>Skandinaven believes that the advocates of the charter are mistaken in this reasoning. It would be folly for the voters to support the new charter for such a reason. If the new charter cannot win on its own merit, it should be defeated. If a voter finds the charter unacceptable in itself, then, of course, he must not favor it on account of some entirely extraneous matter.</p>
   <p>The telephone people have suffered temporary defeat, but they will renew their attack with increased vigor. They will utilize the time at their disposal to attempt to make certain their victory when the matter comes before the city council once more. It is necessary that the opponents be equally alert. The voters need to let their respective aldermen know what they demand in regard to the franchise.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0614.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As everybody knows, there is a certain number of aldermen who are not concerned about the will of the people. These aldermen, fortunately, form a minority. The majority will not dare disregard the will of the people; they realize that the people are in earnest. It depends upon the attitude of the voters whether this "robber-franchise" is to be accepted by the city council. Let the voters demand that their respective aldermen vote against the franchise, and the franchise will fall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
