<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1922-03-18">Mar. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1922-03-18">Mar. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Arthur Olsen writes to us again, as follows:</p>
   <p>"Dear Scandia,</p>
   <p>"Your answer to my statements regarding the Landis proposition did not surprise me, knowing as I did what stand you had taken in your editorial published February 25. You say that by keeping out of politics Landis would make a good mayor. You stop there and say nothing about his qualifications. Our next mayor should be a man who is unbiased, one who would seek advice about current city matters, one who is a good listener, and finally one who will work for the betterment of the people, the majority of whom are the workers. Judge Landis does not possess such qualifications. He does things on the spur of the moment. As for being a good listener, ask the lawyers what they think about him.</p>
   <p>"It is not my intention to discuss with you the merits of the Non-Partisan <pb facs="5423969_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>League, but inasmuch as you mentioned it in your answer to my letter, I must call your attention to a few facts. It has always been my belief that Scandia was a liberal paper, and that its circulation was among the workers. I cannot conceive how Scandia can denounce a party that believes in government ownership of banks, mills, elevators, insurance, real estate, and mines. Do not present conditions show that public ownership would avert unemployment and the hardships of the workers today? Wall Street has bled the farmers and the workers throughout the country. It has deprived the workers and the farmers of their right to make a substantial profit on their products. Wall Street deliberately offered the farmers $1.25 for a bushel of wheat when it cost the farmer $1.75 to thresh it and put it on the market. When Wall Street saw what the Non-Partisan League in North Dakota was doing, boycotting the capitalists and preventing them from making any profit, it turned around and called North Dakota a "Bolshevik State". Do you realize that ninety per cent of the population of that State are Scandinavians--your own people? The money spent by capitalists in propaganda against the Non-Partisan League amounted to millions of dollars. They have succeeded in electing their men <pb facs="5423969_1_0566.jpg" n="3"/>as governors, attorneys general, etc., but they have not broken the spirit which the League has fostered in the people of many States.</p>
   <p>"If you want to enlighten yourself on the subject of the Non-Partisan League and Gomper unionism, why not acquaint yourself with the real facts from the Federal press instead of deriving your ideas from the poisonous papers of Chicago, which have always been enemies of organized labor?</p>
   <p>"I will inform you later as to the man that I would recommend as our next mayor.</p>
   <p>"Yours truly,</p>
   <p>"Arthur Olsen."</p>
   <p>Mr. Olsen seems to believe that our man and our politics are wrong, and that his man and his politics are right. If only we would listen to him and to <pb facs="5423969_1_0567.jpg" n="4"/>his party, then we should be on the right side. Gompers and Frazier are all right, but Landis is all wrong. But, Mr. Olsen, that is the result of all party politics, and also of what is called unionism. All people of this type eat the pudding, and the other fellow pays for it.</p>
   <p>Like a real politician, Mr. Olsen mentions mills, banks, factories, etc., and profit. Can't Mr. Olsen think and speak of these institutions without using a rubber stamp belonging to some one else?</p>
   <p>You say that Wall Street has "stolen" the farmer's profit. Let us ask you what right the farmer has to make a profit. Would it not be better to eliminate all profit, everybody's profit, yours, mine, the farmer's, the mill-owner's the banker's and so on? No. Let us not have any Frazier or Landis liberalism; let us have the real thing.</p>
   <p>Scandia, as you say, is not a liberal paper, but its editor is radical. Well, we will not argue that point. But we will argue whether the workers shall <pb facs="5423969_1_0568.jpg" n="5"/>accept crumbs or shall demand real liberation from exploitation. Let us have a whole hog or none.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
