<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-30">Sept. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Mutual Distrust</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423969_1_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>NORWEGIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1900-09-30">Sept. 30, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">MUTUAL DISTRUST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many native-born citizens are more or less distrustful of the "foreign vote". If this feeling is shared by campaign managers they are, of course, careful not to betray their apprehension, at least not until the ballots have been cast. But the ordinary citizen, who feels that he is responsible for his own vote only, is more apt to express his doubts as to the ability of large numbers of his adopted fellow citizens to vote understandingly and intelligently. This sentiment is probably more prevalent in the East than in the West.</p>
   <p>Such apprehensions will seem but natural to broadminded "foreigners." The impending election will put the intelligence and patriotism of the people to an exceptionally severe test; and the native-born citizen, who, perchance, does not know yet how he is going to vote, cannot be expected to look for better information or safer judgment in his foreign-born neighbor. If he shares the views of the chairman of the Democratic national committee about the "ignorant <pb facs="5423969_1_0466.jpg" n="2"/>foreigners," his anxiety and distraction of mind must be great indeed.</p>
   <p>As already stated, very few adopted citizens are surprised at this--especially if they assume that the information of the average American about political conditions in Europe may be gauged by Colonel Bryan's knowledge, or lack of knowledge, in this particular field. But the native-born citizen would probably be very much surprised if he were informed that he in turn is distrusted by his adopted fellow citizens.</p>
   <p>Yet, such is the fact. And the adopted citizen will point to election returns as ample reason for his distrust, and not without justification; for they prove that the "foreign vote" has been the great conservative force in our politics. This was particularly noticeable in 1896 when the firm ranks of our adopted citizens averted the calamity of free silver. The truth is, the "foreigner" looks upon his native-born fellow citizen as a rather unsteady voter, though he may not know, as yet, how to account for his apparent vacillation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423969_1_0467.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The "foreigner" is impressed with the high intelligence of the average American but no less impressed with what appears to him as a lack of American common sense at the polls. He admires the rugged conservatism of the American on all questions relating to the fundamental law of the land but does not know how to reconcile this conservatism with his fitful radicalism in matters of everyday politics......</p>
   <p>In the present political contest, the most disturbing factor to our foreign-born business and professional men is their dread of the "American impatience for a change".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
