<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Four Important Institutions the Fortification of Jewish Charity in Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Yonah Spivak</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FOUR IMPORTANT INSTITUTIONS THE FORTIFICATION OF JEWISH CHARITY IN CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">by Yonah Spivak</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is barely fifty years, since there began a mass migration of Jews to Chicago, where they have congregated around the district of Canal and 12th Streets., (Roosevelt Road now).</p>
   <p>With the same impetus with which the city in general grew, so also the local Jewish life grew. The greater the colonization became, the more Jewish fortifications were built......Jewish Charitable Institutions, which are an honor to the Jews of our city.</p>
   <p>Several such organizations, religious, social and cultural, were constructed by the Jewish masses in our city. However, we shall only pause upon four, that best express the sentiment toward those who were mistreated by fate and must be provided by their fellow citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1688.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These mercy-institutions are:-</p>
   <p>1. The Home for the Aged.</p>
   <p>2. The Marks Nathan Orphan Home.</p>
   <p>3. The Daughters of Zion Day and Night Nursery.</p>
   <p>4. The Douglas Park Day and Night Nursery.</p>
   <p>THE HOME FOR THE AGED</p>
   <p>Twenty five years ago, when newly migrated Chicago Jews began to feel old age creeping upon them, they began to consider the construction of an old home. At that time, the Jewish population was already quite large.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1689.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Russo-Polish Jew, who had until then turned to the institutions of the German Jews, began feeling a certain amount of independence and also meditating upon social problems.</p>
   <p>A group of Jews assembled in the summer of 1899 to consider the problem of constructing a home for the aged Jews, where they could prolong the Orthodox traditions and on September of that year a charter was granted for the same institution.</p>
   <p>A meeting was promptly called by delegates from all synagogues, societies and lodges and the following officers were elected for the forth coming year:- President, Harris Cohen; Vice-President, Jacob Berkson; Treasurer, Joseph Phillipson; Recording Secretary, William Cohen; Financial Secretary, S.E. Newberger.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jewry became very active in the work forthe old home. In January of the following year, a North West Side Branch was organized by Mr. Finkel and May, a branch was opened on the South Side by Mrs. Benjamin Davis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1690.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The branches were privileged to elect directors, who contributed a part of the main body.</p>
   <p>A mass character was reflected in the growth of this institution. In 1902, the organization already numbered 1700 members, and had a beautiful edifice on Albany Avenue near Ogden, where ample space was provided for hundreds of aged people.</p>
   <p>It should, also, be stated here that the greatest contributor to the building fund was the late philanthropist, Abraham Slimmer, of Velverly, Iowa., who contributed $20,000, then considered a great sum. However, the greatest portion of money was contributed by the membership and by the various undertakings that were arranged for the institution from time to time.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Benjamin Davis consented to be superintendent and matron for the first year and demonstrated that it was possible to conduct an orthodox institution in an orderly system, and disciplined manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1691.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In 1912, when the Federation of Orthodox Charity was organized under the direction of Mr. B. Hurvitz, the Aged Home was placed under its supervision. Until then, funds had been coming in very poorly; canvassing for contributions had to be done from house to house.</p>
   <p>At present, there are fifty nine men in the institution, between the ages of sixty five and one hundred and five, and sixty five women of similar ages. A hospital is located at one end of the building, and a synagogue at another end, where services are conducted every day in a strictly orthodox manner.</p>
   <p>THE MARKS NATHAN ORPHANAGE</p>
   <p>At 1550 South Albany Avenue, not far from the aged home is found the beautiful structure of the Marks Nathan Orphanage, the second great institution built by the Russian and Polish Jews of Chicago. This institution, which is the pride of the Jewish population of Chicago, was founded in 1905 with the fund of $15,000 left by Marks Nathan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1692.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Marks Nathan, were childless, and their principle philosophy in life was to provide a home for the orphans. Throughout their life, they supported and educated many orphans until they became independent men and women.</p>
   <p>In his will, Mr. Nathan bequeathed $30,000 to institutions, of which $15,000 were to go for a Jewish hospital or orphanage, providing that the Jewish community of Chicago would raise $15,000 more.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Lasser, of the Beth Midrash Hagodol, where Marks was a member, called a meeting to discuss the provisions of the will. The meeting consisted of the late Joseph Phillipson, the late Bernard Baumgarden, B. J. Sehiff, Jacob Levy, Nicholas Jr., Pritzker, Dr. M. Meyerovitz, M. Peadstein, Rabbi Ezriel Epstein, Jacob Pivionski, and the late Louis Steinberg.</p>
   <p>The sentiment of the meeting was for a Jewish hospital, but the sentiment changed later to an orphanage. Thanks to Mr. Levy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1693.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Mr. Levy, was at that time president of the Northwest Side Sick Benevolent Verein, an organization with approximately seven hundred members, which was directed by the late Rachel Lifshutz.</p>
   <p>This women's organization, had given a benefit performance in Glickman's Theater, which netted a profit of $5,000. This sum was added to the fund of the Orphan home.</p>
   <p>On September 27, 1905, the orphanage, which bears the name of Mr. Marks Nathan, was established. The first officers of the institution were Rabbi Lasser, president; Jacob Levy, acting president; Jacob Rothschild, vice-president; Louis Steinberg, treasurer; Jacob Cantor, financial secretary; S. Berger, recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The officers, who had raised the requisite sum of $15,000, immediately bought the three story building at North Wood and Blotches Streets, which was remodeled for a children's home and the first thirty children were accepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1694.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The New Marks Nathan Home opened on Albany Avenue, November 24, 1912, and in 1913, this institution founded the Federation. Many members were, at first, not satisfied with the alliance with the Federation. This created many quarrels and factions.</p>
   <p>The federationists,however, succeeded in slowly capturing the orthodox institutions, and in time, the disputes vanished.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, is one of the most active members of this institution and a play ground was built on his own initiative, by a donation, which he received from Mrs. Sarah Bernard, in memory of her husband. Mr. Rosenblatt, also established a summer home fund for the children, to which he, himself, contributed $5,000.</p>
   <p>The institution is now complete with all convenient arrangements for the children. There can be found a Hebrew school, a gym, various classes, an orchestra and a play ground, for the benefit of the children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1695.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>When the children graduate from public school, they are provided with various jobs according to their ability and even then they are taken care of by the institution, which acts as parents to them.</p>
   <p>The principle feature of the institution is that in spite of the enforced discipline, the children feel as though they would be in the home of devoted mothers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
