<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-09">Mar. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The People's Order of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-09">Mar. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE'S ORDER OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The People's Order, a new Jewish organization, has just been recently organized in Chicago, and because this order differs somewhat in principle from other orders, it well deserves our attention.</p>
   <p>For the past few years much has been said and written about the old systems prevailing in other orders, particularly about cases in which officials of the organizations made personal use of the monies entrusted to them. The chief task of the People's Order is to correct these evils by proper management and honesty and to serve as an example for similar institutions.</p>
   <p>The principles of the new order are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. Every by-law of the Order shall be approved of through a referendum by all members of the order.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0743.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. Every member receives a monthly report on all transactions, as well as an accurately written statement of the financial condition.</p>
   <p>3. No insurance, in a death case of a member, shall go for any other purpose.</p>
   <p>4. Insurance must be paid in less than thirty days.</p>
   <p>5. The by-laws are worded in such a manner that it is impossible for officers to defraud or introduce any other irregularities.</p>
   <p>6. It must always be possible for the members to find out the financial status of the order, and to obtain other necessary information.</p>
   <p>7. Friendship and true loyalty to one another will be taught. Entertainment in a decent and clean manner will be encouraged.</p>
   <p>The members and their wives, and those who wish to join the Order, are <pb facs="5423972_6_0744.jpg" n="3"/>requested to come to the West Side Auditorium, Center and Taylor Streets, Mar. 11, at 7:30 P.M., for a medical examination.</p>
   <p>The Organizing Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
