<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1879-06-20">June 20, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[Annual Examination at the Zion Sabbath School]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1879-06-20">June 20, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[ANNUAL EXAMINATION AT THE ZION SABBATH SCHOOL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual examination at the Zion Sabbath School took place last Sunday, June 15, in the synagogue which is located on the corner of Sangamon and Jackson Streets. About 150 children received instruction [during the past school year] in Biblical and post-Biblical history, Hebrew reading, translating Hebrew prayers into English, and cathecism every Saturday from 9 A. M. to 10:30 A. M., and every Sunday from 9:30 A. M. to 11:30 A. M. The pupils were divided into four classes. Reverend Dr. B. Felsenthal is the superintendent.</p>
   <p>For the last five years, during which Mr. H. Eliassof has been connected with the Zion School, he has made it his chief aim and object to acquaint the children with the services at the synagogue and to make them understand and appreciate the beauty of the Hebrew prayers.</p>
   <p>[The exercises began] at 9 A. M. when the children entered the synagogue led by their respective teachers. Reverend Dr. Felsenthal made a short address, and <pb facs="5423972_6_0262.jpg" n="2"/>the children recited in concert the prayers in Hebrew and in English. The classes were then examined by Dr. Felsenthal and Mr. Buxbaum, the children answering the questions promptly and readily.</p>
   <p>The students in the higher class, instructed by Mr. Eliassof, read the Halel [the Hallelujah prayer] responsively, one student reading a verse and the whole class responding in concert. This reading was followed by the translation of the Hebrew prayers contained in the Sabbath service [section] of Dr. Einhorn's Prayer Book. The same class then answered questions in Biblical history covering the period from the death of Moses to the time of Zerubbabel, and each scholar recited two verses from Dr. Szold's Urim Vetumim. The post-confirmation class was then examined in post-Biblical history. The exercises closed with prayers in Hebrew and in English.</p>
   <p>Dr. Felsenthal awarded two prizes to each class: eight elegant and useful books [in total].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
