<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-02">Apr. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-02">Apr. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We know of no other aid society in our community which has functioned as long as the Telzer Aid Society, not only for its own members but for other [groups] as well. It has answered every important appeal for charity, and has supported other Jewish campaigns. Next to the Bikur Holim Society [a society for the purpose of paying visits to the sick] the Telzer Aid Society is the most firmly established society. The fact that the Society has three of its founders still alive and paying dues--each of them is close to seventy--and still taking an active part in the work of their beloved organization, is proof of this claim.</p>
   <p>This society was organized twenty-six years ago by a small group of Jews from <pb facs="5423972_6_0627.jpg" n="2"/>Telz [Russia]. Its purpose was to help newly arrived immigrants from Telz to obtain employment, and to establish themselves firmly on American soil. In the beginning, there were only fifteen members, and the dues were twenty cents per month. With the small sums obtained from dues, it was impossible to go on with the undertaking. So they held services during the High Holidays in what was formerly Brodie's Hall, on Jefferson Street, which brought in a considerable income each year. In the meantime, the membership increased. And now the Telzer Aid Society has one hundred and fifty members who have been paying their monthly dues regularly for years. They own two Sifre Toroth [the Pentateuch in scroll form] which a good-hearted woman donated to the Society for its [religious] services. They gave the scrolls to the Congregation Shaare Thora Anshei Maarov on Sawyer Avenue, and now the members of this Society consider this holy place as their spiritual home.</p>
   <p>Thus the Telzer continue their activity. When one of the members dies, his <pb facs="5423972_6_0628.jpg" n="3"/>family is paid one hundred dollars; sick benefit is paid,; and as a society, it contributes annually to local charities, as well as to charities across the sea. They have contributed, as a body, in addition to the individual contributions of the members, to the Keren Hayesod, the fund which is to be used to rebuild Palestine for the Jews. Last year they gave $1,627 for charity.</p>
   <p>No other aid society in our city can boast of such a record in regards to its accomplishments and activities. And the most remarkable feature about the whole thing is that the Telzer do not bother you every now and then to buy tickets for various benefits, nor do they stampede editorial offices seeking free publicity for every bit of trivia. The Telzer Jews in Chicago are not the very rich verein members; they are, however, as rich as any in spirit, their hearts are in the right places.</p>
   <p>It is not out of place to mention here the names of their officers: <pb facs="5423972_6_0629.jpg" n="4"/>J. Cohen,ex-president, Sussman Jacobson, president, David Horwitz, vice-president, Harry Meyerowitz, treasurer, Barnett Lenton, recording secretary, Sam Brook, financial secretary, trustees, Sam Ordman, Jacob Kaplan, Sam Meyerowitz, and Sam Brim, manager.</p>
   <p>The three charter members of the Telzer Aid Society who are still alive, and as mentioned above, are all close to seventy, are: Abraham Root, Sussman Jacobson, and Sam Meyerowitz.</p>
   <p>Sam H. Isaacson, a well-known businessman, is, so to speak, the guiding spirit of the Telzer Society. In his youth, Mr. Isaacson studied at the Theological College of Slabotky at the time that Rabbi Ephraim Epstein studied there. He is also the chairman of its relief committee.</p>
   <p>It gives us great pleasure to record all of these facts concerning the <pb facs="5423972_6_0630.jpg" n="5"/>Telzer Aid Society in Chicago. And we pray that other societies here [in Chicago] will follow their example.</p>
   <p>You still have time to gladden the hearts of your relatives in Soviet Russia and the Ukraine with an assortment of kosher foodstuffs for Passover. You can do this by coming into the office of the Joint Relief Committee, 720 West Roosevelt Road, and making out your order there. The order is then telegraphed to New York, and from New York to Moscow, where the main office of the American Relief Administration is located. From there, the food packages are sent to the respective addresses.</p>
   <p>It is reported from New York that in the above-mentioned Moscow office, there were 16,500 receipts for packages delivered in Russia up to March 10. Of these [receipts], about 12,000 should now be in London on the way to America. Of the 16,500 packages, 7,500 were delivered in the vicinity of Odessa, Kiev, <pb facs="5423972_6_0631.jpg" n="6"/>and Minsk, i.e., in the Ukraine and White Russia, where the greatest part of the Jewish population in Russia lives. Since March 10, New York reports, the main warehouse in Moscow has been sending 4,000 packages daily to the various local warehouses. The rapidity of delivery in each city, can be seen from [the report] that in Kiev alone 200 packages a day are delivered.</p>
   <p>It is understood that the 16,500 packages delivered are only a small part of the 80,000 packages, amounting to $2,215,000 that have been sold. And the American Relief Administration has now issued a statement explaining the causes which, up to February 15, kept them from conducting their work in Russia with the speed which they desired. Evidently, the agreement made between the American Relief Administration and the Moscow Soviet government did not apply to the Ukraine, and when the Relief began sending food packages to that part of the country, they discovered that a separate treaty with the Ukraine was needed. At the same time, the severe cold weather caused a delay <pb facs="5423972_6_0632.jpg" n="7"/>in the railroad transportation, which prevented the shipment of packages from Moscow into the provinces. It was not until the middle of February that the Soviet Government, as a result of the strong pressure from the American Relief Administration, finally supplied the necessary trains. Then 17,000 packages were immediately sent out from Moscow to the various warehouses. Since then, delivery has been speeded up considerably, and at this date, as previously stated, Moscow can distribute 4,000 packages daily. Thus we can understand why the receipts [of packages delivered], although coming from all parts of Russia, are small in number as compared with the number of packages purchased. Now, however, it is more than six weeks since the delivery of packages reached a normal stage. In addition to the 16,500 receipts now on their way to America, it is quite certain that the rest will be coming in steadily. The setup of the American Relief Administration is such that it should take not more than four or five weeks to reach the remotest part of Russia. All those who have bought packages for their relatives, may rest assured that, since obstacles have been removed, <pb facs="5423972_6_0633.jpg" n="8"/>the packages have by this time reached their destinations.</p>
   <p>Every Jew in America should know that in this case he is not dealing with a Dr. Dubrovsky, or another such faker, who accepts packages, but [instead of delivering them] keeps them for himself. Here you are dealing with the Joint Distribution Committee, which is reliable because it is under the supervision of the American Relief Administration, appointed by Uncle Sam himself.</p>
   <p>It appears that the drive for the Keren Hayesod, which is now being made in Chicago, will be a success. The quota which the local Keren Hayesod administrative committee has set out to raise will be realized, if--if the volunteer workers will do their work energetically. Mr. B. Horwich is chairman of this committee.</p>
   <p>Seventy thousand dollars in cash has come in thus far. But when you take <pb facs="5423972_6_0634.jpg" n="9"/>into consideration the fact that only one thousand people participated in the raising of this sum, you can readily conclude that there is a very good chance of raising the required sum of $150,000 by the end of Passover.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jews have always contributed to all local and national institutions and enterprises. Nor will those who have not yet contributed, refuse to give to such an important fund as the Keren Hayesod. If only one thousand persons have contributed to the Keren Hayesod thus far, it is because the volunteer workers, who are getting subscriptions, have not visited, nor requested contributions from many Jews as yet.</p>
   <p>The volunteer workers have gained new forces now; these are the leaders of the congregations. But don't stop now--on with the work!</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0635.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Before us is a list of Jews who are dealing in sacramental wine. This list was sent to us from the office of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee, 720 West Roosevelt Road. On this list are the names and addresses of seven individuals who have refused to buy and paste the relief stamps on the gallons of liquor that they sell. To print the names and addresses would smack of the informer, and we don't want that. The committee that is gathering money to aid our war--and pogrom--suffering Jews across the sea doesn't want that either.</p>
   <p>We shall do it the other way. We shall appeal to the Jewish feeling and the sympathetic understanding of these people. Don't they sense the great need, at the present time, of their brothers and sisters in the Ukraine, Poland, and other countries? Don't they know that those Jews are in despair, and that we Jews in America are their only salvation?</p>
   <p>What concern is it of theirs if customers who buy wine from them and are willing to pay a high price for it, are also willing to spend another five <pb facs="5423972_6_0636.jpg" n="11"/>or ten cents for relief? If they are selling to gentiles, that is another matter. In that case, the government will not tolerate it; nor will the rabbis, who give them permits.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we advise these slackers to get relief stamps at the Relief office, and paste them on all the gallons of liquor which leave their place of business. It isn't smart to play with fire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
