<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1889-10-04">October 4, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">A New Hospital Project</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1889-10-04">October 4, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW HOSPITAL PROJECT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seems to develop itself among our Russo-Polish Israelites in this city. We have before us an open letter in the Jargon language from Dr. M. N. Regentowitch, 189 Maxwell Street, who in earnest and sincere language urges his countrymen and co-religionists, who owe it to themselves and the community at large to move at once in the erection of a hospital.</p>
   <p>His brochure is replete with reasons why his people should have a hospital of their own and indicates with simple plans how such an institution could be inaugurated and maintained. He makes this plan the basis of the Alexian Brothers Hospital, which started in a small way and has become one of the foremost charity institutions of Chicago. He refers to a Chebra who once asked that all Jewish Lodges and Societies should send a delegate to a mass meeting for the purpose of establishing such a hospital, but that this project was never followed up.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He lays considerable stress on the need of his Jewish patients, that they may not be contaminated with trefa (ritually unclean) food, and should receive attention from their co-religionists and so forth, when inmates of the hospital. We would suggest that the promoters of this hospital call their mass meeting during choul hamold next and we shall do all we can to aid them in perfecting their plans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
