<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-10">Nov. 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Sabbath School at the Waller Street Talmud Torah Reopens]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-10">Nov. 10, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[SABBATH SCHOOL AT THE WALLER STREET TALMUD TORAH REOPENS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been notified that the Sabbath school at the Waller Street Talmud Torah will reopen. Because several teachers were ill, the School was closed for several weeks; but now things are again moving along in their usual manner. The School will be open every Saturday and Sunday. Parents who have girls, and desire to give them some Jewish training, may enroll them now.</p>
   <p>The School will be conducted by the same persons who were so successful in conducting the Sabbath school of the Hebrew Literary Society. The latter School has demonstrated its ability to give the children attending it a more or less thorough understanding of Jewish life and customs.</p>
   <p>Speaking of the decision of the Waller Street Talmud Torah to allow a Sabbath school to be established on its premises, we feel that one of the finest things the Talmud Torahs of Chicago can do is to allow Sabbath schools the use of their educational facilities. The West Side Talmud Torahs should be given a <pb facs="5423972_6_0154.jpg" n="2"/>vote of thanks for recognizing the need of expanding the activities which now take place in their buildings.</p>
   <p>In general, the Talmud Torahs in the United States are patterned after those in the old country. The reasons for this situation are self apparent. The younger generation, imbued with the American spirit, and congnizant of the changing methods in education, are taken up with their own careers, and are, therefore, unable to become actively engaged in the affairs of the community--less so in its educational problems. The older generation, on the other hand, has demonstrated its ability to finance these institutions and keep them going despite the fact that they are not acquainted with the modern educational methods.</p>
   <p>The West Side Talmud Torahs, as is well known, are the Moses Montifiore Talmud Torah and the Rabbi Izhak Elhanan Talmud Torah. These two schools have a budget of around thirteen or fourteen thousand dollars a year, a staff of fourteen teachers, and a school population of eight hundred children. Although the younger generation may be able to point out many faults in the present educational system, we must give the board of education and the officers of the Talmud <pb facs="5423972_6_0155.jpg" n="3"/>Torahs credit for doing the best they know how. Most people do not realize the difficulties involved in raising funds to finance such institutions. We hope that constant improvements will be made, and that the Talmud Torahs will become Jewish academies--the Jewish universities of America.</p>
   <p>Now that the Talmud Torah buildings are being used by the Sabbath schools our youth will begin to take a greater interest in Judaism and Jewish problems. Our old axiom--that all that is poured into children does not go to waste--will continue to prove itself a truism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
