<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-06-10">June 10, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Ceremonial Opening of the B'nai Zion Nursery</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-06-10">June 10, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CEREMONIAL OPENING OF THE B'NAI ZION NURSERY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The B'nai Zion Nursery officially opened yesterday afternoon the first two floors of their new home on the Northwest Side, corner California Avenue and Hirsch Street.</p>
   <p>Over five thousand people came to the consecration of the nursery but as the inside capacity was only for two thousand people, more than three thousand people were forced to turn back disappointed.</p>
   <p>The opening was a real celebration, after so many years of hardships and trouble, yet we were successful in opening the new home of the B'nai Zion Nursery, which building was completed over seven years ago, and standing idle due to a shortage of funds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1467.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The house warming ceremonies were celebrated in the largest hall in the basement of the nursery. The audience was in a holiday mood. The platform was covered with flowers and looked like a bed of roses.</p>
   <p>The program of the nursery opening consisted of speeches, greetings, music, and money.</p>
   <p>The program was announced by Mrs. Edwin Romberg, the president of the nursery, who was also the chairlady of the opening ceremonies. She was highly applauded. A thunder of applause was received by Mrs. Charna Riger, the founder of the nursery, who is now honorary president of this great and noble institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1468.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among those who touched the hearts of the audience with their speeches were Rabbi Silver, Rabbi Burzinsky, and the health commission, Dr. Kagel, who spoke of the devotion of a mother to a child, and of the necessity of a child to have a mother, even though a strange mother, when you have not your own. The president's husband, Colonel Romberg, also spoke and so did Attorney Louis Riger, the superintendant of the building, who also announced the names of those who donated cash, and those who pledged.</p>
   <p>A musical program in which the soprano singer Marcia Shupak was very good also the thirteen year old boy, Herbert Shay, who sang theatrical songs, and his grandfather's Sabbath Hymns. This boy was raised in this nursery, and he explained it with great pride.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1469.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Greetings were offered by many organizations who contributed thousands of dollars. All in all the sum raised at this opening was twenty thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Scenes of real happiness and joy were seen after the ceremonies when a mob of women hugged and kissed Mrs. Riger and congratulated her on this success. Then the people visited the children numbering over one hundred that were already transferred to their new home.</p>
   <p>This afternoon our bazaar for the nursery opens and will continue throughout the week and will end with a banquet next Sunday night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
