<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">January 29, 1923</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">January 29, 1923</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of Jewish women organized in Chicago for the purpose of constructing their own building in the Los Angeles Sanitarium.</p>
   <p>The first meeting of this new women's organization was held last Wednesday evening, January 24, in the Labor Lyceum. Mrs. M. Miller was the chairlady at the meeting.</p>
   <p>At the meeting, Mr. Flantzer, representative of the Los Angeles Sanitarium in Chicago, spoke of the necessity of the Sanitarium and the struggle it carries on for its existence. He paused especially at the condition of the Chicago patients, which is not a very favorable one, because of the quota from patients who have applied to the Sanitarium and because of the inadequate room for the Chicago division. It would, therefore, be a great accomplishment if Chicago will construct their own building - for its patients only. The women's organization has, at its first meeting, determined to work enthusiastically for this purpose. Thus far, the organization consists of twenty-five members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1192.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following were appointed as officers: Mrs. B. J. Rubin, chairlady; Mrs. Sofia Weiner, treasurer; Mrs. D. Burnstein, recording secretary; Miss L. Bernstein, financial secretary; Mrs. Anna Ripkin, first trustee. Executive Committee: Mrs. B. Liss, Mrs. H. Schaffner, Mrs. M. Miller, Mrs. E. Goldberg, Mrs. B. Duboff, Mrs. Finkelstein, Mrs. Kulanoff, Mrs. Scheffens and Mrs. Roff.</p>
   <p>The name of the women's organization is - Chicago Aid for the Los Angeles Sanitarium.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
