<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1926-12-03">December 3, 1926</date>. Vol. 9, p.4.
<title level="a">Continue the Good Work</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1926-12-03">December 3, 1926</date>. Vol. 9, p.4.
<title level="a">CONTINUE THE GOOD WORK</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Star Auxiliary of the Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home will celebrate the twentieth anniversary of its inception next Tuesday. It seems but a short time ago that this organization was founded to definitely assist the Home in coping with the many problems raised by the many needs of over 330 orphan children of all ages.</p>
   <p>At the beginning, the functions of the Auxiliary were two-fold. The Home's constantly increasing budget had to be met, and so recourse was made to every possible source of revenue. The Star Auxiliary did yeoman service in this duty, and turned in thousands of dollars to the Home's treasury. But the founders of this organization had another aim in mind when they founded the Star Auxiliary. It was to help the orphan children in every possible way. Many of the members have acted as foster-mothers. Others have taken upon themselves the burden of supervising outings, of sewing circles, and the other activities of the Home.</p>
   <p>An anniversary is always a period of stock-taking. It seems that one phase of the Auxiliary's activities is definitely ended. No longer is there a need of <pb facs="5423972_6_1471.jpg" n="2"/>a money-raising group, but there is a great and increasing need for a group that will help the children of the Home on their way to sound citizenship.</p>
   <p>These Jewish mothers of Chicago, banded together in the Star Auxiliary, will be serving the Home and the Jewish community by continuing and expanding their present work. Many orphan children, babes in arms when the Auxiliary was first founded, now have grown to young men and women and are leaving the Home.</p>
   <p>A young man or young woman needs the care of some Mother in Israel while finding himself or herself in new and strange surroundings. We are sure that the Star Auxiliary will rise to its new responsibility and new opportunity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
