<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-07">June 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Thirteenth Convention of Brith Sholom Opens Sunday</title><title level="a" type="sub">Over Seven Hundred Delegates from Every Part of the Country Expected; Convention Will Be Held in Baltimore</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-07">June 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THIRTEENTH CONVENTION OF BRITH SHOLOM OPENS SUNDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Over Seven Hundred Delegates from Every Part of the Country Expected; Convention Will Be Held in Baltimore</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thirteenth annual convention of the Independent Order Brith Sholom will open in Baltimore this Sunday and will continue through Tuesday. It is expected that over seven hundred delegates will attend, representing about fifty-five thousand Jews in one hundred and five cities and twenty-two states of America. This Order is one of the youngest in the country. And since many of its members are affected by the war, one of the features of this convention will be war relief.</p>
   <p>It is expected that Governor Harrington of Maryland, Mayor Preston of Baltimore, and Congressman Charles F. Coy will address the convention at its opening, Sunday morning. Many prominent Jews, members of the Order, will deliver addresses of greeting to the members. An invitation to address the <pb facs="5423972_6_0699.jpg" n="2"/>convention was also sent to Lord Reading, the British Ambassador in Washington.</p>
   <p>At this convention a tablet will be unveiled commemorating the "golden record" of this Order for the past year, viz. the sale of Liberty bonds totalling $1,268,350; war-savings and thrift stamps totalling $34, 842.75; eighty-three members and three thousand, nine hundred and twenty-four sons of members in the United States military service. All of these (enlisted men and their families) are entitled to the benefits of the Order, and are exempt from any financial obligations.</p>
   <p>The Chicago delegates to this convention are: David Ossov, deputy of Dr. Halperin Lodge; Samuel Blair, deputy of the Bessarabian Lodge; and Jacob Cohen, deputy of Cobriner Lodge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
