<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-03-27">March 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Danger</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-03-27">March 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT DANGER</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the office of the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities comes the report that despite the continual in flow of subscriptions, the collections are very weak. The people subscribe very readily, but defer the submission of their checks from day to day. This utimately leads to the lack of funds with which to finance all welfare institutions.</p>
   <p>Such conduct imperils the very existence of every Jewish welfare institution in Chicago. It must not be forgotten that no other institution has any source of support than the monthly allowance of the Federation, and if the treasury of the Federation should be emptied, then every institution would remain without an opportunity to function.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0796.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Federation requires more than ten thousand dollars a month to operate and this sum must be raised in cash - not in subscriptions.....</p>
   <p>Four hundred dollars a day must flow into the treasury of the Federation in order to provide for the orphans and aged, impoverished and sick, newcomers and deceased. The Chicago Jewry promised more than the needed sum, but to date they have not kept their promise. The enthusiasm and devotion of the Chicago Jewry terminated with the signing of their subscriptions.</p>
   <p>Of the one hundred thousand dollars, which was promised to the Federation by Chicago Jewry, less than thirty thousand dollars were submitted to the office; seventy per cent of the money is still in the hands of the donors, and this money belongs to our orphans, widows, aged and destitute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0797.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is true that every Jew will send his subscribed sum by the end of the year, out we cannot tell the orphans and widows to wait until the ehd of the year.....A dollar, when in need, has greater value than two when not in need. The subscription is a light matter to the subscriber. A few dollars will neither decrease nor increase his wealth if he should retain the money for a few months, but if all these sums are in the office of the Federation it means a colossal sum, a more secure foundation for all Jewish welfare institutions.</p>
   <p>Tardiness in submitting the subscriptions to the office, results in greater office expense. A person must be hired to send out extra bills, to write appeals, letters, and other announcements; postage, printing, etc., and it certainly is not the object of the contributors to pay such expenses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
