<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-03-24">Mar. 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A New Talmud Torah for the Far West Side of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-03-24">Mar. 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW TALMUD TORAH FOR THE FAR WEST SIDE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since many Jews have moved away from the Jewish center, the Ghetto, farther west, it was discovered that a new Talmud Torah was needed in the new Jewish neighborhood because the present Moses Montifiore Talmud Torah is too far from the new settlement.</p>
   <p>Needles to say, a Talmud Torah is entirely different from any other Jewish institution. Other institutions are supported mainly by the liberal donations of wealthy Jews; but a Talmud Torah, in addition to receiving donations, expects its pupils to pay tuition in order to keep up the institution.</p>
   <p>We are indebted to Rabbi Fisher for this Talmud Torah project in the new settlement. The Rabbi is a young, energetic, religious worker, and he understands the modern way of doing things. He realizes the necessity of this institution for the West Side Jew. The Rabbi assures us that the Talmud Torah will open soon after the Passover holidays and will be conducted in accordance with modern principles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There will be no tuition fee. "The support of this project," Rabbi Fisher said, "will come from Jews who have their Judaism at heart, and who will see to it that this holy cause is taken care of by liberal donations." A free Sabbath school for boys and girls who cannot come to Hebrew school on the weekdays will also be established.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Fisher will be the superintendent, and he will select the very best Hebrew teachers to teach and train our children in a most modern and up-to-date manner. The officers who are selected to look after this holy cause are: Mr. Moses Newman, president; Mr. Moses Schwartz, vice-president; Mr. Stern, secretary; and Messrs. S. Steiner, L. Pichell, and A. Fish, trustees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
