<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-15">April 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Public Cook-Pot. (Local News Column)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-15">April 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Public Cook-Pot. (Local News Column)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>West Park No. 2. - Its activity and development - Men and Jews - The difference - The Beth Michsa Orphan Home - Report of Michael Reese Hospital.</p>
   <p>West Park No. 2, the newest addition to the Chicago Park System, has proved to be a great success. The park is situated in the most thickly populated district and in the heart of Chicago. Within a half mile radius of the park, there is a population of ten thousand school children, who use this park to its utmost advantage.</p>
   <p>West Park No. 2 borders on Barber, Jefferson, Union Streets and 14th Place. The gymnasium of the park already has a registration of 2,200 children. More than 20,000 children visited the park during the month of March last. West Park No. 2 has a kindergarten, gymnasium, various club rooms, assembly hall, showers and many other facilities which the children may use. The park is open from early morning to late at night and children may participate in some activity through out the day.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The park being right in the center of the Jewish Ghetto, is always filled with Jewish children and since it is a public project and not a philanthropic project, people who come there feel perfectly at home. Mr. Sidney A. Teller, the Director of West Park No. 2, is a bright Jewish young man and fully understands the spirit and character of the people who use the facilities of the park. Under his direction, all activities are carried on in an orderly fashion.</p>
   <p>A branch of the Public Library is currently being established at the park, and with the coming of the summer months, many more thousands of children of the neighborhood will take advantage of the facilities of the park. These children will no longer wander aimlessly through the streets and get into mischief. The children have planted a hundred trees in the park and quite a festival is planned for Arbor Day.</p>
   <p>This park should be a lesson to our Jewish Civic Leaders. They should realize that in their efforts to build a Jewish Community, such projects should be left to public officials. Our community has neither the means nor the ability to deal with such a problem. Jewish Civic Leaders should confine their activities to freeing the "Spirit" of the Jew.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0520.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are happy to see our Jewish youth develop physically through their athletic activity, but our meager funds should be spent in an entirely different direction. That money should be spent to build a Spiritual Center, through the establishment of Jewish Libraries, Jewish Schools, Yiddish Lectures, Yiddish Debates, plays of Jewish Life, Jewish Culture Clubs and other activities which will give the Jew a new lease on life. The sooner our Jewish Civic Leaders realize this, the sooner the Jewish Cultural Center will become a reality.</p>
   <p>The last meeting of the Marks Nathan Orphan Home brought out some interesting discussions. It was shown that an orphan who can live with one of the parents lives a happier and more normal life than a child who grows up in an Orphan Home. This is sometimes true in spite of new methods, new approach, and new fangled ideas about how an Orphan Home should be conducted. It is proposed that enough be provided to the mother that she be able to keep the child with her rather than in an Orphan Home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0521.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Why have Jewish Orphan Homes? - To raise Jews. We wish our Jewish orphan youth to have the advantage in training and upbringing of any other Jewish youth. Our Jewish Orphan Home is not being supported mainly out of pity. It is to raise them as Jews with an understanding of their people. Therefore we think an orphan belongs in an institution which understands most.</p>
   <p>The Michael Reese Hospital report for the month of March states that there were a total of 754 patients who remained 7,818 days. Of these, 448 were free patients with 4,891 days; 173 ward patients, 1,756 days; 133 private room patients, 171 days.</p>
   <p>(Signed) The Cook - Spoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
