<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-02-09">February 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">President's Address to Jewish Charities</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-02-09">February 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT'S ADDRESS TO JEWISH CHARITIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Perhaps potentially the most important result of the drive last spring was the formation of the Community Council. In the course of that effort it became apparent not only to members of the Board of the Jewish Charities but also to others who had participated in that drive, that it was an economic waste to build up a campaign organization and then to scrap it at the end of an intensive effort. Furthermore it had always been apparent that the Jewish Charities should reach into the various organizations other than charitable organizations in the community - into the synagogues, clubs and lodges - that the Charities should reach with its message into the homes; that the Charities should reach with its message into all professions, trades and industrial groups, that this in time would bring understanding of the Charities, and would be of great value to the community of Chicago - more particularly to the Jewish community of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This in time, if properly approached and properly carried forward, would create a public opinion favorable to the Jewish Charities as a community instrumentality for the proper organization of Jewish philanthropy. Such a procedure, if carried out, would also create for us an intelligent group of not only contributors but also of active persons who would be a bulwark of strength in all the work that the Charities might attempt to do.</p>
   <p>THE COMMUNITY COUNCIL.</p>
   <p>For all of these reasons, those who were active in the campaign decided that a Community Council should be known as the Community Council of the Jewish Charities; that in a sense it should function as a somewhat separate organization; and that as time goes on, the Community Council should be intelligently informed concerning problems that exist in the world-at-large but with particular reference as to how those problems are being reflected in the work of the Charities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0542.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I would forbear to mention the names of all the 1,035 men drawn from all the professions, industries, trades and social groups in Chicago's Jewish community.</p>
   <p>Our persistence has brought about the organization of thirty-one groups - and eleven groups are in the process of organization. These groups are expanding the list of contributors to the Jewish Charities, particularly among those who might give less than $250.00.</p>
   <p>Three public meetings of the Community Council have been held. Outstanding speakers have come to these meetings, presented problems that directly should interest intelligent Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0543.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>THE WOMEN'S DIVISION.</p>
   <p>Growing out of the campaign last spring, there has also been formed a committee which will build up a Women's Division for the Jewish Charities. The Women's Division of the campaign, as you will recall, was headed by Mrs. Samuel Alschuler, who rendered a notable service, together with Mrs. Milton F. Goodman of our board, who was chairman of the Sponsors' Gifts Division of the women's group, and others who came out of the various women's organizations and gave us, indeed, a very remarkable service. They did raise over $40,000 which is an outstanding achievement in fund raising campaigns in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0544.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Primarily, the Women's Division is going to be an educational force. They are going to find out for themselves what it is that our institutions accomplish; they are going to spread that message, as the Women's Division, across to hundreds and perhaps thousands of women throughout the community; and they will ultimately, we hope, bring the Jewish Charities, its values and its work, into all the Jewish homes in our great city.</p>
   <p>SOCIAL WORK TO CONTINUE.</p>
   <p>That actual experience during the past several years has indicated that in a period of great disturbance there are, unfortunately, large numbers of people who need service, who need elementary and primitive kinds of relief, but who for various reasons cannot, under the laws that have been passed, obtain such relief. Even when the government's <pb facs="5423972_6_0545.jpg" n="6"/>relief law is liberalized, it still lags behind the actual need. For example, in spite of the transfer of hundreds of families from our own agency and thousands of families from other private agencies, we still had to spend, in the Jewish Social Bureau, during the past several years, anywhere from $200,000 to $400,000 more per year than we used to spend in times of prosperity.</p>
   <p>In other words, when you analyze the situation, what this period of depression has brought to us, after the utmost economies have been made and practiced by the institutions and by the Charities, after every possible advantage has been taken in the utilization of governmental funds and tax funds - we are still left with larger appropriations necessary for our institutions than in times of prosperity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
