<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-14">November 14, 1907</date><title level="a">Independent Sisters of Charity to Aid Expectant Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0878</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0878.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-11-14">November 14, 1907</date><title level="a">INDEPENDENT SISTERS OF CHARITY TO AID EXPECTANT MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Worthy public and sisters! The time has come when we should advertise our Society and its activities in newspapers just as other societies.</p>
   <p>Worthy Public! Our Society has now been in existance somewhat over a year. Many of you are already aware of our helpful work and our aid to expectant recent mothers who are in need of financial aid. We help the mother and child with money and clothes and anything else they might need.</p>
   <p>We invite you to our meetings to hear the reports of our secretaries on the activities of the organization. It is indeed tragic when poor mothers must suffer hunger and privation with a newly born babe on her hands.</p>
   <p>Chicago Women! We appeal to you because you as women are well <pb facs="5423972_6_0879.jpg" n="2"/>aware of the troubles of a mother who has just given birth to a child. We appeal to you in the name of the many many young mothers to join our organization and pledge yourselves, to pay five cents weekly to our organization to carry on its work. We beg you to come to our meetings every 2nd and 4th Wednesday of each month at Turek's Hall - 521 West Millar Street.</p>
   <p>Note! On December 7, of this year, our society will run a Ball at the West Chicago Club House,- 50 Throop Street. All proceeds will go to carrying on our invaluable work. We ask you to attend and bring your friends. A very fine evening of entertainment has been planned.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
