<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-21">April 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Hirsch Appeals for Orphans</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-21">April 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">DR. HIRSCH APPEALS FOR ORPHANS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We read an editorial of Dr. Hirsch in the last number of the Reform Advocate, in which he discussed the question of homes for the Jewish orphans in Chicago. He expressed his views on that subject very frankly, that private homes for the orphans is the best solution for the general welfare of the Jewish orphans. Of course, no one will dispute Dr. Hirsch or disagree with him from the standpoint of humanity, but nevertheless, he will admit that a move of this kind would be impossible to carry through for there are not enough homes to accommodate the great numbers of orphans. The Home Finding Society, which secures homes for orphans, is far from being able to accommodate all the orphans, hence, the home on the South Side, which is looked after by the German Jews of Chicago and is filled with orphans to its capacity. Also the Marks Nathan Orphans Home, which takes care of 180 inmates.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Marks Nathan Orthodox Jewish Orphans Home, is a building which is far from being a suitable place for an orphan asylum. That is why Dr. Hirsch is making this appeal to the Associated Jewish Charities, to see to it that the orthodox Jews get the assistance for building a new suitable home for their orphans.</p>
   <p>The non-orthodox orphans home, says Dr. Hirsch, is full of orphans, the Home Finding Society is doing all it possibly can for their orphans. So it is up to us orthodox Jews of Chicago to get busy and not sit with our hands folded when we see the 180 orphans in an overcrowded building, who are begging for more room and more sanitary quarters. We, the orthodox Jews of Chicago, heartily endorse Dr. Hirsch's appeal. We are aware of the fact that it is utterly impossible for us to build a new home, we have not the means to build enough rooms for the 180 <pb facs="5423972_6_1622.jpg" n="3"/>orphans and for other orphans who constantly knock at our doors for admittance. So we hope that our German Jewish brethren will respond to the appeal of their Rabbi Hirsch, their religious and moral teacher. His words, which come from a Jewish heart, will enter into all Jewish hearts and must make a true and proper impression on his listeners.</p>
   <p>We also hope that all our Russian Jews will cooperate in assisting with the building of a new home for our orthodox Jewish orphans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
