<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-11">Jan. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Come and Hear Zangwill Speak Next Sunday Evening at the Hebrew Institute</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-11">Jan. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">COME AND HEAR ZANGWILL SPEAK NEXT SUNDAY EVENING AT THE HEBREW INSTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Sunday evening, all those who have obtained tickets to the lecture at the Hebrew Institute will be able to see and hear Israel Zangwill, England's foremost writer and one of the finest sons of the Jewish people. He will speak on the subject: "Anti-Semitism and other Jewish problems".</p>
   <p>Among other things, you will hear Mr. Zangwill tell what he thinks about the enemy of Israel, Henry Ford, and his friends. He will tell us about the Ku Klux Klan, which seeks to set the Christian world against us, which besmirches the Jewish character, which seeks to undermine our existence in America, which has already caused pogroms against Jews in Europe, which seeks to bribe Jewish traitors so that it may claim that it is not against <pb facs="5423972_6_0302.jpg" n="2"/>the poor Jews but only against the Jewish capitalists. Henry Ford and his friends have recently become staunch defenders of the Negroes--the Jews exploit them, the Jews poison them by various powders and pills. Actually, deep in their hearts, they hate the Negroes but--to strengthen their terrible propaganda--they represent the Negroes as innocent lambs whom the Jewish businessman and the Jewish capitalist seek to rob and kill. Henry Ford and his friends, who seek money, money, and more money, want to bring disaster upon our people. Mr. Zangwill's protest against these wicked and cruel men will do us a great deal of good at the present time. Zangwill has a lot of influence upon the thinking and honest non-Jewish world. It will listen to him. It will not listen to him if we ourselves do not listen to him.</p>
   <p>It is expected that the big hall of the Institute will be overcrowded because the appearance of Mr. Zangwill on Sunday evening will be his first and only public appearance before Chicago Jews during his present visit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0303.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Who of us is not curious to sec the celebrated man? Who of us is not curious to hear what he has to say? The important thing is: Do not forget to buy tickets. The earlier you come, the better a seat you will have in the hall. The price of each seat in the hall is one dollar; gallery--fifty cents.</p>
   <p>A rare spiritual treat awaits you. You will learn a great deal and you will be comforted in your Jewish sorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
