<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">February 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Have Unique Plan to Raise Funds for Charity</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">February 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">HAVE UNIQUE PLAN TO RAISE FUNDS FOR CHARITY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A novel method of securing public support to cover its deficit has been adopted by the Jewish Hebrew Charities. The Jewish communal institution of the city have endorsed the plan and have sent out a circular letter, asking that the gas rebates, which are due consumers, owing to the recent decision of the United States Court reducing gas rates from one dollar to eighty cents be sent to the United Hebrew Charities, which will collect on the account and withhold as much of the net receipts as the consumer may desire, giving him the benefit of the collection, and an opportunity to contribute to the Charities from this unexpected source.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0865.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The circular letter reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Give your gas rebates to the poor:</p>
   <p>"The demand upon the United Hebrew Charities has never been so great in the thirty-four years of its existence. Although industrial conditions have somewhat improved, the number of unemployed is still very large, and their condition is worse than it was a year ago. Savings are completely exhausted, and the year of depression has told upon the vital forces making a tremendous increase in sickness. In the month of December 1908, the Charities distributed $36,000 for rent, food, clothing, coal and other absolute necessities of destitute Jews. In the current month the disbursements are even larger.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0866.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Unless this work shall cease, $120,000 in addition to what is now in sight, must be raised at once. It is, therefore, suggested that in the emergency all interested in the welfare of the Jewish poor should donate to the United Hebrew Charities the money to be refunded for gas rebates. The Charities will relieve the holders of rebates of all trouble of collection, and, if so desired, will send one-half of the full amount, retaining the remainder for the benefit of the poor."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
