<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Sheltering Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0733</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0733.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE SHELTERING HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of the board of directors of the Chicago Hebrew Sheltering Home, which was held last Monday, those present listened to reports announcing the completion of a new Shelter Home by next month. The remodeling and furnishing of the building on Morgan near Maxwell are being rapidly carried out, thanks to the encouraging support, both moral and financial, coming from the Federated Charities.</p>
   <p>The new Hebrew Sheltering Home is the child of the Federated Charities. The Hebrew Sheltering Home differs from the other institutions which are under the supervision of the Federated Societies. These other institutions had all been established on an independent basis long before the Federated Charities was organized, whereas the Hebrew Sheltering Home, from its very inception, has been administered by the Federated Charities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0734.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The relationship between the Federated Charities and the Hebrew Sheltering Home is clearly expressed in the latter's constitution. The constitution adopted by the directors reads in part as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Hebrew Sheltering Home of the Chicago Federated Charities shall be subject to the Orthodox Jewish Charities and must operate under the constitution and the by-laws of the Federated Charities."</p>
   <p>It is of utmost importance for the Chicago donors to recognize and support the affiliation of the Sheltering Home with the Federated Charities. The prospects for the continued maintenance of the new Sheltering Home will thereby be strengthened, because the existence of the Home depends upon the financial success and the moral influence of the Federated Charities.</p>
   <p>The basic aim of the Federated Charities, like that of all united charity <pb facs="5423972_6_0735.jpg" n="3"/>organizations, is unified activity. The community should cooperate by raising funds. The Federated Charities seeks to eliminate the old wasteful methods of collecting funds, and it has been successful in this aim. The public can now see all the other gains which have been achieved through the methods of the Federated Charities and can now appreciate why the organization should be supported. The success of the Federated Charities will mean the success of various charitable institutions, particularly that of its new member--the Hebrew Sheltering Home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
