<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-18">Jan. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-18">Jan. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MARKS NATHAN JEWISH ORPHAN HOME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eighteenth annual meeting of the Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home took place last Sunday afternoon, January 14, 1923, at the Home.</p>
   <p>The president, Charles I. Herron, submitted his report, as did the officers and chairmen of the various committees. Mr. Herron, in his report, referred at length to the recent amalgamation of the Associated and Federated Charities in one central organization "The Jewish Charities of Chicago", and pledged the new organization and its president, Mr. Julius Rosenwald, in behalf of the Home, its loyal support. He also regretted exceedingly, the resignation from the Home Directorate of Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, who has been placed on the Board of Jewish Charities of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The annual report, which was quite lengthy, outlined in detail the main features of the work of the Home during the year 1922 and pointed out the needs of the <pb facs="5423972_6_1504.jpg" n="2"/>home for the coming year.</p>
   <p>The following new directors were elected to fill vacancies for the ensuing year:</p>
   <p>Messrs. Sam Levitetz, Isadore Growoig, Carles Levy, Louis M. Feder, Hyman N. Kohn, George B. Kurtzon, Nathan Gumbinsky, Max Korshak, Louis Gold. The annual meeting was followed by the first meeting of the 1923 Board, when the election of officers took place as follows:</p>
   <p>President, Charles I. Herron, for the tenth consecutive year; Vice-presidents, I. Klawans and Sam Steiner; Recording Secretary, Mrs. H. Olenik; Financial Secretary, M. F. Wittele; Treasurer Leo Shafton. Trustees, Jacob Levy, David Kolb, M. Snower, E. Braude, Charles Mitchell. [Editor's note: This article is in English originally. It has not been edited in the usual manner.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
