<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-05-02">May 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Fine Opportunity for Jewish Boys</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-05-02">May 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A FINE OPPORTUNITY FOR JEWISH BOYS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. David Blaustein, the Superintendent of the Hebrew Institute, has undertaken the task of representing the National Farm School of Book County, Pennsylvania, in Chicago, although he is already overburdened with many responsibilities. At the national farm school Jewish boys are taught modern agriculture. Dr. Kreiskop, who urged Dr. Blaustein to accept the appointment as Chicago's representative, promised him that Jewish boys from Chicago who wish to learn agriculture at the school will be given preferred consideration. Parents who are uncertain about a future for their sons should by no means overlook this opportunity, and should file an application with Dr. Blaustein. Since only a few weeks remain until June 1, the date set for the commencement of the new semester, parents should not delay in filing an application for their sons. Pupils will not be accepted after June 1.</p>
   <p>Everyone should know something about agriculture. Farming and cultivation of the soil are very interesting occupations. Jews, in particular, should be interested in agriculture. Our forefathers, before the Exile, were farmers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We expect to return to our land and be farmers.</p>
   <p>Agriculture is the noblest and healthiest of all occupations. It builds strong and healthy men and women. We need a strong and healthy generation. If anything will increase our strength and national pride, it undoubtedly will be agriculture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
