<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1888-05-04">May 4, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A Magnificent Start</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1888-05-04">May 4, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A MAGNIFICENT START</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A joint meeting of the ladies of the Jewish Training School of Chicago and of a large number of our best Jewish citizens and the committee of the Leon Mandel Gift of $20,000 for a Training School, met on Tuesday evening last, to hear the report of the committee heretofore appointed to present a plan for a common organization. Mr. Joseph Spiegel presided and Mr. Martin Bache acted as secretary. The committee reported as follows:</p>
   <p>That we adopt the present charter of the Jewish Training School and work under it.</p>
   <p>That its board of directors consist of eight ladies and eight gentlemen.</p>
   <p>That the president, vice-president, secretary and treasurer be elected by the association from the members of said directors at their meeting.</p>
   <p>That the objective shall be to maintain a training school for boys and girls under eighteen years of age - 1. To maintain a kindergarten; 2. Girls' serving and kitchen garden; 3. Manual training and trade school.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Said directors to have power to acquire by purchase or otherwise suitable property for that object.</p>
   <p>Membership. - Membership shall consist of three classes: General members paying $4.00 and upwards annually; patron members $125.00 and upwards annually; life members $500.00 and upwards annually, the amount already subscribed to be deducted from said $500.00</p>
   <p>Each of these resolutions was adopted. It will be remembered that the Ladies' Industrial School was organized some six years since; in 1886 a new charter was obtained under the title of The Jewish Training School of Chicago, and the organization will continue using, most likely, the same name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
