<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-03-06">March 6, 1909</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-03-06">March 6, 1909</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>March 3, 1909.</p>
   <p>Mme. President and Fellow Members of the Jewish Consumptive Relief Society of Chicago:</p>
   <p>I beg leave to submit my second annual report of the Aid Committee. During the last two years, the number of cases was steadily increasing, necessitating a greater expenditure of time and labor, in attending to the situation. At present, the cases of tuberculosis under our care are scattered over different parts of the city, and the necessity of closer medical observation of every patient, led to the suggestion by Dr. Sacks, that we appoint a staff of physicians from the different sections of the city to maintain closer medical contact with each individual case. This suggestion was favorably acted upon by our organization, and following physicians were appointed: Drs. I. A. Abt, J. M. Abelio, J. B. Beck, Leo Bloch, M. Biensenthal, Ben H. Breakstone, J. A. Britton, H. Cohn, S. G. Cohen, Charles T. Clark, I. B. Diamond, Theo <pb facs="5423972_6_1387.jpg" n="2"/>Druzdowitz, J. L. Eisendrath, Charles Erickson, D. J. Franklin, Bernard Fantus, B. Feltenstein, E. Friend, J. K. Golden, Louie E. Gordon, Eton A. Gray, N. Galland, Geo. Halpern, G. B. Hassin, A. S. Hirschfield, H. E. Hanke, J. F. Hultgen, Wm. Jaffee, V. Josephson, Harry Kahn, S. Krumholz, H. C. Novalsheslky, Paul Pollock, L. J. Pritzker, A. B. Raff, Wm. Rightman, S. Rosenbloom, A. A. Roth, J. A. Roth, Geo. Rubin, John Ritter, Theo B. Sachs, M. Sahud, M. J. Salmson, A. M. Shabad, Chas. Segal, J. D. Silverman, I. Sissman, R. Sonnenschein, E. F. Snydacker, M. Thorek, F. Tice, F. S. Tuft, J. S. Weiss, B. Weisenberg, C. L. Wisstosky, M. B. Wolff, S. L. Zeltner, and L. E. Zins.</p>
   <p>We are indebted to the visiting nurses' association for their assistance in caring for special cases. The district nurses have taken a great deal of interest in our cases, reporting to us whenever anything of importance occurred. As you know, most of our cases, if not all of them, are living in the congested districts, under the most unhygienic surroundings. The patient is obliged to share his room and frequently his bed with one or more members of the family. This room is often small with only a small window opening on <pb facs="5423972_6_1388.jpg" n="3"/>to a court of dark passageway where the sun never enters. Our first duty is to move this patient to more favorable quarters, and we have succeeded in doing so with eleven of our cases this year. The provision of a separate room for a tuberculous patient requires frequently the removal of the entire family to more spacious quarters. This requires the expenditure of considerable time, labor, and influence. While this measure was fully enforced in only a limited number of cases, it was expected that this line of work will steadily develop. Our friendly visitors, having had four years of experience with tuberculous patients, are capable of giving instructions as to the proper care of the consumptive and his family, and it is gratifying to report that they find the home, after a few visits, kept clean, the windows wide open, and the patient carrying out the instructions. Every incipient case reported to us receives our immediate attention, and an effort is made to secure admission for the patient to the National Jewish Hospital at Denver, Colorado.</p>
   <p>While waiting for admission, our society supplies the patient with the necessary nourishment, and if conditions demand immediate sanitarium treatment, <pb facs="5423972_6_1389.jpg" n="4"/>he is placed in a local institution to prevent further progress of the disease. We receive excellent reports from the discharged cases sent to the National Jewish Hospital. A cure is effected in most cases, or an arrest of the disease takes place, thus enabling them to resume their former usefulness. During the year we have treated one hundred and four cases, of which sixty-three were new cases, and forty-one cases that have received treatment before.</p>
   <p>We have had an average of fifty-four cases continually on our books at the cost of $7.59 per month for each patient, for milk, butter and eggs. Besides the above mentioned aid, each patient has been attended by one of our staff of physicians and a visiting nurse. Whenever necessary we provide the patient with proper clothing and furnish all medical supplies.</p>
   <p>We have had a large number of advanced cases on our books this year, which accounts for the large number of deaths, but it gives us satisfaction to know that we are able to prolong life, and give them all the necessary attention <pb facs="5423972_6_1390.jpg" n="5"/>so that their last hours were comfortable and none of our patient's members of the family had cause to regret that their beloved ones had died without medical attention, or other assistance.</p>
   <p>We have also attended to the disinfection of all houses occupied by a former consumptive, through cooperation with the City Board of Health.</p>
   <p>Of the one hundred and four cases under our observation, three were cases of bone tuberculosis, two of throat, one of the spine, and ninety-eight suffering from pulmonary tuberculosis. Twelve patients were sent to the National Jewish Hospital at Denver, three to the Jewish Consumptive's Relief Societies Sanitarium at Denver, four to Maywood for permanent residence, where they are under our observation, two were deported by the authorities, two went to Europe of their own accord, one left for Texas, two for California, one for New Mexico, our society contributing to their transportation. Twenty-eight patients were partly maintained by our society at Dunning. Nineteen have died.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1391.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Expenditures.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Milk</cell>
     <cell>$1,018.02</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Butter and eggs</cell>
     <cell>663.85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Naperville Sanitarium</cell>
     <cell>367.08</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>St. Ann Sanitarium</cell>
     <cell>231.70</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Dunning</cell>
     <cell>533.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Transportation</cell>
     <cell>27.60</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Laundry</cell>
     <cell>38.54</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$2,880.54</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>It is very unwillingly that I approach this portion of my report, but the report would not be complete if I do not mention the difficulty which we encountered in our work with the consumptives, namely: the frequency with which the consumptives have children. This fact is deplorable because children born under such conditions are bound to have tuberculous tendencies. Two babies are being nursed by tuberculous mothers at the present time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1392.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In closing I wish to express my sincerest thanks to the following: to Mrs. S. Contarsy for the thorough and conscientious investigations. To members of the Aid Committee for their friendly visiting and complete reports. To the physicians of our staff who responded to all our calls. To the Visiting Nurses' Association, the Board of Health, the Jewish Aid Society and the West Side Ladies Charity Society for their friendly cooperation. To the President, Officers and Board of Directors for extending all possible assistance to me.</p>
   <p>Respectfully submitted</p>
   <p>Mrs. J. B. Malkes, Chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
