<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-21">June 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">New Hospital to Open in September</title><title level="a" type="sub">Plans for Opening Mt. Sinai Hospital Are Complete</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-21">June 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEW HOSPITAL TO OPEN IN SEPTEMBER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Plans for Opening Mt. Sinai Hospital Are Complete</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago will soon have a new kosher hospital on the West Side. That is, the hospital will not be new. But the name and the administration will be new. It will be the old Maimonides Hospital under the new name, "Mt. Sinai Hospital". And according to the reorganization committee, which met last night, the Mt. Sinai Hospital will open the second week in September of this year.</p>
   <p>The reorganization committee is practically finished with its work. It has everything in readiness for the opening of the hospital. And at the next meeting the election of regular officers and a board of twenty-one directors will take place.</p>
   <p>For the two years during which the reorganization committee has worked, it has raised fifteen thousand dollars and has worked out plans for an annual <pb facs="5423972_6_1250.jpg" n="2"/>income of a similar sum. And according to the committee, this will be enough to cover the deficit resulting from charity cases.</p>
   <p>The building and everything in it belong, as is known, to Mr. Morris Kurtzon, who purchased it all over a year ago. He could have made a profit on this purchase. But his plan was to establish a kosher hospital for the local Jewish community. And now Mr. Kurtzon believes he stands at the threshold of the realization of his plan, his dream.</p>
   <p>Last night at the meeting he displayed a letter from Mr. Edmond J. James, president of the University of Illinois, offering seventy-five thousand dollars for the hospital. He refused this huge profit in order to enable the Chicago Jews to have their own hospital. The principal and the accrued interest on the building will be refunded to Mr. Kurtzon; yet his act in refusing to sell the hospital for a profit will remain everlastingly to his credit.</p>
   <p>The hospital will repay him the fifty thousand dollars and the interest in <pb facs="5423972_6_1251.jpg" n="3"/>the form of rent, and other forms of reimbursement, at the rate of about seven thousand dollars a year.</p>
   <p>According to the plans, the hospital will open with fifty beds, most of them for charity cases. People have already been employed to fix and remodel the interior of the building.</p>
   <p>At the next meeting all details will be worked out. The superintendent of the hospital will be the well-known surgeon, Dr. H. M. Richter, and he will have the authority to choose doctors and nurses.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Edwin Romberg, chairman of the ladies' hospital auxiliary, which numbers about eight hundred members, handed over a check for forty-two hundred dollars at last night's meeting, which sum was made up of the dues from the women of this organization. The hospital will also have a young people's auxiliary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1252.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The most active members of the reorganization committee who deserve most credit for the reopening of the hospital are: Morris Kurtzon, J. Bernard, Marcus Yacobowsky, vice-president of the Fort Dearborn Bank, Mrs. Edwin Romberg, Mrs. Ignace Reiss, Mr. and Mrs. Meyer Helstein, Mrs. Jacob N. Grossberg, Mr. Henry Reissman, Mr. George Fine, and many others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
