<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Daughters of Jacob South Side Day and Night Nursery Opens a Drive for Forty Thousand Dollars</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-12-30">December 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DAUGHTERS OF JACOB SOUTH SIDE DAY AND NIGHT NURSERY OPENS A DRIVE FOR FORTY THOUSAND DOLLARS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Friends:</p>
   <p>We know that you faithfully trust in the aim for which this appeal is being made. We ask you, in the name of the homeless children, to read this appeal and contribute your share. You fully understand what it means for children who are without a mother or father, and are deprived of a home to be taken care of by some one who will provide them, as much as possible, with all necessities. This is one of the holiest and noblest things that a man can do.</p>
   <p>You know the golden rule, "Do unto others as you would have them do unto you."</p>
   <p>Thus, we are in need of a larger place in order to accept the orphans that are waiting for a home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1477.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have, therefore, made arrangements to purchase the building at 6401 South Peoria Street. The building must be paid for. New things must be bought in order to enroll children in the nursery.</p>
   <p>The Daughters of Jacob is an independent organization and is not connected with any other charity organization. We received a charter from the state in 1919 and the nursery was opened at 6320 S. Aberdeen Avenue, with ten children. Now there are always thirty children in the nursery and many more are taken care of during the day. The nursery is supported by dues and donations and proceeds from undertakings. Medical and dental services are rendered free by Drs. J. Greenberg and H. Semon.</p>
   <p>We call your attention to the fact that no high salaries are paid. The officers give their services without pay.</p>
   <p>Help the orphans. Send your contribution in promptly and see that your friends shall do the same. Lets make this drive successful.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>The Committee of the Drive,</p>
   <p>Dr. J. Greenbert, chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
