<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1930-10-30">October 30, 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1930-10-30">October 30, 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Board, the report by the Executive Director on the unemployment situation and condition of the Charities was submitted. The following facts were revealed. At present there are about 350,000 people unemployed in Chicago losing over $1,000,000 a day in wages. Relief agencies spend only $8,000 a day, therefore taking care only of those cases where the direst need exists.</p>
   <p>The Employment Bureau showed a steady upward trend of applications which had begun long before the stock market crash and which at the present time showed a doubling over last year. At the same time the number of placements have declined.</p>
   <p>Applications to the Jewish Social Service Bureau showed an upward trend but there was little variation in case count because of the fact that the Supervisors have been strict in their intake policy turning away service cases normally taken on and limiting intake to relief cases.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dispensary cases at Mandel Clinic and Mount Sinai show a steady upward trend in new patients with an increase of 100% in the case of Mandel Clinic. Many who formerly went to their own doctors are now coming to the dispensaries.</p>
   <p>If the present situation continues, the application to medical agencies will undoubtedly grow. The Governor's Committee on unemployment and relief will appeal to the various elements in the community to support their own charities and to give to those well organized to deal with the present emergency. The Charities must go to it's contributors before a multiplicity of drives now contemplated take place and confuse them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
