<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-13">Feb. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Our Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, a Principal in a Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-13">Feb. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, a Principal in a Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem remaining [Editor's note: this is the last of a series of articles by the same author] is the method a teacher should use in order to be successful in teaching his course of study. [In order to solve this problem], the first prerequisite is that competent and experienced teachers should be engaged. It is a well-known fact that a non-experienced craftsman will ruin his work even though he possesses the most elaborate tools, and a poor, incompetent teacher will not help his students become proficient even though he employs the best methods. A simple, ordinary, practical, but mechanical method of teaching Hebrew, like that used until the present, can be employed by "common" teachers--by people with "average" knowledge; but it will bring the least possible results. A new method, adaptable to the mental faculties of a child, and adjustable to the differences of the children should be put into practice. Such a method requires correct application, a knowledge of which few teachers possess. Any <pb facs="5423972_6_0057.jpg" n="2"/>teacher can pound the alphabet into the minds of his pupils; but teaching them to read intelligently instead of mechanically is another matter.</p>
   <p>To continue with the old methods, with the antiquated system, is very bad. In order to improve our teaching, a new method--one which will be a Jewish, national method and will be suited in our land and to the present conditions--and good practical teachers who can apply the method in a practical manner are needed. Where can we get such teachers?</p>
   <p>The teacher in an American Talmud Torah must have a thorough knowledge of the Hebrew language, the Bible, Hebrew grammar, Talmud, and modern Hebrew literature. He must also have a good command of the English language. The children are Americans, and if the teacher does not speak English properly they will lose respect for him. He must be a practical teacher, love his profession, and be devoted entirely to the Jewish studies.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Jewish teachers cling to teaching as part-time work--as an addition <pb facs="5423972_6_0058.jpg" n="3"/>to their chief financial sources. Most of them are shohatim who are engaged in slaughtering animals during the day and who conduct classes in the evenings. Very often they come to class unprepared to assign work. Usually they are tired from overwork and their hands and face are covered with drops of blood. Other teachers work in the factories until 3 P. M. in the afternoon and are very exhausted when they begin their work in the Hebrew schools. Aggravated and impatient, they pour out their wrath, anger, and grief piled up throughout the day upon the children. This sort of a teacher, who works part-time at a trade and part-time as a teacher, is a great pessimist. He, himself, does not believe in the possibility of [giving a child] a good Jewish education in America. His soul is filled with despondency. He detests his work. He looks forward to the happly day when he will be able to discard his teaching profession when he can get rid of this "cheap" and "ungracious" profession.</p>
   <p>There are, however, several intelligent young men who have good command of both the Hebrew and English language. Obviously they would make good teachers--in fact, they can become excellent teachers within a very short time. They possess the prerequisites in satisfactory proportions. They, however, refuse to become <pb facs="5423972_6_0059.jpg" n="4"/>teachers in Talmud Torahs since the wages are extremely low and the work is so hard. The wages are tragically low! I believe that picking feathers from chickens pays much more. Is it then surprising that the teachers seek other positions? The salary they receive as teachers is barely sufficient to supply a wife and children with food. And with what will they pay rent or buy clothing?</p>
   <p>We may say that the officials of the Talmud Torahs in Chicago do not wish to consider the necessity of an intelligent man making a decent living--a man in whose hands lies the future of Judaism in America; who is engaged in the most sacred of Jewish tasks, teaching; who is the peacemaker in a school; and who must influence and rear the future Jewish generation in this country. In fact, the teacher makes less than the poorest [dress] operator. Poverty leads to many [unpleasant] situations. He finds no peace in his home; the grief of his wife and his children embitter his life. He must resort to other means of a livelihood. He must lower himself and become ingratiatory. Our officials of the Talmud Torahs are responsible for bringing such a condition about by fixing such low salaries for the teachers. The day is not far when <pb facs="5423972_6_0060.jpg" n="5"/>the directors and the teachers will set forth, each, their new demands--the former will plead for better teachers, whereas the latter will demand human wages! Moreover, I wish to state with positiveness that so long as the teachers' work is evaluated at such a low level--so long as the wages will be so drastically low--so long will we not have any real professional teachers, and so long will we have to wait before scientific methods will be applied in all the Jewish schools of Chicago.</p>
   <p>[Several things can be done to better the situation]. First, all Jews should demand of the directors that a unified system should be set up to include all the Jewish schools in Chicago. All the teachers should then unite themselves into one association--at least the outstanding professional teachers of Chicago. The teachers should discuss the various methods of education and hear lectures on the subject. Such a union of all the Jewish schools and of the better teachers would help a great deal in improving the system of Hebrew instruction. Moreover, propaganda on the subject of education should be disseminated among the parents so that they may become more interested in the material welfare of the teachers. Let us trust that we have enough people in Chicago who will undertake this difficult, but vital task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
