<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-25">Oct. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Women of Charity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-25">Oct. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN OF CHARITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-known lady, Mrs. Chudnov, together with a few more distinguished and intelligent ladies, visited the Talmud Torah, and decided to organize a ladies auxiliary society. The board of the Talmud Torah was, naturally, very glad to accept this organization. This Society is now already established.</p>
   <p>The newly elected president said, in a written statement to the Talmud Torah organization: "Never would I have believed or dreamed that such conditions could exist in this holy institution on the West Side of our city. I am now aware of the circumstances: namely, that the expenses are double the income. I was very much surprised yesterday when I discovered this condition. I am very pleased and happy to see these charitable women on their second visit here, and welcome their fresh enthusiasm, energy, and encouragement in the new Auxiliary Society of the B'nai Zion Talmud Torah."</p>
   <p>The officers of the new Society are: Mrs. Chudnov, president; Mrs. Williams, <pb facs="5423972_6_0102.jpg" n="2"/>vice-president; Mrs. Karlinsky, treasurer; Mrs. G. Levin, secretary; and Mrs. Hoffberg, Mrs. Raft, Mrs. Estrin, and Mrs. Rosenthal, trustees.</p>
   <p>The new Society presented to the Talmud Torah $50.00. This is its first good deed. The members are confident that more money will follow. The president extended her thanks to the few women of charity for this great mitzvah (holy deed). We urge the Chicago Jewish public to join this Society and help the Talmud Torah teach our religion to the poor Jewish children in the proper manner.</p>
   <p>With lots of success,</p>
   <p>H. Weiss, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
