<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-08-27">Aug. 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Model Nurses School</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-08-27">Aug. 27, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">MODEL NURSES SCHOOL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By November 1st a model training school for nurses will be opened in connection with the Michael Reese Hospital. The contractors are now working on the first story of the building. Its name will be the Michael Reese Training School Building.</p>
   <p>It is being erected 100 feet north of the hospital the size being 30 x 80. The style is Romanesque with small towers, three stories, an attic, and basement. The building will have two fronts of pressed brick and Bedford stone with ornamental brick trimmings and mansard roof. On the first floor there will be a large lecture hall and matron's office.</p>
   <p>In order to make the instruction of the nurses more practical and complete there will be, in connection with the school, a hospital department. Obstetrical cases only will be taken in this department. Most of the first story and a portion of the basement will be used for the hospital department. There will be two general and two private wards, an operating and an isolating room, and large bath room to make the department complete.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The contracts call for the most scientific sanitary fittings and every room is to be plastered with cement so that the hose can be turned on them without damage. There will be separate entrances for the training school and the hospital department. The second and third stories are to be devoted entirely to sleeping rooms for the nurses and others. There are to be eighteen bedrooms with accomodation for forty nurses, but fifty persons can live comfortably in the building.</p>
   <p>The basement is arranged so that it can be used in the future for a large dining room and kitchen. The school which will cost over $15,000 will be paid for by the trustees of the Michael Reese estate and is expected to be self supporting.</p>
   <p>Simeon B. Eisendrath, the architect, spent much time in this and other cities examining the arrangements of hospitals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
