<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-18">Feb. 18, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Education for Girls</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-18">Feb. 18, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH EDUCATION FOR GIRLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several young Jewish men and women in Chicago have recently become interested in the matter of Jewish education for girls. According to their views, Jewish education, in which the best Jews are interested, is denied to the female sex. They, therefore, are determined to establish an organization to be called Agudoth Beth Sefer Lenaaroth. The program in the school for girls will include course in Hebrew, Bible, Jewish history, Hebrew literature, and national and Hebrew songs. The fee will be only fifteen cents a week.</p>
   <p>The organizers of this group know that it is impossible to create something of importance if the dues are so small. They are, therefore, attempting to secure the support of generous hearted men for the Agudoth Beth Sefer Lenaaroth so that the best teachers may be hired and the finest methods of teaching introduced. There is no doubt that such a school is a necessity in so large a Jewish <pb facs="5423972_6_0054.jpg" n="2"/>community as Chicago. It is also natural that as a result of the changes in the social structure, which are constantly occurring in our own times, the woman will become more independent.</p>
   <p>Truthfully speaking, we are not so much in need of an organization to extend Jewish education to Jewish girls. What Chicago needs is an organization to extend Jewish education to Jewish children. The first question, therefore, which we can put before these noble people is: If you have the financial and cultural opportunity to erect Jewish school--let us assume even only one modern Jewish school--why should boys be excluded from that school? Even the gentile suffragettes demand only an equal status for women. Why should these Jews go farther and bar boys from securing a modern Jewish education?</p>
   <p>It is true that the Talmud Torahs, which were established up to date, were founded upon Jewish religious principles; and, because women are exempt from fulfilling religious obligations, the Talmud Torahs become "masculine institution" from which girls were barred. Nevertheless, it is also true that the <pb facs="5423972_6_0055.jpg" n="3"/>future Talmud Torahs which will be built in the Chicago Jewish community will be established upon broader principles. Religion will be merely one of the many studies taught there. When the Chicago Jewish community is ready to establish these Talmud Torahs then the question of Jewish education for girls will become a part of the question of Jewish education for Jewish children.</p>
   <p>Instead of spending time in solving a phase of Jewish education--each one adhering to a different opinion, creating confusion, and obstructing the practical work to be done--it would certainly be much better if those who are devoted to Jewish education would create a suitable system of education for boys and girls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
