<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-03-22">March 22, 1930</date>. Volume 79, Page 172.
<title level="a">The Hungry Years</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-03-22">March 22, 1930</date>. Volume 79, Page 172.
<title level="a">THE HUNGRY YEARS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The days that followed the World's Columbian Exposition were days of hunger and distress, of failure and suicide, of poverty and want. These conditions spread throughout the land and affected all classes of people. The Jews were no exception to the rule, and those of Chicago were doomed to suffer most. Thousands of people who came here to attend the World's Fair, either for business or pleasure, were stranded here with their money spent, and without the means to carry them back to their homes.</p>
   <p>Shortly after the exposition, the big railroad strike broke out, and strike breakers from all over the country were brought to Chicago, the principal seat of combat. These poor creatures, who came here to find a market for their strong arms, and thus earn enough money to buy bread for the dependents they had left at home, helped to swell the already overflowing population.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0569.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All the existing charitable institutions were worked overtime, but they did not have sufficient facilities to cope with the ever-increasing hunger and want. On Jefferson Street, the heart of the ghetto, a soup-kitchen took its stand and a Jewish bread line came into being.</p>
   <p>The winter of 1893 and 1894, was the most horrible in the history of the city. People were literally starving. Conditions outside of Chicago were not much better. Millions of honest workers, eager for work of any kind which would earn them enough on which to subsist, tramped the highways of this vast land, but could find no work.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, new philanthropic institutions were founded to alleviate to some extent, if only temporary, the distressing conditions which prevailed everywhere.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0570.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of these institutions, the Bureau of Personal Service, while not rendering actual relief and not feeding the hungry, nevertheless, was a direct result of those and other conditions.</p>
   <p>It is still functioning and is a part of the Associated Jewish Charities. This agency, which has played an unusual part, ostensibly in the ghetto, but in reality in the entire city of Chicago, came into existence without outlining a definite program.</p>
   <p>The high standing which it attained as one of the most efficient social agencies of the city was due to the kind heart and remarkable ability of its superintendent, the late Minnie F. Law, and her capable assistant, Minnie Jacobs, later known as Minnie Berlin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
