<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1893-03-04">March 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">From Mr. H. Eliassof's Report as Superintendent of the Society in Aid of Russian Refugees</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0962</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0962.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1 (Russian)</item>
     <item>V A 2 (Russian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1893-03-04">March 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">FROM MR. H. ELIASSOF'S REPORT AS SUPERINTENDENT OF THE SOCIETY IN AID OF RUSSIAN REFUGEES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Society was organized on August 23rd, 1891, and the work of relieving the refugees commenced the following month. On Jan. 31st, 1893, it completed 17 months of work. During the first 6 months, 391 applications were considered with $5,616 disbursed. In the following 11 months, 671 applications were taken and $25,038 expended, making a grand total of $1,062 applications and $30,654 cash disbursed for 17 months.</p>
   <p>In the beginning of March, 1892, the Society was reorganized and arrangements were then completed to receive, care for, and distribute a greater number of refugees than before. Energetic efforts were made to enable the Society to send away from Chicago to the country towns as many refugees as could be induced to leave the large and crowded city. The work of distribution was done systematically. The refugees were not forced upon the <pb facs="5423972_6_0963.jpg" n="2"/>communities, but were shipped to places only, where our traveling agent found parties who were willing to accept the new-comers and help them find homes and work. All families or single men, who were sent from Chicago to the country, were assigned with credentials to one man or to a committee, in the respective town, who took charge of them. The 1,062 applications during the 17 months represent a total number of 2,968 persons, the number of families being 603. Among the total number of applications were 387 mechanics, with 75 trades represented, 26 professionals, and 44 farmers.</p>
   <p>915 persons were sent away from Chicago, of which 129 returned. Some of these came back because they preferred not to stay in small towns where they could not live Kosher, according to the dietary laws of the Mosaic Code. The Employment Bureau was in operation from March 23rd to Sept. 17, 1892 and during this time found work for 505 applicants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0964.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Taking into consideration the large number of people in the care of the Society, very few deaths occurred during these 17 months.</p>
   <p>The results of the work can be considered very satisfactory. From reliable bits of information received by the Society, it may be safely concluded that the majority of those refugees who were sent to the country communities are well taken care of and are in a better position than those who remained in the city. Most of them have found employment and are becoming self sustaining. Some of the married men who had left their families in Russia were able, after working 6 or 8 months, to send enough money to bring their relatives here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
