<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1891-11-13">Nov. 13, 1891</date><title level="a">Our Visit to the Jewish Training School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1891-11-13">Nov. 13, 1891</date><title level="a">OUR VISIT TO THE JEWISH TRAINING SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A magnificent institution richly endowed by Leon Mandel and the Jews of Chicago by voluntary contributions, situated on Judd between Clinton and Jefferson streets, and in the midst of the Russian-Polish settlements; containing now some eight hundred children of both sexes and under the superintendency of Prof. Gabriel Bamberger.</p>
   <p>The editor of The Occident paid a brief visit to this school last week and was most agreeably impressed with the system, order, decorum and general arrangement of the school which is destined to reform and improve the new generation of these helpless people, who were driven from their homes and firesides in Russia. We noticed many interesting features which exhibit the acumen of a thorough pedagogue, and by progressive instruction leads the hands and minds into channels of practical knowledge, even the youngest children from 3 to 5 years of age. A corps of able assistant teachers are at work in carrying out the discipline and systematic studies which are so greatly simplified and improved, that nothing can impede the acquiring of all elementary branches of education. It is not only a pleasure <pb facs="5423972_6_0071.jpg" n="2"/>to observe the deft hands of those children in their work but one of the greatest blessings which humanity is capable of bestowing upon their less favored brethren. Eighteen spacious school rooms are now fully occupied with these children. From the most infantile apartments to the most advanced and higher branches of tuition this school is a model. The manual training department is however the great aim and is destined to make the pupils not only self-sustaining in after years but useful members of society. The English language only is used. The kindergarten for the infantiles is one of the most inductive of its character in our city. The sewing, dress-making, embroidering, mending and repairing departments are well nigh perfect. The modeling and designing in clay department is a feature which in our youth was not known except in schools of art and sculpture, but even this is a part of this school so as to bring out all the genius and talent which children and youth possess. The greatest facilities are given in this school. Great care is taken in giving children the physical exercise through gymnastics and calisthenics.</p>
   <p>The ventilation and heating of the rooms are perfect. The scholar of this institution when he graduates may retain a record of his work from the day <pb facs="5423972_6_0072.jpg" n="3"/>he enters until he leaves the institution. Professor Bamberger is the patentee of a triangular pencil which is used in this school and by other institutions in this country, which has entirely supplanted the slate and slate-pencil. It does away with smut, avoids the crating and scratching so annoying to many. Altogether, this Jewish Training School is a model of its kind in the Far West.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
