<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-05-15">May 15, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[Various Activities]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-05-15">May 15, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[VARIOUS ACTIVITIES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Jewish Training School was held on Tuesday night in the Sinai Temple vestry rooms. The Training School was organized for the purpose of helping the children of the hapless victims of Russians who settle here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It endeavored to make of them useful citizens, and send them out in later years equipped to make a decent livelihood for themselves. The course of study is divided into three departments. The Kindergarten, the Primary Department, and the Grammar Department. It was designed to cover twelve years.</p>
   <p>The children are enrolled at the age of three years in the Kindergarten Class. In this class, is laid the foundation of future education. By means of a variety of fitting songs and dances and by a large number of interesting games and exercises, the slumbering mental powers of the child are rationally awakened, and later on he brings to his studies, activity, attention and vivacity. 180 children are enrolled in the Kindergarten Class.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0230.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Primary Department is divided into four classes, each of which has a class instructor who teaches the ordinary branches, while special branches are taught by specialists. The course of study in English branches include Arithmetic, Reading, Spelling, Penmanship, Elementary Geography, and language. Upon completing four years in this grade, the child is prepared to enter upon more advanced work. He is able to pronounce and spell ordinary words correctly, and is capable of using whole numbers and fractions in their written and oral form. He is acquainted, in a general way, with the people and great industries of different parts of the world, and can express his acquired knowledge in simple but correct English. History is taught in a simple way, as are also Sewing, Free-hand Drawing, Slojd and Paste-board work, Gymnastics and Music. 280 pupils are enrolled in the four primary grades.</p>
   <p>The Grammar Department also consists of four classes. The instruction, imparted by special teachers only, embraces: 1) English (Reading Writing, Grammar and Composition). 2) Systematic History and Geography. 3) Arithmetic, Geometry and Algebra (the latter in the two highest classes only). 4) Physics and Chemistry <pb facs="5423972_6_0231.jpg" n="3"/>(by experiment only). 5) Natural History (Zoology in winter, Botany in spring and fall). 6) German. 7) Art (Modeling, Free-hand Drawing and Designing). 8) Mechanics (Wood-work, Bench-work, Machine-work (Wood and Metal for boys), Sewing, cutting and fitting, (Dress-making for girls). 9) Gymnastics and Music.</p>
   <p>About 250 pupils are enrolled in the Grammar Department.</p>
   <p>All these branches are now being raught in the school. The difficult lesson of cleanliness has been learned by the cildren and through Mothers' meetings, we have won the confidence and co-operation of the parents.</p>
   <p>The night school, under the charge of our Superintendent, educates some 300 adults in the elements of our language and the history of our country, as well as in Book-keeping and Dressmaking. These classes have accomplished incalculable good.</p>
   <p>The financial reports showed that the total receipts had been $59,171.61, and the total disbursements, $54,855.88, leaving a balance of $4,315.73. The cost of the <pb facs="5423972_6_0232.jpg" n="4"/>of the grounds and building, complete, was $52,276.01.</p>
   <p>The buget for the coming year estimates the expenses at $17,000, and the receipts at $10,000. The matter of devising ways and means to meet the deficit was referred to the new Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>The election for the eight new directors resulted as follows: Mrs. E. Mandel, Mrs. M. Rosnebaum, Mrs. M. Loeb, J. L. Gatzert and Mr. H. B. Frank. Mrs. Witkowsky and Mr. Hefter were elected to fill the places of Mrs. Harry Meyer and Mr. Julius Rosenthal, the remainder were re-elected.</p>
   <p>The meeting then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
