<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-12">November 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Federation Organized, Will Function January 1St</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-12">November 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">FEDERATION ORGANIZED, WILL FUNCTION JANUARY 1ST</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the Daily Jewish Courier predicted, the United Jewish Orthodox Charities will begin financing all Jewish welfare institutions, January 1, 1913.</p>
   <p>This was decided, last evening at a meeting where representatives of the twelve Jewish institutions assembled with the original Committee on the Organizing of the Federation.</p>
   <p>The roll call of representatives of the welfare bodies showed that the following institutions sent these delegates:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0813.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Home for the Aged - August Turner and Isadore Lasker. Moimonedes Kosher Hospital - S. S. Korshak and U. Rosenzweig. Hebrew Sheltering Home - J. Wolfson and M. L. Fox. Yeshiva Eitz Chaim - H. Halper and A. Adler. West Side Hebrew School - David Slepior and the Rev. Neuman. Hebrew Speaking Society - N. H. Boldtin and H. Shodd. West Side Ladies' Charity Society, Mrs. L. M. Silverman and Mrs E. A. Rivkin.</p>
   <p>Jewish Consumptive Relief Society - Mrs. I. J. Rubin, and Mrs. S. Tanner. Free Loan Society - Paul Vitkowsky, and J. Weinstein. Northwest Side Free Loan Society - M. Nathan and George Mordock.</p>
   <p>M. Stone, who should have represented the Marks Nathan Home, sent an excuse that he could not be present at the meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0814.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After a lengthy discussion a resolution was passed to the effect that an organizational and by-laws committee should be appointed, which would introduce a program no later than December 1st, designating how the federation should be organized and function when it will take over the finances of all Jewish institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
