<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1889">Year 1889-90</date>,
Pp. 7-8.
<title level="a">The Relief Office, During the Past Year, Assisted Over Sixty-Five Hundred People</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1022</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1022.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1889">Year 1889-90</date>,
Pp. 7-8.
<title level="a">THE RELIEF OFFICE, DURING THE PAST YEAR, ASSISTED OVER SIXTY-FIVE HUNDRED PEOPLE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have now more than one hundred orphans at the Cleveland Orphan Asylum, and fifteen applicants are awaiting action. Why not establish an institution here to take charge of these little ones? Chicago is large enough to supply an adequate number of inmates. The movement for a sheltering home should be inaugurated, out of which may grow a permanent orphan asylum. But, in any event, we should have the facilities for caring for the numerous little ones who are neglected by or bereft of their parents, and whose surroundings breed still more degradation and distress.</p>
   <p>The Society for the Education of Orphan Children, established by Mrs. Eliza Frank, is now taking care of eleven children, and of whom would have been charge upon your association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1023.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The assistance which this society and the Home for the Friendless render your association is of great value. Let there be an effort made to build a sheltering home in our city, where the numberless unfortunate children may be educated and reared in such a manner as to be worthy of the respect of the community into which they have been cast. With the assistance of a generous public, this could be done.</p>
   <p>The usual annual complaint of insufficient means must be made. It may be asked, why suggest the establishment of these various institutions if we have not money enough to defray the expenses of those which we already have? The reply must be: Because money is given your association in certain quarters very grudgingly, it does not follow that the institutions suggested should not be established. The institutions are or will be in the immediate future of an absolute necessity, and this community must establish them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1024.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The collections are in amount small, and the sum total is contributed by a comparatively small number. Thousands of people in Chicago could contribute who do not. These must be reached. Each component society turns over its quota, and rests there. Some members of each society contribute additional sums. But the societies as a rule, excepting the different congregations and the Young Men's Hebrew Charity Association, make no effort either among the members or among its friends to collect money. The duties of your board have become such that it is impossible for the committee on collection, even with the assistance of the office, to canvass the whole city, and the only way to reach these thousands who contribute nothing is by personal appeal.</p>
   <p>We appreciate the moral and financial support given by those who contribute but we should not cast the burden on them alone. If you will examine the list of contributors, as published during the last few years, you will find that this association gets its support practically from the same people from year to year, and from a class which rarely, if ever, makes demand for aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1025.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is no question about the amount of good work your society is doing, and has done, and it should be a matter of pride, therefore, with every Jew in Chicago, to be a contributor to this cause.</p>
   <p>The report of the financial secretary will give you full details as to the amount and disposal of the money of your association. It is but proper, however, that a few totals be submitted to you. As stated before, nearly $17,000.00 was expended for relief, the bulk of which, some $13,500.00, was contributed by the various congregations, and less than $1,000.00 from component societies. Mr. Kiss collected alone over $1,200.00 which was turned into the relief fund. The general expenses of the hopsital amounted to nearly $27,000.00, exclusive of over $15,600.00, which was expended for permanent improvements. The total amount received by donations and subscriptions for relief, and for the hospital, amounted to $33,457.56.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1026.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The receipts from pay patients, together with the amount of interest collected from the sinking fund, amounted to less than $14,000.00. It may not be inopportune to call your attention to the fact that the sum total in the sinking fund, of every kind and character belonging to your association, amounts to but a little over $94,000.00.</p>
   <p>This gross sum may appear large, but if you will consider that the actual value is but $15,000.00, per year, you will concede that earnest efforts are necessary on the part of our association and its friends to increase not only the sinking fund, but the subscriptions so that your association may be financially able to meet its expenditures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
