<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-26">Apr. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Hundred Thousand Dollars for a New Hebrew Institute</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-26">Apr. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">HUNDRED THOUSAND DOLLARS FOR A NEW HEBREW INSTITUTE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Jacob M. Loeb, president of the Chicago Hebrew Institute, in his annual report given at a special meeting, stated that there are over 300 new members in the institution, and he also informed the audience of their great success in collecting the necessary funds of a hundred thousand dollars for the building of a new structure for athletics.</p>
   <p>It has often been discussed in the past, i.e., the necessity of a building for athletics to adjoin the Hebrew Institute, and at last we have succeeded in raising the necessary fund.</p>
   <p>Mr. Julius Stone, the secretary of the institution, reported on the financial status of the Institute by stating that during last year the Institute received 358 new members; with this view, it looks very much as thought the income from the old and new members will prevent a deficit this year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0470.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Philip Simon, the superintendent of the Institute, through stereoscopic pictures showed all the activities of the institute with its different departments. Every picture was accepted by the audience with great applause, especially the pictures which showed the different athletic body movements of hundreds of small Jewish children. These athletic exercises certainly help the development of the children's bodies and spirit.</p>
   <p>The immigration department, in its classes, evoked great enthusiasm from the audience, especially when it described the arrivals of young Jewish girls, who work all day in shops and factories and then find the Hebrew Institute a great place in which to acquaint themselves with the English language and American ways and customs.</p>
   <p>Judge Jullian Mack also delivered a rather lengthy speech. He spoke on the importance of an institute of this kind, and expressed the opinion that it does not matter whether we are Zionistically inclined or anti-Zionistically inclined, one thing we are sure of and we must face: that it will be a long time before the masses of Jews who are persecuted in Russia and Roumania <pb facs="5423972_6_0471.jpg" n="3"/>will find a home of tranquillity, for Palestine is as yet too far away and so far the country is still in a pioneer stage. America is the only country, and its Jewish institutions are the ultimate solution for the persecuted Jews of Russia and Roumania. Such institutions as our Hebrew Institute will extract the poison from the mouths of the anti-Immigrationists in our country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
