<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1888">Year 1888-89</date>;
Page 8 To 9.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1888">Year 1888-89</date>;
Page 8 To 9.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Hebrew Charities of Chicago was incorporated on the 24th of November, 1888. The real estate and other property belonging to the United Hebrew Relief Association was transferred to the United Hebrew Charities of Chicago, and a new constitution and by-laws was adopted at a special meeting, held October 7, 1889.</p>
   <p>The total receipts for the relief fund, during the year, were less than $14,000.00. Many of the lodges have ceased to be members of our association. The names of many former contributors do not appear on our subscription list. At the end of last year, we were in possession of a surplus of some $12,000.00. This, together with the collections made during the year, has been practically wholly expended. The question then arises: Where shall we find a remedy? How shall we increase our receipts? The population of the city of Chicago continually increases, and the number of poor, proportionately. It is not for us to say that those who contribute do not contribute adequately.</p>
   <p>We can state, with assurance, that there are over two thousand well-to-do Jews in the city of Chicago, who do not contribute a penny to our institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the city of Philadelphia, $26,500 was expended by the United Hebrew Charities, during the last year, in aiding and assisting the poor. We, with a $16,000 expenditure, eared for 1400 cases.</p>
   <p>Philadelphia has a Jewish population, about the size of Chicago's. Its total receipts, during the past year, amounted to over $30,000. Ours were less than half. Chicago certainly should make a better showing than that.</p>
   <p>Were it not for the admirable assistance given by the Ladies' Aid Societies, we could not cope with the demands made upon us. The West Side Ladies' Sewing Society assisted us by distributing clothing and money to the extent of over $2,200,00; the West Side Ladies' Aid Society to the extent of $1,800; $1,800.00; the North Side Ladies' Aid Society, about $800.00; and the South Side Ladies' Sewing Society, over $3,000.00. The amount of money contributed by the Young Ladies' Aid Society cannot well be estimated, but wearing apparel was supplied by them in goodly quantities, thus saving large expenditures on our part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
