<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-08-04">August 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Seven Thousand Dollars for the Kosher Hospital</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0825</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0825.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-08-04">August 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SEVEN THOUSAND DOLLARS FOR THE KOSHER HOSPITAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently, we received several reports from various orthodox charity institutions. These reports are the accounts of incomes and expenses of the respective institutions. What pleases us so much about these reports is the clearness of the accounts, and the fact that they are inspected by a public accountant.</p>
   <p>We confess that we are highly pleased with this, because it is a result of our many years of agitation that developed responsibility within our social institutions and eradicated waste of which many of our social workers are so proud.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0826.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true that the statements published are very mournful, due to the previous management of our social institutions. In the business world such statements would imply a degradation in the credit of the establishment. Regardless of how poor the statements may be, regardless of how much negligence and irresponsibility they cast upon our social workers, we can infer from each statement that, in the future, many reforms and improvements will take place, and if the management is not up to par, there is an assurance that everything will be conducted in a business manner in the future.</p>
   <p>Of all the numerous statements of the various institutions that lie before us, we are permitted to publish but one on the results of the Maimonedes Hospital Bazaar which was held recently in their building.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0827.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This statement was approved by W. R. Singer, a public accountant, and sent to the chairman of the Bazaar Committee, Judge Joseph Sabbath. This report is a very accurate one including all particulars.</p>
   <p>The report is divided as follows:- 1. General total amount of incomes expenses, pledges and balances. 2. Sources from which the money was raised. 3. Management. 4. Expenses. In the first part of the report we found the following:- Cash taken in amounted to $7,087.66; pledges amounted to $1,923.00; expenses amounted to $1,818.47; disbursement to building fund amounted to $5,269.19. There was a clear profit of $7,192.19.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
