<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1932-05-26">May 26, 1932</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Charities Minutes</title>,
<date when="1932-05-26">May 26, 1932</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the board in the report of the Executive Director, the question of federal aid and relief was discussed. It was disclosed that there were 1,450 Jewish families under care of emergency relief service of the Cook County Bureau of Public Welfare. Of these, 890 were transferred from the Jewish Social Service Bureau, the remainder having applied direct. 1,250 families receive relief from the J. S. S. B. and about 3,050 families are under the care of the J. S.S.B</p>
   <p>It being doubtful whether federal money will go direct to private agencies, it would therefore be necessary to transfer over, more families to public agencies.</p>
   <p>In reply to a question by Judge Fisher, Mr. Goldsmith stated that the families turned over to the Emergency Relief were those families that did not include involved situations such as illness, mental hygiene, protection of Child Welfare etc. The average case load of a worker in the relief stations is 175. The Jewish Social Service Bureau case load is normally 45. It can readily be seen that the relief station cannot do as intensive a job as the J. S. S. B. is in a position to do. No families are transferred to the relief stations where it is the opinion <pb facs="5423972_6_0554.jpg" n="2"/>of the Bureau that the transfer would be detrimental to the family, for example 250 aged are being taken care of by the Bureau in private homes. Though all could be transferred to the Cook County Bureau, The J. S. S. B. is doing so only where the persons involved can make a decent re-adjustment under county care.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
