<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditation of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATION OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Gentile newspaperman, the sporting editor of a local daily, informs the writer that the old theory that Jews are physical cowards is disproved by statistics in the field of athletics, where the number of Jewish participants is a good deal out [of] proportion to their population. He further points out that the number of Jewish pugilists in the front ranks of this country's fighting fraternity is [so] sufficient that the Jews are not outclassed in physical courage by any racial group in this country. We think both the thesis and the proof inconsequential. While it is undoubtedly desirable that our young men and women in this country and elsewhere develop their bodies no less than their minds, and much more so than was the custom among us formerly, we think that participation in athletics, which from every point of view we hold desirable, is yet no proof of the physical courage of a people, let alone the spiritual courage of that people. The Jews have never been <pb facs="5423972_6_0460.jpg" n="2"/>lacking in either we hold, and as for our highly honored members of the fighting fraternity, we may say that if the Jewish people has anything to contribute to the common civilization and culture of the race, such contributions are rather to be sought in the realm of their intellects than in that of their fists. The Jews have shown numerous examples of both physical and spiritual heroism in the course of their history, and may expect no new renaissance in their national creativeness as a result of the activities of certain pugilists in their field. As a matter of fact none of these pugilists may be said to be Jews except in the accident of their birth. We should certainly encourage clean athletics, but we need not bother about the pugilists. Let them take care of themselves. They believe they can very well do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
