<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-22">June 22, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-22">June 22, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anarchy now prevails in the Marks Nathan Orphanage. Scenes, which only the Russian Jews have undergone while persecuted in Russia when they were driven from villages to towns and from towns to cities, are now appearing in the great orthodox institution, the Marks Nathan Orphan Asylum, and the welfare of the orphans is imperiled.</p>
   <p>The Admission Committee has suddenly issued a decree whereby one hundred and twelve orphans will be forced to leave the home. The decree maintains that several will go to the German-Jewish Home for Boys; others will turn to the Home Finding Society. The rest are sentenced to exile and may find whatever home they like; but all must vacate from the home; give up their education and seek a livelihood in the factories, without regarding the many who longed for careers and hoped to accomplish things.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1616.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was disclosed yesterday that the order by the Admission Committee is somewhat similar to the Russian laws, which cannot be appealed. An order was given to the superintendent, Mr. Sol Druker, to send out the children and when Mr. Druker refused to obey the order before the Board of Directors' approval, they told him that the Admission Committee is supreme in its order and that the Board of Directors has no right to interfere with it.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, Mr. Druker did not carry out the order and this matter will be taken up at the next meeting of the Board of Directors which will be held Wednesday evening, January 25.</p>
   <p>The orphans, for whom the edict was meant, are the most able and best children of the home. Several are sophomores in high school, other are students of the Chicago Musical School, while others are attending the Chicago Art School and have only two years to complete their studies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1617.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The news of the Admission Committee's decision stirred up a great part of the Chicago orthodox Jewry and many directors determined to fight this order at the next meeting. A movement also began which demands the resignation of the present Admission Committee and election of another in its place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
