<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-08-07">August 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[Day Nursery]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-08-07">August 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[Day Nursery]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Important Institution which is being Supported by the Pennies of Poor Women. by Morris Ziskind.</p>
   <p>It is an open secret that in Chicago, there are thousands of small children without mothers or fathers, who grow up to become non-productive citizens. In such a chaotic situation the children could not be educated. In this emergency, a group of women came to realize the necessity for a Day Nursery, where working mothers would be able to leave their children during the day, with the assurance that proper care would be given them.</p>
   <p>These noble pioneers of the Douglas Park Day and Night Nursery did not rest until they had interested a larger number of women in the project. In a short time the necessary money was raised and a beautiful building, located at 13 St. and Independence Blvd. in the heart of the aristocratic neighborhood of the Douglas Park district, was purchased.</p>
   <p>As soon as it became known that such an institution had been organized, great numbers of fathers and mothers applied for placement of their children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1553.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first day of the Institution taught the founders two things: first, that there are very many children who deserve to be accepted, and secondly, that it will be a difficult matter both organizationally and financially to maintain such a nursery. After the Day Nursery had become established, it was seen that the tragedy of the poor helpless mothers or fathers, and that the tragic position of the helpless children was worse than had been imagined. In response to this problem, the Night Nursery project was developed as an adjunct to the Day Nursery.</p>
   <p>At present there are 55 children in the Day Nursery, who are in attendance the entire day, but are taken home by the parents for the night. Also there are 35 infants, many at but 2 years of age, who remain at the Nursery, day and night. Many applications are on file, but cannot be accepted, due to lack of room.</p>
   <p>As one passes through the building on an observation tour, one notes the sympathy and understanding which the children receive. The cleanliness and the sanitation is excellent. Each child has his own bed. The rooms present a clean appearance, with fresh linen on the beds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1554.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Berger is the superintendent. The doctors are Messrs Sarnoff, Feinstein, Kipnis, and Schaffner, the dentist. They give their services freely.</p>
   <p>The expenses of the Day Nursery are about $2,500 monthly. The income consists of contributions from various sources.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
