<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-07-16">July 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Anti-Semitism in the Women's Western Golf Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-07-16">July 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ANTI-SEMITISM IN THE WOMEN'S WESTERN GOLF ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is well known that the anti-Semitic serpent has injected its poisonous fangs into those American colleges and universities where Jewish students have been excluded. That this anti-Semitic virus has also infected the sports world--that phase of American life wherein Americans have always maintained racial intolerance is not to be found--has just become known as a result of a golf contest which is to take place in Chicago today among women golf players for the championship of the West. Not one Jewish name is to be found among the ninety-one women who will play, despite the fact that many Jewish golf clubs exist in Chicago, the members of which would have participated had they been invited. The reason for this situation is, of course, that the officials and members of the Women's Western Golf Association (which arranged the contest) are so anti-Semitic that it was impossible for a Jewish girl to obtain permission to compete in the contest.</p>
   <p>The Jewish golf clubs felt this spirit of anti-Semitism two years ago when <pb facs="5423972_6_0451.jpg" n="2"/>the Women's Western Golf Association voted to select certain clubs, which belonged to the Association, to be members, and voted to give the others only limited privileges. After this election all the Jewish golf clubs, one after another, submitted their resignations because the Jewish clubs were excluded from active membership. Not one Jewish golf club is now a member of this Association. The officials and the members of the Women's Western Golf Association are not ashamed of their anti-Semitism and have declared themselves against admitting Jewish clubs. Mr. Farlin B. Hall, president of the Association stated that a club wishing to join the Association "must have a membership that will please the executive committee". Jewish golf players did not "please" them. Therefore, the Jewish golf clubs cannot become members of the Association and their members cannot participate in the various golf contests. The Chicago Tribune has made an accurate investigation of the entire matter and came to the conclusion that anti-Semitism plays a large part in preventing Jewish golf clubs from joining the Association and Jewish players from participating in golf contests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
