<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-18">May 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Dorf Remains Grand Master of the Brith Avraham</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-18">May 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DORF REMAINS GRAND MASTER OF THE BRITH AVRAHAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Atlantic City. The convention of the Brith Avraham (Brotherhood of Abraham) closed after the adoption of the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>Members of the Order admitted in an incorporated institution or Home may bequeath half their endowment for that specific institution, but no one is permitted to bequeath or leave his endowment to his lodge.</p>
   <p>Members of the Order for less than a year, committing suicide, lose their privileges of endowment.</p>
   <p>This resolution was accepted on the basis of Mr. Dorf's explanation. In the last two years, the Order paid endowments to relatives of twenty-two suicides.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The convention also decided that the Order contribute $250 yearly to the Jewish Sanitarium for Consumptives in California, where the Order has a tent of its own.</p>
   <p>After the election and installation of new Grand Officers, the convention closed with a reception given in honor of the delegates and their families.</p>
   <p>The next convention of the Order will take place in 1921, also in Atlantic City.</p>
   <p>The following is a list of the newly elected Grand Officers of the Order Brith Avraham:</p>
   <p>Samuel Dorf, Grand Master; Morris M. Green, first deputy; Josef Wagenheim, second vice-president; Jacob Gould, third vice-president;</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1085.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Max Fine, fourth deputy; Frank Ravson, fifth deputy; Moses Reinseinhmer, sixth deputy.</p>
   <p>As Grand Secretary they elected George V. Leizerson; Grand Treasurer, Bennett Freidman; endowment treasurer, Max Kedziarak; endowment chairman, Hayvid Troitman; finance treasurer, Louis Keller; chairman of loans, Charles Banus; chairman of appeals, Leon B. Ginsburg; chairman of State Order, Max Oberahams; chairman of rituals, Edward Rosenstone; chairman of relief, Jacob Wise; chairman of printing, Julius Berliner; chairman of Trust fund, William Markin; chairman of reserve fund, S. Aaronson; chairman of propaganda, William Izaacs; chairman of disability, Sam Rozenberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
