<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-29">Sept. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Peace at Marks Nathan Orphanage</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-29">Sept. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PEACE AT MARKS NATHAN ORPHANAGE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>They, who have sown with tears, have reaped with mirth.</p>
   <p>Whoever witnessed the last meeting of the Board of Directors of the Marks Nathan Orphanage unconsciously reiterated the words of King David: "We rejoice when we see that the tears were not in vain; they made the soil so fertile that flowers grew."</p>
   <p>The orphanage was on the the agenda for discussion every day, for the last two and one-half years. The readers of the Courier know how the movement to purify this institution began. Chicago Jewry built this asylum for the poor orphans and it was transformed into the property of the collectors and "welfare workers."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1606.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago Jewry intended to establish a home for the orphans, but instead it turned out to be a means of seeking honor and personal interests for the leaders.</p>
   <p>A conflict between Truth and Falsehood arose, between light and darkness. From one side a cry was heard "more light; tear the masks off of those who control the orphanage, open up the gates and doors so that pure air and life may enter." From the other side, they pleaded, "God forbid! This should not be done. Light can harm the eyes of the orphans; if the windows and doors should be opened, the children would perhaps catch cold; to tear the masks off would be a shame and a disgrace to all Jews, and therefore, forget about everything."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1607.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The controversy, which developed into a bitter struggle, lasted two and one-half years. It was a difficult and tenacious battle. Many innocent people have suffered, but all guilty ones fell in battle. When the Board of Directors called the meeting to order at the home of the president, Moses Stone, last Wednesday, the directors who were seeking honor and personal interests were not present to answer the roll call; those who brought in light, decency, responsibility and Jewish spirit in the home were present and listened to the various reports by the committees.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. S. Roy, secretary of the admission committee, had a surprise for the directors. In an accurate report, he revealed that the admission committee - which was attacked by the "leaders" - had admitted eighty-six orphans in the last nine months.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1608.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The report of the acting superintendent, Mr. E. Trotsky, was distinguished by its clearness. The superintendent did not attempt to obscure the facts. He had nothing to conceal. He pulled the curtain and each director saw the orphanage as it is with all its good qualities and all its faults.</p>
   <p>It will cost them about $7,000 to place the orphanage on a sound basis.</p>
   <p>Dr. Gordon, chief of the medical staff, read a report written by Dr. Hirshfield of the medical sub-committee in which it urges remodelling of the building, so that it will be more sanitary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
