<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 21, pp. 305, 307,
Wk.of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">First Charity Institution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 21, pp. 305, 307,
Wk.of <date when="1901-05-04">May 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">First Charity Institution</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the last few years various Jewish organizations of the city maintained a special relief fund for the assistance of non-members. There was also a relief society for the assistance of needy co-religionists. At a meeting in Feb. 1859, held in the vestry rooms of the Congregation Anshe Maarabh, the various leaders of these organizations met for the purpose of starting a charity association. This association was to be known as the United Hebrew Relief Association.</p>
   <p>A convention composed of delegates from the Hebrew Relief Society, Hebrew Benevolent Society, Ladies' Benevolent Society, and of the presidents of K.A.M., and B'nai Sholon Congregation, held several meetings, adopted a constitution and elected an executive board.</p>
   <p>The final object of this association was to provide a hospital in which the poor co-religionists could be cared for and an asylum to receive Jewish widows and orphans without means. On November 20,1859, the executive board held its first meeting, and elected Henry Greenebaum, president, Isaac Greensfelder, treasurer, and Edward S. Salomon, recording secretary.</p>
   <p>An effort was made to organize a society for a widows' and orphans' home in 1863. A meeting was held on August 3 of that year in the K.A.M. Synagogue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0914.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following ladies were appointed as a committee to perfect the organization: Mrs. Henry Horner, Mrs. L. Rosenfeld, Mrs. S. Goodkind, Mrs. L.F. Leopold, and Mrs. Isaac Lucky.</p>
   <p>The hospital lot was located at North LaSalle Street, between Schiller and Goethe Streets. At a mass meeting held on October 22, 1866, for the purpose of raising funds, over $17,000 was subscribed. On September 2, 1867, the cornerstone of the hospital was laid. The hospital was finally opened on August 9, 1868, and patients were received next day.</p>
   <p>In April 1869, Mr. Greenebaum became a life-member of the institution by paying $100, thus creating an endowment fund.</p>
   <p>On October 9, 1871, the building was destroyed in the great fire. Owing to the efforts of Dr. Wm. Wagner, and the steward, Mr. Levy, none of the patients or occupants of the hospital perished in the flames.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
