<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute</title><date when="1918-01">January 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Observer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute</title><date when="1918-01">January 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Observer</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Estimate and a Hope</p>
   <p>As the tide of time rushes on and our own daily pursuits are annexed to it, we are carried along by this tide, and the yesterday often seemingly becomes a negligent quantity until some strong emotion moves us, and then we know that the vision our eyes carried to the mind have painted indestructible pictures and the today is either a richer or poorer link to the collection--depending upon the usage of the interval of time.</p>
   <p>And my introspection today, inspired by the event of the Tenth Anniversary of the Athletic Department of the Chicago Hebrew Institute is colored with happiness for the achievement of all concerned with its work and study--for the masters and students alike.</p>
   <p>It is easy to bring back to the canvass the Gymnasium in its original form, A room of good size, quite dingy, unadorned, uninviting and yet still somehow alive! Well, what was there? The enthusiasm, aspirations and future expectancy of the teacher, Mr. Harry Berkman, and his pupils! It was this spirit, strong and persistent, that reached out beyond the confines of these four walls and by virtue of its strength forced itself into the hearts and <pb facs="5423972_6_0466.jpg" n="2"/>minds of those at the helm of the Institute, and, as a result, here is our Gymnasium of today. In value of architecture, equipment and modernity, it is second to none in the country. A worthy monument and spokesman to the generosity of the Jewish Community of Chicago! But more than that, the record of efficiency and athletic possibilities set by the members of the Gymnasium refutes forever the charge of the Jewish physical disability and lack of courage.</p>
   <p>Rather must it be unanimously admitted that physical inferiority in the Jew is a censure to the non-Jewish world rather than a reflection upon himself, for it is due totally to the reluctance in swinging the doors of opportunity open to all alike.</p>
   <p>Now, with our Boys' record in the world of sports and on the battlefield of democracy, our pride swells to the inclusion of all, and God grant that with the dawn of the world, peace, the chance of the Jew will also come.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Julius Stone</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
