<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-08">Apr. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To the Chicago Jewish Public from the Maimonides Hospital</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-04-08">Apr. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CHICAGO JEWISH PUBLIC FROM THE MAIMONIDES HOSPITAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Board of Directors of the Maimonides Hospital feels that it owes an explanation to the large Jewish public, more especially to those who contributed money and devoted valuable time in helping build the great edifice of the Maimonides Hospital, which will remain a monument to the Orthodox Jewish Charities in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We think that an explanation is in order now, for every Jewish charity institution in the city is somewhat financially in trouble and their expenditures are much larger than their intake. In addition to their general expenditures there is interest due on mortgages which are in default.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So there is only one way to keep things going, and that is to call on our Jewish public for financial aid. We, the Maimonides Hospital board, are not the only ones making an appeal for help. In behalf of some of the other institutions, such as the Jewish Orphans Home, the Jewish Home for the Aged, etc - we are all under one federation and when one is financially affected we all feel the sting.</p>
   <p>We appeal to you good hearted Jewish men and women for help. Help the Maimonides Hospital which you built and when you help us, you are not only helping our institution, but you are also helping every Jewish charity institution in the federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In behalf of the Board of Directors of the Maimonides Hospital, we remain</p>
   <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
   <p>I. Lurie, president</p>
   <p>Meyer Linker, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
