<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-23">Aug. 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of Western Star Closed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-23">Aug. 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF WESTERN STAR CLOSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Special to the Courier) Buffalo, N.Y., August 22: To the tunes of "Hatikvah" ("The Hope", Jewish national anthem) and "America", the twenty-second annual convention of the Independent Western Star Order was officially brought to a close this evening. Max Levy of Cincinnati was elected Grand Master by eighty-six votes and Ike Shapiro of Chicago was elected Grand Secretary by one hundred and eighteen votes.</p>
   <p>There was a bitter campaign during the election. Before the election took place, the Chicago delegates held a caucus in order to work for the election of their delegate, Mr. Joseph Marks, to the high office of Grand Master. At this caucus many delegates were in favor of Levy and this immediately established the greater opportunity for Levy to become elected. The result was that Marks received only fifty-six votes. But the campaign for the secretarial position was even more bitter, because Shapiro had many relentless opponents. Characteristic of this campaign was the circulation of a card by friends of <pb facs="5423972_6_0729.jpg" n="2"/>Abe Kalish of Chicago, the opposing candidate for Grand Secretary. This card read as follows:</p>
   <p>"If Kalish is elected, he promises not to speculate with the money of poor members nor will he spend thousands of dollars of the Order's capital in order to have lawyers balance its accounts. Neither will he settle a claim of $1,000 and then not turn the money over to the Order. Don't you think that a change in this office will be of benefit to the Order? If so, vote for Abe Kalish for secretary."</p>
   <p>When the votes were counted, it was shown that Kalish had received in all only eight votes and Shapiro was elected by a great majority.</p>
   <p>Before the election began, the convention determined to impose an assessment of $1.20 on each member in order to pay up about twenty of the fifty old debts that the Order had incurred. According to the present records of the <pb facs="5423972_6_0730.jpg" n="3"/>Order, there are a total of fifty assessments "on ice" and there is simply no money to make repayments on debts.</p>
   <p>The Convention granted $50 to the Zionist Emergency Fund and also resolved to give donations for other purposes. [Translator's note: A long list of elected officers is given.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
