<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1909-02-08">Feb. 8, 1909</date>, 3:3.
<title level="a">Dedicate Hospital for White Plague Victims</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Winfield Farm Scene of Appropriate Exercises Monument to Zeal of Hebrew Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1909-02-08">Feb. 8, 1909</date>, 3:3.
<title level="a">DEDICATE HOSPITAL FOR WHITE PLAGUE VICTIMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Winfield Farm Scene of Appropriate Exercises Monument to Zeal of Hebrew Women</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the dedication yesterday afternoon of the Chicago-Winfield Tuberculosis Sanitarium at Winfield, Illinois, the Jewish women of Chicago scored a distinct triumph.</p>
   <p>It marks the first efforts of the Jews of Chicago to care for the consumptive members of their race, and to the women is given the credit for originating the idea. Without their energetic efforts, which resulted in the opening of the institution six months after the purchase of the property, it is conceded that the sanitorium would still be visionary.</p>
   <p>The two women who are given the greatest credit for the new sanitarium are Mrs. Joseph Fish and Mrs. Emma B. Mandel. By common consent Mrs. Fish was given the position of honor yesterday, presiding at the exercises, introducing the prominent speakers and having general charge of the afternoon's program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1397.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The institution which is nonsectarian is located on a twenty-acre fruit farm twenty-eight miles west of Chicago on the Chicago &amp; Northwest Railroad. The main building was formerly a rest cure. The property was purchased and alterations made at an expense of about $28,000, most of which was secured through the personal solicitation of the women. The dedication ceremonies were attended by 600 representative Chicago Jews, who went on a special train.</p>
   <p>After an inspection of the buildings and grounds Mrs. Fish introduced Dr. E<gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>il G. Hirsch, who told of the peculiar susceptibility of the Jews to consumption, mostly due to the life that they were compelled to live in Russia and their enforced employment in sweatshops after arrival in this country. He declared that the Winfield institution was to be educational as well as curative and that patients would be taught how to take care of themselves and prevent the spreading of the disease germs.</p>
   <p>Carl Stonehill, president of the association, presented the sanitarium to Health commissioner W. A. Evans with the understanding that it was always to be under the control of the Chicago-Winfield Association. In reply Dr. Evans congratulated the Jews on their fraternatism and the success with which they met difficult problems of distress among their own people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1398.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He disagreed with Dr. Hirsch and believed that the educational results of such private sanitariums would be so great that the legislature would wake up and render assistence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
