<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Fulfill Your Pledge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FULFILL YOUR PLEDGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish Infant Home has received some four hundred applications seeking the admission of Jewish infants, but the home, at present, cannot admit more than sixty or seventy [of them]. To satisfy the needs of the community, a new home must be established as soon as possible. A drive for one hundred thousand dollars has been inaugurated by the Daughters of Zion Jewish Day Nursery, the representatives of which intend to establish a home. The public has responded generously to the appeal made by the rabbis and lay leaders of the drive, and a sum in the neighborhood of some forty thousand dollars has already been collected in cash and pledges.</p>
   <p>We urge, however, that those who pledged money for the Jewish Infant Home should make their pledges good as soon as possible, because the establishment of the Home cannot be delayed much longer, and the Daughters of Zion Jewish Day Nursery cannot start to build the Home unless it has the necessary cash <pb facs="5423972_6_1558.jpg" n="2"/>funds at its disposal. No good service is rendered by pledging money and withholding it from the cause for which it is needed.</p>
   <p>The community in Chicago is in dire need of a Jewish infant home and those who are ready and willing to take the responsibility for the establishment of such a home should be given all the aid and support needed to carry out their noble project.</p>
   <p>We understand that out of the forty thousand dollars raised during the drive, fifteen thousand dollars are in pledges. The leaders of the drive should do their utmost to collect this money if they intend to live up to their program, and those who have made pledges, are asked to facilitate the task of the workers by sending in their pledges without delay.</p>
   <p>When they have forty thousand dollars in cash, the representatives of the Daughters of Zion Day Nursery will be in a position to begin to build the home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
