<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November 1912</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November 1912</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Corset factory hands</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Printers</cell>
     <cell>11</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Clerks</cell>
     <cell>26</cell>
     <cell>Carpenters</cell>
     <cell>13</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Druggists</cell>
     <cell>12</cell>
     <cell>Locksmith</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Weaver</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Shoemakers</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Blacksmith</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Hebrew teacher</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Messenger Boys</cell>
     <cell>3</cell>
     <cell>Egg Candlers</cell>
     <cell>3</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Milliners</cell>
     <cell>15</cell>
     <cell>Timners</cell>
     <cell>11</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Barber</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Dressmakers</cell>
     <cell>33</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Optician</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Laundresses</cell>
     <cell>4</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Furriers</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>Electricians</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Collector</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Hairdresser</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Laborers</cell>
     <cell>9</cell>
     <cell>Painters</cell>
     <cell>22</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Bookbinders</cell>
     <cell>11</cell>
     <cell>Milkman</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Photographers</cell>
     <cell>4</cell>
     <cell>Brass Worker</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Peddlers</cell>
     <cell>17</cell>
     <cell>Machinists</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Jewelers</cell>
     <cell>7</cell>
     <cell>Watchmakers</cell>
     <cell>7</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Office Workers</cell>
     <cell>7</cell>
     <cell>Brass Polisher</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Upholsterers</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>Janitor</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cabinetmakers</cell>
     <cell>5</cell>
     <cell>Newsboy</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Stockyards</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>Plumbers</cell>
     <cell>9</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The above includes new pupils only and does not account for those carried over from the previous year.</p>
   <p>The pupils of this department are organized into a club called the Institute Educational League. The meetings are devoted for the most part to social and educational purposes. The lectures and social programs of the club were of excellent quality. One of our English teachers, a post-graduate student of the University of Chicago, is the director of the club. Recently the members decided to make financial contributions to the institute at regular intervals. The first check was already received by the Institute a few weeks ago. Many of the pupils of this department come to us from long distances, including the Lawndale district as well as the Northwest side.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 2,691.99</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 2,287.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>1,876.43</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>1,100.18</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>We are very glad to say that the certificate from our school is accepted by the board of education and also by factory inspectors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0077.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Kindergarten.</p>
   <p>In our kindergarten we had 212 individual children, 110 male and 102 female, against 138 last year, not including the Summer registration. Owing to the larger registration four teachers, instead of three, were employed. The work of this department is somewhat handicapped by the lack of exclusive accommodations. The kindergarten room, just like the other rooms in the building, because of limited space, has to be used for various purposes. The total attendance for the year was 9,300 against 9,237 last year. The average attendance per day was 39.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 800.92</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 789.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>40.88</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>53.80</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Sewing Classes.</p>
   <p>Two sewing classes were maintained, one for beginners and the other for more advanced pupils. The registration (indoor and outdoor) was 129 as against 86 (indoor registration) last year and the total attendance was 2,734 as against 3,626. The average attendance per day was 15. There were 5 free pupils. The decrease is probably due to the fact that greater emphasis is being laid in the public schools of the <pb facs="5423972_6_0078.jpg" n="4"/>neighborhood, on manual training. Upon investigation among the hundreds of children who visit the Institute it was found that the great majority of them take sewing in the public schools.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 413.67</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 409.79</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>32.34</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>35.09</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Dancing Class</p>
   <p>Just as during the previous year the dancing class was conducted every Saturday evening in the social hall. The total attendance this year 4,165 as against 3,192 last year, representing 471 season card holders, 267 male and 204 female. The average attendance per night was 97 against 62 the previous year. During the winter season the attendance frequently ran up to over 150. The price of admission was 10 cents per lesson but only season cards, containing ten admissions, were sold,. No single admissions were permitted. This was done for the purpose of securing a more regular attendance and also to limit the number of individuals to some extent. The net profit of this department for the year was $238.75. The class was continued all through the Summer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0079.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 332.25</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 260.80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>571.00</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>332.15</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Civics Bureau.</p>
   <p>The bureau consists of two divisions, one for regular instruction in American citizenship and the other where information is furnished regarding American citizenship. A charge of $1.00 for four months is where expense is involved. In that event the actual cost of securing the information desired is charged. In the regular class there were 36 individuals, against 22 of the previous year. The total attendance was 693 as against 204 last year. The age of applicants varied from 21 to 45 years.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 118.75</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 72.16</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>27.50</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>23.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Pool and Billiards</p>
   <p>Our Billiard Room continued to be one of the most popular activities at the Institute. The total attendance for the year was 10,329 against 3,121 last year. (the room was thrown open to the public in December 1911). This activity is not only self-supporting but has given the Institute a net profit of no less than $145.85.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0080.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The quarters where this activity is situated are entirely too small for the purpose. It would be a great convenience both to the frequenters and to the other activities of the Institute if the billiard room could be located on one of the lower floors. This will be accomplished, perhaps when our present gymnasium is moved to the new building, which we hope will take place some time next Fall. A charge of 25 cents an hour per table was made. The tables were used 1,695 hours against 654 last year. In addition to pool and billiards, chess, checkers and dominoes were also played, for which no charge is made and of which no record is kept.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 321.80</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>charged to Young Men's Club</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>467.65</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>$ 204.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Social Dances</p>
   <p>Our Saturday evening social dances were continued all through the year including the summer months. The total attendance at these dances was 16,585 not including institute workers and committees to whom no charge is made. The average attendance was 326 per dance. They gave the institute a net profit of no less than $1,263.90. This activity is undoubtedly one of the most useful, from whatever point of view considered. At the Institute, it provides a wholesome amusement for the thousands of <pb facs="5423972_6_0081.jpg" n="7"/>young men and women of the nighborhoods immediate as well as the mere distant. So popular has this activity become and so great has been the desire on the part of the young people, as well as the parents, for an amusement of this kind. Without the dangers and pitfalls usually accompanying it, that the greatest punishment that can be inflicted upon those who fail to comply with our strict regulations of conduct is suspension from these dances for a greater or lesser period of time. We had a number of young people, who, because of improper dancing, from our point of view, were expelled from these dances and who returned after the stated period and felt grateful for the lesson they had received. We have decided to introduce another dance on a week night. The dances will be continued all through the Summer.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 1,237.70</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 740.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>2,501.60</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>1,132.55</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Hebrew School.</p>
   <p>This department has experienced quite a few changes during the past year. Rabbi Levine, who was principal of this school, resigned his position last Summer. It was decided to continue the work under the direct supervision of the Superintendent with one of the teachers as assistant principal. A number of changes were introduced in <pb facs="5423972_6_0082.jpg" n="8"/>the method of teaching, as well as the work in general, with the aim in view of giving the children more religious instructions and of getting them better acquainted with the Hebrew prayer book. The registration was considerably larger than it was last year, despite the fact that we have less free children than we had the year previous.</p>
   <p>There were 14 free pupils during the year. We feel that with two free Hebrew schools in the vicinity of the Institute there is little need for admitting children free to our school although we have made some exceptions. We have four classes with an average attendance per day of 100. In the course of the year we handled 271 individual children against 206 last year. This department shows a slight increase in expense owing to the raise in the salaries of the teachers and the salary of Rabbi Levine, paid up to September, as principal of the school, which was formerly charged to the Synagogue instead of the school as was done this year.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 2,146.40</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 1,990.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>1,200.96</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>1,314.80</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Game Room</p>
   <p>The game room was placed last Autumn in our former trade school. It is a large <pb facs="5423972_6_0083.jpg" n="9"/>room and afforded accommodations for a great many more children than did the room used for the same purpose last year. The game room was divided into two sections, one for the small children, with special furniture for that purpose, and the other for elder children. A section of the room, which was partitioned off, was kept open for the elder boys and girls in the evening while the other section was used as a reading room for adults, (Since January 29th) where light lunches were also served. Even this large room, however, was not sufficient to accommodate all these who came. It was decided, therefore, to admit children by ticket, for which a very small fee, five cents for the entire season, was charged. In addition to this large number many children were admitted free. The daily attendance nevertheless frequently ran up to 300; the total attendance for the year was 21,312 against 11,003 last year. No record was kept of the adult attendance.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 201.48</cell>
     <cell>Expense</cell>
     <cell>$ 81.43</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>14.90</cell>
     <cell>Revenue</cell>
     <cell>15.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
