<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">For the Little Jewish Orphans of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-02">Mar. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE LITTLE JEWISH ORPHANS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish workers of Chicago cannot boast of having many philanthropic institutions. They also cannot brag about being as charitably inclined as the Jewish workers of New York, who respond with enthusiasm to every philanthropic appeal for aid and support for the masses. Now an appeal is being made in Chicago, to which our Jewish workers must respond, because the appeal is made for an institution which will benefit them more than anyone else. We mean the home for the little orphans, which the Daughters of Zion Day and Night Nursery is going to build. We might say that this home, which has been planned for the innocent orphans, should come first in the interests of the Jewish workers. Of the seventy-five orphans who are now being raised in the temporary home of the Daughters of Zion Day and Night Nursery, ninety per cent are children of working people. This will also be true in the future, when the new home, which the Daughters of Zion <pb facs="5423972_6_1560.jpg" n="2"/>Day and Night Nursery are planning to build, is completed. This home will be able to house four hundred children.</p>
   <p>The Jewish workers of Chicago must support the one hundred thousand dollar drive for this home. Unfortunately, they have not shown, up to now, an adequate amount of interest in this institution, from which they, as a class, will benefit most. When one glances through the list of contributors, it becomes evident that there are very few workers represented. We would prefer to see twenty thousand Jewish workers donate one dollar each to the drive, than to see one rich person donate twenty thousand dollars. The largest part of the money which has come into the headquarters of the Daughters of Zion Day and Night Nursery was made up not of small donations by workers, but of large contributions from individuals. We do not say that Chicago's rich have done their duty toward this institution, which is such an elementary necessity. Far from it! If the rich did their duty, the one hundred thousand dollars would have been collected long ago. So far, only forty thousand dollars has been collected. We emphasize, therefore, <pb facs="5423972_6_1561.jpg" n="3"/>the fact that if the workers would show a greater interest in the institution, which basically concerns them, then the rich Jews would also respond more generously to the appeal.</p>
   <p>The drive for one hundred thousand dollars to build a large and beautiful home for the Jewish orphans of Chicago, has been going on now for five weeks. Should the campaign continue to drag on for another five weeks, at its present tempo, then we don't know whether the one hundred thousand dollars will ever reach the treasury of the Daughters of Zion Day and Night Nursery. The campaign must end immediately, because in a few days, the Zionists and the Mizrachi open their drive for one million dollars, which is Chicago's quota to the restoration fund for the rebuilding of Palestine. The Jewish workers of Chicago must help to build a home for the Jewish orphans, and must participate at this eleventh hour, in the one hundred thousand dollar drive.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the drive must now concentrate all their efforts on contacting <pb facs="5423972_6_1562.jpg" n="4"/>the working class and winning its sympathy for the noble enterprise. We cannot believe that the Jewish workers of Chicago do not want to support an institution from which they, themselves, will benefit. A home for Jewish orphans in Chicago means a home for the orphans of Jewish workers, and when the latter participate actively in founding this infants' home, then they will have their own institution and will be able to point with pride to their accomplishment.</p>
   <p>Jewish workers of Chicago! It is your sacred duty to help build a home for the hundreds of Jewish orphans in Chicago, and to contribute to the one hundred thousand dollar drive for the Jewish Infant Home which has been planned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
