<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago's Melting Pot</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0758</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0758.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO'S MELTING POT</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday in Chicago a new Jewish fraternity came into being, named the "People's Order," and composed of Jewish young folks who have taken upon themselves to create a modern order to suit our modern times.</p>
   <p>During the last few years much has been said and written to defeat the old and almost deteriorated system that exists in our lodges, but, it appears that the old leaders turn a deaf ear to modern improvements, both in respect to the management and the insurance upon which the order proper is built.</p>
   <p>You become a member in the lodge to get security for those you love and work for, but, you also wish to have a voice in the expenditure of such moneys <pb facs="5423972_6_0759.jpg" n="2"/>that you pay by the month. You do not want the president to be the "be all." You wish to know what is being done to your money, how it is distributed and especially what your dear ones may get after numerous years have passed during which time you have made regular payments.</p>
   <p>Under the present system of insurance methods that exist in most lodges, it is impossible for the order to fulfill its program or in other words to do its duty to you as a member. Many orders wish earnestly to do so; their intentions are good but their insurance system is so poor that even their best efforts cannot right it.</p>
   <p>There is but one way of improvement. Each order should adopt the modern system of insurance, abolish the old fermented spirit that hovers in the form of "Self-Rule" and all install the true democratic form.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0760.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the orders do not do this it will certainly lead to their downfall. This we must not permit. But why are they silent, those old ring leaders of fraternal orders? Do they not see the new surge coming on? Do they not know that sooner or later they must give way to the demands of the times and the people, - or perhaps they are loathe to relinquish their "fat jobs" and for this reason will eventually alter and fit their ways to the modern system, after it is too late.</p>
   <p>The new order that has just been founded has submitted its application for a charter. It is the direct result of our modern times. "The People's Order" built on democratic principles, with the slogan, "Let the People have their Say." The insurance system of this new order will be the last word in insurance improvement. In this position the order will truly be able to fulfill its necessary duties, giving the people the right to administer their <pb facs="5423972_6_0761.jpg" n="4"/>business and to see that the security or death policies, or better yet, that this protection of widows and orphans should not be a dead issue in their constitution, but should truly be the foundation of the order.</p>
   <p>At its last meeting the new order organized officially. Election of the following officers took place: Samuel Miken, president; Saul Druker, vice president; H. Harris, second vice president; Max Baum, secretary; Mr. Briar, treasurer; M. Schuman, financial secretary; Ab Miller, guard.</p>
   <p>Further information may be secured at Briar's Hat Store, 1220 S. Halsted Street, at Samuel Miken's, 903 W. 12th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
