<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-27">May 27, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-27">May 27, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Public Cook-Pot.</p>
   <p>Twenty-fifth Jubilee Celebration for Austro-Hungarian Aid Society. - Benefit for children suffering from tuberculosis. - Commencement Exercises of the Chicago Hebrew Institute Sabbath School. - Beneficial Lodges join "Order Knights of Zion." - Dr. Herzl's 50th birthday is celebrated. - Land and earth in Palestine.</p>
   <p>The Austro-Hungarian Aid Society which counts among its members some of the more influential Jews in America will celebrate its 25th Jubilee next Sunday at the North-Side Turner Hall. An especially interesting program has been arranged.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Consumptive Relief Society of Chicago needs a vacation camp and summer home for those children suffering from tuberculosis. To raise funds<pb facs="5423972_6_1368.jpg" n="2"/> to carry out their plans they have arranged a theater benefit for this Sunday, at the Colonial Theater.</p>
   <p>The Commencement Exercise of the Sabbath School of the Chicago Hebrew Institute will take place this Sunday at 2 o'clock in the afternoon. Miss Rosenberg will present 80 books as prizes to those children who achieve honors.</p>
   <p>The Order Knights of Zion, not being a "beneficial" organization whose main purpose is much more that to ameliorate the material needs of the individual, has now found it expedient to join the "Beneficial Orders of the United States." These lodges have finally decided that they should join with others and participate in activities other than Zionist. The "Beaconsfield Lodge" was one of the first to join the Beneficial Orders of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1369.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The 50th birthday of Dr. Theodore Herzl will be celebrated this Sunday afternoon at the North West Side Talmud Torah along with the installation of officers of the Zerubabel Gate. The question of land in Palestine will be discussed and every member will be asked to buy at least one dunam of land. A fine program has been arranged. Children from the Orphan Home will recite.</p>
   <p>"The Value of a Dunam of Land in Palestine" will be the theme of Mr. Leon Zolotkoff's talk tomorrow for the "Ha-Techya" Gate at a meeting at the Waller Street Talmud Torah. Everyone is invited to come and listen to this very interesting discussion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
