<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-04">June 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Necessity of Sabbath and Sunday Schools in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0172</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0172.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1906-06-04">June 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE NECESSITY OF SABBATH AND SUNDAY SCHOOLS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a land where general education is compulsory and where the public schools take up a major portion of our children's time, there is very little time left for attending a Hebrew school. Very often it is physically inadvisable for children to spend anymore time in a classroom. In spite of all the failings of a Sabbath school, therefore, we deem it necessary that such schools should be established. Surely we should pass on to our younger generation as much Jewish history and Jewish lore as time will permit.</p>
   <p>We are very happy to live in a land where compulsory education exists. Since the public schools, however, do not undertake to teach religion (and rightly so), we Jews should, as other religious groups have seen it fit to do, establish schools of our own to make up whatever deficiences we feel exist in the education of our children. It is our duty to inform our children of our past. Let us not shirk our duty. Let us provide more Sabbath and Sunday schools wherever it is necessary to do so. We are not forsaking the Hebrew schools [when we <pb facs="5423972_6_0173.jpg" n="2"/>advocate the establishment of more Sabbath and Sunday schools]. On the contrary, we feel that in this way we shall build up our schools more intensively.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
