<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-27">January 27, 1907</date><title level="a">Heard and Seen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-27">January 27, 1907</date><title level="a">Heard and Seen</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There were several matters of importance published recently in the Daily Jewish Courier, concerning some vital problems of the Jewish Orphans' Home. The first problem was shown of the shortage of funds to take care of the big mortgage that is hanging over the Orphans' Home. This mortgage needs to be paid, and there are no funds with which to satisfy the mortgage. There is not enough money to continue the support of the Home. Now, you Jews in Chicago, instead of making your donations direct to the Home, you are continually bothering yourselves and the officers about theatre benefits, etc. It seems that it is just as Mr. Jacob Levy, the president, reminded you: that you are ever ready to help the Home with your sighs and sympathy, but when it comes to sending money, you leave it entirely to the "Heavens Above". However, you of a certain class are not to be blamed much, if any. This class has never visited the Orphans' Home to see what we have accomplished in the Home. You just simply do not know nor realize the noble work that is done in the Institution. We teach the Jewish Orphans Yiddish. We have a Sabbath school, and school every other day in the week. Good, wholesome food, lots of good warm clothes, and a good place to sleep, etc. are provided. So now we inform the Jewish Public of the annual meeting of the Home, which will <pb facs="5423972_6_1645.jpg" n="2"/>be held today at 2 PM, at the Fraternity Hall, #70 E. Adams Street. All Jews of Chicago who have paid their last year's dues will be entitled to a vote in the election of Directors of the Orphans' Home for next year. Every other Jewish person can pay the annual dues at this meeting.</p>
   <p>It is useless to write in these columns, of the necessity of this Temple of Mercy here in Chicago. This is only to remind you at this meeting, to raise enough money to pay off the mortgage on the Orphans' Home, for it is against the laws of God to mortgage a Holy Temple of Mercy of this kind. So we repeat this appeal to the Jews of Chicago - to the members present, especially, to pay their annual dues at this meeting. Those who are not members are requested to come to this meeting and become members of this worthy cause. We want you all to come with your minds made up that this mortgage on the Jewish Orphans' Home must be paid off. Do not put this off for another day. Today is the day to free the Home of its mortgage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
