<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-07-03">July 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[Hope for Our Children]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-07-03">July 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[HOPE FOR OUR CHILDREN]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The friends, who attende the closing exercises of the Training School and inspected the exhibited work of the classes, must have carried away from their visit, the deep impression and certainty that marcelous results have been attained in the incredulously brief time that the school has been in operation.</p>
   <p>For our poor Russian brethren's children, the Training School offers the weapon for contest which they, will have to fight, most unrelentingly and most fiercely. A double portion of the world's distrust has come to them. They are Jews and Russian Jews. For the Russian children, the school holds a promise which, were its pupils recruited from other elements or our population, would perhaps not be so prominently noteworthy.</p>
   <p>The school will neutralize hereditary instincts, alive in consequence of centuries old persecution among their class, and difficult to eradicate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A love for manual labor will be inculcated into the souls of our pupils. They will appreciate once more the dignity of a mechanic's station, and will learn to shun the paths of petty commerce. And the children cannot fail to re-act upon the parents.</p>
   <p>It is a curious fact, and one to be pleased with, that the settlers from the dominion of the Czar, regard the school as their own. They take pride in it. They are eager to have their sons and daughters attend, and the evening classes comprise men and women of all ages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
