<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November, 1912</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November, 1912</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Trade School.</p>
   <p>In accordance with our recommendation last year, our Trade School was abandoned. While there is a great demand for such an activity, we found it impossible to obtain the desired results, particularly because the physical accomodations for such an activity are entirely lacking in our Institute, and secondly, because the condition of unionism in our city, especially in the plumbing line, is such that it was almost impossible for our graduates to make use of the training received at our school.</p>
   <p>If however, the physical facilities for such an activity were there we should strongly recommend the resuming of work along the trade line. There is very little doubt that there is a great need in the Jewish community of Chicago for a school, where not only the immigrant could, without much difficulty, learn a trade, and the Institute ought to provide this very opportunity. Many an immigrant could be started on the right track and could have material <pb facs="5423972_6_0088.jpg" n="2"/>success made a greater certainty for him, if he were given an opportunity either to learn a trade or acquire the American ways, in the trades which a good many of them bring with them from Europe. Such a department at the Institute would also encourage many parents to send their children to learn a trade, if they were sure that the boy or girl is not taken advantage of, as is frequently done in the shop or factory, while he or she is acquiring the knowledge of some trade or other.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
