<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-14">Sept. 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Jewish Order That Lives and Influences Jewish Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">by B. Fleischer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-14">Sept. 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A JEWISH ORDER THAT LIVES AND INFLUENCES JEWISH LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by B. Fleischer</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before in the age-old history of the Jewish Diaspora, never before in the history of Jewish misery and suffering, never before in the history of bloodshed and pogroms upon Jews has there been manifested so sharply and so boldly [a demonstration of] the great significance and the enormous aid that a Jewish organization can extend to the Jewish people in times of stress as well as in times of joy, as is now manifested when we consider the work and accomplishments of the Independent Order Brith Sholom. This Order was born about fourteen years ago in Philadelphia--the city where liberty for the American nation and equal opportunities for all men in this country were first proclaimed. This Order has its branches in every city that has a large Jewish community.</p>
   <p>Jewish orders in America have been in existence for many decades. They first made their appearance simultaneously with the great influx of Jewish immigration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0665.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Prior to the founding of the Independent Order Brith Sholom, the organizers of Jewish lodges had no clear understanding of what should and could be done for the Jewish masses. They were interested in Jewish life not for the sake of creating something, not for the sake of accomplishing something new, not for the sake of pursuing a certain ideal, but in order to overcome that strangeness and loneliness which existed among the Jewish immigrants, who had been torn away and driven from their homes, their surroundings, and everything dear to them. During the period of distress and misfortune, the Jewish immigrant was particularly in need of a helping hand and the lodges promised to extend such aid. It is no wonder, therefore, that large numbers of Jewish immigrants joined these lodges.</p>
   <p>Years have gone by. From the small Jewish groups, large Jewish communities have developed. A unique Jewish life began to spring up in the new home. The Jewish immigrants soon assumed a role in public life, but the character and methods of the Jewish lodges remained the same. The local environment was of no concern at all to the leaders. The Jewish lodges had hundreds of <pb facs="5423972_6_0666.jpg" n="3"/>thousands of members in their ranks. From the standpoint of organizational strength, the Jewish lodges became a very important factor, but Jewish life in general did not benefit by it at all.</p>
   <p>Jewish life in the old country became more and more difficult. The wave of pogroms instigated by the czarist regime put an end to the hopes of the Jewish intelligentsia for equal opportunities and equal rights for the Jews in Russia. It became clear even to the stupid that Palestine was the only solution--that only Palestine could liberate the Jewish people--but the Jewish lodges here remained static, as if they were not concerned with the pain and anguish of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>The Independent Order Brith Sholom, however, put an end to this tragic situation. The Independent Order Brith Sholom adopted a new program and formulated for itself new principles which would be appropriate to the needs of the times and which would express the real hopes of the Jewish people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0667.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The founders of Brith Sholom foresaw the importance which the lodges would have for the people, and the tremendous role the lodges could play in Jewish life if they were administered by persons who lived in and influenced the Jewish neighborhood. The fourteen-year-old history of Brith Sholom proves the correctness of this attitude.</p>
   <p>As soon as the Independent Order Brith Sholom became firmly established and was in a position to secure all the material benefits which its members had a right to expect from a safe insurance society or fraternal order, its leaders began to perfect a powerful and well-disciplined organizational machine which would benefit not only its members, but all the Jews as well.</p>
   <p>The Brith Sholom was the first Jewish order which resolved to make the Zionist movement a part of its own movement, and to induce its thousands of members to become directly affiliated with the Zionist movement. And so it was decided that each member of the Order was morally obligated to buy "shekels" [Certificates entitling a Zionist to vote for delegates to the World Zionist Congress]. This decision had a magnetic effect upon the entire Zionist movement and gave <pb facs="5423972_6_0668.jpg" n="5"/>the most devoted Zionist workers new courage and new hope with which to inspire the Jewish masses. The Zionist propagandists gained direct contact with the people because Brith Sholom opened its meetings to them so that they could speak and awaken the Jewish masses to work and struggle for the Jewish liberation from the Diaspora.</p>
   <p>The decision of Brith Sholom had a remarkable influence upon other and older Jewish lodges. Naturally, this did not happen immediately. It took some time before they realized the truth and [then] they also began to speak a new language, the language of modern times. The same occurred when the Congress movement took place. The Brith Sholom became deeply involved in the Congress movement. The [Jewish] Congress movement appeared to be and probably was the one single factor which was instrumental in forcing the Peace Conference at Versailles to compel Poland, Rumania, and other anti-Semitic countries to recognize the rights of minorities, which in this instance meant equal rights for the Jewish people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0669.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The lodge meetings became interesting and significant. The average Jew, to whom the lodge meeting meant spiritual consolation, began to hear new thoughts expressed and started to acquaint himself with the duties which always rest upon the Jew and especially so at a time when Jewish life is more intolerable than ever before in the bloody history of the Jews. Through the lodge meetings, the Independent Order Brith Sholom brought new life and courage to the Jewish people. Every movement, whose objective was to aid the struggle for the material or spiritual interests of the Jewish people, in any way and at any time, began to develop. The Zionist movement, the Congress movement, the movement to extend aid to the war victims, and many others began to grow.</p>
   <p>At the same time, the leaders of the Brith Sholom forged ahead, making their organization strong and powerful. They were solicitous of the needs of their members at all times and never forsook them under any circumstances. A member of Brith Sholom always has someone to turn to--his organization is alive and influential in his interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0670.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>This was clearly evident during the last years of the war when it was necessary to help our country in the struggle against the enemy, and at the same time to deal a deathblow to the Jewish enemies who continued to spread false accusations that Jews were slackers and friends of the enemy. We need only mention what the Order did for the Jewish young men who were called to war.</p>
   <p>The Welfare Board found the Brith Sholom to be its best co-worker and greatest aid. The relief committees of America found the Brith Sholom to be their greatest support, and the same holds true with regard to all the recognized Jewish philanthropic institutions throughout the country. But regardless of the importance of all of this, the Brith Sholom's most glorious and enduring achievement was its remarkable and self-sacrificing work to help the victims of the recent influenza epidemic which has raged so horribly throughout America, and particularly in Philadelphia.</p>
   <p>The Jews of America cannot remain indifferent to the Brith Sholom and its <pb facs="5423972_6_0671.jpg" n="8"/>leaders. The Jews of America must recognize the importance of this work by joining this organization, and responding enthusiastically to the call of the Brith Sholom. That this is true is proven by the fact that while in the past few years, almost all of the Jewish fraternal orders in America have suffered something of a setback, the Brith Sholom has continued to expand, becoming larger and stronger.</p>
   <p>When the two high officials of Brith Sholom, Dr. L. S. Rubinson, grandmaster and Mr. Adolph Rosenblum, assistant secretary and head of the propaganda committee of the Order, who are delegates to the Zionist Convention which is being held here, address the local Brith Sholom members at their general meeting, they will learn that the local Jews know how to appreciate true friends and real leaders of an organization which, through its work, has written the most glorious chapter in the history of Jewish orders. They will learn that splendid work is ultimately recognized.</p>
   <p>For particulars about this great and successful Order see our seventh deputy <pb facs="5423972_6_0672.jpg" n="9"/>grand master, Samuel Blair, 165 North Clark Street; telephone, Central 6167.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
