<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnasium</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1912-11">November 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnasium</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our gymnasium met with great success this year. The registration was 761 (478 male and 283 female, varying in age from 5 to 27 years) which is the largest in the history of the Institute. The total attendance was 18,914 - against 16,233 last year:</p>
   <p>There is no question in our mind, that no matter from whatever point of view considered, a well-equipped gymnasium is the most necessary thing in a social institution such as ours. There is no doubt that in our new gymnasium with such excellent equipment and accommodations as we hope to have the work in this department and the good accomplished will be unexcelled.</p>
   <p>The fact that we are to have such a splendid gymnasium in the near future is proof that there are at least some Jewish citizens in our midst who are far sighted enough and have a sufficient understanding of our social problems and their possible solutions to appreciate fully the great social and educational value of such a department in a social and educational center.</p>
   <p>Our boys have won many victories and have made the institute known far and wide. Their conduct, wherever they were, was admired by all and won many a friend for <pb facs="5423972_6_0475.jpg" n="2"/>them as well as for the institute. The older boys have organized themselves into a club whose purpose it is to foster a spirit of good fellowship among the members of the gymnasium as well as to provide for certain expenditures not provided for by the institute, such as buying of suits for the athletes, paying car fares, awarding of prizes, etc. Many of the boys have also rendered personal service and assistance to the institute whenever called upon.</p>
   <p>In the course of the year six team prizes and sixty-eight individual medals were won by the members of the gymnasium. One of our athletes represented the institute in a contest at New Orleans, where he won the championship in wrestling in the Southern States, and in St.Louis, one of our members carried off a medal in the marathon.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1912 - 1913</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>1911 - 1912</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expense.</cell>
     <cell>$ 2,757.64</cell>
     <cell>Expense.</cell>
     <cell>$2,564.67</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Revenue.</cell>
     <cell>1,347.05</cell>
     <cell>Revenue.</cell>
     <cell>1,042.54</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
