<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-11-10">November 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Charity Question in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0845</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0845.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-11-10">November 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH CHARITY QUESTION IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of how much charity is being given by our Jews, is a matter of guess work. Some say that it is very much; some have remarked that it is not enough, and others say that the Jewish charity is so little, that it is not worth-while mentioning. Considering the large Jewish population of Chicago, the amount of charity given by those Jews, whom we call German Jews, is known and accounted for to a penny. The United States charities publishes every year the amount of charity collected from its different sources, how much was received from each institution and how much was spent that year, the amount spent for each institution it supported. For example, last year the United States charities spent $400,000 on the fifteen institutions under its jurisdiction, but with our orthodox Jews, there is never a correct or definite account given; one may say that we give $100,000, another will say five times that much - for there is not much system with our orthodox brethren; no one knows how much the next one is giving or what he is doing.</p>
   <p>Many of our prominent Jewish citizens here in Chicago are of the opinion and insist that it is very important to have an accounting for every dollar collected and spent, so with this in view, a committee was organized to gather statistics of our Chicago Jewish charity. The committee consists of B.Hurwitz, <pb facs="5423972_6_0846.jpg" n="2"/>president of "Ezres Nedochim" Congregation and the well-known Jewish leader, Dr. Swaiton, superintendent of the Jewish Home for the Aged, and Mr. Drucker, superintendent of the Marks Nathan Orphan Home. The committee got in touch with all the Jewish institutions, such as lodges, synagogues, and other different aid societies, with an appeal for help. The committee requested these institutions to furnish them the names of their respective presidents and secretaries, addresses of their meeting places or headquarters, and the amounts collected and the expenditure of last year.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rosenshon, librarian of the Hebrew Library, together with the committee, decided to publish all proceedings of these activities in the Daily Jewish Courier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
