<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-01">Sept. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish National Labor Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Stoolman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-01">Sept. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH NATIONAL LABOR ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Stoolman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Shortly after the Poale Zion (Left wing Zionists) was officially established in this country, individual comrades thought of establishing a Workers Order, which would be able to fight for the economic needs of the Jewish worker, and at the same time, not be in opposition to his national sentiments and inclinations, as are several existing workers' orders.</p>
   <p>As time went on, this thought penetrated the minds of the Poale Zion comrades throughout the country, and the question of creating such an order became an issue on the agenda of the Buffalo Party Council at the close of 1908.</p>
   <p>In 1908 Comrades Wexler, Miller and Meyer Broun of Philadelphia began the practical realization of this plan and founded a benevolent Verein by the <pb facs="5423972_6_0719.jpg" n="2"/>name of "National Workers Alliance".</p>
   <p>A short time later a Poale Zion Benevolent Verein was launched in New York, and other such Vereins sprang up in Pittsburgh, Chicago and other cities. In spite of the independent character of each Verein, they all sought the same aim: to remove the Jewish worker from an atmosphere of assimilation, and bring him into a purely Jewish environment where he shall move about freely.</p>
   <p>The extent that this plan answered the demand of the time, and quenched the thirst of many nationalistically inclined Jewish workers was a demonstration of the great interest it aroused, and the heated discussions which took place among the intelligent Jewish workers at that time. They accepted joyfully this plan of creating their own order, which would give them the necessary economic assistance and benefits, and at the same time,would satisfy their nationalist hopes.</p>
   <p>This idea spread throughout every city and hamlet. Group after group began <pb facs="5423972_6_0720.jpg" n="3"/>to organize, calling for a convention which should introduce clarity and create a common understanding among the various groups.</p>
   <p>A conference was held in June, 1910.</p>
   <p>This conference unitedly declared that the National Workers Alliance strives to unite all nationalistically minded Jewish workers on the grounds of common economic and national interests.</p>
   <p>The New York Poale Zion Benevolent Verein remained independent of the Philadelphia branch and carried on propaganda urging groups to join the New York outfit.</p>
   <p>Discussions in several party Vereins forced the Central Committee of the Poale Zion to take an official position toward this important question, and they decided to place the issue of the National Workers Alliance on the agenda of the <pb facs="5423972_6_0721.jpg" n="4"/>Poale Zion Conference in Chicago, July 4.</p>
   <p>The fourth Poale Zion convention was held in Philadelphia, and the delegates were urged to organize Alliance branches in their respective cities. But the existing Vereins had been weakened and partly dissolved, including the first Philadelphia Verein.</p>
   <p>For a few months, work was at a standstill. The Poale Zion, upon its own initiative, began to organize one Verein after another, and urged a general assembly to draw up a platform of principles for the Alliance.</p>
   <p>An organizing conference of the Alliance was called in Rochester, June 19, 1910.</p>
   <p>An appeal was sent to the comrades throughout the country to organize more Vereins in order to have a larger representation of delegates who could deal competently and firmly with all questions. This conference should have established not only the principles of the Alliance and drawn up a constitution, <pb facs="5423972_6_0722.jpg" n="5"/>but should have set up also an insurance system. At this organizational conference, eleven Vereins were represented through twenty-five delegates. The conference lasted four days.</p>
   <p>Sunday Jewish Courier, Sept. 3, 1916.</p>
   <p>One of the chief questions which the congress should have clarified was that of a Jewish homeland. The extremist Poale Zion delegates demanded that our position on this question be a positive one, i.e.,the Alliance should declare specifically that the complete national emancipation of the Jewish people is possible only in their own land, in Palestine. The majority, however, argued that the National Workers Alliance should become the central organization of a large number of Jewish workers, and the Alliance could only realize this aim if it would make possible the free expression of opinion of every nationalistically inclined Jewish worker.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0723.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Another question of utmost importance which the convention had to consider was the legalization question. This was closely related to the question of setting up an insurance system for the Alliance.</p>
   <p>By adopting the most modern and secure insurance system, which is known as the "American Experience Table", based on a legal reserve of four per cent, the convention laid the foundation of a sound and strong National Workers Alliance.</p>
   <p>The following basic principles were adopted:</p>
   <p>A. The Jewish National Workers Alliance declares its basic aim to be:</p>
   <p>1. Mutual aid in case of need, sickness or death.</p>
   <p>2. Education of the Jewish worker in full consciousness of his national and social interests.</p>
   <p>B. The National Workers Alliance supports all workers who work for the national emancipation and revival of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>C. The National Workers Alliance supports all workers who strive for the <pb facs="5423972_6_0724.jpg" n="7"/>strengthening and emancipation of the working class.</p>
   <p>Establishing in the Alliance such a brilliant insurance system, and imbuing the Alliance with a nationalistic and radical spirit which could lead to the emancipation of the Jewish people, and could strengthen and fortify the position of the working class, made it possible for the Alliance to become one of the most important and necessary Jewish workers' institutions in the country. Fortunately its rapid growth and development could be used as evidence.</p>
   <p>The general sentiment of gathering all nationalistically inclined Jewish labor elements into a great Alliance that would accept and support all work that led to the national emancipation of our people, and of the working class, was also acclaimed by the Chicago Poale Zion in 1908.</p>
   <p>In the Jewish Labor Voice of January 15, 1905, an appeal was published by <pb facs="5423972_6_0725.jpg" n="8"/>M. Melamed, Philadelphia secretary of [the organization of] all radical and nationalistically minded Jews; his appeal urged Jews to help in the organizing of the National Workers Alliance.</p>
   <p>This appeal had a good effect on the small group in Chicago. It gave them courage to begin intensive work for the establishment of an Alliance branch. More Jewish workers became interested in the new organization. The small circle grew, and on Monday, June 14, 1909, a foundation in Chicago was laid. At the Hebrew Institute, the first branch was organized with Harry Resnick as secretary.</p>
   <p>The Alliance, however, did not last long. A few attempts were made later to revive it but without success.</p>
   <p>Then the Chicago Poale Zion convention brought clarity to the Alliance question, and again the comrades undertook organizational work, until finally, there existed grounds for the establishment of the first branch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0726.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The official installation of this branch took place May 15, 1910. The Alliance participated in the formulation of the agenda for the Organizing Conference which was held in Rochester, June 1910. It sent as delegate, A. Molin, instructing him to vote for a free platform, which should give the Alliance the opportunity to receive all nationalistically minded Jewish workers as members.</p>
   <p>The Organizing Conference united all the various groups and Vereins into a single Alliance, with a unified program and induced the comrades to work energetically in behalf of the organization, and towards the strengthening of the Alliance in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The legalization of the Alliance on January 6, 1913 was greeted with overwhelming joy. And upon knowing that the material aspect of the Alliance was completely secured, the comrades began with keener interest to broaden Alliance activities and to make the theoretical, as well as the practical, functions of the Alliance more popular among the Jewish workers in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0727.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The Alliance in Chicago became active in social work, carrying on general propaganda amongst the Jewish workers for national and radical ideas. It became interested in educational work, and took an active part in founding the first Jewish daily "Peoples School" (in the John Smythe School), resulting from a petition bearing 5000 signatures. It influenced the Chicago Public Library Board to open a library and reading room in the Lawndale District. It was active in organizing the "Young Macabbeans"; it supported the Jewish unions, participated in all labor struggles and strike conferences, participated in all social and labor activities and became an important factor in Chicago Jewish life.</p>
   <p>Thus was Philadelphia the cradle, the foundation of this young Jewish order which produced a net of branches throughout the country, and serves as a splendid example of the extent to which orders can become advantageous for their class and people--through idealistic principles and social activity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
