<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-19">Apr. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of Medical Staff of Mount Sinai Hospital</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-19">Apr. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF MEDICAL STAFF OF MOUNT SINAI HOSPITAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Annual Meeting of the Medical Staff of Mount Sinai Hospital was held Friday evening, April 13, 1923, at the Hospital.</p>
   <p>Dr. M. Lewison, president, in his annual report, stated that the Hospital had grown very rapidly during the past year, while, for lack of space, the facilities had not been correspondingly increased. It was the unanimous sentiment of the members of the staff that immediate steps must be taken toward meeting the needs of the Hospital, and a motion was passed that the Medical Staff meet with the Board of Directors to discuss ways and means of providing same at an earliest possible date.</p>
   <p>At this meeting, the urgent needs of the Hospital had to be discussed, and needs for immediate financing of same determined.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1181.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Morris Kurtzon, president of the Board of Directors, and Mrs. Edwin Romberg, vice-president, were present and spoke of the proposed drive, which is to include the Mount Sinai Hospital. The Medical Staff is willing and anxious to co-operate in this drive, providing it will take care of the immediate needs of the Hospital.</p>
   <p>A committee was appointed to co-operate with the General Drive Committee to promote its work among the doctors of the West and Northwest Sides.</p>
   <p>Election of officers for the following year ensued, and the following were elected: President, Dr. M. Lewison; Vice-President, Dr. V. L. Schrager; Secretary, Dr. Charles Newberger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
