<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-29">April 29, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0850</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0850.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-29">April 29, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Public Cook-Pot. (Column of Local News).</p>
   <p>The Young Men's Associated Jewish Charities and their Entertainment. - The Passover Seders as conducted by the Shelter Home and by the Jewish Culture Verein. A Benefit for Maimonides Kosher Hospital. - The Kadimah and Clara Dr Hirsch Lecture.</p>
   <p>The Young Men's Associated Jewish Charities was originally organized to aid the parent organization. Infrequently they give an entertainment which shows the character of their work. Yesterday evening they ran an affair at the Standard Club with Julius Rosenwald presiding. Mr. Emil G. Hirsch was the principal speaker and E. M. Newman, a member of Ex-president Roosevelt's African Expedition displayed motion pictures of their trip. Mr. Newman gave vivid verbal explanations of these pictures.</p>
   <p>Next Saturday, the South-west Side committee of the Young Men's Associated Jewish <pb facs="5423972_6_0851.jpg" n="2"/>Charities will run a smoker at the West Chicago Masonic Temple, 12th st. at Oakley Blvd. A good time is assured to all who come.</p>
   <p>The Seders conducted by the Shelter Home and Jewish Culture Group were indeed interesting. The Shelter Home was host to more than 150 people. The Seder was conducted in traditional manner and with the greatest enthusiasm. The Jewish Culture group started its Seder in the traditional manner but then branched off in a manner alien to us. However it was Judaism as they wish it and as such can be accepted.</p>
   <p>The Maimonides Kosher Hospital will give a musical under the personal direction of George Burza with a choir of 30 female voices, Sunday evening, May 8th at the Chicago Hebrew Unstitute.</p>
   <p>The last regular monthly lecture and dance of the season of the Kadimah and Clara De Hirsch Gates, will take place next Sunday evening at the Chicago Hebrew Institute. <pb facs="5423972_6_0852.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Israel Cohen will be the lecturer and Miss Jennie Liebson will render a piano solo.</p>
   <p>The Prospect Hospital Aid Society is a society organized for the purpose of taking over the Prospect Hospital and turning it into a Jewish Hospital. This society will run a dance on May 30th at Masonic Temple Drill Hall. Dr. A. Goldstein is president and Dr. B. N. Novi, secretary of the society.</p>
   <p>(Signed) The Cook-Spoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
