<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-04">Nov. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Marks Nathan Orphanage</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1591</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1591.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-04">Nov. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARKS NATHAN ORPHANAGE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We bring to the readers of the Courier the entire report of Mr. Trotsky, the superintendent of the Marks Nathan Orphanage. Many times before has the Courier written about this important institution, but now we are giving all the facts regarding the good and the bad in the orphanage. It presents to the reader a clear and concise picture of the conditions in the institution and the state of the orphans. Let the reader peruse carefully the superintendent's report with its rich information and he will get the same idea.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1592.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I wish to thank you for the confidence you have bestowed upon me in your choice for this important position and to assure you that I have accepted knowing all the difficult tasks thereof. May I point out that in so doing I have received not only the usual administration, the institution, but also, so to speak, the physical and spiritual well being of a large group of about 225 small children. Again, may I indicate, that in accomplishing my duties, I am responsible not only to you, but to the entire Jewish community of Chicago - perhaps to the city in general, because the children at present under my supervision will later be a part of the community and the general moral tone of that group, will, more or less, be influenced by the background that our children receive at present, by the ideas and ideals that are now being molded in their minds and in their hearts. Yes, with total understanding of my duties, <pb facs="5423972_6_1593.jpg" n="3"/>I have begun, and wish to continue thus with hard work. This should be a sufficient guarantee of my future undertakings.</p>
   <p>"It is not my intention to make a long flowery speech, because, first of all, I am a person of action, not of speech; secondly, in this present day practical era, one is judged not by his promises, not even by his efforts, but by the results that only the future can bring. What I want to say is that if earnestness, alertness, devotion, steadfastness, and a practical knowledge of the position makes a person's work successful, I see no reason why my administration should not be successful.</p>
   <p>"Yet, honorably expended energies and constant decisions, although absolutely fundamental in bringing about success, can not <pb facs="5423972_6_1594.jpg" n="4"/>and do not always assure and lead to this success. A good deal depends on cooperation, circumstances, and conditions. I am sorry to say that the circumstances and conditions existing at present in our home are, to say the least, far from elevating and encouraging. Our institution has physical shadows that are like rocks in the path of attaining a good administration, that hinder a good administration even more than just another obstacle. You must, therefore, accept it as natural and reasonable when I point to these dark clouds. Do not spare any energy to annihilate them as soon as possible. I well know that to do away with obstacles will require great sacrifices on your part. But I am also happy to know that the Executive is empowered to use all opportunities for improvement and I am a staunch supporter of the old saying, 'Where there is a will, there's a way.'</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1595.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"The main trouble in our institution lies in two factors. First, the unfinished building, and second, the bad partnerships. I will not dwell very long on the results of an unfinished building. This will, as I understand, be shown by skilled workmen in their report to the Medical Board with whom I have already spoken. I will say, in short, that broken walls make a good place for dust and that unpaved, muddy playgrounds with stagnant puddles after the rain make cleanliness and health impossible. Just imagine this scene of 225 pairs of little feet running back and forth from the building to the mud puddles and vice versa.</p>
   <p>It might appear funny, but the white stones in the undecorated halls and the floors throughout the entire building bear proof that this is no laughing matter. Then too, the children's shoes are not waterproof <pb facs="5423972_6_1596.jpg" n="6"/>and on a rainy day they become water soaked. This leads to colds and it is just short of a miracle that our hospital wards are not overcrowded with these sufferers. The sad appearing walls with broken plaster, although at present offering a broad field for the artistic abilities of the children, as their bold writings and engravings show, do not of course develop their refined or aesthetic abilities. The lack of furniture in the children's rooms has the same sad significance. A child should be made to feel as if he were in his own home, - not on some broken school bench, but in a comfortable, restful chair. The front of the house would also look better if there were trees and grass to relieve the striking contrast with the beautiful park across the street. All this means, naturally, money. But, it also means the making of the institution. It is an important matter and it should be worth your while to make this great sacrifice. Especially now when you are <pb facs="5423972_6_1597.jpg" n="7"/>free from rent worries, you can and you must direct your activities in united efforts to raise the necessary funds.</p>
   <p>"By bad partnerships I mean, of course, the public schools and the Schul. This institution as you understand is built on the 'Double Wing' plan. One side is for boys only, the other, for the girls with all the comforts that they need. But the girls' wing was taken over for public school purposes, and their rooms were erected on the same side as the boys. This, of course, has made it very inconvenient for the girls in many ways. For instance, they have to take their shower baths in the public school wing, and then, directly from their hot baths, must run across a stone floor, which easily exposes them to colds. Besides, half undressed, they pass through the front hall and the boys' hall. We have grown boys and girls - this, to say the least does not raise our morale.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1598.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"Then again, to set aside eleven rooms, tends to crowd and inconvenience us. A dining room and dormitory are not sufficient rooms to rear children. They must also have study rooms, a recreation room, a gymnasium and an assembly room. All this they lack. The same is true of the Schul, which they must have to themselves for their own use without being disturbed by strangers. It should be definitely understood that our building has been constructed for the children and for them only. I hope that our present lease with the Board of Education will not be renewed. I am happy to know that our Executive is considering these matters earnestly and thoroughly, and I hope that you will give us your aid and approval in improving our condition. What we need at present is money, money, and money.</p>
   <p>"Money to color their entire education, money to accomplish our work as it should be done, money to improve our playgrounds, and money to install play rooms. That, I cannot give you. No superintendent can do this, it is your task.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1599.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"It is my pleasure to report that our children are happy here. Our home, as far as possible, is very much like a private home in which the children, to this extent, receive a natural home life. I am endeavoring to find a happy medium by exerting a little discipline. By discipline I do not mean, as you understand, heavy, burdensome rules and regulations, but, what I would call a natural discipline. That is to teach and instill industrious and purposeful habits, economy, punctuality, etc. This is especially important since we have no large playgrounds and our children are under the influence of the "Street." As our president at one time so cleverly expressed it: "Our home is at present a large Ghetto home." We wish to transform it into a harmonious, well regulated home which, of course, will require a certain amount of discipline. The club activities that have been established by my predecessor cannot be tendered enough praise. It works miraculously. I wish you could see the eagerness and impatience with which the girls look forward to their Tuesday club evening. They have all sorts of clubs, a piano club, <pb facs="5423972_6_1600.jpg" n="10"/>a violin club, a dancing club, social clubs, a club of "Truthful Friends," and others with appropriate names. The club work, without doubt, greatly increases our electric bills. But at the same time, they elevate and make the childish hearts happy. Amusements help to refine childish natures. We must give them as many indoor pleasures and entertainments as possible, especially in the sad winter days.</p>
   <p>"All this was regarding the clubs of the girls only. Our boys are envious. I have, therefore, appealed to the Menorah Society of the Jewish students of the Chicago University, with the purpose of getting them to take up social club work with our boys every week-end. Our boys, we expect, will, thus, have their own athletic club shortly, as well as literary and debating societies which would be a huge step forward <pb facs="5423972_6_1601.jpg" n="11"/>in developing their individualities and personal abilities that go into the making of the man. It also teaches self-control. Special attention will be given to physical culture. We Jews have devoted two thousand years to our minds. It is high time that we devoted some of our time to the development of good strong muscles. Our children, I am happy to say, love to read, so much so, that I found it necessary on my own accord to put deep green illumination in the dormitories. In the public school, they are diligent, attentive and ambitious, and are highly lauded by the principal. We have five boys and five girls in the high school, all of them are progressing well. The health of our children is quite satisfactory. In the last month, twenty-six were in the hospital, all suffering with light colds. This measure helps to prevent any further development of this malady. Please consider these colds that have developed due to the bad conditions of our playgrounds that I mentioned before, and yet you will find this number small.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1602.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>"When I accepted this position there were 204 children, (127 boys and 77 girls). During the month seven boys left and fourteen boys and three girls entered, making a total of 214 in the home. Eleven more will soon be entered, completing the sum of twenty-five that were voted upon at the last meeting.</p>
   <p>"Regarding general management, much has been said and written about it recently. Many have criticised and condemned, others passed judgment on its good qualities. It was said that our expenses were too large compared with that of other institutions. That our household expenses are not dispensed in the most economical way. Naturally such reports are greatly exaggerated. As a newcomer, I know very little of the matter, but I can assure you that I shall study this problem thoroughly and bring <pb facs="5423972_6_1603.jpg" n="13"/>expenses down to the most economic level, but not at any cost to the children. Our children use twice as much milk, butter and eggs as those at any other institution. Bless their little hearts! I believe in keeping them well fed. Feeding them well is one of the best investments for the children.</p>
   <p>"One point I have intentionally left for the last. That is their Jewishness and their Jewish education. I am not a rabbi nor the son of one but I am for a strong national Jew. And my greatest ambition is to see that our children grow up to be good Jews, not simply Jews, but Jews that know all about Judaism, Jews with Jewish thoughts and Jewish hearts. I am not satisfied with Sunday or Sabbath school Jews. I will bring all my energies to bear on the fact that our children should learn and know Judaism. Naturally, in the school everything is taught in English, but I hope that in time our Hebrew School will be the model one for all Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1604.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>"I touched on many points. The rest I shall leave for some other time when I shall be more familiar with local affairs. I wish only to voice my hope that every member of the Board of Directors will cooperate and aid in this immense task that I have undertaken. Then and only then will my work be successful."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
