<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1893-09-02">September 2, 1893</date>. pp.41-42.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1893-09-02">September 2, 1893</date>. pp.41-42.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On September 14th, A South Side Training School will be opened for boys and girls of all ages, under the management of Prof. G. Bamberger, of the Jewish Training School.</p>
   <p>The school will be located at 32 College Place, fronting south on the old Chicago University grounds. The house is being refitted with a special view to the needs of this school, which will be supplied with workshops and all modern conveniences for manual training and physical culture. The departments to be opened first will be Kindergarten, Primary and Grammar departments.</p>
   <p>Because of his duties at the West Side School, Prof. Bamberger will not be able to devote his entire time to this school. He has secured the services of Mr. T. J. Shea, as principal. Mr. Shea is highly recommended as an educator and is a graduate ofthe Indiana State Normal School and Indiana University.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Kindergarten and Primary departments will be under the supervision of Miss Little, formerly principal of West Bay City, Mich., Normal Training School. Miss Little has had experience as a practical and successful teacher in Kindergarten and Primary methods.</p>
   <p>The rates for tuition will be as follows: Kindergarten, $50 per year, Primary Grades, $80, Grammar Grades, $100. The fees will include Gymnastics, Drawing, Modeling, Manual Training and all branches commonly classes "extras." Application for admission will be received, and further information will be given at 32 College Place, on and after Sept. 4th, daily from 10 to 12 a.m., and from 2 to 5 o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
