<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-08">November 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Charity Trust and Cheap Politicians</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Nachumson</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-08">November 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY TRUST AND CHEAP POLITICIANS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By Nachumson</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the previous article concerning the Jewish Charity in Chicago, we were told of a clique of cheap politicians who organized the Federation of the Orthodox Institutions hoping to embrace all institutions within their power. The clique had concerned themselves very little with the welfare of the poor orphans, and of the aged, and the sick. The Federation was not founded for them but for the politicians themselves. The original founders of the Federation utilized their machinery in persuading the Republican and Democrat bosses that they had the Jewish community in their pocket and could deliver the Jewish votes for a price - and jobs. Several of them obtained these jobs.</p>
   <p>The Federation was, literally speaking, a federation of the cheap politicians. When it became too uncomfortable for them because of agitation by the Forward, the Jewish Record, and the English-Jewish press, that they ought to leave (from the Federation, but not from the political jobs), the institutions lost their old sources of income and from the new sources and <pb facs="5423972_6_0708.jpg" n="2"/>subscriptions, very little came in. The institutions had reached a critical moment and in order to exist they had to go in debt to cover their previous loans. The departure of the political clique did not help the institutions because what had once been spoiled cannot be so easily altered.</p>
   <p>Thus the Federation went from bad to worse until it was eventually obligated to the wealthy class on the South Side. It was an unconditional surrender to the autocracy of German-Jews, who conduct the charitable institutions, in a strict business manner. In such fashion, the West Side institutions are now being managed, and the public has no authority. The West Side institutions now prevail under a trust, conducted like all other trusts. It, therefore, remains a fact that the institutions that were established by the nickels and dimes of the masses of the West Side are now depending upon the mercy of the money-bags of the South Side. But who is guilty? No one but the clique of cheap politicians and job-hounds, who organized a Federation, not for the good of the public, but for the good of the individual, who use the community's institutions in order to procure fat jobs from the Democrats and Republican bosses, and to whom they are always prepared to sell their Judaism for a pot of lentils.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
