<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1932-01-08">Jan. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">What the Medical Department of the Workmen's Circle Does for the Members</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1932-01-08">Jan. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT THE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT OF THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE DOES FOR THE MEMBERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The medical department of the Workmen's Circle, assuming the task of organizing the members for cooperative medical aid, so that they will not have to pay too big a price for medical service and enabling them to obtain the best care, has broadened the activities of the department.</p>
   <p>In his report to the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle, the chairman of the medical department has made it known, that the medical committee has made arrangements with prominent physicians, who will give the members of the Workmen's Circle the best medical service at a very reasonable price.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Gracy, the noted heart and lung specialist, and Dr. Noah Schoolman, well-known ear and nose specialist, are among those with whom the medical committee has concluded arrangements.</p>
   <p>The medical department also has a staff of well-known and experienced physicians, who are serving the members and their families for a very small honorarium, which the members are paying annually to the medical department. These doctors visit members in their homes, when called, or will see them in their offices, in regular office hours.</p>
   <p>The medical department is connected with the Social Service Department and helps the members to obtain hospital service, when in need of it.</p>
   <p>In short, the department is organized for the main purpose of giving the members the best that medical science is capable of for a minimum price.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Naturally the medical department could accomplish much more in the field of medical aid, if all the members of the Workmen's Circle belonged to it. A large membership would enable the medical department to install modern and up-to-date methods, which would be of great benefit to the members and their families.</p>
   <p>It is not only the duty, but it is to the best interests of each member of the Workmen's Circle to become affiliated with the medical department and thus derive the medical and material benefits enjoyed by those who belong.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
