<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-09">May 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Curriculum in the Talmud Torahs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-09">May 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">CURRICULUM IN THE TALMUD TORAHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The educational subcommittee of the reorganization committee of the Talmud Torah has, according to our point of view, the most difficult task: namely, how to raise young Jews and teach them Judaism. As yet, the method which will accomplish this task has not been decided upon, the reason being that those who are supposed to decide such matters are not equipped to do so.</p>
   <p>It is easy for certain people to get up, make speeches, lament about our educational system, criticize others for their methods, and desire to change them; but when it come to actualities--to solving the actual problem--these people find themselves at a loss. How should a Talmud Torah be conducted in the United States? That is a very difficult question to answer at this time. We all agree that the old system should be changed; yet no one seems to know what changes to make.</p>
   <p>We think that before we decide upon a course of study for our children we should decide just what we expect of them as Jews. Are we to prepare them for <pb facs="5423972_6_0125.jpg" n="2"/>emigration to Palestine to form a government there? Is it our duty to conduct a Hebrew school which will train our future public officials, Hebrew orators, Jewish financiers, engineers, doctors, etc.? Or maybe we should conduct a Jewish "Gymnasium"?</p>
   <p>If we wish to raise our children as American citizens, however, then the Hebrew language loses its primary importance, and should receive no more emphasis than any other part of the curriculum. We feel that Hebrew is not absolutely essential, and that the mastery of it should be stressed in the higher educational institutions and not in the Talmud Torah. A Talmud Torah is not an idealistic undertaking.</p>
   <p>The Talmud Torah should, therefore, not be transformed into a mere Hebrew school. Changes in method are necessary, but not such changes. The Hebrew language alone cannot make the child a Jew. Is it not strange that most of the people who are demanding that Hebrew should be stressed in the Talmud Torah curriculum are the very same people who object most strenuously to our Orthodox way of life? The educational subcommittee will have to solve this problem.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0126.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The problem of securing a principal in the Talmud Torah is also something the education committee should consider seriously. The era of beating and subjugating the pupils is gone. Any teacher who indulges in this practice in order to maintain discipline should be dismissed immediately--no matter how good a teacher he may be otherwise. We need a fine man for the job of principal--one who will command the respect of the teachers, as well as the pupils. It is not the duty of the principal to decide on methods of finance. This work belongs to the board of education. The principal should see that the decisions of the board are carried out in an orderly fashion. A principal should be appointed before school opens on Sunday. We hope that the board will realize how necessary it is to appoint one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
