<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-11-24">November 24, 1911</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-11-24">November 24, 1911</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's Cook Pot.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Dr. Shoenfarber will address the audience today at the Hebrew Institute. His subject will be "The Science and Knowledge of our Jewish Prophets."</p>
   <p>On Sunday afternoon the Hebrew Institute will conduct the fourth in a series of Sunday concerts. The Thomas Orchestra will play under the direction of Alexander Zukowsky. Compositions by the following popular composers will be played: Chopin, Delieb, Brahms, Mendelssohn, Schumann, etc. The young talented pianist, Miss Mesirov will be piano soloist. From this Sunday on, these concerts will be conducted every other Sunday.</p>
   <p>The Players Club of the Hebrew Institute is giving a presentation at 4 P. M. Sunday, in the Red Room of the La Salle Hotel.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0386.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The well known actor-manager, Henry Miller who is now playing the leading role of the drama "The Havoc", the author of this drama, Chas. S. Seldon, and the president of the Drama League of America, Mrs. A. Starr Best, will introduce Mr. Isidor Berger, the violinist and the gifted singer, Mrs. Fred Kaufman, who will complete this musical program.</p>
   <p>The Jews of the Douglas Park neighborhood will have the pleasure of hearing the great Cantor, Bernard Waldowsky, and his choir who will perform the services this evening and tomorrow morning at the Sha'areh Torah Synagogue, Sawyer Ave. and 13th St. Because of Cantor Waldowsky's popularity, we expect the Jews of Chicago to turn out in masses to hear him. It is seldom that you have the opportunity of hearing the great Cantor and his choir and in addition you will perform a charitable deed, for the proceeds from these services will be given to the Denver Jewish Consumptive Sanitarium.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0387.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Geo. K. Rosenzweig will be the main speaker at the meeting of Sha'areh Tfilah Synagogue, 1105 S. Paulina St. Mr. M. Abraham will lecture at this meeting on the subject "The Jewish Heroes."</p>
   <p>The Vilno Aid Society recently decided to lower the price of admission to new members. This will no doubt increase the membership and improve activities. The Aid Society is calling a mass meeting Sunday evening at Lessing Club House, 1208 W. Taylor St. where we expect a few speakers who will explain matters of importance to the Aid Society.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, Dec. 17th, at the West Side Auditorium, a most interesting event will take place. That is the 2nd annual Oriental Ball of the Poale Zions (Workers of Zion). This year's ball will without a doubt surpass the one we had last year. We will present live pictures of Jewish history which will be the main feature of this affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
