<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-08-04">August, 4, 1894</date>. p.442.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-08-04">August, 4, 1894</date>. p.442.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Articles of incorporation have been granted by the Secretary of State to the Jewish Orphan Society. The incorporators are Henry L. Frank, Dr. Hirsch and Julius Rosenthal. The formation of the society effects the legal establishment of a private charity that has been the source of considerable good in reclaiming homeless Jewish children in this city.</p>
   <p>The charity has up to the present been known as the Elise Frank Orphan Fund. The purpose in transposing the institution from a private to a public organization is to enlarge the scope of its work and increase the endowment. Some years age Mrs. Frank gave $30,000 for the purpose of ameliorating the condition of the Jewish children of Chicago. The money was put in the care of trustees and the income from the fund was to be employed in finding homes for orphans and placing them in positions of comfort.</p>
   <p>The merits of the plan became apparent and many philanthropic Jews were enlisted among the sympathizers of the project. Gradually the original <pb facs="5423972_6_1673.jpg" n="2"/>sum of $30,000 grew and each additional donation made it more imperative to arrange the affairs of the fund to invite more public bequests. This need resulted in the incorporation last week.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Elise Frank, to whose generosity the Jewish Orphan Society owes its existence, was an old resident of Chicago. Her fortune was a large one and her gifts to the hospital and poor were many. She was one of the chief heirs of Michael Reese's property and her real estate holdings in this city alone were estemated at $300,000. She died Nov. 6, 1893, at the age of eighty. Her will detailed bequests amounting to $1,800,000. The Michael Reese Hospital, the United Charities and the orphans fund were among the beneficiaries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
