<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-17">Aug. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Federation Banks</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0762</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0762.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-17">Aug. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE FEDERATION BANKS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order to satisfy the small contributors who cannot afford to give a few dollars in a lump sum to charity and yet want to cooperate with the Jewish community in supporting its needy, the Federation determined to distribute Federation banks to these contributors.</p>
   <p>However, they, who think that these Federation banks will be similar to the former charity boxes, which were controlled by irresponsible men, are badly mistaken. The Federation system of banks will be consistent with its regular policy, i. e., whatever anyone donates towards charity will go for charitable purposes only, and not for collectors or side expenses. A system was inaugurated whereby each cent thrown into the banks will reach the treasurer of the Federation and every bank holder will get a receipt and will be considered a subscriber to the Federation.</p>
   <p>The Federation has, until now, proved that it can operate in such a manner that the costs of collecting and distributing charity funds are only four per cent, <pb facs="5423972_6_0763.jpg" n="2"/>whereas, prior to the Federation's existence the costs were from thirty to sixty per cent.</p>
   <p>When the system of federation banks will be introduced the expenses of the Federation will certainly be increased and that will lead to the widening of charity work. The Talmud Torahs must be multiplied; a new Hebrew Sheltering Home must be constructed, and these Federation banks will be the source from which all activities shall be financed. Every Chicago Jew will be able to be proud of the fact that he carried stone and cement to build this great charity temple.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
