<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>
      <date when="1895">Years 1895-1896</date>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0943</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0943.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>UNITED HEBREW RELIEF ASSOCIATION</title>
     <date when="1895">Years 1895-1896</date>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We began the year with a deficit of nearly $5.00. We ended it with a deficit of over $1,100. and we have kept it down to this, practically ceasing work in May last.</p>
   <p>There is little need to recount to you again our plans and methods. Do we give effective aid? Sometimes. Do we pauperize? To some extent. Can we do otherwise? We can when you will give us sufficient funds annually to do it with. We cannot when you cut us down to $26,000, of which $6,000 must be spent for administration and $2,300 is expended for transportation.</p>
   <p>The latter items show a marked decrease from last year and the year before, but it ought and it must be cut down to a few hundred dollars. For four years and more, we have been repeating this; other cities have adopted an absolute rule that they will not forward transients to other places or assist those sent to them without their consent. We must follow their example. This alone will not be enough cooperation between the Jewish charities of the country, but it is essential. Whether this can be accomplished only by a convention such as we suggested four years ago, or by letter, remains to be seen.</p>
   <p>Money alone, however, will never solve the problem of the poor. There is but one solution - personal service. Before the days of large cities, before the <pb facs="5423972_6_0944.jpg" n="2"/>aristocracy of wealth began to rule, the Jewish poor were not given only money, they were aided by advice, by friendship, by personal service. In our times this had died out to a considerable extent. A few years ago, however, a revival took place. Everyone wanted to be engaged in charity work. Was it but a fad? We hope not, but in this Jewish community at any rate, it has not developed as it should. There is very little personal service, very little friendly visiting among our poor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
