<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-21">April 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Great Work of the Associated Jewish Charities</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-04-21">April 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT WORK OF THE ASSOCIATED JEWISH CHARITIES</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Associated Jewish Charities was held last night at the Sherman Hotel with its seven newly elected directors and eight hundred members. The usual big banquet was in order during the meeting.</p>
   <p>According to the report of Mr. Julius Rosenwald, the president of the Associated Jewish Charities, the income was three hundred and ninety-five thousand dollars, and the expense of running the office and the collection of this fund was only five thousand, five hundred dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0835.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The pledges for next year have already reached the sum of four hundred and thirty thousand dollars. The sum of six million dollars was paid out for charity in the last six years.</p>
   <p>One hundred and ten thousand dollars was distributed on the West Side. Forty thousand dollars of this amount was given to widows and their children. Seventy-eight mothers with a total of 277 fatherless children received this benefit.</p>
   <p>The cost per year for each orphan last year at the South Side Orphans Home was $164.00 and the cost of an orphan who was kept in a private home was only $140.00, while the cost of a child being raised at its own mother's home was only $105.00 per year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0836.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One hundred and fifty thousand dollars was saved since the establishment of the Home Finding Society.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch urged the Association to establish a home for the Jewish feeble-minded, and a hospital for incurables and consumptives.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
