<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-16">May 16, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-16">May 16, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Facts and Thoughts. (Local Column).</p>
   <p>The Jewish Fellowship Club.</p>
   <p>It is indeed very fine when young educated, professional Jews assemble to discuss and exchange thoughts on questions of a general Jewish nature. We can even condone the fact that the group has assumed a name similar to that of an Irish group of a similar nature. It is no crime for people not to be original. It is only regretful that the cream of Jewish culture must also imitate.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Fellowship Club assembles each Saturday afternoon in one of the Loop restaurants, to have dinner and carry on their discussions. We think that it is bad enough that this sort of thing takes place on the Sabbath, let alone the fact that this restaurant does not carry "Kosher" food. This in view of the fact that the group purports to be a Jewish group dealing with Jewish problems.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0395.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Certainly the Irish Fellowship Club, whom the Jews in this instance are imitating, would not eat meat during Lent. Must our Jews eat non-Kosher food even when meeting as a Jewish Group?</p>
   <p>Good-Bye - and Regret It Not.</p>
   <p>The writer of this column has the pleasure of speaking to the Chicago Jewish public, through this column, for the past six years. Under various pseudonyms he has expressed his views, and various topics of the day. Now because of other pressing personal business, I will discontinue giving opinions where they are not wanted. In these six years, I have expressed many opinions with which you have disagreed, but these opinions were honest convictions and therefore I have naught to excuse myself for.</p>
   <p>I must express my thanks to the publisher of this paper, in that at no time, did he attempt to control my utterances. I have given my best to these columns and I think I was not found wanting.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Aleph.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
