<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-23">June 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Where Can We Get Fathers?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-06-23">June 23, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE CAN WE GET FATHERS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plan by the Admission Committee, that all children 14 years of age now in the Marks Nathan Orphan Asylum, should step out of the guidance of the Home and be transferred to the Home Finding Society, sounds good theoretically, but can not work, in practice, as the Admission Committee thinks.</p>
   <p>One of the chief principles which justifies the existence of the Marks Nathan Orphan Asylum is the orthodox character of the institution, and with all the respect that we can have for the Home Finding Society, it is still not conducted in an orthodox manner, and the idea of recruiting children for the society from the Marks Nathan Orphanage is certainly not in harmony with the desire of the great masses who contribute to and support the orphan home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The list of those waiting to be accepted in the Marks Nathan Home, who are now refused admittance by the Board of Directors' contract with certain persons specifying that the number of orphans should not exceed 225, contains children whose parents will approve this decree, and the well meaning people, can have more work than they can attend, if they will only take care of the children who have not even entered the home.</p>
   <p>Why should the children, who have received a certain degree of orthodox training, be torn away from their surroundings, from their customs and from everything which they have been taught to hold sacred and dear?</p>
   <p>The claim is that a contract was made and must be lived up to. The contract reads that the Admission Committee, composed of these members of the Board of Directors and three from some where else, has the full right to reject applications and exclude children regardless of the approval of the directors. If this is true who granted permission to the contract makers to sign such stipulations? Who can undertake to act like that with the welfare of the orphans?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1613.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Board of Directors is authorized, by those who support the home to rear the orphans and exert all efforts to make them men and Jews, but the Board is not authorized to turn the orphan home into a recruiting station for the Home Finding Society.</p>
   <p>The framing of such a contract was, in principle, un-Jewish and un-manly. Children are not nations, which can be designed according to a model. Every child is a world in himself as parents with children know well. One child becomes mature and competent at the age of thirteen while another must still cling to his mother's apron at the age of sixteen.</p>
   <p>The issuance of an order, specifying that children of a certain age should go out to earn a livelihood for themselves, shows that the orphans' guardians, regardless of how devoted they are to their work, are still far from being fathers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1614.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What the Marks Nathan Orphanage should have is fathers who should not practice their theoretical ideas, but should allow the children to grow up as Jews and men in the home, which was built for them by Chicago Jewry.</p>
   <p>The Marks Nathan Home can, itself, be compared to an orphan - parentless. Everyone thinks that it should be run as he sees fit. Poor orphans, poor Marks Nathan Orphanage!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
