<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1928">1928</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1928">1928</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Camp Chi.</p>
   <p>Returning to Camp Chi, we note that of the 551 girl campers, 368 were under the age of sixteen, seventy-nine between sixteen and eighteen, and 104 over eighteen years of age. Of this number 147 represented full or partial scholarships. The agencies with whom we cooperated in this regard were the Jewish Home Finding Society, the Jewish Social Service Bureau, the Jewish Tuberculosis Society, the Michael Reese Dispensary, the Marks Nathan Orphans Home, and others who came to the desk, and applied for scholarships. In other words about one-third of the camp represented the group that either paid only a small portion of the actual cost or were offered camping privileges entirely without cost. In spite of this situation the camp was practically self supporting; that is due to the contributions toward this Scholarship Fund made by the Institute Women's Club. We should have a larger scholarship fund to draw from in order that we may be able to serve a still larger number of applicants for scholarship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With the exceptions of minor additions to camp facilities there have been no changes made during the past year. We are, however, hoping that through some means or another we shall be fortunate enough to secure a Nature Study Museum and Workshop Cabin. We have felt the lack of this equipment considerably. It should take not over $1,500 to build such a shack. So far, everything that we have immediately hoped for, and that was a distince necessity, came forward. Let us hope, in this instance, that our wish may come true the following season.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
