<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Progressive Order of the West</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0686</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0686.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Forward</title>,
<date when="1919-05-25">May 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROGRESSIVE ORDER OF THE WEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the following article, in which we discuss the Progressive Order of the West, it is unnecessary to dwell upon details, upon the activities of the Order during the past years of its existence; it is sufficient to give an account of its present activities.</p>
   <p>The Progressive Order of the West is the most modern fraternal order in America. The statistics of the Order show its progress. Its gain in membership proves that every Jew has confidence in the Order. Let us take into consideration the year 1919, which is one of the most difficult years for lodges in America. It is a war year and a year of epidemics. A great many members of the Order of the West are enlisted in the Army, and a considerable number have fallen victims to disease. It was almost impossible to secure new members; in fact, the Order was doubtful as to whether it would have any members left. But because of the spirit of our members, our membership has increased from 18,000 in 1918 to a total of 22,000 in May, 1919. The Progressive Order of the West <pb facs="5423972_6_0687.jpg" n="2"/>grows because of its liberalness. It takes part in all Jewish activities; it regularly pays a large sum to the Denver Sanitarium, to the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society, to the Jewish National Fund, and to all other Jewish institutions.</p>
   <p>The benefits of the Order are many--disability to man or woman $500; death benefits $500 and $50 more for funeral expenses. There are also many other large benefits.</p>
   <p>You owe it to yourself and to your family to become a member of this, the outstanding Order of America. The only Order to which every Jew should belong is the Progressive Order of the West.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
