<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">February 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago - Winfield Tuberculosis Sanitarium to Be Dedicated</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-02-06">February 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO - WINFIELD TUBERCULOSIS SANITARIUM TO BE DEDICATED</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new charitable institution for the treatment of Chicago sufferers from tuberculosis, which has been in course of preparation, will be dedicated on Sunday, February 7th. It will be conducted along scientific lines, and its course of treatment will include the most up-to-date ideas. The new enterprise has been launched by several prominent Jewish clubwomen who have been planning this institution for the last year.</p>
   <p>Their plans and hope have been finally realized through the generosity of Mr. Charles A. Stonehill, who purchased a fine estate at Winfield, Illinois, thirty miles from Chicago on the Northwestern road and gave it to the public for a tuberculosis sanitarium.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This estate covers seventeen acres of ground, and has a beautiful modern building on the crest of a hill overlooking the Du Page river. A fine vegetable garden, a fruit orchard and a number of chicken houses are also the features of the estate.</p>
   <p>The sanitarium will be managed by a board of directors, and it is planned to have it furnished and maintained by private donations and subscriptions. The organizations interested in this sanitarium are the Baron Hirschs' Women's Club, the Jewish Consumptive Relief Society, and the Willing Workers. The Baron Hirschs' Women's Club has paid for remodeling the building and improving the ground. It has also furnished Rest Cottage, a five-room building to be used for directors' meeting and for the visitors. The Baron Hirschs' will also contribute $2,500 for maintenance. The Jewish Consumptives <pb facs="5423972_6_1401.jpg" n="3"/>Relief Society will endow and furnish a shack and will contribute $1,000 for maintenance. The Willing workers will also build a shack and subscribe 8500 a year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
