<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1884">Year 1884-85</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>United Hebrew Relief Association</title>,
<date when="1884">Year 1884-85</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>Of three thousand, eight hundred and fifty applicants in the fiscal year, 1884-85, one thousand, two hundred and sixty-seven have received assistance at our office; one thousand, one hundred and fifty-four residents and one hundred and thirteen strangers, showing an increase in the number of both applicants and recipients over those of the previous year. Fifty-five residents and fifty-two strangers were granted transportation to other cities or countries, at an expense of $734.60. Nearly half of this sum was expended on strangers, who with the amounts received in cash, caused a total outlay of $466.10.</p>
   <p>This figure does not vary much from that of the previous year. Only a constant struggle against pretenders made it possible tokeep it within these limits. Seven residents were sent back to Europe, and in each case, we, in conjunction with other societies of this city, paid the expenses to their respective destinations. Of the residents assisted, one hundred and fifty-seven were new cases.</p>
   <p>The list of monthly pensioners was reduced from twenty five to thirteen, due to the following causes:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1044.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Seven became self-supporting; two died; two are supported by the society for the Education of Jewish Orphans in Chicago; and one was sent to the Montefiore Home. The present cheap rates of transportation, $100 from New York to Chicago, induced many of our people to send their savings to poor relatives in order to enable them to come here. Many others are driven to emigration by the harsh treatment of Jews in Russia. All these causes combined have brought and are bringing large numbers of poor immigrants to this country.</p>
   <p>Recent occurrences have shown conclusively that the existing laws regulating immigration afford little or no protection, and even their stricter observance would make only a slight difference. The oppressed, who have yet some spirit left in them, will persist in seeking a refuge in this free and blessed country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
