<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-27">November 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle and its Task</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By M. Strausman</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1917-11-27">November 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY CENTRAL COMMITTEE OF THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE AND ITS TASK</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">By M. Strausman</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The position of the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle is not clear to several members. Of what does it consist? What is its task? I shall attempt, as much as possible, to give a brief survey of the miscellaneous activities and work of the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle.</p>
   <p>As is known, the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle in Chicago is composed of delegates from the Workmen's Circle branches in the following manner: There are exactly forty-four branches. Two delegates are annually elected from each branch and the committee is composed of eighty-eight delegates. These delegates are divided into various departments, for example, the Labor Lyceum department, Cemetery department, Educational department, etc. Every separate department represents a small but very active organization(in which the elected officials conduct regular meetings). On the whole, these departments are responsible to the City Central Committee, when a report must be given of their work and activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1094.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All these departments are discussed at the regular meetings of the City Central Committee. Several delegates present certain recommendations from their branches or complaints against the action of certain departments. All these matters are collectively discussed by the delegates and instructions are given to the various departments about their further activities. As may be seen, the branches of the Workmen's Circle are informed of the work and activities of the various departments by their delegates. Speaking of the activities of the various departments, I can not refrain from extending credit for their good and noble work, to the Labor Lyceum Committee. They have made exceptional progress. Taking into consideration the war, which has cast a horrible gloom upon everybody, the Labor Lyceum Committee (naturally with the support of the branches) purchased a magnificent and suitable site. It is to be hoped that if the Labor Lyceum Committee will still receive the support of the branches, we can soon expect a temple for the Workmen's Circle in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The same can also be said about the Cemetery department, which is administered by an able committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1095.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Educational Committee did not encounter great success last year. There are, naturally, various reasons.</p>
   <p>The City Central Committee has a permanent control committee, that controls all money of the various departments and reports to the City Central Committee. The City Central Committee also plays an important role in community life. As a large and strong body, it is represented by its delegates at various conferences and undertakings in all branches of the Socialist and labor movement, which receives the fullest sympathy and support from the Workmen's Circle in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
