<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-10">Nov. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Junior Auxiliary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-10">Nov. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">JUNIOR AUXILIARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Junior Auxiliary of the Marks Nathan Orphan Home is one of the most interesting organizations in Chicago. It is an organization that has been steadily increasing in membership, in fact it has tripled its membership in the last twelve months. Organized eight years ago by a few active young men and women, the Auxiliary has steadily worked for the education and recreation of the children at the Home. Its activities in the past have all been on a large scale, but they have been successful. The social activities offered to its members and friends have been on a very high level. It has arranged dances, program meetings, and several big affairs, such as an annual dance, and the presentation of a musical comedy twice a year.</p>
   <p>The monthly dances and monthly program meetings, at intervals of two weeks (sic), are always attended by the largest and finest gathering of congenial, wholesome, sociable Jewish young men and women. The membership now numbers <pb facs="5423972_6_1548.jpg" n="2"/>about twelve hundred, and, if one can judge from the way in which applications are being turned in, the membership will probably reach the fifteen hundred mark by the end of the year.</p>
   <p>The proceeds from all affairs and activities of the Junior Auxiliary are turned over to the Home for use in the recreational activities, etc., of the children at the Home.</p>
   <p>The month of November is a gala month in the activities of the Junior Auxiliary, for some wonderful affairs have been arranged for this month. A delightful dancing party has been arranged for Sunday afternoon, November 14, at the beautiful Douglas Park Auditorium. There will be another dance on November 28.</p>
   <p>A gigantic program of the best musical entertainment, including many novelties, as well as classical and popular numbers--in short, a program that would cost three dollars in any loop show--will be given on Sunday afternoon, November 21, <pb facs="5423972_6_1549.jpg" n="3"/>in the Herzl School, Douglas Boulevard at Lawndale Avenue. Admission is free, and everybody is welcome.</p>
   <p>The biggest affair of the Junior Auxiliary will take place on Saturday night, November 27, at the Second Regiment Armory, Madison Street and Washtenaw Avenue. The occasion is the tenth annual reception and ball. A twenty-piece orchestra, under the direction of Jack Fredenberg, will play the most wonderful dance music. Those who attend are promised a memorable evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
