<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jottings</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L. M</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JOTTINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L. M</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the present economic stress and unemployment we find in Chicago two organizations competing with one another for the "privilege" of burying poor Jews who cannot afford the "pleasure" of paying for their burial. This competition often causes very unpleasant results. When a poor man dies and hasn't the money to pay for his funeral, the Gomley Chesed Shel Emes of the West Side sends the body to the Gomley Chesed Shel Emes of the North Side, and then back and forth. Sometimes several days elapse before the poor man or woman is finally brought to the last resting place.</p>
   <p>Why there should be two organizations of this kind in Chicago, no one seem to know. It may only be a question of officers. This one wants to be president, and there surely cannot be two presidents and two sets of officers when there is only one organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1130.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To make things worse the North Side organization is receiving a subsidy from the Chicago Jewish Charities, while the one on the West Side is operating on its own resources.</p>
   <p>There was a time when the latter organization was quite affluent and often arrogant, but now since the number of its members has considerably diminished, and there are no contributions permitted on the cemeteries, which was part of their income, they are in financial straits and are unable to take care of the demands on them for free burial and are obliged to make a charge. Whatever the case may be, it is absolutely unreasonable and uncalled for to have two charitable institutions competing with other and often fighting for "business."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
