<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-04-24">April 24, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[Patriots at Elections]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1891-04-24">April 24, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[PATRIOTS AT ELECTIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch spoke last week at theAda Street Methodist Church, on "Patriotism" . The building was packed to the utmost capacity with the regular members of the church and visitors from other congregations.</p>
   <p>Rev. Dr. Brushingham, Pastor of the church, introduced the speaker, and Dr. Hirsch was greeted with applause when he took the stand. In his address he said: "April is a fitting month for me to address you on the subject of patriotism, as that month recalls many heroic deeds. Thomas Jefferson was born in that month. It was in that month the first battle for liberty was fought by the American people, and the month has been marked by victory in the history of our country".</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0420.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"There are different kinds of patriotism; one is the kind which shows itself in making a loud noise, shouting and firing a cannon. But a true patriot must do more than march in torch-light processions and march to music. Patriotism is often silent but steadily at work. The true patriot does his duty without calling attention to it. Then there is the patriot for revenue and office. He has a disreputable character and it is too often observed. A nation is fortunate which has honest people for office seekers. One great reason given for refusal by business men to go into politics is that it hurts their business. Then some go into politics as a business. The only way to have an honest government is to have the offices so organized that the professional office-seekers will not want them because there will be no money for them. We are to blame for the state of politics. We do not attend the primaries and help nominate the men who would make good officers, but after this is done we generally hurry around and try to defeat somebody who should never have been given the chance to run for the position. The only way is to educate the foreigners and teach them the meaning of politics. Try to make them good earnest, understanding citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0421.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"There are professional foreigners who trade on their nationality for votes. You can set me down as saying that no Jew will ever vote for another Jew who runs for office by parading his race as the reason for trying to get it."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
