<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Kurlander [Aid Society] Celebrates</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE KURLANDER [AID SOCIETY] CELEBRATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today is a big day for the Kurlander Aid Society. It is celebrating its tenth anniversary with a banquet at the Lawndale Hall. About three hundred people will be there. Almost all will be people who come from towns and villages near the Baltic Sea: Riga, Libau, Tukums, Goldingen, Mitau, Boisk, Jacobstadt, Ilukst, Windau, Tolesno, and so on.</p>
   <p>The Kurlander Aid Society supports not only its own, dues-paying members but it also supports, out of its treasury, our charity institutions, Zionist campaigns, and the relief work that we have undertaken in behalf of the unfortunate Jews of Eastern Europe. Their celebration is, therefore, a celebration of the whole Jewish community of Chicago. It would be no more than right that the rabbis, the synagogue presidents, the Zionist and relief workers should be represented there.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0642.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From a small group of members, the Kurlander Aid Society has grown to be one of the most important in town. Each member of the Society pays thirty-five cents a month for [individual] dues, fifty cents a month for couples. The Society occasionally arranges affairs such as balls and picnics, the income from which is used for outside charity. Out of the dues, they help members of the Society who are in need and they pay two hundred dollars death benefit to the family of a deceased member.</p>
   <p>The Kurlander has given five thousand dollars for war relief; it contributed a nice sum of money to Palestine, and sends hundreds of dollars a year to the nurseries and other institutions. The members also give, individually, for all Jewish campaigns.</p>
   <p>This is the place to mention the names of the presidents of the society during the last ten years: S. Strauss, R. Orensberg, Reverend J. Taub, Max Goldman, Harry B. Kolp (deceased), M. W. Klaff (deceased), Harry Lipschultz, S. E. Neuberger, Louis Pearlman, Herman Magidson, and Harry Wippman. Among the present officers <pb facs="5423972_6_0643.jpg" n="3"/>are: Marcus Blumenthal, J. Lewis, S. Shulman, Oscar Elgenson, Dr. M. I. Kaplan, Max N. Block, J. Shulman, H. Wagner, J. Fedman. Leo Zaltzman, an intelligent young Jewish man, is secretary, and, one may say, the moving spirit of the Kurlander Aid Society.</p>
   <p>We would like to see a good Jewish representation at the Kurlander ball tonight in Lawndale Hall. Excellent speeches will be delivered. Good drinks and good food, including the national dishes of the Kurlander, will be served.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
