<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-06">October 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Melting Pot</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0840</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0840.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-06">October 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Melting Pot</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Young Mens Associated Jewish Charities will hold their annual meeting Wednesday night, at the Hotel La Salle, where a report will be given of all the work accomplished by their association through-out the year, and new officers and directors will be elected.</p>
   <p>The Nominating committee has already recommended as officers the following men: Abel Davis for President, Sol Klein, Vice President, Walter Greenbaum, Treasurer, Adolph S. Gordon for Secretary. For directors, Herbert Friedman, Milton A. Straus, S. Myer, Arthur, M. Hurwitz, Dr. E. Klein, and Dr. Walter Hamburger.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that the West Side has not enough Culture Centers for the Jewish youth, and that the Christian Mission is opening reading rooms, and using other methods of attracting the Jewish youth, the Council of Jewish Women have, therefore, sent out an appeal to all Jewish organizations and societies, for a fund of $1,500, to be used for reading rooms and Sabbath schools on the West Side.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0841.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Council appropriated the first $100 and several societies have pledged themselves with smaller donations, but the pledges have not yet been collected, and they are appealing to the rest of the organizations to contribute toward a bigger fund.</p>
   <p>The pledges may be sent to Mrs. Benjamin Davis 437 E. 43rd Place, who is the chairman of this committee.</p>
   <p>With the small donations thus collected, the committee has succeeded in opening a Sunday school-room for girls in the Talmud Torah.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
