<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-17">Mar. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Doctor Moss's Plans Concerning Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-17">Mar. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DOCTOR MOSS'S PLANS CONCERNING HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The medical staff of the Maimonides Hospital held a regular meeting on March 15, 1914, at 4 P.M.. Dr. H. J. Moss, new superintendent of the hospital, addressed the doctors to tell them of his plans in regard to the management of the hospital.</p>
   <p>The doctors were exceedingly pleased with Doctor Moss's plans, and everyone expressed his utmost confidence and promised to work hand in hand for the success of the only Jewish hospital in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A temporary committee of five was appointed, which consists of Doctor Richert, chairman, and Doctors Jacques, Freeher, Greenger, and Schraeger. The committee will draw up plans for improvements on the hospital and submit its report at the next meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1303.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Moss was welcomed with due respect and encouragement. For the four days in which the hospital has been under his supervision, much improvement is noticeable. Everything is run by a strong, disciplinarian hand. Ten patients were admitted, and a very successful operation was performed yesterday.</p>
   <p>In an interview with a Courier's reporter last evening, Doctor Moss revealed interesting facts about his plans and about the impression the hospital has made upon him. "I have found everything in good order, except for a few things which can stand improvement," said the new superintendent. "The hospital is equipped with the most modern, scientific devices.</p>
   <p>"I think the staff consists of competent and suitable men in the profession, and a great deal can be expected from them, not only in matters pertaining to the hospital proper, but also in contributions to medical science."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1304.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He did not have much to say about the internes' and nurses' staffs. Nevertheless, he stated that these staffs will soon be reorganized. Both the internes and nurses will have to undergo examinations.</p>
   <p>"In a week or so," continued Doctor Moss, "I expect from New York one of the most capable directors in the country for the nurses' division. She is Mrs. Fannie Gershon, a Jewish woman, who has distinguished herself in Mt. Sinai Hospital, New York, for her services."</p>
   <p>As to the financial condition, Doctor Moss said that the hospital will be laid on a basis such as will reduce the expenses and at the same time yield better results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
