<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-09-05">September 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Jewry Agog on Eve of Inter-Seminary Debate</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-09-05">September 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO JEWRY AGOG ON EVE OF INTER-SEMINARY DEBATE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day of the great inter-seminary debate is drawing near! And judging by the profound interest shown by the Jewish community of Chicago in this debate, it promises to be one of the most unique events in the history of orthodox Jewry in America, for it must be remembered that the debate between the Hebrew Theological College of Chicago and the Isaac Elchanan Theological Seminary of New York has the distinction of being the first verbal combat between two Talmudic institutions. Formerly, the Yeshiva has been considered as a place where young men confine themselves to Talmudic studies only.</p>
   <p>The American Yeshiva, however, has trodden new paths, which will probably decide the future of orthodoxy in America. Our revolutionary age, with its new demands and complex problems, has compelled traditional Judaism to seek a solution to these phenomena, in order to bring about a reconciliation between its traditions and the currents of modern thought.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Hence, American Orthodox Jewry is proud, today, in having the two flourishing Talmudic institutions, the Hebrew Theological College of Chicago and the Isaac Elchanan Theological Seminary of New York, which have been justly compared to Sura and Pumbeditha of old. The work that they have accomplished during the comparatively brief period of their existence is stupendous.</p>
   <p>Now they have proceeded a step further and challenged American Jewry to witness this intellectual combat, which has taken the place of the Tannaitic and Amoraitic dialectics.</p>
   <p>The debate will take place on September 7, 1927; 8 P. M., in the magnificent auditorium of the New Jewish People's Institute, on the corner of Douglas Boulevard and St. Louis Avenue, opposite the building of the Hebrew Theological College. The subject to be debated is : "Resolved, that the Parochial School System is the sole solution to the problem for permanency of traditional Judaism in America."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The team of the Hebrew Theological College, which will uphold the negative side of the question is composed (in the respective order of their speaking) of Rabbi H. Miller, Solomon Perlman and Meir Simchak Ostrinsky. The New York team, which will defend the affirmative is composed of, Israel H. Weisfeld, H. Berman and Morris Max.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
