<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-12">Feb. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Our Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, Principal of a Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-12">Feb. 12, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Moses Levin, Principal of a Talmud Torah</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We believe that the method of gaining the confidence of a child, so that the teacher will be considered as a friend, guide, and guardian, is as follows: It is wise and good for a teacher to amuse and entertain a beginner in a Hebrew school in a sociable manner, to show him pictures and acquaint him with their Hebrew names, to permit him to move about freely, and, at the same time, to teach the child Hebrew. Under no circumstances should the Hebrew school be turned into a prison. The child must find some attraction in the Hebrew school which will give him pleasure. It isn't very sensible to give the young child who can hardly connect the letters of a word together a prayer book and command him to read.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that a child in first grade cannot read a third-grade reader, and that a child in the third grade is unable to understand a seventh-grade reader. Shakespeare's works are taught in high school and college for <pb facs="5423972_6_0062.jpg" n="2"/>the first time. Is our prayer book, which contains prose and poetry, any easier? Yet it is given as reading material to a small child after he learns the alphabet. Would it not be proper for the teacher to reconsider his technique and employ a more simplified method whereby he can attain the same purpose more easily.</p>
   <p>The teacher need not walk blindly in his way. Let him consider the suggestions of nature, and observe those things which the child likes best--with which he is most familiar. Why not teach the child, at first, words known to him: household words and names of animals which he sees, understands and can conceive of in his mind. After he has mastered this step give him enough small, easy sentences so that he will be able to understand a short story in Hebrew. Select easy Hebrew books for children which are attractive and interesting and let the child read them. Do not give him a prayer book or the Pentateuch until he knows how to read. Prayers should also be taught after the child is able to read. As far as the actual study of the Pentateuch is concerned, notwithstanding how dear, sacred, and precious we consider it and how eager we are to have our children <pb facs="5423972_6_0063.jpg" n="3"/>study it, it should not be taught to children before they are adequately prepared. After a child has acquired a sufficient knowledge of Hebrew, he can then be taught the Pentateuch.</p>
   <p>The teacher should remember, above all other things, that he is dealing with children who possess different backgrounds and abilities. There are always exceptional students which the good teacher can pick out from among his class. The children should be treated in a mild and friendly manner. To scold and spank children is an antiquated method of discipline. Children can be taught valuable habits only by using humane methods.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
