<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-23">October 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Answer as Jews</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0103</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0103.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-23">October 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Answer as Jews</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday, Mr. Weiss, the new President of the Talmud Torah, appealed to the Jewish people of Chicago, to help him in expanding and improving the Talmud Torah, in order to make the courses more interesting for the children, as well as to provide adequate, comfortable class rooms, and good teachers, who thoroughly understand their trade. In order to accomplish all this, the new administration wants to build a new, all-modern Talmud Torah, with all conveniences.</p>
   <p>An undertaking such as this, the president realizes, cannot be carried out by the board of directors alone, as this project requires a great deal of money, which must be paid by the members of the community; therefore, I appeal to the people of this community to help me in this noble work, each according to his means. That the Chicago Jewish public will cooperate in this work is not in question.</p>
   <p>Among our sympathizers are the rich, with their donations, the strong with their energy, and the wise with their ideas. If all will work together, <pb facs="5423972_6_0104.jpg" n="2"/>this can be realized.</p>
   <p>The new board of directors are the best Jews of Chicago, who are always ready to give donations towards the building of Jewish institutions. This alone is sufficient assurance that a new modern Talmud Torah will be built in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
