<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-09-11">September 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Happy New Year</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-09-11">September 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A HAPPY NEW YEAR</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Daily Jewish Courier wishes to extend to all its readers, subscribers, advertisers, as well as all brethren of Israel a Happy &amp; Prosperous New Year.</p>
   <p>The last year was very satisfactory for the Chicago Jewry. The Jewish community began to feel its responsibility to Israel and commenced to organize accordingly.</p>
   <p>Our synagogues became much better organized. The rabbis' appealed to the people from their pulpits and exhorted them to take the road of righteousness and Judaism. Their sermons are so effective that the youth is drawn into the activities of the congregations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0821.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our charities have, through the past year, made pace - great pace forward. The Aged Home built an annex for the convenience of aged men and women. The Marks Nathan Home was not neglected in any way. A new edifice is being erected, which will accommodate many Jewish orphans.</p>
   <p>Our Hebrew Schools and Theological College are now in an excellent condition. They are discarding all antiquated systems and adopting modern methods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0822.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Maimonedes Kosher Hospital is no longer a dream, but a reality. The hospital building is already complete and ready to accommodate patients. The dedication of the hospital is merely delayed, because it wants to gather all elements together at one grand opening.</p>
   <p>The Hebrew Sheltering Home stepped out of its infancy last year. A new system and new methods will be applied next year and it is expected that this will be one of the finest institutions in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0823.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The main activity of the Chicago Jewish work was to unite the Jewish Orthodox Charities of Chicago. This movement, in which the finest Jews of Chicago are interested, shows how far the Chicago Jewry have progressed, how profoundly they understand their obligations. The movement of uniting the Jewish Orthodox Charities means a movement for liberating all charity institutions from financial worries, it means convenience for our aged; good rearing for our orphans; proper care for our sick; Jewish education for our children; food and shelter for our destitute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0824.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The organization of a united Jewish charity will lay the foundation to all problems that are connected with Jews and Judaism. It will drive dissoluteness and irresponsibility from the Jewish religious, social, and political life. It will establish a Jewish society in Chicago where the opinions of our leaders will be in close relation to the Jewish, as well as the non-Jewish, world.</p>
   <p>And when the time will come to write the Jewish history of Chicago, the past year will be a great chapter, because this movement started to develop that year (1911 - 1912).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
