<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-25">Mar. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">What Are the Fraternal Organizations Doing for the Keren Hayesod?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-25">Mar. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT ARE THE FRATERNAL ORGANIZATIONS DOING FOR THE KEREN HAYESOD?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What are the Jewish fraternal organizations doing for the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization]? The synagogues are doing something. They make at least an attempt to do something, and the probability is that they will be successful because they are taking their tasks seriously, and they work very hard to attain a certain goal; but the heads of the fraternal organizations have done next to nothing up till now. They have started to do things in the middle of the winter and they have laid out certain plans how to do it, but nothing has turned out, mainly because of lack of co-operation and co-ordination. There are a few among the leaders of the Jewish fraternal organizations who would like to do things right and who are ready to work for the cause, but some of them do not take their tasks seriously. They promise a whole lot and keep very little. This is especially true of the head of the Progressive Order of the West, who, although <pb facs="5423972_6_0607.jpg" n="2"/>a Zionist, cannot make up his mind to throw himself into the work wholeheartedly. The Progressive Order of the West is a solid and wealthy organization and consists of a good class of people, and if the leaders of the Progressive Order of the West would make up their mind to get some money for the Keren Hayesod from among the members of the Order or from among the lodges, they would certainly succeed because the membership is in such cases always ready to follow the lead of the grand officers, and the grand officers cannot be moved to do anything substantial. Inasmuch as the Progressive Order of the West is the leading fraternal organization of our people in the Middle West, its inactivity is also determining the attitude of the other fraternal organizations, and it is, therefore, harmful to the cause of the Keren Hayesod from a double point of view. We hate to appeal to the membership of the Order over the head of its leaders, but we are afraid that unless we get some action from the grand officers, we will have to appeal directly to the members of the Order, and the Keren Hayesod organization will have to make an attempt to get in touch with the membership of the Order without regard to the attitude of its leaders. It is true that the grand master of the Progressive Order of the West is a very busy man and is a great <pb facs="5423972_6_0608.jpg" n="3"/>deal out of town, but if he cannot do the work himself, it is at least his duty to delegate somebody else to do it, and this he hasn't done either; and as long as the leading Jewish fraternal organization of the Middle West is not active, we can scarcely hold out any hope for bringing the forces of the other fraternal organizations into motion, but we must reach the fraternal organizations because otherwise the Keren Hayesod will only reach the classes and not the masses. Our masses are organized in fraternal organizations, and if the Keren Hayesod is to become popular among our masses, we have to get the so-called lodge Jews to understand it and support it. Many attempts have been made to cause the heads of the various fraternal organizations to act, but only three of them, Dr. George Sultan, Mr. H. M. Barnett, and Mr. Shapiro, have promised their aid and have shown that they want to do real work. Mr. Sam Epstein has also promised to do work, but he has not lived up to his promise, although we know it to be a fact that he is a genuine Zionist and is dominated by Zionist ideals. We do not blame him for not being active himself. It may be that it is physically impossible for him to participate personally in the work, but we do blame him for not delegating somebody else to represent him and <pb facs="5423972_6_0609.jpg" n="4"/>to work for the Keren Hayesod in his behalf. We beg to remind Mr. Epstein of his manifold promises to work for the Keren Hayesod, to address the lodges of his Order for the Keren Hayesod, and to solicit funds for the Keren Hayesod. We think that he is in duty and in honor bound to do it, first because he is a Zionist, and then because he has made a solemn promise, and we warn him that by not living up to his promise he will do great harm to the Keren Hayesod, and that surely is not his intention. Or would he be glad to see the Keren Hayesod workers visiting the lodges of his Order for the Keren Hayesod without his guidance, leadership, and advice, in short would he like the Keren Hayesod leaders to appeal to his lodges over his head? If he is satisfied that this shall be done, then it will be done.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
