<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1880-10-01">October 1, 1880</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1880-10-01">October 1, 1880</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reese Hospital.</p>
   <p>On last Tuesday (Sept. 28) ground was broken and work commenced on the Reese Hospital, which will be located on the corner of 29th St. and Cottage Pl. The establishment will consist of an executive building in the center, and wings on each flank. It will be built of red pressed brick (upon a stone base constituting the cellar) with stone trimmings and a slate roof. The heating and ventilation of the entire building will be, according to the opinion of experts and physicians, the most perfect of the kind.</p>
   <p>The executive building will be three stories above the basement. The basement will contain a large dining room, a kitchen and pantries. On the first floor will be the main entrance, directors' and physicians' offices. Behind the offices will be a hall, running through the whole width of the building, with three private wards, and toilet rooms opening into it. On the second floor will be situated four private wards, bathrooms, operating room, medicated bath, inhaling room and library. On the third floor will be six private wards and bathrooms.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The wings will contain the general wards,for female patients in the right, and for male patients in the left wing. Each of the wings will be two stories high, with a ward on each floor; fourteen beds will be placed in each ward. There will also be situated on each floor, three private wards, a nurses' room, a toilet room, and a closet with ready access from the ward. The two flights of stairs in the building will be cut off from the halls with glass partitions, thus keeping the halls in the same temperature with the rooms. On each of the wings, facing the east, between the stairs and the corner-tower, will be a spacious veranda, commanding a full view of the lake.</p>
   <p>In the basement of the male department, the heater's, the engineer's and domestic rooms, and water closets, will be situated. In the basement of the female department there will be the physicians' room, waiting room, drug store, laboratory, three "strong wards" for unruly patients, store-rooms, water closets, etc. A cellar will run the entire building.</p>
   <p>Forty feet back of the executive department will be situated the laundry and the morgue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
