<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1913-12">December, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gymnasium.</p>
   <p>You have heard from the president's report the plan for the new gymnasium that is to be built shortly, on the grounds of the Institute. There were 944 boys and girls, men and women who registered in the department this year. This does not include over 200 women, mentioned in the early part of the report, who are members of the Department of English for Foreigners and are given instruction under the auspices of the Gymnasium Department. There was a total aggregate attendance of 17,281 during the year.</p>
   <p>For ages it has been the opinion that physical development of the young is highly essential. The Jew until lately has not actively taken to the development of the body. The Institute, however, has made wonderful progress in this work and has proven that when the Jewish boy is placed under instruction he in time surpasses his non-Jewish opponent. Our boys, in the various tournaments, carried off the most honors. During the last international gymnastic union wrestling tournament, the boys carried off thirteen individual medals from a total of thirty prizes with twelve different organizations competing, and won <pb facs="5423972_6_0473.jpg" n="2"/>two junior and senior team shields for the Institute. At the present time, we have 655 men and women, boys and girls under physical instruction. During the summer, a good part of the gymnasium work is done outdoors on the grounds. The tennis courts are in constant use from May to October. The hand-ball courts are likewise in use, with very little intermission. It is astonishing in the report submitted by the physical director of the summer work on the grounds, that the total number of accidents reported was eighteen; of this number none were serious.</p>
   <p>The April number of the Observer, which was devoted to the Athletic Department, gave so complete a report of the growth of our work, in the interest of the physical up-building, that it would be merely repeating what was so ably stated by the physical director and the chairman of the Athletic Department.</p>
   <p>I therefore respectively refer you to that number of the Observer for details.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
