<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-12">December, 1914</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-12">December, 1914</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Boys' Brotherhood Republic.</p>
   <p>The meeting of the Boys' Brotherhood Republic was of absorbing interest as well as a liberal education. The writer had looked in for a few minutes from curiosity, and remained to the end by choice. It was a literary meeting, and though the participants were boys, the topics considered and the manner of handling them were worthy of men. Boy after boy took his stand and kept the interest of the audience alive to the very end. If the Republic is meant to be miniature embodiment of our country, then the present citizens of the Republic will make the ideal citizens of the future. They will be citizens alive to all vital issues, the fault of mental indifference and sluggishness will not be theirs.</p>
   <p>Ten topics were treated at the meeting, all on a par as far as their importance and interest were concerned. Noticeably enough, the speakers favored <pb facs="5423972_6_0371.jpg" n="2"/>the humane, liberal side of their respective topics. The abolishment of Capital Punishment was advocated by one, while another denounced the Boy Scouts' movement as nursing the ideals of blind obedience and glory of war. Child Labor, one compared to the ancient practice of sacrificing to Moloch. The Reform School was condemned as a training school where hardened criminals are manufactured. No more flattering a stand was taken in the case of Orphan Asylums that turn out their inmates at sixteen, without any sure means of self-support. In the words of one, Preparation for War meant invitation to war, while still another glibly argued in favor of Prohibition. Peace at all cost was the next ardent plea. Moving Picture Censorship as a useless and even baneful institution ended an evening thus spent to very good advantage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
