<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-01-10">January 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The B'nai Brith Evening School</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1890-01-10">January 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE B'NAI BRITH EVENING SCHOOL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of many public institutions inaugurated by the Order is undoubtedly the above. The little stipend originally allowed in the convention of 1888 in this city amounting to four hundred dollars per annum, and increased to about six hundred dollars for 1889, is bearing fruit. The utility of this institution as is now observed proves to have been a great boon to the Russo-Polish citizens in the vicinity of Jefferson, Canal, Liberty, Wilson, Judd and 12th Streets, where these people are domiciled.</p>
   <p>The school at present has but meager facilities, being confined to only two departments and with only two teachers. It began with only fifty scholars, while at this writing its number has increased to one hundred and thirty pupils of both sexes.</p>
   <p>The branches taught are:- Reading, Writing, Arithmetic, English Grammar, and History of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0241.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The school is open during six evenings each week to wit: from 7 to 9 P. M. The expenditures during this year exceed the amount set apart in the last budget, the expense is eight hundred dollars which no doubt the convention will authorize. An able and interesting report has been prepared bythe chairman of the committee, Dr. B. Felsenthal, under whose guidance the school was organized.</p>
   <p>The principal rules insisted on in this school are that no Jargon languages shall be spoken; that the same discipline as in the public schools shall be employed. The teachers are Messrs. S. Knopfnagel and Jacob G. Grossberg, both able and intelligent teachers. The school is located at 71 Judd Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
