<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-09">Apr. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Daughters of Zion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_1489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-09">Apr. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE DAUGHTERS OF ZION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In 1922 unusual work was done toward the erection of the new Jewish infant home in Chicago.</p>
   <p>With the aid of our devoted workers of the Daughters of Zion Nursery and of the Infant Home Society, who had given their time and money for this noble purpose, it became possible for the building committee to close contracts with builders who had, in the course of six months, constructed the large edifice on Hirsch [Street] and California Avenue.</p>
   <p>According to a report from our finance chairlady, Mrs. Louis Katz, which was confirmed by a certified auditor, Mr. Andrew Quigley, our finances are as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1490.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand January 1, 1922</cell>
     <cell>$26,087.86</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Subscriptions and donations</cell>
     <cell>12,858.09</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Auxiliaries</cell>
     <cell>19,314.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Brick certificates</cell>
     <cell>8,320.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Tag day income</cell>
     <cell>2,186.97</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Concerts, theaters, dances, and picnics</cell>
     <cell>23,037.08</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>[?]</cell>
     <cell>65,716.19</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Income</cell>
     <cell>$91,804.05 (sic)</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Expenses</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Maintenance of nursery</cell>
     <cell>$18,024.96</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Material and labor</cell>
     <cell>94,956.11</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Expenses</cell>
     <cell>$125,490.37 (sic)</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1491.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Resources</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Foundation and lots</cell>
     <cell>$33,585.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Building, 1441 Wicker Park Avenue</cell>
     <cell>20,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Furniture and fixtures</cell>
     <cell>1,127.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Subscribers' debts</cell>
     <cell>15,743.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cash on hand and in banks</cell>
     <cell>667.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Material and labor</cell>
     <cell>94,956.11</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Resources</cell>
     <cell>$166,080.16</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Debts</cell>
     <cell>38,686.32</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Last year's income from auxiliaries:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Almer Sigel</cell>
     <cell>$4,302.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Logan Square</cell>
     <cell>3,952.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Central</cell>
     <cell>2,510.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Humboldt</cell>
     <cell>1,800.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Midwest</cell>
     <cell>1,500.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1492.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Rebecca Fox</cell>
     <cell>$2,600.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Wide Awake Worker</cell>
     <cell>400.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Albany Park</cell>
     <cell>400.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Junior Oak</cell>
     <cell>1,850.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total Income</cell>
     <cell>$19,314.05</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>I am proud of the chairmanship of Mrs. H. Steinberg. The number of children that we have had last year was too much for our present institution. Yet, it is merely a small fraction of the number of children who are waiting for admission. With aching hearts, we must defer those on the waiting list from time to time. Each case presents a great tragedy in the lives of the lonely orphans. We have more than 200 applications on our waiting list. Every child that we accept is investigated by our admission committee, and only the helpless and destitute children are admitted.</p>
   <p>With pride and joy, I can report that the children admitted to our small <pb facs="5423972_6_1493.jpg" n="5"/>institution, 1441 Wicker Park Avenue, are given a good home. They are given motherly attention, both physically and spiritually. They are reared in a typically Jewish atmosphere. Nowhere else can a happier and healthier group of children be found.</p>
   <p>We are also glad to report that our house has the best trained nurses who take care of the babies, and a competent physician, Dr. L. H. Block, who has been visiting the children daily for the last three years without any remuneration. A special thanks we owe to our superintendent, Mrs. W. Lewis, for her remarkable ability in keeping the nursery and the children in excellent condition.</p>
   <p>In the course of the last year, 1,871 children were admitted each month. The general number of admission was seventy children a day, or fifteen more than a year ago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1494.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Words are inadequate to express my respect and gratitude to Mrs. Charwey Rieger, founder and president of the Daughters of Zion Nursery, for her aid and support to the unfortunate infants in Chicago. May God grant her health, strength, and long life, so that she may live to see her wish fulfilled, and that is: To have a sanitary Jewish home for the Jewish orphans in Chicago. She has sacrificed her health and her own comforts for so many years, and had to overcome the many obstacles in her path. It is only through an act of God that she carried out her work.</p>
   <p>Due to the fact that the reports are so lengthy, I regret that I am unable to give an account of each officer and chairman of each committee separately. But I assure all workers that we are grateful to the officers of the auxiliaries for their good work last year. We owe a special thanks to the building committee for its successful work.</p>
   <p>At the present moment, we should like to make an appeal to the Chicago Jewry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_1495.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Our appeal cannot and must not be ignored. We are now campaigning for funds, so as to finish the inside work of the most beautiful and most indispensable institution in Illinois. We are now selling hospital rooms, and other "honorary" rooms, windows, and doors. By purchasing any of these honors, you will perpetuate your name in the beautiful temple on California Avenue.</p>
   <p>Remember, friends, that this is the only Jewish infant home in the Middle West. Everyone should at least have mercy upon the motherless infants who cannot help themselves, and who are subject to the compassion of the good, but busy public. Your subscription, large or small, will help our lonely infants.</p>
   <p>In behalf of all directors, I thank the Jewish public for what they have already done and for what they will continue to do for our home.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, permit me to express gratitude to the board of directors <pb facs="5423972_6_1496.jpg" n="8"/>for the services they have rendered last year for this sacred work, and it gives me honor, pride, and courage to be the presiding officer. It is certainly a great honor to work with a group of noble women who are in our society.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Mrs. Samuel Sigel</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
