<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Jewish Charities</title>,
<date when="1921-10-27">October 27, 1921</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Jewish Charities</title>,
<date when="1921-10-27">October 27, 1921</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of the Board, Louis M. Cahn in his report as Executive Director reported various costs in Home Finding budget and read extracts from case records illustrating the various types of demands made upon the resources of the Home Finding Society. He stated that the funds now given allow for 185 children to be boarded out and 500 to live with widowed mothers but at that time it was necessary to board out 198 and to take care of 540 with widowed mothers. The Home Finding has told the other Jewish Agencies that it cannot take on additionas cases, but this would badly obstruct the work of the other agencies and Mr. Cahn therefore feels that the Home Finding Society must handle emergency cases even if the deficit grows until the amounts to be expended are definitely fixed. He added that he is studying the advisability of placing the widowed mother cases which are really family cases under the Jewish Social Service Bureau, and having the Home Finding Society restricted to a children's bureau to take care of children who are without relatives.</p>
   <p>In regard to comparison of allowances, Mr. Cahn stated that the <pb facs="5423972_6_0649.jpg" n="2"/>United Charities used the Nesbit budget just as the A. J. C. but that it is impossible to obtain definite data from the Catholic Charities although he believes they are below the Nesbit budget. He added that in cities where there are community chests it is recognized that the Jewish families because of mode of living and kosher diet need more money than non-Jewish families, and they are given more money. Mr. Cahn stated that the overhead expense of the Home Finding Society, approximately $40,000 a year can be greatly lowered by the transfer of family cases as recommended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
