<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-06-06">June 6, 1920</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_6_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-25">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-06-06">June 6, 1920</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish Life in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The slack season is on now at the Chevra Gomel Chesed Shel Emes (The Pauper's Field Society). For the last five years immigration has almost come to a standstill with a consequent decrease in the number of poor Jewish people in Chicago. The poor homeless Jews who came here about five years ago became a lettle richer and are no longer wanderers. They are earning more, they have established homes and have joined lodges and societies, workmens circle and synagogues, which furnish burials for their members. This has caused a decline in the activities of the Paupers Field Society.</p>
   <p>This slack causes the Paupers Field Society to become rich as funds are raised and not expended. This is the only Chicago orthodox Jewish institution with a rich treasury. It was organized when Chicago had only a handful of orthodox Jews. At that time there were no organizations aside from a few synagogues. It happened that a poor man died, and since there were <pb facs="5423972_6_0658.jpg" n="2"/>no friends or relatives to bury him, a few Jews assembled and each paid a share and buried the body, and shortly thereafter organized this Paupers Field Society. About ten years ago, a federation of all the orthodox institutions was organized, and the Paupers Field Society was the last to join this federation and one of the first to leave. What is the reason?</p>
   <p>Mr. Paul Witkauski who was president of the Paupers Field Society for eleven years says, "We came into the federation with capital, because the federation was about ready to dissolve. We were ready to do anything to save them, but they tried to leave the whole burden for us to carry and in addition they wanted us to collect all the funds necessary to keep up Paupers Field Society. This created a comical situation. We lost our independence, and, as before, had to go out by ourselves and collect all our money; therefore we dropped out of the federation. We started out, enthusiastically collecting funds and saving them. Then we beautified our cemetery."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_6_0659.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Rosenblatt, active in the federation, states, "The reason the Paupers Field Society withdrew from the federation was because they refused to submit the financial records to the federation, which is in accordance with the federation's rules. Any institution joining the federation must turn over their financial records to them so that the federation will know these records in order to install a modern financial system. We must know how much money is needed in order to know how much money we need to raise each year."</p>
   <p>The Paupers Field Society has $15,000in cash. They have an income of $11,000 yearly. Of this, one-half comen in through collectors and the other half through appeals at funerals or the cemetery and from appeals at lodges and synagogues.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
