<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Power of the Printed Word</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE POWER OF THE PRINTED WORD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Looking around through the Russian colony in Chicago one finds poverty of mind and spirit everywhere. No books. No newspapers. Only one road is wide-open--and that to the saloon.</p>
   <p>All Russian individuals and organizations who have worked for the welfare and the uplift of the Russian masses have often been ignored and ridiculed. Those who know agree that it is extremely difficult to work among the Russians in America. In the Russian jungle in America conditions are even more nauseating than among native Americans.</p>
   <p>But as difficult and meager of results as this uplift work actually is, it is not nearly as difficult as the work of the Russian press, not only in the United States, but everywhere in the world where there are Russians. The Russian writers and journalists in this country are the connecting links between the Russian group in America and the great outside world. We must <pb facs="5423967_2_1580.jpg" n="2"/>wonder at their surprising patience and their capacity to bear the suffering and martyrdom which seem to be a part of their profession. Their economic needs and their love of the printed word are no doubt responsible for their continued efforts, and as a matter of fact, for the existence of the Russian press in America. Through the medium of that press they share their thoughts, all their mental and intellectual possessions, with the Russian masses.</p>
   <p>Those Russian newspapers whose first and foremost consideration is financial gain have a much easier road to travel, because their only worry is how to squeeze money out of the reader or the advertiser. The newspaper whose chief aim is to deliver repeated jolts to the readers making them to forge ahead to knowledge, happiness, and a better life, usually overlooks or neglects the pecuniary aspect of the publication, and as a result the paper suffers many setbacks. Rassviet belongs to the latter group of publications. It is not difficult, therefore, to understand and appreciate the sacrifices made on the altar of the Russian cause in America by the staff of Rassviet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1581.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Ten years in the life of a newspaper is not a long time. In the case of Rassviet, however, ten years is a long time because these ten years have been devoted to a constant struggle for existence; the years have been filled with strife, with breath-taking battles with the enemies, with victories and defeats. The amount of mental strain, energy, and nervous tension expended during these ten years by the men behind Rassviet is known only to them. No one can truly ascertain the amount of work accomplished by these workers with the aid of the pen, the typewriter, the linotype, the press, and any other machine, including the functions of the delivery branch of this publication. Nor would it be possible to approximate the thought that went into their work during this ten-year period.</p>
   <p>The greatest value of Rassviet's ten years of work lies in the fact that it has taught many people how to think. Thousands of others have been taught what to think. Still others have been shown the way to higher accomplishments.</p>
   <p>Throughout its entire existence Rassviet has always been true to the slogan <pb facs="5423967_2_1582.jpg" n="4"/>incorporated in the very name of the publication: Rassviet (The Dawn). Slowly, after having encountered many obstacles and setbacks, the dawn, as conceived and first brought forth by Rassviet, is now spreading farther and disseminating more truth. Its light disperses the clouds of darkness which still linger in the minds of the Russian people. When, as a result of the great work of Rassviet the "dawn" finds its permanent place in the minds and hearts of the Russian people, life will be a sweet experience brightened by the rays of knowledge and understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
