<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-11-02">Nov. 2, 1905</date> p. 2-4
<title level="a">Sympathy for Russ Rebels. Chicagoans Indorse Revolution and Congratulate Leaders.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-11-02">Nov. 2, 1905</date> p. 2-4
<title level="a">SYMPATHY FOR RUSS REBELS. CHICAGOANS INDORSE REVOLUTION AND CONGRATULATE LEADERS.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Russia's dawning freedom was the theme of speakers who addressed a mass meeting under the auspices of the Russian Social Democratic party and the Chicago branch of the bund, in Apollo Hall, 256 Blue Island Ave. last night. Five hundred former subjects of the Czar were present.</p>
   <p>Resolutions of sympathy with the revolutionists of Russia were adopted, as follows:</p>
   <p>Whereas: The Russian despotic government is the bulwark of all the reactionary forces of the world and the foes of civilization; and</p>
   <p>Whereas: The defeat of Russians despotism will be a blow of reaction and oppression everywhere and an inspiration to all who are fighting for freer institutions and better conditions of life; and</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas: The defeat of Russian people led by the classconscious proletariat, are now engaged in a heoric struggle to wipe out of existance Russian autocracy - the last vestige of feudalism - which is a disgrace to our so much vaunted 20th century; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we extend our sympathy and congratulations to our heroic comrades who have so bravely raised the banner of revolution, determined to obtain liberty or die fighting for it; and be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we pledge our moral and financial aid to our Russian Comrades in their heoric struggle for Russia's freedom.</p>
   <p>The speakers were Dr. A. J. Dubin; Charles H. Kerr, and Peter Sissman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
