<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">1924--December 8--1934</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">1924--DECEMBER 8--1934</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today marks the tenth year since the publication of the first issue of Rassviet. This is but a short period of time in the long process of history, but it is quite a long time in the life of a small, progressive newspaper. Forward-looking, progressive publications like Rassviet usually die early as a result of too many obstacles in their path.</p>
   <p>Rassviet has emerged the winner after its first decade of hard fighting for the ideals and principles we cherish in this freedom-loving country, the ideals constantly threatened by dark forces of destruction and anarchy. If we have been able to pull through the most severe industrial crisis this country has ever known, we will undoubtedly survive, especially now that the economic depression has abated somewhat. We can say now with all certainty that our future is assured.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1576.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today's anniversary issue of Rassviet, containing sixteen pages of interesting and enlightening articles, gives a clear answer to the question of how it was possible for Rassviet to stand erect, to fight, and to win its first ten-year battle for its existence and success. These articles reflect, mirror-like, the friendly attitude toward this newspaper on the part of the more progressive and freedom-loving portion of the Russian colony in Chicago and elsewhere. Throughout all these articles, one single thought, one idea, stands out and is constantly emphasized: that Rassviet is the only Russian newspaper in the United States which truly represents the views and convictions of the Russian group as a whole, and that it alone serves the interests both of the organized groups and societies and of the unorganized part of the Russian population of this country, defending them against the attacks of all their enemies. These are the reasons why Rassviet has been able to live through these ten hard years, and why it will be able to continue so long as there are Russian immigrants living in this country.</p>
   <p>This newspaper has many friends among its readers and among Russian organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1577.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Its friends and supporters are spread all over the United States, Canada, and all parts of the world. Even in enslaved Russia, we have some friends and readers of Rassviet. But they seldom see our newspaper, since it is not allowed in Russia by the Bolshevik regime. We are, therefore, not surprised that the local Bolsheviks are conducting such a bitter fight, not against the capitalist press but against Rassviet. Their rage will know no bounds when, after seeing our big anniversary number, they realize that our work has brought splendid results, that Rassviet has led thousands of Russian people out of Bolshevik darkness and slavery into the light of knowledge and understanding, and that this newspaper's influence has saved many Russian organizations from utter ruin and destruction by the Bolshevik hooligans.</p>
   <p>We did not know until now how many friends we had, nor did we know the extent and the quality of their friendship toward this newspaper. Now, however, we know all our friends and the power of their friendship. The publishers, as well as the editors and all others connected with this newspaper, now know <pb facs="5423967_2_1578.jpg" n="4"/>and realize with great satisfaction the fact that they do not stand alone in their missionary work of spreading knowledge and true information among their countrymen in America. They find new comfort and a new incentive for further effort in the fact that their work is appreciated.</p>
   <p>We are happy to take this opportunity to express our sincere thanks and gratitude to our many friends, to the Russian organizations, and to our readers for their loyal support of our efforts during the first decade of our work. At this time, we also want to say that Rassviet and its publishers, encouraged by this new and overwhelming proof of friendship surrounding us on all sides, will exert still greater effort and energy in defending the interests of the Russian people in America and in fighting every evil which may threaten our well-being here in this country.</p>
   <p>Rassviet will now raise to an even greater height its banner proclaiming freedom, civilization, and justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
