<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-10">Feb. 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Abuse of Authority by Police</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-10">Feb. 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">ABUSE OF AUTHORITY BY POLICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several days ago the police authorities of the city of Los Angeles decided to forbid entrance into California to vagrants and generally to such people as have no money. With this purpose in view police details were dispatched to the borders of the State adjoining Oregon, Nevada, and Arizona; these details will search all trains coming into California and detain all undesirable persons. To those caught on the trains will be given the choice of going back to their own States or going to jail on the charge of vagrancy. Their finger-prints will be sent to the Criminal Investigation Bureau in Washington and to the police in Los Angeles for investigation of their criminal past, if any.</p>
   <p>Persons entering the State in automobiles and having no money to pay their way will not be arrested. To them all means of persuasion will be applied not to enter the forbidden State.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0895.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to telegraphic advices the border between California and Arizona has already been closed by the police against all undesirable citizens. The measures adopted by the police authorities in Los Angeles are of course, outside the pale of the existing laws and flagrantly violate citizens' rights. They are a clear abuse of the police power and as such should not be tolerated. Several members of the California State legislature and other prominent officials have already subjected the actions of the Los Angeles police to severe criticism.</p>
   <p>Thus, for instance, the Attorney General's assistant, Mr. Jesse Hession, has declared that he is very much in doubt about the legality of the measures adopted by the chief of police in Los Angeles.</p>
   <p>"A man's poverty," said he, "is not a valid reason for closing the doors of a State against him. The man can always insist on his constitutional rights and demand admission to the State."</p>
   <p>The chief of the State highway police declared that the authorities in Los Angeles <pb facs="5423967_2_0896.jpg" n="3"/>have no legal rights outside their own city limits. State Senator Scollan called the orders "outrageous" and declared that Los Angeles had "exceeded its own authority". In his opinion a man without money may be taken off a train, but he may not be hindered from proceeding into the State on foot or from riding into it in an automobile.</p>
   <p>Some of the members of the State legislature declared that the lower house had declined to act on the bill offered for consideration at the last session simply because the proposed measure meant closing the State borders to vagrants and moneyless men. The reason for the refusal to act was that the provisions of the bill, if adopted, would flagrantly violate constitutional guarantees and the citizen's right of personal freedom; in particular, they violate his right to freedom of movement and [to choice of] domicile.</p>
   <p>Governor Merriam declined to discuss the matter on the ground that officially he had not been advised about the action taken by the Los Angeles police.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0897.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The police authorities on their own behalf state that the police squads were sent to the borders because the majority of the vagrants and the destitute people, among whom there are many criminals, find their way to Los Angeles and stay there, becoming in a short time public charges.</p>
   <p>But such explanations and excuses do not hold water. It is not difficult to visualize a picture of American social and national life in which every State and large city in the Union should begin to act in imitation of the example of the police force of Los Angeles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
