<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-17">Mar. 17, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Capitalism and War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-17">Mar. 17, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITALISM AND WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a recent talk with a representative of the Scripps-Howard newspaper syndicate Stalin stated that the main cause of the war menace is capitalism.</p>
   <p>"Recall to your mind," declared Stalin, "how the last great war came about. The desire of a great power to remake the map of the World may also lead to the same consequences. There are states which are absolutely convinced that they did not get their proper share of the territories, markets, raw materials, and spheres of influence. Capitalism in its imperialistic phase considers war as a perfectly proper and legitimate means for settling all controversial matters of international scope."</p>
   <p>Commenting on this declaration, one of the Paris newspapers tells its readers <pb facs="5423967_2_0625.jpg" n="2"/>that "it would be very difficult for any man to say anything more foolish. Everywhere capitalism needs peace more than anything else. Young Japanese imperialists bent on war are certainly pursuing an anticapitalistic course. Russia, a country which, as it seems, it would be impossible to suspect of capitalistic learnings, is ready to come to Mongolia's assistance. The latest reforms introduced by Mussolini are directed against capitalism. Hitler himself does not profess any tender feelings toward capitalism either His nationalism has a socialistic background.</p>
   <p>"And yet capitalistic England is striving for peace. Capitalistic France also professes pacifist tendencies. Stalin, sitting shut off from the outside world within the walls of the Kremlin, obviously is not aware of anything that is going on now, and therefore he continues to repeat the old Marxian refrain, which was disproved by the facts in the most cruel way a long time ago."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0626.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One should take notice of one fact which was not mentioned by the Paris newspaper, namely: The Bolsheviks are ready to come to the assistance not only of Mongolia, which is actually in their hands, but also of capitalistic France, in conformity with the existing Franco-Soviet agreement of mutual military assistance. Stalin's declaration does not hold water for another reason also, namely, because wars were fought long before the time when capitalism, as it is understood by Marx's disciples, appeared on this earth.</p>
   <p>But Martists, whether of the Boleshevik or of the Menshevik school of thought, disregard facts. They try to find the roots of every evil in capitalism and at times in other forms of social order, entirely forgetting that the people themselves create and develop all forms of social organization. Even if we agreed with them on the point that capitalism is the cause of many social evils, still we should be tempted to ask them what other social system they intended to introduce instead of capitalism. If they want to replace it by the kind of socialism which at one time existed in Germany under the Social <pb facs="5423967_2_0627.jpg" n="4"/>Democratic government or by the variety of socialism which at present prevails in Russia, such forms of socialism instead of doing away with the existing social evils will only aggravate them.</p>
   <p>In order to convince foreigners that Bolshevik intentions are peaceful, Stalin made a declaration to the effect that the Bolshevik government has no intention of interfering with the domestic affairs of capitalist countries.</p>
   <p>"There are no grounds for the fear that the Soviet Union will resort to force for the purpose of imposing its own ways of life on the capitalistic countries. Of course the Soviets would be glad to observe a change in the order of things in other countries, but this change concerns chiefly the countries which are in need of such a change.</p>
   <p>"Our ideas cannot constitute any kind of menace for those who have firmly resolved to live under the regimes existing at present and prefer to live under <pb facs="5423967_2_0628.jpg" n="5"/>them. We have never aspired to stage a world revolution."</p>
   <p>However, this latter declaration is in sharp contradiction to the first. If capitalism is the cause of most social evils, if not of all, including wars and other calamities, the Bolsheviks quite logically should strive to remove the cause with the help of revolutionary action, which in itself is a sort of war. And it is no secret to anybody that they work day and night trying to fan the fires of a worldwide communist revolution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
