<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. III, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, III.
<title level="a">Russian Citizens of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. III, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, III.
<title level="a">Russian Citizens of Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, June 5, America will make the first steps toward joining the ranks of the fighters for the freedom of nations, against the military tyranny of the German Kaiser and his henchmen. On that day all young men from 21 to 30 years of age must register for future draft, to form the regiments, which will defend the ideals of free Russia and the democracy of the whole world. Which way does your heart incline? Whom do you favor? Recently, our Russian name in Chicago was disgraced by a group of Russian radicals, who stepped out publicly, agitating against war, advising not to register and, vilifying the name of the President of the glorious American Republic, because of the declaration of war to the Kaiser.</p>
   <p>Let us show the Americans, that we Russians, are in favor of the war; that we are glad that America has entered the war; that we greet them as our brothers, and are ready to go with them side by side. Come everyone of you <pb facs="5423967_2_0746.jpg" n="2"/>to the gigantic demonstration-parade on Tuesday, June 5th. The meeting will take place at Mr. Bobruk's hall, Union and 14th streets, from 8 to 12 A.M. The parade and the march with music will start at noon. Come everyone, who is against the Germans and for the allies, against tyranny and for freedom! Admission free.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Russian Patriotic Committee.</p>
   <p>(Note: Issued in 1917 or 1918, probably 1917, no date appears)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
