<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1927-09-28">Sep. 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Beginning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1927-09-28">Sep. 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A BEGINNING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Editorial concerning the celebration of anniversaries of great Russian writers and poets.)</p>
   <p>It is pointed out in this editorial that in the beginning of the autumnal season of 1927 the Chicago Russians have shown that they are very much alive. There had been already several well attended lectures and festivities, and many more have been announced. One of the Russian schools, that named in honor of Pushkin, had arranged a celebration in memory of A. N. Radishakev, one of the first protagonists of freedom and justice in Russia. The editor says that such a good example should be imitated. The church reveres the memory of the saints and has instituted celebrations of a religious character in their honor. Why should not the Russians in Chicago celebrate also the anniversaries of the most prominent Russian great men authors, poets, scientists, etc., such as V. Korolenko, N. Gogol, Hertzen, Kropotkin, Tshernyshevsky and others? Meanwhile only two such celebrations had been announced: <pb facs="5423967_2_1450.jpg" n="2"/>those in honor of Leo Tolstoy and S. Yesenin. Russia has given birth to so many great men that every Sunday during the year could be devoted to the celebration of some such anniversary. And the editor thinks that gathering for such a purpose and devoting some time to a friendly talk about some great personality would be, perhaps, the most pleasant and at the same time the most useful pastime and rest on holidays. He expresses the hope that the good example set by the Pushkin Memorial School, which arranged a celebration in honor of Radishchev, will be imitated by other Russian organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
