<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Zhizn</title>, Vol. V,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Telegram to President Wilson</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Zhizn (Russian Life)</title>, Vol. V,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A TELEGRAM TO PRESIDENT WILSON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting on May 1, 1918, in the Pulaski Hall, under the presidency of Dr. Krasnow, three thousand Russian people of Chicago resolved to send a telegram to the President of the United States, Woodrow Wilson, regarding the Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>The contents of the telegram as as follows:</p>
   <p>(1) We greet you, Honorable President, as the head of the well disposed American nation, and the friend of Russia; and we thank you for your friendly attitude toward Russia, expressed in your solemn promise not to let anybody in the world interfere, at Russia's expense, in her affairs, without the call of the Russian democracy which soon will be recognized by all the Allies; and we beg you to patiently await the time when Russia will be organized as a real nation, when honor will be restored, and the freed Russian people will be called back into the fighting ranks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0697.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(2) We are exceedingly glad to help friendly America in whatever way we can, and therefore we are happy to obey the call of the Federal Government to help the Liberty Loan; but all our hopes are centered on saving Russia and the idea of democracy in the world. We count upon the quick growth of Russia's co-operation with all the allied countries on the now disgraceful Eastern Front, open to Germans. We hope that Russia will start up, and that you will help our ruined fatherland. We wish the great American nation to prosper in good health. And long live her valuable chief leader, President Wilson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
