<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-10-27">Oct. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Cooperative Factory of Astronomical Clocks in Chicago; a Russian Invention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-10-27">Oct. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN COOPERATIVE FACTORY OF ASTRONOMICAL CLOCKS IN CHICAGO; A RUSSIAN INVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This factory was organized on cooperative principles and incorporated in the state of Illinois with a capital of $150,000.</p>
   <p>We inform all the members of the Russian Corporation (Astronomical Clock Manufacturing Company), and all persons interested in our Russian factory, that the board of directors has bought for the clock factory a building at 1416-18 W. Ohio Street, and the factory has been already moved to this building.</p>
   <p>We beg that inquiries about all affairs concerning the corporation or the factory, personally or by letter, be made at the following address: Astronomical Clock Mfg. Co., 1416-18 W. Ohio St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>A Short Description. The clock shows how the sun illumines the earth and <pb facs="5423967_2_1091.jpg" n="2"/>the moon, how the earth rotates on its axis in twenty-four hours, causing the change of day and night; how the earth moves around the sun, and how this causes the change of the four seasons(spring, summer, autumn, and winter); how the moon rotates around the earth, and how the changes (phases) of the moon are caused thereby. It shows how the earth and the moon rotate together around the sun and how solar and lunar eclipses are caused. Besides all that the clock has a dial plate with subdivisions corresponding to a whole year's calendar, and the hands of the clock show exactly the hours, days, months, and seasons.</p>
   <p>By its original and new construction this clock surpasses all that has been invented in this line. The clock has been invented and constructed by a Russian mechanic, Michael Bulka.</p>
   <p>A patent has been taken out for this clock, and the American School Board has approved it as an important and necessary article for all American schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These astronomical clocks are being made in various sizes and are adapted for use not only in schools, but also in public institutions and private homes.</p>
   <p>The price of the clock ranges from $5 to $300.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
