<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On the Dumping Grounds</title><title level="a" type="sub">by E. Moravsky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE DUMPING GROUNDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by E. Moravsky</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About three years ago, one could see such horrible sights in large cities that the most shocking scenes described by Andreiev in his story, "Czar-Hunger," became commonplace by comparison. These nightmarish scenes could be seen at the city refuse grounds, which attracted thousands of human beings as though gold were to be found there.</p>
   <p>In those days, from early morning until late at night those grounds were beehives of activity. Hungry and homeless men impatiently awaited the arrival of trucks with the city refuse, and when the trucks arrived, these people threw themselves on the heaps of rubbish just like wild rapacious beasts and began to dig into the refuse with their hands. They extracted from the heaps everything that resembled food or clothing: moldy bread, pieces of putrid meat, spoiled vegetables, worn-out clothing and footwear, metal scrap, bottles, and various other objects. Consequently, the heaps of freshly unloaded refuse grew smaller. Part of the garbage found its way into the stomachs of these human <pb facs="5423967_2_0066.jpg" n="2"/>beings and part was carried off to be sold or to be used as something valuable.</p>
   <p>Such scenes were photographed by American cameramen, but none of them over succeeded in showing these scenes in a way that would produce the shock which grips the observer when he looks at the scene. The impression received is beyond human words.</p>
   <p>At the present time, however, these ghoulish scenes no longer occur. Now the unemployed do not have to dig into the heaps of rubbish in search of a piece of stale bread or decayed meat, because they receive assistance from the authorities. I do not know how much help is given, but according to the statements made to me by some of the Russian unemployed, they are no longer starving.</p>
   <p>At present, however, the same horrible scenes can be seen in the spiritual life of the nation. Formerly the city refuse heaps were besieged by hungry workers; now some of the American intellectuals are crowding around the dumping grounds of every type of ideological rubbish, of every kind of refuse of human thought.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0067.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>American intellectuals are, at present, living through a severe crisis, a sickness of some sort. They are in search of a way out of the situation; they are looking for a way to a better future. They are subjecting to reappraisal every old doubtful value and are attempting to create new values.</p>
   <p>As a result, we see, in America, the appearance of several new currents of thought (Technocrats, Utopians, and others). It may be that these new currents of thought will have no influence on the social life of the country, it may be that these new theories will prove to be stillborn infants, but all these are secondary considerations. The important fact is that people are looking for new ways of life, are in search of new forms, and are bent on creating something new.</p>
   <p>But among these people there can be found individuals who live on that which they find in the garbage heaps. They are digging into the heaps of the ideological rubbish, into the piles of refuse of human thought, and are extracting all sorts of discarded ideas and concepts in the conviction that they are gaining some valuable treasures lost in the course of human history.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0068.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I have in mind that section of the American intelligentsia which during recent years has begun to take an unusual interest in German Marxism and Russian Bolshevism. Strange as it may seem, there are to be found professors, students, literary men, painters, and jurists in America who feed themselves on what they find in the garbage; they feed themselves on the Marxian-Bolshevik rubbish and want to feed it to others. It is true that Russian intellectuals also fed themselves on it sometime ago, but that happened at the time when Marxism existed only in theory.</p>
   <p>Marxian reality was anticipated and foreseen only by F. Dostoievsky, but nobody took his views seriously enough at the time. Russian intellectuals were so much under the influence of the Marxist narcotic that it took the Russian Revolution to wake them up. And the Russian Revolution took its course just as Dostoievsky had predicted.</p>
   <p>After the Russian Revolution, Marxism was discarded and was tossed on the garbage heap in all countries. With horror all truly cultured and freedom-loving <pb facs="5423967_2_0069.jpg" n="5"/>people turned away from it. But a small section of the American intelligentsia still regard the decayed Marxian casuistry and bloody Bolshevik reality as the basis upon which the social life of all of mankind should be reared.</p>
   <p>One feels that such intellectuals are to be pitied and scorned at the same time. Their situation is many times worse than that of those unemployed who used to dig in the rubbish piles in search of a crumb of bread. The unemployed did it under compulsion, because they were hungry; these people voluntarily gorge themselves on the refuse of human thought.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
