<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-13">Feb. 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Lincoln Enjoyed Wide Popularity Among Immigrants</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Flis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-13">Feb. 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">LINCOLN ENJOYED WIDE POPULARITY AMONG IMMIGRANTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Flis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Abraham Lincoln, sixteenth President of the United States, up to the present time remains an outstanding historical personality and continues to attract the attention of American biographers. With each passing year new volumes are added to the tremendous store of books, written about Lincoln. Among the immigrants Lincoln is undoubtedly the most popular American national leader. This popularity had been gained by him even in his lifetime, when he enjoyed the esteem and the confidence of all the newcomers from all countries.</p>
   <p>The romantic life history of Lincoln is known to everybody. He was born on February 12, 1809, in a humble log cabin in an out-of-the-way village in the State of Kentucky. His father was an illiterate farmer. He was taught to read and write by his mother, who was herself a self-taught woman. He remained on the farm until he reached the age of twenty-one, and only then did he <pb facs="5423967_2_0886.jpg" n="2"/>embark on his independent life. He was a youth of gigantic stature, six feet and four inches tall, with a very meager stock of knowledge, but he had a pair of hands that made the local lumberjacks and carpenters envious.</p>
   <p>Employment as carpenter, farm hand, clerk in a grocery store, postmaster, and finally as lawyer--such were the stages of his career. For many years he industriously educated himself, showing not only exceptional abilities but also extraordinary perseverance in overcoming the deficiencies in his education. In his mature years he was a well-read man, a brilliant speaker, and a first-class stylist. By far the most important social and political problem in those days was that of negro slavery. The foundation for this institution was laid in the earliest days of the colonial history of America. During the two centuries that followed, slavery, like a cancerous growth, spread all over the country, with its roots deeply imbedded in the South. There the conditions of servitude under which the colored population lived became "the sacred pillars" on which rested the welfare and prosperity of the white plantation owners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0887.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the time of the American Revolution the question of slavery somehow had not been raised. The Congress at that time merely forbade the importation of new slaves, assuming obviously that this social evil would die out of itself. But cotton-raising became the chief industry of the South, and the plantations were in need of cheap labor.</p>
   <p>By joining the movement for the liberation of slaves Lincoln in a short time became the leader of the "abolitionists". Nobody could ridicule so ably and so sharply the statements of Southerners to the effect that "Negroes do not constitute a part of the human race". Nobody so fired the imagination of the masses. The campaign carried on for the liberation of the Negroes and the total abolition of slavery reached its culmination in the nomination of Lincoln and his election to the presidency of the United States.</p>
   <p>The South declined to recognize the validity of the election. Six Southern States formed their own confederation and elected Jefferson Davis as their president. A fratricidal civil war broke out in the country. It lasted four <pb facs="5423967_2_0888.jpg" n="4"/>years, until the resistance offered by the South was shattered. In 1863 Lincoln issued his famous proclamation on the liberation of the slaves. In 1864 he was re-elected, and in 1865 an assassin's bullet ended his fruitful life. His death literally shook the entire civilized world. The first to respond to this sad news were the liberal elements through out the world. Among the latter were the two giants among those who fought for freedom--an Italian by the name of Mazzini and a Hungarian by the name of Louis Kossuth.</p>
   <p>From the very beginning of his political career Lincoln maintained very friendly relations with various immigrant groups and was particularly interested in political refugees. Particularly prominent among the latter at that time were the victims of the reactionary period in Germany. At one time Lincoln was actually the owner of an immigrant newspaper, the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, the editor of which, Dr. Theodore Kanisius, was Lincoln's friend.</p>
   <p>Among his political advisers were Carl Schurz, who had been a political prisoner in Germany, and had escaped from prison, the sociologist Gustav Kerner, <pb facs="5423967_2_0889.jpg" n="5"/>and Dr. Francis Lieber.</p>
   <p>German refugees of the middle of the last century played a prominent part in the organization of the immigrant masses for the support of Lincoln in the election. This is also true of Scandinavian immigrants.</p>
   <p>There were only a very few Russian immigrants at that time, but the arrival of two Russian flotillas in the autumn of 1863 had its effect and kept European countries, particularly England, from recognizing the Confederacy and coming to its rescue. One of the flotillas, under the command of Vice-Admiral Popov, entered the port of San Francisco, and the other, under the command of Vice-Admiral Lisovsky, came to New York. Both flotillas left the American shores as soon as the danger of attack on the Federal Union passed away.</p>
   <p>In the army which was mobilized by Lincoln there were representatives "of all countries and all peoples". At the termination of the war the Congressional <pb facs="5423967_2_0890.jpg" n="6"/>Medal was awarded to several hundred combatants, among whom were forty-eight German revolutionaries and also immigrants from such countries as Norway, Poland, Hungary, and Syria.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
