<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-02-26">Feb. 26, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Program at the Chicago Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-02-26">Feb. 26, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN PROGRAM AT THE CHICAGO THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning February 22, 1929, there will be shown at the Chicago Theater a Russian moving picture entitled "The Red Dancer." Connected with this picture will be a special Russian show, or rather a "prologue." This prologue will be staged by the ballet-master A. M. Burman artist of the Petrograd Imperial Ballet. Mr. A. M. Burman has been invited to the Chicago Theater in the capacity of ballet-master and stage manager. He is one of that company of famous artists which has been given us by the Mariinsky Theater. He began his career abroad with the ballet of S. I. Dyaghilev, with which in 1915 he made a way for the triumphal progress of Russian art abroad. It is not necessary to say much about his capability as an artist. Enough will be said if we mention that Mr. A. M. Burman has been during five years the ballet-master of the Strand Theater on Broadway, New York. One must have an extraordinary imagination in order to be able to prepare every week for such a long period of time something new and interesting for the Americans. The Broadway public has been spoiled by such titans of the ballet art as M. M. Fokin, M. M. Mordkin etc. Mr. A. M. Burman invited to participate in the "Prologue" the ballet artist A. I. Bolshakov well known to the Russian public; the balalaika orchestra conducted by Mr. Malakhovsky and the artists of the cabaret "Petrushka, Miss Mirayeva, Mr. Sankarzhevsky and Mr. Gulyaev.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
