<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-21">Feb. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Demand Break with Ussr</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-21">Feb. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DEMAND BREAK WITH USSR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A wave of protests against the spread of communistic propaganda by Moscow has rolled into Congress, and demands are heard for a complete break of diplomatic relations with the Bolsheviks. Senator McCormick has submitted evidence to Congress to show that a month after Mr. Litvinoff promised to stop communist propaganda in the United States, if the Soviets were recognized, the Moscow International issued a call for world revolution and confiscation of private and church property. The secretary of the Communist party in the United States, Mr. [Earl]Browder, under questioning, admitted that these slogans were adopted by the American Communists at their Cleveland Convention in 1931.</p>
   <p>Senator Short appears to be the most antagonistic opponent of Bolshevism since he visited Russia in 1931. The Senator declares: "They (the Bolsheviks) imposed on the Russian people one tyranny after another. Now they enjoy diplomatic privileges here, and attempt to spread their system to the United States. We must put a stop to it!" Senator Tinkham joined Senator Short <pb facs="5423967_2_0115.jpg" n="2"/>in his demand in asking that diplomatic relations with the Bolsheviks be broken off immediately, as they both feel that the American Government has many reasons for taking such action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
