<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-09">Feb. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Counterrevolutionary Villains</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-09">Feb. 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY VILLAINS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reporters of the foreign press in Moscow state that in connection with the abolition of the bread cards, the growth of opposition groups has increased. Russian workers regard this move as the removal of their last privilege under Bolshevism--their right to buy bread at low prices.</p>
   <p>The growth of opposition to the present regime is observed not only among workers, but also among other groups, particularly students and young professors. This is evidence of the extent to which disappointments have affected the opinions of Soviet youth.</p>
   <p>According to one correspondent, Soviet youth reconciled itself to the difficulties of life as long as there was an element of equality in the daily lives of the people. Formerly, all of the simple benefits of life were equally accessible or inaccessible to all. But now money has regained its influence, and the situation has changed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0123.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Moscow there are fashionable restaurants, cafes, and stores where one may obtain articles of luxury; but only the wealthy have access to these places. In other words, inequality has reappeared; consequently envy rears its head once more. And this leads to the growth of strong opposition, particularly among the young.</p>
   <p>According to the same correspondent, the Bolsheviks regard all these elements of opposition as followers of Zinoviev or Trotsky. They are classed as counterrevolutionary elements, and as supporters of fascism and capitalism. The Bolsheviks assume this attitude even though the opposition has nothing in common with the former dissident groups and their leaders.</p>
   <p>Zinoviev, as chairman of the Communist International, was considered commander-in-chief of all the Bolshevik forces in the world. Now they call him a "counter-revolutionary villain".</p>
   <p>Pravda (January 19) writes of Zinoviev's supporters:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0124.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"History has pilloried the followers of the counterrevolutionist, Zinoviev--the agents of international capitalism. Pitiful cowards, flunkeys of capitalism, and fascism--they should have no place among citizens of the Socialist motherland."</p>
   <p>In other places Zinoviev's followers are called traitors and snakes.</p>
   <p>The Bolshevik press now pours choice epithets on the head of all Zinoviev's followers. Zinoviev and his disciples are denounced every day in more venomous terms than were ever used to denounce international capitalists, facists, or the Russian "white guard" abroad. Zinoviev is now considered the most despicable villain in the world, although only recently he was the most upright and outstanding man in the party.</p>
   <p>It cannot be doubted, however, that the same fate will someday overtake Stalin, when his dictatorship is overthrown. The same epithets will be applied to Stalin, for there is no essential difference between the two.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0125.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Sooner or later this must happen, for revolutions, like Saturn, very frequently devour their own children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
