<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title level="a">Decennary of the Russian Press of Chicago</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">(Condensed from editorials, an article by Mr. Rubezhanin and a report in the Nov. 6 and Nov. 9, 1926, numbers of Rassviet).</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title level="a">DECENNARY OF THE RUSSIAN PRESS OF CHICAGO</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">(Condensed from editorials, an article by Mr. Rubezhanin and a report in the Nov. 6 and Nov. 9, 1926, numbers of Rassviet).</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, Nov. 7, 1926, there took place at the West Side Auditorium a celebration of the decennary of the existence of the Russian press in Chicago, a decennary which just coincided with the second anniversary of the Chicago Russian Herald and Rassviet. The editorial of Nov. 6 points out the great difficulties that had to be overcome by the Russians of Chicago in order to create a Russian press of their own. The chief difficulty was caused by the low cultural level of the majority of the Russian residents of Chicago and the small number of educated men and women among them. It cost a lot of trouble and hard labor to arouse among the Russian colony of Chicago interest in the attempts to create a good daily paper <pb facs="5423967_2_1703.jpg" n="2"/>but ultimately these attempts have been crowned with success, and the various cultural and educational Russian organizations of Chicago possess now a daily newspaper, Rassviet, where they can discuss freely their needs and voice their hopes and aspirations.</p>
   <p>The publishers of the Rassviet had to overcome many difficulties caused by the selfishness of some of the linotype operators who were getting a very high remuneration for their work from Mr. Gugis while the paper belonged to him. Rassviet was paying them at the same rate, but they demanded still higher union wages, and being instigated by the Communists, even started a strike. The Communists, who were behind it, hoped thus to ruin the newspaper of which they were enemies, detesting it for its criticism of Bolshevist tactics and its support of non-partisan organizations. Yet the "strike" <pb facs="5423967_2_1704.jpg" n="3"/>proved to be an entire failure, and Rassviet continued to appear regularly, which was a proof of the fact that this newspaper had gained the sympathies of the great majority of the Russian workers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This fact was strikingly illustrated at the celebration of the decennary of the Russian press of Chicago, which was also a celebration of the second anniversary of Rassviet. Crowds of Russians streamed into the large hall of the West Side Auditorium, on the corner of Racine Avenue and Taylor Street. This hall can hold over one thousand persons, and it was very crowded. The Russians of Chicago had proved that they were on the side of the non-partisan Rassviet, and not on that of the Bolsheviki who had tried to ruin this paper by instigating a strike without any good reasons whatsoever.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1705.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Rubezhanin opened the celebration by a short speech in which he explained the significance of the festivity and exhorted the Russians to support the only daily Russian newspaper of Chicago. This speech was followed by a very interesting musical program. In this program participated the best forces of the Russian colony. Miss I. G. Gheorghievskaya, dramatic soprano of the Petrograd Opera, Mr. S. N. Sergheyev, baritone of the Moscow Opera, Miss Stephania Timkevich, contralto, and many others. Mr. Moravsky made a speech, congratulating the Russians of Chicago for their achievement in creating a daily newspaper which was able to voice their needs and aspirations, and greeted the Russian labor organizations which had given their hearty support to the newspaper and now practically were its owners. After the concert there followed dancing till late in the night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
