<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-24">Jan. 24, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Communists Shed Tears Over Nra and Aaa</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-24">Jan. 24, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNISTS SHED TEARS OVER NRA and AAA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everybody knows that the American Communist party fought a hard battle against Roosevelt's New Deal particularly against the NRA and the AAA. The Communist press persistently asserted that the NRA was created by the Roosevelt administration only for the purpose of making the situation of workers worse and of,saving capitalist America from certain collapse. The same thing was said by American communists about the Agricultural Administration (AAA).</p>
   <p>But when by a decision of the Supreme Court the NRA and the AAA were abolished, the American communists and their Russian parrots of the Novy Mir turned about and appeared as defenders of the New Deal by declaring war on the Supreme Court.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0904.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to the Novy Mir the leaders of the American Communist party have addressed an appeal to American workers, farmers, and even small businessmen to resist by all possible means, the encroachments of the Supreme Court's dictatorial power on the prerogatives of the executive and legislative branches of the Federal Government. They consider that the Supreme Court judges have become by usurpetion of power uncrowned kings of the country and virtual dictators, for they have abrogated laws which are most essential for the well-being of farmers and workers by finding them unconstitutional.</p>
   <p>The parrots of the Novy Mir, as was to be expected, proved to be even more ardent defenders of the New Deal than their American comrades. Shkliar in his article in the issue of January 13 appeals to his readers to fight against the dictatorial acts of the United States Supreme Court. The appeal is addressed not only to farmers and workers but also to the great mass of the American people.</p>
   <p>"This Court," writes Shkliar, "has assumed the right to declare unconstitutional laws passed by the legislative branch of the Federal Government."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0905.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus Shkliar finds himself in the ranks of the defenders not only of the NRA and the AAA but of all the other laws enacted in connection with the New Deal. Shkliar has become so wise that he gives unsolicited advice to Americans and tells them what steps they should take in order to overcome the dictatorial powers exercised by the Supreme Court.</p>
   <p>His advice and suggestions can be summarized as follows:</p>
   <p>1) Congress and the President should deprive the Supreme Court judges of the right to declare laws unconstitutional.</p>
   <p>2) They should bring into court judges infringing on the rights of the people.</p>
   <p>3) The Constitution should be amended so as to deprive the Supreme Court judges of the power to declare laws unconstitutional.</p>
   <p>From this summary we see that Shkliar advises not only limiting the powers of the Supreme Court but even bringing into court the judges who dare to declare <pb facs="5423967_2_0906.jpg" n="4"/>laws unconstitutional. He apparently desires that the United States Supreme Court shall play the same role as that of the superior courts in Soviet Russia or in Germany, where the ruling parties so limit the powers of their judges as to make them servile flunkies.</p>
   <p>Perhaps it is difficult to find among American farmers and workers men who approve of the Supreme Court decisions on the NRA and the AAA, but one should not infer from this attitude that the Supreme Court as an institution has outlived its usefulness and should be abolished, or that its prerogatives should be limited to a degree which would not permit the annulment of any law passed by the legislative chambers. As a matter of fact the Supreme Court is not a dictatorial institution. On the contrary, it is a judiciary body which does not permit either Congress or the chief executive to acquire dictatorial powers. It prevents certain things that we observe occurring in several countries in Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
