<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1928-03-29">Mar. 29, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Concert, Etc., for the Benefit of the Miners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1928-03-29">Mar. 29, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT, ETC., FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE MINERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert and theatrical performance arranged by the Russian progressive organizations of Chicago on Sunday, March 25, 1928, at Walsh's Hall for the benefit of the striking miners, was a success in spite of the Lent and the absence of dancing on the program.</p>
   <p>The program was opened with a speech by Mr. Radcliff, president of the Chicago branch of the A. F. of L., who very eloquently related the history of the origin of the miners' strike and the various phases of its development. The orator made a soul-stirring appeal to those present not to forget the 750,000 sufferers who are fighting for their rights.</p>
   <p>The comedy, "On a Revision," was another fairly successful number on the program.</p>
   <p>The picture "The Destitute Children," staged by Dr. Korablinov, deserves great praise. The children who participated in this picture received much applause.</p>
   <p>The concert opened with solos by Misses Maksakov and Groschinsky, who had <pb facs="5423967_2_1138.jpg" n="2"/>to sing several encores.</p>
   <p>Very good as usual were the young dancers, - pupils of Russian schools, taught by Mrs. J. M. Sholy. Mr. Chernyshev's string orchestra also pleased the audience.</p>
   <p>The greatest "hit," however, was made by the Moscow Quartet, which was something new for the Chicago public. Especially Mr. V. Barstov's magnificent bass voice was greatly appreciated by the public. Mr. V. Barstov had to sing several times.</p>
   <p>Our popular baritone, Mr. T. K. Korablinov, as usual earned much applause. He and Miss Maksakov also sang very well a duet.</p>
   <p>The Gypsy Camp Chorus sang several beautiful songs with which the public was very much pleased.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Before the end of the program Miss Maksakov, at the request of the committee, went through the audience and collected $30.10. The proceeds from the concert were sent to Frank Morrison, Secretary of the American Federation of Labor, A. F. of L. Building, Washington, D. C.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
