<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Vote for the Democratic Candidates on April 2</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">VOTE FOR THE DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES ON APRIL 2</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, April 2, elections will be held in Chicago for city officials. The offices of mayor, city clerk and city treasurer will be voted on.</p>
   <p>The principal candidates for these positions are on the Democratic and Republican tickets.</p>
   <p>All Russians who are American citizens must, without exception, take part in this election, for our participation in the election, makes us full-fledged citizens. This participation determines the merits and the numerical strength of the group of and nationality. A grave error is being made by those who think they should not go to the polling place because nobody will know whether they voted or not, anyhow. The city authorities through the precinct captains and their helpers know exactly who voted and who did not. For this purpose the precinct workers from time to time go from home to home and take a census of the voters. Persons not taking part in the elections are usually classed by them as foreigners who are not citizens. To such people, aldermen and <pb facs="5423967_2_0525.jpg" n="2"/>committeemen refuse to give any help. This must be remembered by all Russians.</p>
   <p>For whom should Russians vote? In order to know for whom to vote we must look into the not distant past. We remember quite well what took place recently in Chicago. The city taxes increased to unprecedented heights. The City of Chicago became known throughout the world as the haven of gangsters and bandits. The city treasury was empty. Policemen, firemen and other city employees had not received any wages for a year or longer. City life was practically at a standstill. The city was facing bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>In such a condition the city was handed over to Mayor A. Cermak and a Democratic administration. Mayor Cermak began to bring order out of chaos in city affairs, but his efforts were cut short by his assassination. His place was taken by a no less able mayor, Edward Kelly. Mayor Kelly, as a good administrator, brought order into city life, and put the city finances on a sound basis by eliminating deficits in the city treasury. During his administration back wages of the city employees were paid up and taxes were cut considerably.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In general, city life again became normal and now, in spite of the long economic crisis, social life in Chicago is gradually assuming a normal aspect.</p>
   <p>This is the reason why the Russian-American Democratic League advises all Russian people to vote for Mr. Edward Kelly, present mayor of the city, and for the other candidates of the Democratic party for city offices.</p>
   <p>Central Committee of the</p>
   <p>Russian-American Democratic League</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
