<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-05">Mar. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Horrors of Famine in Ukraine in Spring of 1934</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0091.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-05">Mar. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HORRORS OF FAMINE IN UKRAINE IN SPRING OF 1934</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his third serial article, the American journalist, [T.] Walker, describes what he had seen in the provinces of Poltava and Kiev in the spring of 1934. With a great deal of difficulty he managed to reach the city of Poltava, and immediately upon his arrival he went on foot to neighboring villages. He was told that in the vicinity of the city there were many hungry people, and this statement he was able to confirm through his own personal observations. Within a half a mile from Poltava he came across a small peasant hut at the thresh-old of which stood an old man. The old man's wife had gone away in search of food. The old man told Walker that during the last two weeks he, together with his wife, ate nothing but a pound of black bread, and that during the last two days they had eaten nothing.</p>
   <p>He also told Walker that not far from the hut there was a cemetery where the exposed bodies of hunger victims were lying. Walker tells that without much difficulty he found the cemetery, for it could easily be found if one were guided by his sense of smell alone.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0092.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On a plot of ground approximately one acre square lay eleven corpses, some of them entirely decomposed. He was particularly impressed while viewing the body of a peasant woman about 22 years old, a beauty in life. Her head was covered with a black kerchief and her body with a patch quilt. In her hands she still held a bunch of roots which she [undoubtedly had] dug up for food.</p>
   <p>Such, in part, are the conditions prevailing in famine-stricken Ukraine under the Bolshevik regime.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: This article is one of several relative to the attacks and counterattacks between the Hearst-owned papers and the Bolshevik press. At this time efforts were being made to have the United States break off diplomatic relations with Russia. The Hearst papers were using their columns in support of the movement, and T. Walker was their foreign correspondent.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
