<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-11-22">Nov. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Story</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-11-22">Nov. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD STORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Revolutions are sometimes unavoidable, but every revolution is a great misfortune. It invariably brings some degree of ruin to the country. That which may have been given to the people voluntarily is taken by force, accompanied by brutality and violence, and always those least guilty suffer most, while those who are the most responsible for the flare-up will manage to make a safe and timely escape.</p>
   <p>The instigators will run and will carry away with them valuables, whereas the victims paying for the subversive act are those who hardly know what it is all about.</p>
   <p>Much blood was spilled in unnecessary battles in the recent White guard outbreak. Hundreds, possible thousands, were killed, wounded and maimed for life. Those were the White soldiers who were none but simple-hearted village chaps, who blundered into the White army from silliness. Those at the top are without a scratch and are abroad now. There he sits and giggles at the nation's wrath.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0300.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The smaller fry made its way to Harbin. For these the Chinese are already cleaning up and getting ready barracks, while the foreign White Hundred will feed them. The birds of greater feather, the generals and ministers headed by Dietrichs, generalissimo of the White Guard, also the brothers Merculov, all these left Vladivostok on very comfortable stolen boats, carrying away huge sums of money with them. Why not travel a bit around the world? They will come back and will be on hand as soon as a new scheme is cooked up.</p>
   <p>The same is true of all the White subversivists.</p>
   <p>Denikin is living well, so is Wrangel, Yudenich, too. Semenov is living like a prince.</p>
   <p>Unscathed are all of the White ministers. The same is true of the many other counter-revolutionists.</p>
   <p>In 1918, when the reins of government went over to the Soviets from the provisional government, then, too, people were killed or wounded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0301.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Kerensky, by the way, was defended by a woman's battalion. A perfectly innocent bunch of hens armed with guns, which they could not handle, for some reason was pushing for a fight with the Red army. Cadets and junkers, kids of 15 and 18 years who knew nothing about life, empty-headed from sheer stupidity, were fighting that battalion.</p>
   <p>But Mr. Kerensky himself, for whom the fight was on, arrived abroad safely and even leisurely, with pockets filled with foreign money. He did not see the necessity of waiting for the final outcome of this combat. Instead, he made himself comfortable abroad.</p>
   <p>During the great Russian revolution many perished, yet, of those who deserved it very few were punished.</p>
   <p>Several people of the royal family perished, among them a child of 12 and about ten conspicuous officials, generals, rich landowners.</p>
   <p>The majority of those who were guilty of Russia's decay, and who were <pb facs="5423967_2_0302.jpg" n="4"/>tormenting the Russian nation, remained unharmed. They are abroad, waiting. The majority of them has money also.</p>
   <p>It is the petty officers and the petty, colorless human catch, who hardly knowing how, fell into the White army and bore the brunt of the suffering. The White guard of kids, the empty hot-heads, but more than anyone else, the workers and peasants who suffer from revolutions. They are the ones who starve and freeze.</p>
   <p>Indeed, revolutions are hard.</p>
   <p>N. Naletov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
