<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-01">March 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Legislative Chaos</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0832</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0832.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-01">March 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">LEGISLATIVE CHAOS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning with their school days, Americans are told that the supreme legislative power in the United States is vested in Congress. As a general statement, that is correct, but as in everything else, there are certain reservations. Everybody knows that Congress passed a law with regard to national reconstruction, known as the NRA. This law has been in effect for some time, and yet in a number of cases, it is being violated by the industrialists. The essential thing is not that manufacturers evade this law (officially accept, but in reality ignore it), but the fact that some large industrialists reject it entirely and do not obey the government. Among such concerns are Ford Motor Company and Weirton Steel Company.</p>
   <p>The government and the former head of the NRA, Hugh Johnson, brought pressure <pb facs="5423967_2_0833.jpg" n="2"/>to bear several times upon Mr. Ford in order to force his acceptance of the automobile code, but all their efforts failed. Finally, the government had to leave Mr. Ford alone. With regard to Weirton Steel Company, the government decided to break down the resistance of this concern and compel it to comply with clause 7 A of the NRA, which provides and guarantees to workers the right to form unions of their own choosing in every commercial or industrial establishment and obligates the companies to regard representatives of such organizations as lawful agents for collective bargaining purposes. With this aim in view, the government brought a suit in court against Weirton Steel Company in the Delaware district. The proceedings in this case continued for several months and ended rather comically: Judge D. Nields sided with the company and decided that clause 7 A of the NRA is unconstitutional. He rejected the government demands concerning the issuance of an injunction against the company forbidding any interference in the organizational activities of its workers.</p>
   <p>As a result of this decision the impression has been created that the laws <pb facs="5423967_2_0834.jpg" n="3"/>passed by Congress are worthless as long as they can be abrogated by the Federal District courts, and that the executive branch of the government has no authority at all as long as it cannot enforce the laws passed by the legislative branch of the government. Of course, the government is dissatisfied with this decision and intends to appeal the case to the Supreme Court.</p>
   <p>Almost simultaneously, a similar case was heard in Connecticut, where another federal judge found unconstitutional the coal code authority and permitted coal companies in the state to establish such order as they desired, disregarding meanwhile all NRA provisions. All this indicates that in the legislative life of the United States, complete chaos prevails.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
