<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-12-04">Dec. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Progress of the Society "Znanie."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-12-04">Dec. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">PROGRESS OF THE SOCIETY "ZNANIE."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the short time of its existence the society "Znanie" (Knowledge) has made a tremendous progress. In one year this small group of people has gained the confidence and approval of all the Russian colony. This society has arranged several beartiful concerts and theatrical performances. It staged the play, "Days of Our Life," by L. Andreyev, on December 1, 1929, proving thereby how energetically it worked. Owing to the efforts of the members of the society the best actors have been invited, and the play, "Days of Our Life," was a great success both financially and from the artistic standpoint.</p>
   <p>On December the 1st Walshe's Hall was crowded. The acting of the artists was magnificent. Words cannot adequately express it. I shall only mention the names of those whose acting was exceptionally good: A. Tatarinov, K. Shein, E. Nelidov, Mme. Mirayev, and Mme Mikhailovsky. The public was delighted. These actors are not amateurs; they are real talented artists.</p>
   <p>Since the visit of the artists of the Moscow Art Theater to Chicago Russians here have not seen such magnificent acting. Among the audience one would <pb facs="5423967_2_1335.jpg" n="2"/>hear such exclamations as: "This is remarkable!" "The acting is wonderful; it holds you spellbound." "We should have more plays like this one," etc.</p>
   <p>In conclusion I want to point out that the Society took care that examplary order should reign in the hall. When this society arranges concerts or stages plays, these begin promptly at the time advertised. During the performance complete silence is observed by the audience. No noise disturbs the artists and the public, who can hear every word spoken on the stage. All Russian organizations should follow this good example. Unfortunately disorder often reigns at other Russian musical and theatrical performances; and this has a repelling affect on the audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
