<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1929-05-15">May 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Day of Russian Culture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-05-15">May 15, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE DAY OF RUSSIAN CULTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Upon the initiative of the members of the societies "Women's Circle" and "Znanie" (Knowledge) there is going to be arranged on June 8th, for the first time in the city of Chicago, a solemn celebration of a "Day of Russian Culture."</p>
   <p>The committee which is organizing this festivity requests all the Russian cultural and educational organizations and societies, as well as separate individuals who sympathize with this undertaking, to unite for the celebration of this great festivity. For the elaboration of the program of this celebration and for the elucidation of various questions connected there with, the committee begs all who are willing to participate in this work to attend a meeting of the committee which will take place at the head quarters of the societies "Znanie" and "Women's Circle," at 1902 W. Division St., on Friday, May 17, at 8:30 P.M. (Note: This notice is important for the history of the life of the Russian Colony of Chicago as since that time the Russian Colony has started to celebrate periodically such "Days <pb facs="5423967_2_1432.jpg" n="2"/>of Russian Culture," and such celebrations have been carried on to the present time. N. K.)</p>
   <p>Program of the Celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture," to Take Place at the Municipal Pier of the City of Chicago on Sunday, June 9 at 3 P.M.</p>
   <p>Part I</p>
   <p>Mr. N. F. Erin's introductory address; Mr. N. S. Gribov speech on the meaning of the "Day of Russian Culture;" Mr. D. V. Stranden; Mr. S. I. Goosev-Orenburgsky- will read one of his stories; Mr. N. A. Birsky--will speak on the inner essence of the spirit of the Russian people; Dr. Spivak; Dr. Sahud on the influence of Leo Tolstoy on the world--culture; E. O. Tupikov.</p>
   <p>Part II Concert Program</p>
   <p>1) Students of the Musical and Vocal Studio of Mr. G. Khrzhanovski. Singing--<pb facs="5423967_2_1433.jpg" n="3"/>solo by Mr. P. Aluyevich, baritone.</p>
   <p>2) Students of the Musical Studio of Mr. A. Nakutin. Singing--solos.</p>
   <p>3) Mr. A. M. Aster, well known pianist, who has a studio in the Kimball bldg., will play "Scheherazade" by Rimsky-Korsakov;</p>
   <p>4) Miss Jean Moorey, talented pianist--piano solo.</p>
   <p>5) Chorus conducted by Mrs. P. M. Maksakov.</p>
   <p>6) Orchestra of students of the University of Chicago will play a potpourri and some other interesting numbers.</p>
   <p>7) Mrs. P. M. Maksakov, well known Russian singer--Russian folk-songs and songs by Russian composers.</p>
   <p>8) Mr. I. Kulgar, well known violinist.</p>
   <p>Part III Declamation</p>
   <p>1) Miss M. I. Ostroumov-"Russia"--a poem.</p>
   <p>2) Mr. V. I. Baycher--one of Nikitin's poems.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1434.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>3) Mr. S. Bakal--humoristic stories in the Ukrainian language.</p>
   <p>4) Mrs. A. A. Mikhailovsky--humoristic stories.</p>
   <p>5) Mr. B. M. Khmara--humoristic stories in the Ukrainian language.</p>
   <p>6) Mr. A. I. Pokotilov--a piece of poetry.</p>
   <p>Part IV Dances</p>
   <p>1) Mr. B. M. Klmara--Ukrainian "Hopak."</p>
   <p>2) Students of the University of Chicago--Russian "Cozachok," Ukrainian "Hopak" and other dances.</p>
   <p>3) Mrs. Gribov--classical dances.</p>
   <p>The committee announces that the return from the sale of tickets will be sent to the "Fund for the relief of Russian writers and scientists."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1435.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>From the United Committee for the Organization of the Celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture."</p>
   <p>The first celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture" in the city of Chicago, on June 9, 1929 proved to be a great moral success. In spite of the fact that on that day there were taking place several Russian picnics and a large "Press Day" picnic, the very large artistic hall of the Municipal Pier was crowded by lovers of Russian culture. The following persons were on the literary part of the program of the celebration: the Russian writer Mr. S. I. Goosev-Orenburgsky; the artist of the Moscow Art Theater Mr. I. V. Lazarev; the representative of the American literati Mr. Krause, Mrs. N.A. Birsky, Mr. D. V. Stranden, Mr. S. Scheinman, Mr. V. I. Baycher, Mr. N. S. Gribov and Mr. N. F. Erin.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened with a short speech by the responsible manager of the celebration, Mr. N. F. Erin who bade all those present a hearty welcome, and then introduced the chairman of the literary part of the program, <pb facs="5423967_2_1436.jpg" n="6"/>Mrs. N. A. Birsky. The speakers explained the meaning of the "Day of Russian Culture" and the importance of Russian Culture in general for the whole world. After the literary part of the program there followed a concert and some dances and declamation. The following artists participated in this part of the program: The well known singer Mrs. Maksakov; Mrs. P.G. Gribov who performed the Russian boyars' dance; Mrs. A. A. Mikhailovsky (declamation;) Miss Jean Moorey, pianist. Mr. P. Aluyevich, Croatian baritone; Mr. Weisspferd, tenor and Mr. Kulchar, violinist. Mr. Aster and Mr. Bremer were at the piano. The performances of all these artists were excellent and they earned much applause. The stage of the hall was adorned with the portraits of Leo Tolstoy and A. S. Pushkin. These portraits were very successfully enlarged from pictures by the self-taught amateur painter, Mr. P. I. Pokhaznikov. There were also the portraits of the artists of the Moscow Art Theater with Stanislavsky and Nemirovich-Danchenko at the head. Right in front and somewhat below were symbolic pictures representing labor, music and some other arts, science, culture and the theatrical art, painted by Mrs. S. Alexeyev. On the wall, right above the table, there was a large <pb facs="5423967_2_1437.jpg" n="7"/>poster with the words: "The Day of Russian Culture."</p>
   <p>The celebration was a great success. Everybody who has attended it will preserve the best reminiscences about it, and it will probably become good enough for the Russian Colony of Chicago to imitate in the future.</p>
   <p>The United Committee for the organization of the celebration of the Day of Russian Culture offers its hearty thanks to all the representatives of Russian literature and art who participated in the literary and musical parts of the program of the celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
