<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1930-01-03">Jan. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Events of the Knowledge Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1930-01-03">Jan. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">EVENTS OF THE KNOWLEDGE SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, November 22, about 1:00 A.M., at the hall of the Knowledge Society, the following were present: the chorus of the Society in a body, together with its conductor, V. V. Shumkov; representatives of the Knowledge Society; the public; children, who are invariably present at all Russian entertainments and so on...</p>
   <p>V. V. Shumkov who had previously finished conducting the chorus, nervously walked in the hall waiting for the guest of honor, the well known composer, A. M. Grechaninov, who is paying a short visit to Chicago. The expectation reached its climax, when finally there appeared in the door the familiar figure of Alexandre Tikhonovich... The chairman of the Knowledge Society, J. Erin, in a brief speech greeted the great composer and introduced the conductor V. V. Shumkov to him.</p>
   <p>The guest took the place reserved for him, and the somewhat nervous chorus began its program. A. M. Grechaninov listened to the chorus very attentively and from time to time exchanged remarks with the musical director of radio <pb facs="5423967_2_1299.jpg" n="2"/>station WLS, who accompanied him. After the conclusion of the short program, Alexandre Tikhonovich expressed, in a brief speech, his admiration of such an excellently organized chorus and rendered tribute to its creator, V. V. Shumkov. To this, V. Shumkov thanked A. M. Grechaninov heartily, for honoring the chorus with his praise and begged him to allow to name the chorus in his name. A. Grechaninov agreed to this idea and remarked that he would be proud to tell of this in France, his second fatherland.</p>
   <p>Whereupon the conductor announced the news to the chorus, and his announcement was greeted with a storm of applause. After a short conversation with some of those present, A. M. Grechaninov left the hall to finish some important proof reading.</p>
   <p>He promised to visit the Society again on his return to Chicago. The public whose enthusiasm was aroused by this rare visit remained in the hall long after the guest had left.</p>
   <p>This modest celebration is especially important to the Knowledge Society which began its cultural work only a few months ago. The composer, A. M. Grechaninov, prominent representative of Russian genius gave his name to the young chorus <pb facs="5423967_2_1300.jpg" n="3"/>and thus greatly helped it to gain a high reputation. Let us wish good luck to the Knowledge Society which has undertaken the good work of creating a center of Russian culture in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A member of the colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
