<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1932-01-29">Jan. 29, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Colonies in the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1932-01-29">Jan. 29, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN COLONIES IN THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish newspaper Zgoda of Chicago, has published an editorial on January 28th, in regard to the Bolshevik activities in the United States. The editor of this newspaper has declared that the number of the Bolsheviks in the Polish colony is very insignificant. This statement of the Polish paper is based not on statistical data of the Central Committee of the American Communist Party, or of the American authorities, but merely on information received through channels of well informed persons.</p>
   <p>According to those well informed individuals, the ranks of the Bolsheviks are composed mostly by Russians. The Jews follow the Russians; the Latvians the Jews; then come the Finns; Lithuanians and Ukranians respectively; as for the Poles, they are last.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Polish newspaper is of the opinion that the Russian colony of Chicago in its majority is communistic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0227.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is hard to say what prompted the Polish paper to write such nonsense about the Russian colony, and to bring disrepute upon it. If the editors of this paper had the desire to learn what was the predominating group in the Russian colony, they should have approached those persons only, who are closely connected with the Russian colony for this information, and not those well-informed persons, who stand far away from it and have not the slightest knowledge about its internal affairs.</p>
   <p>The former would advise the editors of this Polish paper, that in the Russian colony there is a very insignificant number of Bolsheviks. For Chicago as is known, there are several scores of Russian organizations, but the majority of them are non-Bolshevik organizations and have no connections whatsoever with the Bolshevik movements in the United States.</p>
   <p>The most prominent among the Russian organizations in Chicago is the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society of America, and this organization has nothing in common with the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0228.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One could easily indicate several other Russian organizations, which are very inimical to the Bolsheviks, but this is unnecessary, as it is a well known fact to the majority of the Russian immigrants, as well as to the Bolsheviks, but not to the editors of the Polish newspaper.</p>
   <p>It is understood, of course, that there are some Bolsheviks in the Russian colony, but they are not missing too in the Polish colony; this apropos, is not denied by the editors of the Polish newspaper Zgoda. Where do they number more-in the Russian or Polish colony? It is indeed a very hard question to answer.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there are some Russian Bolshevik groups, but they are very small. In these groups there may be a few score of men, but the Russian colony of Chicago comprises scores of thousands.</p>
   <p>The same condition is noticeable in all the other cities of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0229.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is evident by the fact that the Bolsheviks have only one newspaper, and that is a weekly. But a similar Bolshevik paper is published in Polish. It may be inferred from the above fact that the Russian colonies have no more Bolsheviks than the Polish colonies.</p>
   <p>The Russian United Society of Mutual Aid (the most important Russian organization in the united States) has nothing in common with the Bolsheviks. It is true that the Bolsheviks succeeded by means of deception and demagogy to grab the Pittsburgh organization, but this does not mean that the rank and file of this organization favor the Bolsheviks, as day by day the dissatisfaction with the present leaders of this organization grows among the members.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that sooner or later this organization will rid itself of the" Bolshevik yoke."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0230.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In view of the facts given above we consider therefore, that the editors of the Polish paper have acted very unfairly in making the statement that the "Russian colony has more Bolsheviks than any other colony."</p>
   <p>We are even inclined to think that the Russian colony comprises comparatively lesser number of Bolsheviks than others. Neither the Poles nor Lithuanians or Finns, have tasted as the Russians did the "delights " of the Bolshevik dictatorship, and that is why it is easier for them to become the prey of the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>As to the Russian people most of them have already tasted the "delights" of the Bolshevik regime; The rest receive letters from Russia from their relatives and friends and are very well posted on the present conditions and well being, of the Russian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
