<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-12-03">Dec. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Evening Entertainment Given by the Newspaper Russian Herald</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-12-03">Dec. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE EVENING ENTERTAINMENT GIVEN BY THE NEWSPAPER RUSSIAN HERALD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The evening entertainment given by our newspaper was a tremendous, almost unique success. (Note:- This refers to the entertainment which took place on Nov. 30, 1924, at the Schoenhofen Hall. N. K.)</p>
   <p>The program lasted three hours, and the audience listened to every number of it with rapt attention.</p>
   <p>Some of the performances were rewarded by stormy applause.</p>
   <p>The artists on that evening were at their best and performed their numbers with great spirit.</p>
   <p>Especially inspiring was the playing of A. N. Kaminsky, that highly talented violinist. The opera singer S. A. Borovsky sang beautifully several numbers. The harmonious blending of the voices of the Russian American a capella chorus was very pleasing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1719.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The rendering of "Khutorok" and "Grechaniki" by Sophia Pavlovna Stranden was artistic and delightful. The jokes and manner of the comic artist Arrigoni made the public laugh heartily. The artists Kopelevich- Luganov and A. J. Pokatilov performed excellently the literary part of the program and their declamation of some short pieces was a success. George Morozov and Miss Ada Mirskaya enriched the program with some songs and dances.</p>
   <p>According to the sincere declarations of many of the guests and, which is important, of some very strict judges from among old members of the colony, the entertainment arranged by our newspaper, both as to its rich program and as to the great number of guests, was the most successful entertainment given in the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>It is a pleasure to remark that this entertainment has attracted the select part of our workmen's colony. Many representatives of the intelligentsia were also present. Exemplary order reigned during the entertainment. There was complete silence during the performance <pb facs="5423967_2_1720.jpg" n="3"/>of the program.</p>
   <p>The members of the colony, by coming in large numbers to this entertainment, have shown their friendly attitude towards our paper. By listening attentively to the program they have demonstrated their respect for the editorial staff and the artists who participated in the entertainment.</p>
   <p>The editorial staff of our newspaper has the right to be proud of this evening's entertainment which was worthy of the kind of institution that our paper is.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
