<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-04-01">Apr. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Statement of the Ownership, Management, Circulation, Etc., Required by the Act of Congress of August 24, 1912.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-04-01">Apr. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">STATEMENT OF THE OWNERSHIP, MANAGEMENT, CIRCULATION, ETC., REQUIRED BY THE ACT OF CONGRESS OF AUGUST 24, 1912.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rassviet, published daily at Chicago, Illinois for April 1st, 1931. State of Illinois, County of Cook ) s.s.</p>
   <p>Before me, a Notary Public in and for the State and County aforesaid, personally appeared Julian Carpich, who, having been duly sworn according to law, deposes and says that he is the Business Manager of the Rassviet and that the following is, to the best of his knowledge and belief, a true statement of the ownership, management (and if a daily paper, the circulation), etc., of the aforesaid publication for the date shown in the above caption, required by the act of August 24, 1912, embodied in section 411, Postal Laws and Regulations, printed on the reverse of this form, to wit:</p>
   <p>1. That the names and and addresses of the publisher, editor, managing editor, and business manager are:</p>
   <p>Publisher Russian Publishing Co., Inc., 1722 W. Chicago Ave.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1677.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Editor M. J. Roubezhanin, 1722 W. Chicago, Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Managing Editor- none</p>
   <p>Business Manager Julian Carpick, 1722 W. Chicago, Ave., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>2. That the owner is :(If owned by a corporation, its name and address must be stated and also immediately there under the names and addresses of stockholders owning or holding one per cent or more ot total amount of stock. If not owned by a corporation, the names and addresses of the individual owners must be given.</p>
   <p>If owned by a firm, company, or other unincorporated concern, its name and address, as well as those of each individual member, must be given.)</p>
   <p>Russian Publishing Co., 1722 W. Chicago Avenue., Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Russian Society Rassviet, Inc., 1722 W. Chicago Ave., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1678.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Russian National Orthodox Society, 917 N. Wood St., Chicago,Ill.</p>
   <p>Martin Martysiuk, 1551 S. California Ave., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>International Co-operative Assn., Inc., 9219 Russell St., Detroit, Mich.</p>
   <p>3. That the known bondholders, mortagees, and other security holders owning or holding 1 per cent or more of total amount of bonds, mortgages, or other securities are: ( If there are none, so stated.)</p>
   <p>None....</p>
   <p>5. That the average number of copies of each issue of this publication sold or distributed, through the mails or otherwise, to paid subscribers during the six months proceeding the date shown above is 20,000.</p>
   <p>(This information is required from daily publication only.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1679.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Julian Carpick, Business Manager.</p>
   <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this 31st day of March, 1931.</p>
   <p>(Seal)</p>
   <p>Alexander J. Pikiel, Notary Public,</p>
   <p>(My commission expires Sept. 4, 1932.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
