<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Clipping from an unidentified Russian newspaper</title>,
<date when="1930-03-22">Mar. 22, 1930</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 W. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a" type="sub">A Russian-American Cooperative Bank in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Clipping from an unidentified Russian newspaper</title>,
<date when="1930-03-22">Mar. 22, 1930</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 W. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a" type="sub">A RUSSIAN-AMERICAN COOPERATIVE BANK IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To all Russian organizations and citizens of America! To all friends of Russians!</p>
   <p>On the 22d of March 1930, following the appeal in Rassviet on March 21st, appeared this article stressing even more vigorously the need for a widely patronized Russian-American People's Cooperative bank in this city, which will afford to its depositors cooperative membership, with shares of $15, $10 capital, $5 reserve capital. Total capital $200,000, $100,000 reserve capital.</p>
   <p>The appeal holds forth the benefits from such a bank to members, - better food products for less money, comfortable dwellings at reasonable cost, <pb facs="5423967_2_1027.jpg" n="2"/>then the great possibilities for a broad program in the fields of education, art, science, histrionics, community problems, all, of course, on a Russian foundation, with ample nourishment for the Russian language through all these activities, and for the Russian culture.</p>
   <p>The financial advantages to the depositors of such a bank seem only too obvious to its founders as compared with other finance institutions.</p>
   <p>This bank "will be controlled by a general assembly of all stockholders. The People's Cooperative Bank cannot operate on the stock exchange, will not, cannot support speculations. It will work and keep in touch with tens of thousands small tradesmen, and will therefore not risk nor disfranchise its depositors."</p>
   <p>The appeal stresses the absolute necessity to keep this institution free from politics, quibbles, discords, etc., for this bank is equally devoted to workmen, traders, intellectuals, as long as they realize that this institution can be maintained only by their own efforts. "The bank enemy is also <pb facs="5423967_2_1028.jpg" n="3"/>our enemy when he brings in his individual hobbies for law of his own political, racial or other conflicts, foisting them on this cooperative institution. Our friends are those who will leave all that behind and will come to us with a pure heart for cooperative work." Follows the concluding avowal of faith in the Russian colony, that it will "flock to the cooperative for membership."</p>
   <p>Good luck.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
