<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Society of Workers in the Arts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>,
<date when="1923-02-03">Feb. 3, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY OF WORKERS IN THE ARTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under this name there has been organized recently a sound new society the urgent need of which has been felt for a long time in our colony.</p>
   <p>The objects of this new Society are as follows:</p>
   <p>a) The drawing closer together of Russian literary men, artists, musicians and other workers in the arts residing in Chicago.</p>
   <p>b) The publishing of a monthly magazine devoted to literature and art.</p>
   <p>c) The staging of theatrical performances, the arrangement of exhibitions, of readings of literary works, of evening parties with musical and vocal programs, of lectures, readings of essays and papers, etc.</p>
   <p>d) The discovery and development from among the members of the Society of new talents, unknown to the public.</p>
   <p>e) The creation of studios.</p>
   <p>f) The creation of a nook where the members of the Society, as well as all persons interested in art, would meet and pass their time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All persons who can be in some respect useful in the pursuing of the objects of the Society, and can further its development, are eligible to membership of the Society.</p>
   <p>The fees and dues are as follows: an entrance fee of $2, and monthly dues of fifty cents.</p>
   <p>Besides the administrative committee and the various commissions managing the internal affairs of the Society, the general assembly has organized three special committees: an editorial committee, a theatrical committee, and a committee of the fine arts.</p>
   <p>All these committees are already working assiduously at the realization of the objects of the Society, and the Russian colony of Chicago will soon witness the first fruits of their labors.</p>
   <p>The committees meet periodically when necessity arises. General assemblies of the Society are held regularly twice a month. These meetings are open to all those interested in the activites of the Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
