<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-03">Nov. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Russians Should Participate in Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-03">Nov. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE RUSSIANS SHOULD PARTICIPATE IN POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the American Constitution, all citizens of this country, the naturalized as well as the native-born, enjoy the same rights and privileges. This fact gives us Russians who have become American citizens full right to participate in the public and political life of our adopted country. To make our participation in American political life useful to our group, we should be well organized. We should then adopt that courses of political action which is most suitable to our needs. And next, we should affiliate ourselves with the American political-party whose program best answers our interests.</p>
   <p>We all know that there are two major political parties in the United States. They compete for power and for the privilege of administering the affairs of the nation. During the elections, whether Federal, state, county, or city, they wage a desperate campaign for the possession of political power. These <pb facs="5423967_2_0528.jpg" n="2"/>two parties are the Republican party and the Democratic party. The Republican party is supported mostly by big financiers, industrialists, and big merchants--all dominated by Wall Street--since the Republican party especially serves the interests of Big Business. The Democratic party derives its power chiefly from the working classes and from small businessmen and small manufacturers. The Democratic party stands for equal rights for every citizen irrespective of his economic status. The Democratic party favors proportional taxation in the Federal, state, and municipal governments.</p>
   <p>The overwhelming majority of Russian people in America belong to the working class. For this reason, the Democratic party is closer to their interests than the Republican party. During the forthcoming election, all Russians should cast their votes for the Democratic candidates, for the entire Democratic ticket.</p>
   <p>Older Russian immigrants well remember the prosperous times the American <pb facs="5423967_2_0529.jpg" n="3"/>people had during a period of continuous Democratic administration, in the years from 1912 to 1920, when Woodrow Wilson was the President. The Democratic party was then in power, and there was no economic depression of any considerable duration. Everyone had work and was earning good money. The present-day extreme exploitation of the working people--especially of women and children--was unknown then. Women and girls stayed at home, and children went to school, because the head of the family was making enough money to maintain his home without the help of his wife or children. The working people were not being robbed by the bankers, the stock-exchange brokers, the real-estate men, and other speculators. The industry and business of the entire nation were at their peak. The nation prospered, and the fortunes of its citizens flourished. Such was the condition of this country when, in the year 1921, the Republican party came into power, with Mr. Harding as President of the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
