<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Art in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN ART IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Moscow Art Theater, which won world-wide interest and fame almost at the beginning of its existence, came to America eleven years ago to show to this country the new methods of presenting theatrical plays. Several members of the party remained in this country even after the group returned to Russia. These experienced actors--every one of them with fifteen to twenty years of stage work behind him--were engaged as instructors in various American schools of drama and in art centers. Messrs. Uspiensky and Bulgakov went to New York; Mr. Boleslawski, a Pole, went to Hollywood to direct moving pictures; Mrs. Lazareva came to Chicago. Mrs Lazareva with her husband Ivan Lazarev, also a great actor, remained in Chicago after coming here with the spectacle-play, "The Miracle," produced by Reinhardt. Mr. Lazarev played the emperor in that production, Mr. and Mrs. Lazarev, with the aid of their American friends, opened an experimental theater here under the name of the "Chicago Art Theater". It was located at 410 South Michigan Avenue. This was an English-language theater <pb facs="5423967_2_1207.jpg" n="2"/>conducted according to methods and ideas borrowed from the Moscow Art Theater. Mr. Lazarev had chosen Chicago for his experimental theater as a result of a most enthusiastic reception by the public of his Russian play presented here and in Ravinia. He had organized a similar experimental theater in New York before he came to Chicago. He was assisted in his New York undertaking by Mr. N. K. Rerich, the famous Russian painter. When Mr. Lazarev joined the "Miracle" troupe on its tour through the country, Mr. and Mrs. Bulgakov took his place and Mrs. Lazareva's in New York.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Art Theater was open for seven years. The Lazarevs sacrificed themselves to the idea of creating the new art theater in America, where all drama could most easily find a new interpretation and a new way of presentation to the public. This theater offered courses of intensive training to American actors. These actors, after graduation, served as instructors in drama in many American universities and in schools of dramatic art. After two years of hard work, Mr. Lazarev <pb facs="5423967_2_1208.jpg" n="3"/>developed heart disease, and died soon afterwards. His widow carried on for five years, directing the theater and the school for instructors in acting. The Chicago Art Theater was regarded by competent authorities as the only modern institution of art offering a complete and up-to-date education in drama. The theater was closed when the economic depression and the unemployment situation made it impossible for Mrs. Lazareva to continue her beloved work.</p>
   <p>One of the most enthusiastic admirers of the Lazarevs' work in this country was Miss Jane Addams of Hull House. One of Miss Addams's relatives was with the Russian Moscow Theater for four years. When Mrs. Lazareva was forced to close her theater and her school, she was invited by Miss Addams to Hull House to continue her work there. During her eighteen months' stay at Hull House, Mrs. Lazareva was constantly in touch with hundreds of American young people anxious to learn drama in the new way.</p>
   <p>The Moscow Art Theater methods of teaching and of presenting drama have <pb facs="5423967_2_1209.jpg" n="4"/>been adopted by many American art schools, dramatic societies, and clubs.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Lazareva and her theater have had a direct influence upon the work of the Slavonic Students' Club of the University of Chicago. This club, the members of which are Russians, Poles, Czechs, Yugoslavs, and Ukrainians by birth or by descent, for the last seven years has been acquainting the American public with the treasures contributed to the world of art by the Slavonic race in the fields of music, drama, song, and dance. The Slavonic Club of the University of Chicago is also interested in acquainting the new Americans, the recent arrivals from foreign shores, and their American-born children with American life far removed from the cosmopolitan melting-pot influences of the big cities. The Club presents today the famous American play entitled "Sun-up," which pictures the life of the mountain folk of North Carolina. The play will be given today, December 8, at 8:30 in the evening at the International House auditorium, 1414 East 59th Street. The receipts of this performance will <pb facs="5423967_2_1210.jpg" n="5"/>be used for establishing a Slavonic scholarship fund at the University of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
