<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-13">Jan. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">To the Readers of Rassviet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-13">Jan. 13, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE READERS OF RASSVIET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The publishers of Rassviet appeal to all our co-workers, correspondents, readers and organizations, to take a more active part in the work of improving the contents of our publication, and in widening its circulation among the Russian masses in many places of the United States and Canada. The improvement in the contents of our newspaper will be possible only when all our correspondents in the field will look seriously after the business of supplying us with suitable and interesting material. The problem of our contributors is to explain clearly the current world events, comment upon them, and draw proper conclusions. It is also very important for this newspaper to receive material relative to the conditions in Russia, material which throws light upon the economic life, social situation, and political persecution of the people in the land of the Soviets. Our field correspondents also have the task of maintaining close contact with the local Russian colony in any given city, town or farm, and of reporting happenings, conditions and changes not only within the colony, but also in shops, factories and other places of work. The wide variety of <pb facs="5423967_2_1646.jpg" n="2"/>colorful manifestations of Russian life in many American cities and towns is not known to the readers of our newspaper, because of the poor reporting service of our Russian newspapers. Therefore, it is necessary for our correspondents to penetrate into every corner of the Russian colony, observing everything worth observing and reporting it immediately to Rassviet. All correspondence should be brief and clear, with emphasis on the facts and the circumstances that caused them. The correspondents should always be impartial and should not distort facts. As a rule, the correspondents, stress the negative side of the life our group, forgetting that the colony has its positive side, its strong points, which are frequently overlooked by our Russian press. The better portion of our colony spares no efforts in directing all our public plans and activities into the progressive channel of thought, as the best road toward their realization.</p>
   <p>In the United States and in Canada there live many Russian farmers of whose life and activities there is never any mention in the Russian papers. Our correspondents would do well to cover this field; their objective description of the life, conditions and affairs of the Russian farmer in the United States and <pb facs="5423967_2_1647.jpg" n="3"/>in Canada would be most welcome material to our readers. Some of the Russian farm colonies have a long history, but they live in isolation, and no one knows about them. Let's take, for instance, the Dukhobors, who have lived in Canada several score years. The majority of them live in close-knit communities, preserving their customs and sect regulations. Yet to this day not a single member of the Dukhobor community has ever tried to send to Rassviet even the briefest historical sketch of their life and development throughout these years on Canadian soil. There are also Russian Colonies and farming communities in California and in North Dakota. We do not hear much of them, and yet the news of them would be of immense interest to this newspaper and its readers.</p>
   <p>The organizations connected with our publication, those who sympathize with our work, and also all our readers should start to work seriously to expand the circulation of our newspaper. The field is broad everywhere--in cities, in towns, on the farms, wherever there are the Russian people. This publication is not conducted for financial gain, and it is not a private business <pb facs="5423967_2_1648.jpg" n="4"/>enterprise. Rassviet has always pursued, and intends to pursue in the future, the purely cultural and progressive aims which are bound to bring the greatest amount of happiness and well-being to the greatest number of people. On the pages of Rassviet, as in a mirror, there have been reflected thoughts, views and opinions of the more advanced part of our Russian group, which has always tried to bring within the reach of the masses a better, richer life. This newspaper will continue in the future to follow the same course, safeguarding to persons of different views and convictions the right, and affording them the opportunity, to publicly express their opinions on various public questions.</p>
   <p>Rassviet is a true beacon, showing the way to social justice. We live in dark and threatening times, when the world is overhung with black clouds of reaction --communism from the left, fascism from the right. We must counteract these two movements, to prevent them from extinguishing the torch of truth and that liberty which was passed on to us by former generations. We came to this world not to spread lies and deceit, and not to exploit or enslave one another, but <pb facs="5423967_2_1649.jpg" n="5"/>to fight all lies and evils in whatever form they may appear. Our newspaper has always served as a weapon with the aid of which the progressive part of our Russian group here has combated all the dark forces obstructing the light of truth and justice.</p>
   <p>We must display the greatest amount of energy and must do much actual work before we can celebrate the common friendship, solidarity and enlightenment of the working masses. It is sad, but there are still great numbers of people living in complete ignorance. The common ideal has not yet reached their consciousness, and they continue to live outside the Russian colony and outside the beneficial influences of our organized life. Into this lagging portion of our Russian community it is necessary to carry light by means of the printed and the spoken word. It is hard work, but it must be done, for without the education of the masses it is impossible to rebuild life according to the principles of justice and liberty. Only with the aid of education will it be possible to attain a more sensible and enlightened life. This problem, as it relates to our Russian group in America, can be successfully solved only with <pb facs="5423967_2_1650.jpg" n="6"/>the aid of all our readers--only if they become sufficiently interested in this question of the education of the Russian masses in America. One way of helping the cause is to spread the newspaper Rassviet among all your friends and acquaintances, and secure new subscribers to our publication.</p>
   <p>We advise all our Russian organizations, contributors, correspondents and readers to exert a serious common effort to accomplish this important and urgent task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
