<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title><date when="1929-09-07">Sep. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title><date when="1929-09-07">Sep. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The monthly Russkoye Obozrenie becomes a weekly newspaper. Instead of appearing once a month, there will be four editions. Quietly and calmly, without display and clamorous advertising, we have changed to a weekly publication with only one thought in mind - to serve the Russian colony dutifully.</p>
   <p>Whether we perform our task successfully or not, it is for our readers to judge. And we earnestly beg everyone to show us frankly and open mindedly our faults and shortcomings in the Russkoye Obozrenie; to point out our errors and to express desire for improvements of any kind.</p>
   <p>Every word of our reader or his wish will be taken into consideration, and all advice will be judged, and then we will gradually take the proper steps in improvement if such steps are timely and appropriate.</p>
   <p>Most of the attention of the Russkoye Obozrenie will be devoted to the life of our colony and our native land. We will not force the sections "Colony" and "Russia" into some unnoticeable corner on the last page. We will give these sections select spots and place them on the front page.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1689.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And after all, that is what offers the greatest interest to us, immigrants from Russia, who find ourselves in an alien country. And to chase it somewhere into the back yard means to shut our eyes to the life of our colony, paying no attention to its interests and needs. This, of course, is what we least wish for the Russkoye Obozrenie.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
