<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-01">Nov. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Russians Should Vote for the Candidates of the Democratic Party</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-01">Nov. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE RUSSIANS SHOULD VOTE FOR THE CANDIDATES OF THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because President Roosevelt is a Democrat and the defender of the common people;</p>
   <p>Because our President needs supporters who hold views similar to his and who would look after the interests of the people, not after the interests of the Morgans and the Mellons;</p>
   <p>Because the Republican party espouses the principle that capital should rule over the people, while the Democratic party believes that the people should rule over capital; (We Russians belong to the working class, not to the capitalist class; therefore, the Democratic party is our party.)</p>
   <p>Because President Roosevelt, has abolished Prohibition and has stopped the <pb facs="5423967_2_0531.jpg" n="2"/>thoughtless spending of millions of dollars to maintain Prohibition agents, as was done during the Hoover Administration; because he has increased the government income by levying taxes on the manufacture and sale of all alcoholic products, and has created jobs for the unemployed, since the beverage industry has given work to many thousands of people heretofore idle;</p>
   <p>(The Republicans say that if they return to power they will lower taxes. But they are too late. Taxes have already been lowered by the Democrats.)</p>
   <p>Because, we know that--thanks to the efforts of the Democratic party--thousands of persons of Slavic origin have received appointments in Federal, state, county, and city administrations, and have been elected to public office, where the Slavonic race is now well represented; (If we examine the tickets of both parties, we find that the Republican ticket contains among its many candidates only one of Slavic blood, whereas on the Democratic ticket several candidates of Slavonic <pb facs="5423967_2_0532.jpg" n="3"/>extraction are listed.)</p>
   <p>For all these reasons, every Russian should support the Democratic party if he wants the Russian group in Chicago to grow stronger and to gain the recognition accorded to other Slavonic groups of the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
