<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill (Unidentified newspaper clipping between
<date when="1918-05">Feb. and May of 1918</date>)
<title level="a">Russian Committee of Chicago Cooperates in Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill (Unidentified newspaper clipping between
<date when="1918-05">Feb. and May of 1918</date>)
<title level="a">RUSSIAN COMMITTEE OF CHICAGO COOPERATES IN THIRD LIBERTY LOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This article, signed R. L. Osky, was apparently written close on the heels of G. Beskin's initial appeal. It gives an outline in some degree of the federal plan to raise the Third Liberty Loan; "The seventh Federal Region combines five states, with Chicago as their headquarters, for raising the loan. Thirty nationalities, the Russian one of them, make up the Foreign Commissions of the Committee."</p>
   <p>"... Already the Russian Commision had held several sessions with satisfactory results for the Liberty Loan..."</p>
   <p>The characteristic and remarkable thing about this committee is that in it are at work side by side "Progressives" and members of church fraternities (bratchiki), and both are equally concerned not to lag behind other nation-alities in the work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0712.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The writer further describes the tasks as they are distributed among the members of the several commissions, some to contact organizations, others to look after publicity, still others to contact banks, churches, also large institutions. Central points have been set up and the local General Consul, A. Volkov, being a member of the committee, offered the Russian Embassy offices as one of the centers to sell bonds, distribute literature ...." the Chicago Russian organizations are busily at work. "The Russian club Znaniye (Knowledge) ruled that each club member obtain a bond, and a special commission was appointed in connection with it. At the opening of its new quarters, Obshchestvo Prosveshcheniaya (Society for Englightenment) sold $600 worth of bonds for the Third Liberty Loan. Besides, the Russians buy these bonds also in banks and in factories. Dr. H. Krasnow is chairman. He is also in charge of several sub-committees in this work. Beskin is secretary. Others participating in the committees are G. Korablinov, I. Erin, I. Prilla, Dr. N. Spiegelglas, G. Kane, A. Louis, J. Solyanski, Russian Consul Volkov, G. Lazareff, A. Lutnitski, N. Klekner, and M. Polak.</p>
   <p>The article mentions that a mass meeting is contemplated with very popular <pb facs="5423967_2_0713.jpg" n="3"/>speakers from New York, possibly also with Messrs. I. Okuntsov and Count E. Tolstoy or A. Bublikov.</p>
   <p>In conclusion the writer stresses that by working energetically for the loan the Russian colony is helping its fatherland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
