<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Manifestation of the Russian Independent Society</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MANIFESTATION OF THE RUSSIAN INDEPENDENT SOCIETY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian and Ukrainian independent societies showed their power on June 3, 1917, in a parade in which 3,000 persons marched. Passing with flags and banners to the sounds of a march through the Northwest side, they had their massmeeting at Wicker Park Hall. Among the orators were the priests Nikolenko and Popel.</p>
   <p>It is consoling to hear a call to the people from a priest, begging complete unification for the support of the Provisional government of Russia in its hard task. Only a priest who is connected with the Independent Society can say (such words as) "the government of the people, for the people; liberty, equality and brotherhood, freedom of religion; the separation of the church from the government; land to the peasants," etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0429.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A not less vigorous speech was made by an American, Clarence Darrow, who said:</p>
   <p>"I greet you here, Russians, brothers of those who have cast off the yoke of tsarism in Russia - brothers of those who made Russia one of the freest countries in the world. Do not forget, comrades, that new free Russia in two months did more for its people than other countries have done in the whole history of their existence. It freed hundreds of thousands of political criminals in Siberia from forced labor and prisons; it proclaimed full freedom of speech, press, conscience and unions; it promised land to those who till it, and (it) makes all necessary preparations for a speedy convocation of a constituent assembly, elected by general and equal suffrage.</p>
   <p>"And this," continued Darrow, "was made by Russia, which everywhere <pb facs="5423967_2_0430.jpg" n="3"/>they used to call a country of barbarians. There was a time when on all favorable occasions they used to point to Russia. When a policeman was rude to somebody they used to say, He acts as they do in Russia; but time has come when in Petrograd on such occasions they can say, He acts as they do in America.</p>
   <p>"I am against war because it is horrible, but all victims of the present war were redeemed by the freedom attained by Russia. I wish that this war would continue till the full liberation of the whole world."</p>
   <p>Among other things there was an interesting concert program, in which the following participated: Madame Grinevezkaya, the Ukrainian Chorus, Mr. Pokatilov, and others.</p>
   <p>Starik</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
