<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Greetings to Mr. Rerich</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREETINGS TO MR. RERICH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having just learned of the arrival in New York from India on March 14 on the S. S. Paris of Mr. [Nichlas]Rerich, our venerable painter and one of the great leaders in the realm of world culture, Rassviet sends him cordial greetings.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rerich, whose name and works have been honored by the American people by the establishment of an art gallery bearing his name and containing over one thousand of his canvases, is not only a powerful and tireless painter and profound thinker but also an outstanding authority on the Orient, where he spent more than ten years of his life. He has returned to this country after a four-year absence.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rerich is the originator and first member of the international peace society known as the "Banner of Peace." Thirty-four nations were represented at the recent third international conference of this society in Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>He is a preacher of the highest human ideals. His peace appeals to the world and his "Peace through Culture" movement have brought wonderful responses from <pb facs="5423967_2_1188.jpg" n="2"/>all corners of the globe.</p>
   <p>Our newspaper, which last year published a number of articles written by Mr. Rerich, and which devoted several reviews to his latest book, "The Flaming Stronghold," now welcomes our great artist back to America.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Nicolas Rerich, noted contemporary Russian painter, for over five years was a member of the editorial staff of Rassviet, and his articles were very popular among the Russian group here.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
