<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1930-03-21">Mar. 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A Russian-American Peoples Cooperative Bank in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1930-03-21">Mar. 21, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A RUSSIAN-AMERICAN PEOPLES COOPERATIVE BANK IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A vigorous appeal appeared in Rassviet on March 3, 1930, addressed to all Russian organizations and friends of the Russians to help establish a cooperative bank in Chicago, after the pattern of Slavyanskaya Vzaimnost (Slavic exchange) in Prague, established by the Czecho-Slovaks.</p>
   <p>This appeal starts with a vigorous notice informing all Russians that "We, the undersigned, here assembled on March 16, 1930, ruled to establish a People's Cooperative Bank in Chicago." They further proclaim that while this group, together with various Russian organizations, had the honor to be initiator of the cooperative bank, it is nevertheless fully aware of the fact that simultaneously with its own an effort to do some similar work is in full swing in the Russian communities of New York, Detroit, Seattle, San Francisco, and other United States cities with Russian communities.</p>
   <p>This bank, it is said, is to cater primarily to the Russian workmen, peasants, and intellectual workers. They will keep their savings in the bank, and by <pb facs="5423967_2_1030.jpg" n="2"/>so doing they will also enjoy such cooperative membership benefits as cheaper and better food products, sanitary homes at reasonable cost, decent restaurants and dining rooms, and numerous other benefits secured through cooperative membership, because they are depositors in the Russian-American People's Cooperative Bank. This institution would also cater to merchants and small tradesmen. It would concern itself with Russian culture, Russian language, a people's university, the stage, sports. All this would be organized "to develop and prosper only if we ourselves would warm up to the idea of a people's cooperative bank." It is further pointed out that to neglect the establishing of such an institution is not only a loss of the mentioned privileges, but also is a risk of entrusting hard earned pennies to unsafe keeping.</p>
   <p>The bank, it is said, must be on a strictly cooperative basis, and all partisan or factional differences must be completely discarded as far as membership in this cooperative bank of $200,000 capital and $100,000 reserve capital. Each share to be $15 denomination, of which ten is capital and five reserve capital. This is the smallest denomination permissible in Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1031.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The founders of the cooperative bank express their profound concern for each and every co-member irrespective of how big a stock holder he may be, the objective being primarily to have every Russian, and sympathizer as a stockholder in the Russian-American People's Cooperative Bank.</p>
   <p>In the end this appeal avows its perfect faith in the Russian colony and its sympathizers, and its belief that all will flock to the Russian-American People's Cooperative Bank for membership, leaving behind all political and factional differences. It is further indicated that, in compliance with state regulations in Illinois, this bank is established as an independent, self-supporting institution, "although in sentiment or spirit it is but a part of the work which is now in process in other centers of United States ,Canada, and Europe."</p>
   <p>The founders aver that they will take all necessary measures "to actually coordinate and unify our work for the benefit of all."</p>
   <p>Names of Founders: P. Alekzeiyev, V. Antziferov (cooperator), Mr. Augustinovich, engineer; V. Bekker (cooperator), Bortoshevic, engineer; V. Bernard, <pb facs="5423967_2_1032.jpg" n="4"/>G. Volos, D. Vorobei, G. Golski, P. Grigaitis (Editor of Lithuanian paper), N. Gribov, Attorney Zissman, E. Goroshenya (chairman P. W. P.), E. Denisov, I.Yerin (chairman of the society Znanie), B. Joffe, Dr. H. R. Krasnow, V. Kunashevski, E. Karpin, N, Kozak, V. Kishun, engineer; E. Lavator, M. Levata, V. S. Mansvetov (chairman of the department of SS-Savings Bank in Prague, Czecho-slovakia), P. Morezki, D. Michalchik (president, St. George Brotherhood), U. Mikhalovskaya, S. Mikhalovski, Dr. A. Nedzelnitski, E. Neishul, V. Oleinik, Dr. L. Pertzov, Attorney U. Pikiel, G. Petruchik, A. S. Pristupa (president Trinity Brotherhood:, A. Pasiuk, V. Pustovoitov, engineer, O. Slioznik, V. Sabinski, M. Siman, D. Svenchanski, engineer; Fedukevich, R. Churovich, agricultural expert; K. Shulokov.</p>
   <p>Temporary address 2732 Warren Blvd, Chicago. Tel. Seely 4731.</p>
   <p>Provisional Management of the Russian-American People's Cooperative Bank.</p>
   <p>B. Kishun, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
