<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-20">Feb. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Mortality. Among American Workers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-20">Feb. 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">MORTALITY. AMONG AMERICAN WORKERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federal Bureau of Health has published some interesting data concerning the mortality among workers in ten principal states of the Union. From this data it is evident that the unskilled laborer, besides earning less than the qualified [skilled] worker, has a shorter span of life. The longevity of workers earning their livelihood by pick and shovel is about half that of workers who learned a trade. Such are the conclusions drawn by the Federal Bureau of Health.</p>
   <p>Agriculture, according to the data of the same Bureau, is the most healthful occupation. This only confirms the truth of the adage: The closer man is to nature, the healthier he is and the longer he lives. For example, out of every thousand between the ages of 15 and 64, there die annually; from among the farmers only 6.2; from professional men, only 7; from among <pb facs="5423967_2_0978.jpg" n="2"/>the merchant class the rate rises to 7.4; from the skilled workers, 9.9; and, from the unskilled laborers it rises abruptly to 13.1, or almost double that of professional men.</p>
   <p>The Federal Bureau of Health claims that the high mortality rate among the unskilled laborers is due to undernourishment, bad living conditions, lack of proper and adequate medical attention, and other factors existing because of their low earning power. This is particularly true in respect to mortality from consumption, pneumonia, and accidents. Thus, the statistics about consumption revealed the mortality per thousand as: 46.5 among farmers; 72.1 among skilled workers; and, 184.9 among unskilled laborers. From pneumonia, the mortality per thousand was: among farmers, 46.5; among skilled and professional men, 59.7; and among unskilled laborers, 51.7. This statistical data covers such industrially developed states as New York, Illinois, New Jersey, and Ohio.</p>
   <p>Through a series of researches made during the past several years, it was <pb facs="5423967_2_0979.jpg" n="3"/>established that the demand for unskilled labor continues to decline from year to year. New, improved machinery and tools, new materials and production methods require skilled men more or less. One of the American economists quite truthfully remarks: "The demand is growing not for hands, but for heads." This is the reason why many economists think that every man nowadays needs special training.</p>
   <p>The data on the various mortality rates show conclusively that the worker with professional training lives better and longer than the common laborer. Moreover, it is not difficult to learn a trade in America, for there are free trade schools and courses in every industrial city or town.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
