<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">State Undertakings in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">By E. Moravsky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-27">Apr. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">STATE UNDERTAKINGS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">By E. Moravsky</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many American economists consider that the industrial crisis cannot be overcome unless planned economy is introduced, or until a form of state--rather, government--capitalism is established, with the government regulating production, consumption, working hours, wages, trade and other phases of human endeavor. Private interests, claim these economists, also could regulate all these matters, but they do not do so because they think only of their personal gain, forgetting entirely the well-being of society as a whole. And, if this is so, the state must take over and run the industries so that there would no longer be any industrial stagnation or unemployment.</p>
   <p>Those who defend private enterprise--rather, those who defend the existing order of things--say that state control of industrial enterprise will not bring <pb facs="5423967_2_0036.jpg" n="2"/>the needed results. They point to the present-day Russia, where the government controls not only all industrial enterprise but also all the economic life in the country, and say that the economic condition of the people has not improved, but on the contrary, has grown steadily worse. Even though everybody works, nobody, except the Communists, has even enough bread, clothes, shoes, or other articles of the first necessity. This is the situation in a country where totalitarian state capitalism dominates the entire economic life of the people and where private enterprise has been entirely done away with. Quite erroneously, of course, many people consider this form of government as socialism or communism.</p>
   <p>One of the most violent opponents to the state capitalism is W. M. Pearsons, a well-known American economist, who lists in his book, "Government Business Experiments", practically all government enterprises that have existed in the United States from the beginning of the last century up to the year 1933.</p>
   <p>From his book it can be clearly seen that the government in this country <pb facs="5423967_2_0037.jpg" n="3"/>at one time or another had control over numerous business enterprises, and that these state controlled businesses brought nothing, but great losses. [Translator's note: In the two succeeding paragraphs, which are omitted by the translator, the author lists the names of the government controlled enterprises, giving the time when they existed, their capitalization and the losses they incurred].</p>
   <p>All these enterprises either went bankrupt or were sold to private individuals. Some of them simply went to rot. According to Mr. Pearsons there were only a few government undertakings which were able to cover their expenses. A great majority of them were run at a loss.</p>
   <p>From all this the author draws the conclusion that under state capitalism in the United States, just as in Russia, the economic conditions of the people, instead of improving, would grow worse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
