<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-25">Aug. 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Many Thanks to the Russians in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-25">Aug. 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MANY THANKS TO THE RUSSIANS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League in Chicago expresses its profound gratitude to all Russians in Chicago and vicinity who were present at the Russian picnic last Sunday, August 19. We also extend our thanks to all the members of the League and to all our friends who helped to organize the picnic and were instrumental in making it a great success.</p>
   <p>Let us remark, first of all, that in the entire history of our group in Chicago we have never witnessed such a great public demonstration of our unity and of our power. More than five thousand persons took part in the picnic, and thus showed the Americans that we Russians are not behind other national groups when it comes to displaying our group solidarity or giving general support to any undertaking in which our national honor is involved.</p>
   <p>Many prominent persons in Chicago's political life were present at the picnic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mayor Kelly was represented by Mr. Clayton Smith, one of the outstanding members of the city administration, and a member of the Cook County Board of Commissioners, Two congressmen, Mr. [A. J.] Sabath and Mr. Schuetz, sent telegrams wishing success to the enterprise. The following public officials were also present at the picnic: Otto Kerner, Attorney General of the State of Illinois; Robert M. Sweitzer, county clerk; [C. J.] Vopicka, former United States envoy to Rumania; Mr. Link, manager of the city properties; Mr. Miroslawski, assistant State's attorney; Mr. Ketzlik, chairman of the Czech press bureau; Mr. Skriba, representing the Slovak organizations; Mr. Vroytzik, representing the Jugoslav organizations; Mr. Sluk, representing the Ukrainian Democratic Party; and many others.</p>
   <p>Almost all the leaders of the Slavonic groups in Chicago were there to express their happiness at our success. They praised highly the musical portion of the program, which consisted of a concert given by the Russian Cossack Chorus and the Carpatho-Ruthenian Chorus.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0562.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many thanks to you Russian people in Chicago and its suburbs. By your presence at the picnic you have strengthened our political position in Chicago, and you have enabled the Russian-American Democratic League to help you and your children in the future. The American political leaders attending our picnic have obtained a strong impression of our unity and potential political power. They will judge us accordingly, and will treat us according to our merits. Thus the Russian-American Democratic League feels that its efforts expended in organizing the picnic have not been wasted. Our young generation will be the chief beneficiary of all our broadly planned and well-executed actions on behalf of the Russian group in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
