<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1918-01-18">Jan. 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Project of the Constitution and By-Laws of the Russian Social-Democratic Club</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1918-01-18">Jan. 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PROJECT OF THE CONSTITUTION AND BY-LAWS OF THE RUSSIAN SOCIAL-DEMOCRATIC CLUB</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. The Russian Social-Democratic Club has for its object:</p>
   <p>(a) The unification of all Social-Democratic Mensheviki of Chicago and suburbs on a basis of fellowship,</p>
   <p>(b) The propaganda of Social-Democratic ideas and of methods of organization and tactics of Menshevism among the masses of the Russian colony, and</p>
   <p>(c) The lending of moral and material support to the Consolidated Russian Social-Democratic Party.</p>
   <p>2. In order to realize the objectives mentioned above the Club</p>
   <p>(a) organizes independently, or in cooperation with other kindred <pb facs="5423967_2_0364.jpg" n="2"/>labor organizations, lectures, readings of papers on different subjects, talks, public discussions, meetings, circles for the furthering of self-education, and socialistic schools;</p>
   <p>(b) orders, or publishes independently, popular Socialist literature to be circulated widely among the masses;</p>
   <p>(c) participates as far as possible in all manifestations of the public life of the Russian colony of America.</p>
   <p>3. Any person accepting the program of the Consolidated Russian Social-Democratic Party and ready to take the pledge of submitting to the decisions of the guiding institutions of the party can become a member of the club.</p>
   <p>4. A recommendation is required from those who apply for membership <pb facs="5423967_2_0365.jpg" n="3"/>in the club and, in case of absence of seriously motivated protests against the admission of the applicant, he is considered as admitted, if the majority of the members in session vote for his admission.</p>
   <p>5. The funds of the club consist of profits derived from cultural and educational enterprises, donations, collections and fees and dues.</p>
   <p>6. The fees and dues are subdivided into monthly dues and membership fees. Monthly dues are 15 cents per month, and membership fees are 25 cents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
