<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Belorusskaya Tribuna (White Russian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1931-03-30">March 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Life of White Russians in America Anton Cermak and White Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <!--                    <catRef target="#grp-white russian"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
     <item>WHITE RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Belorusskaya Tribuna (White Russian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1931-03-30">March 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE LIFE OF WHITE RUSSIANS IN AMERICA ANTON CERMAK AND WHITE RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anton Cermak, president of the Cook County Board of Trustees, is one of the two candidates for mayor of Chicago in the coming election of April 7th.</p>
   <p>Anton Cermak is an old friend of the White Russians, whom he came to know during the last presidential campaign in 1928. At that time the White Russians supported the candidacies of Alfred Smith for President of the United States, and Anton Cermak for senator. Anton Cermak is of Czech origin, and came as a lad to the New World. He began his career as a miner, and today he holds one of the most outstanding positions among the politicians of Illinois, and particularly in our giant city, Chicago.</p>
   <p>At present a goodly half of the Chicago population of several million people is fighting to see him elected as mayor of this city. Particularly <pb facs="5423967_2_0580.jpg" n="2"/>hot is the fight of the Slavic races, and of those Americans (Democrats as well as Republicans) who wish to bring about a change in the city's administration, who thirst for reforms, who are eager to exterminate abuse, to re-establish the good name of our city, etc.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that, if elected, Anton Cermak will prove himself capable of being at the summit of his new post. His entire past activity speaks in his favor, and, with his election the White Russians will have the opportunity to come out in the open, struggling as they are in an effort to protect their interests from being trampled upon.</p>
   <p>The most outstanding representatives of the White Russian colony fervently support the slogan: Anton Cermak, the next Mayor of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
