<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Approaching Mayoralty Elections in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE APPROACHING MAYORALTY ELECTIONS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, April 2, the election for mayor of the city of Chicago will be held. In this connection the central committee of the Democratic party opened headquarters of the National party at 155 North Clark Street, on the second floor. Mr. V. A. Kishun, state highway engineer, was appointed to take charge of the office. He invited a number of Russians to assist him in the conduct of the campaign. Among the Russians named were P. Chopko, I. Stakovich, K. Tana-schuk, I. Artemenko, I. Kalinaka, P. Rozdelsky and T. Tureyko. All these men are now working to re-elect the present Democratic mayor, Edward Kelly.</p>
   <p>The election next Tuesday will only serve to demonstrate the power of the Democratic party in Chicago and the popularity enjoyed by Mr. Kelly among the people in the city. The Mayor was actually re-elected during the primaries, when the people cast over five hundred thousand votes for him, a number unprecedented in the political history of the city.</p>
   <p>Next Tuesday this figure is expected to be increased considerably, as Mr. Kelly's opponents--Republican and independent candidates--enjoy no popularity and do not <pb facs="5423967_2_0522.jpg" n="2"/>possess enough ability to run a large city.</p>
   <p>Mayor Kelly, who was born into a poor family, created a good name for himself while working as a civil engineer in the Sanitary District. He revealed himself as a very able executive, and for that reason was appointed mayor on A. Cermak's death. In selecting him for this high office the Democratic party made no error. Mayor Kelly proved his ability in the new capacity also, and this explains his immense popularity among the people.</p>
   <p>Though less than two years has passed since he was appointed mayor, Kelly has managed to re-establish the financial reputation of the city. He has lowered the city taxes; he has reduced administrative expenses by fifty per cent; he has paid the back wages of the city employees to the tune of eighteen million dollars; and all this has been done without imposing and additional taxes.</p>
   <p>Mayor Kelly saved the Chicago schools from a financial crash. He managed to pay the back salaries of teachers. He re-established the good name of the city by carrying out an intensive fight against criminal elements, in which he reduced <pb facs="5423967_2_0523.jpg" n="3"/>the number of crimes by twenty-six per cent. He revived industrial activity in the city, established strict sanitary inspection over the sales of milk, and introduced a number of measures designed to benefit the entire population of Chicago.</p>
   <p>All nationalities support the candidacy of Mayor Kelly; so it is the duty of all Russian-American Democrats and those who sympathize with the Democratic party to elect a good and able mayor by casting their votes for Edward Kelly next Tuesday.</p>
   <p>If the Russians desire recognition in the political life of the city, and from the mayor, this can be secured only by participating in the coming elections, because each precinct captain and each ward committeeman always keep track of the number of votes cast in each precinct and each ward, and they know what nationalities cast the votes.</p>
   <p>V. A. Kishun,</p>
   <p>Manager of the Russian</p>
   <p>Branch of the Central Committee</p>
   <p>of the Democratic Party</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
