<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Our Best Wishes for Rassviet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-08">Dec. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">OUR BEST WISHES FOR RASSVIET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On this day of joyful commemoration of the tenth anniversary of Rassviet, the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society conveys its hearty greetings to this, the only Russian publication in Chicago. We wish Rassviet will pursue in the future the same unwavering straightforwardness and vigor in defending the Russian Cause in this country that it has displayed in the past.</p>
   <p>Rassviet plays a tremendously important role in the life of the Chicago Russian colony. Without Rassviet, all local Russian activity would cease. Praise and honor to the tireless Rassviet workers who have been faithful to the ideal of public service, who for ten years have been serving the people to the best of their ability under the most trying conditions!</p>
   <p>In all these years, Rassviet has always been true to its ideals and <pb facs="5423967_2_1602.jpg" n="2"/>straightforward in all its actions. Many times, when the newspaper found itself in difficulties, its workers worked overtime without asking for any extra remuneration; they even reduced their own wages to make it easier for the publication to carry on during the trying times. Having always in view the public good above all other considerations. Rassviet has fought, and will continue to fight, all enemies of the Russian people, particularly the Bolsheviks, frequently even to the extent of harming its own interests and its own financial position.</p>
   <p>The Russian independent Mutual Aid Society--always responsive to everything which is good and useful to the Russian people--has always closely cooperated with Rassviet. The Independent Society has often extended its aid to the publishers of Rassviet, even to the extent of becoming a sort of co-publisher of this newspaper. The future of the Russian colony in Chicago depends upon the closest co-operation of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society and the Rassviet Publishing Company, the two largest Russian institutions <pb facs="5423967_2_1603.jpg" n="3"/>in Chicago. The successful future of either of these two organizations depends upon mutual close understanding and co-ordinated action. Both these organizations serve one and the same ideal; their common aim is service to the Russian people. Therefore, all the efforts of the enemies of these two institutions to separate them and tear them asunder will fail.</p>
   <p>The Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, as well as Rassviet, strives to unite all Russian people in America, to educate them and make them more accessible to art and culture, thus making their lives in this country fuller, happier, and more useful. We deeply believe that, after rallying around the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society, and with the support of the enlarged, more powerful Russian newspaper Rassviet, the Russian group in America will emerge unto a new, brighter, and wider road leading to a better life and success.</p>
   <p>All members of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society join us in offering <pb facs="5423967_2_1604.jpg" n="4"/>you our best wishes and felicitations on your tenth anniversary. We wish you many more years of successful work among the Russian people.</p>
   <p>Rassviet will hold its Tenth Anniversary Banquet on January 27, 1935. At this banquet, we shall all meet and have a heart-to-heart chat, and we shall have a good time together, forgetting all our worries and trusting that better days will come for Rassviet and for our organization. Our power lies in our unity. We are all brothers, all Russians. And every Russian should join the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
   <p>The Board of Directors of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
