<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-09-20">September 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">On the Wrong Path</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1927-09-20">September 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE WRONG PATH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago the American Federation of Labor held its closing session. The representatives of the workers organizations were discussing matters that had nothing to do with labor. Instead of considering the situation of the labor market and discussing the immediate problems arising out of this situation, the delegates suddenly began to talk about the next presidential candidacy and, like real patriots, nominated to this office the mayor of Chicago, Mr. W. Thompson. Such a decision is comical and sad. Comical because nobody in the political spheres would ever get to the White House; sad because such a decision has no place in the program of a convention of labor organizations. The workers have to discuss plenty of questions own which cannot be deferred. The question about the president, however, was innocent in comparison with the resolution which was adopted before closing the convention. This resolution was directed against <pb facs="5423967_2_0684.jpg" n="2"/>the pacifists and radically-minded workers. During the debates about this question one of the most ardent partisans of this resolution was the president of the Builders' Union, Mr. Samuel Luso, - the same Luso who categorically refused to protest against the execution of Sacco and Vanzetti. This friend of the workers thundered against all those who condemn war and preach brotherhood and love among humanity.</p>
   <p>"There is only one way to secure peace," cried Luso, "and that is the Army and Navy." Having repeated this old but very wrong adage about the way of preserving peace, Mr. Luso declared that all persons who are against imperialistic war are practically destroying the morals of the workers. According to Mr. Luso one should think that Leo Tolstoy was a great immoralist because he condemned all <pb facs="5423967_2_0685.jpg" n="3"/>fratricide, and that the Kaiser was a great moralist because he was always ready to make war. From the resolution it is seen that the workers must be staunch partisans of war if they want to preserve their morality as workers. Here we have two grave mistakes; one of a mortal nature, the other has to do with class interests. It has been known for a long time that morals and fratricide are two incompatible things. If war is defended by capitalists and imperialists, one can understand it. War for them is necessary and advantageous. But if imperialistic war is defended by the workers, it is altogether inconceivable how they can do it. The workers in an imperialistic war lose a lot and gain nothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
