<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-10-26">Oct. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From the Conference of Russian Socialist Organizations in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-10-26">Oct. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CONFERENCE OF RUSSIAN SOCIALIST ORGANIZATIONS IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In answer to the address of the conference to persons who had suffered from the illegal actions of the authorities in connection with the mobilization, the conference received hundreds of letters and continues to receive daily from fifteen to twenty letters. In spite of the great deal of work the conference did not employ any paid labor. But even though the workers are not paid, funds are required for the work. For example, the conference issued questionnaires to be filled out by the sufferers. The filled-out copies of the questionnaires are sent to the Ministery of War at the Russian Embassy. From all the letters it was clear that the majority had suffered mainly from ignorance of the laws and regulations about mobilization, therefore the conference decided to print and distribute without charge, in Russian and other languages, a pamphlet explaining what the Russian <pb facs="5423967_2_0719.jpg" n="2"/>citizens-conscripts should know. The pamphlet is being prepared for printing. In order to print it funds are required again. But the conference has not any money for that purpose. In order to be able to continue this work, the conference decided to organize a special fund. We call upon all those who find our work necessary to help us. If help does not reach us in time we will not be able to continue the work or be able to issue the pamphlet. We call upon the organizations and individuals to contribute to our special fund for the protection of Russian citizens as much as possible, and send it immediately. Checks and money-orders should be made out in the name of the cashier of the conference, A. Liakhowich, Chicago, but send them to the financial secretary, M. Korolko, 2736 W. 15th Place, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>All inquiries and all the correspondence for the conference should be sent to the new address of the corresponding secretary, M. A. Stolar, 2507 W. Division St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>With greetings,</p>
   <p>The Conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
