<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1926-12-18">Dec. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Twins</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-12-18">Dec. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TWINS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This editorial is devoted to the comparison of Fascism and Communism. The author of the editorial finds that these two political and social systems, though arch-enemies, have some important characteristics in common - hence the title of the editorial, "Twins." Basing his assertions on the views of Turati, the leader of the Italian Socialists, the writer of the editorial quotes the words of the latter, who maintains that if the Italians had real freedom, the Fascists would not remain in power even for twenty-four hours. According to Turati, the Italian Fascists succeed in keeping the political power in their hands only because they pitilessly persecute and confine in prisons all their most dangerous political enemies. The population is terrorized and is afraid to show any discontent, as those who dare to do so are in danger of losing their jobs and often also their liberty. Freedom of press, speech, and of creating free labor and other organizations <pb facs="5423967_2_0273.jpg" n="2"/>has been abolished. Even in his own home the Italian is not secure from the invasions of the Fascists. It looks as if every Italian had become a Fascist; but it looks so only because everything that does not bear the official Fascist stamp has been eliminated, and the population is afraid to voice any protest.</p>
   <p>The author of the editorial compares this state of affairs with the conditions existing in Communist Russia and finds that, though in some respects the two systems are very different, yet - in one important respect at least - they are quite similar, namely, in their utter contempt of all political freedom and of the rights of the individual, who in both cases becomes the slave of a despotic government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
