<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XI, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. Novy Mir, New York,
<date when="1918-02">February, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Scandal in a Good Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XI, owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. Novy Mir, New York,
<date when="1918-02">February, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A SCANDAL IN A GOOD FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This letter, signed R. Bobrova, gives a picture in vivid colors of the well-to-do Russian professionals and other ranks of material contentment in the Russian emigres of Chicago, who were long since practically severed from Russia. At the first tidings from Russia of the debacle there, they found it in themselves to organize the "Friends of Russian Democracy." These thoroughly acclimated folks could find nothing to do except to be bored to tears at lectures and meetings held at regular intervals, enlivened only by petty scandals.</p>
   <p>"I have often wondered," says the writer, "why these people called themselves 'Friends of Russian Democracy'; what is there in common between these Americanized, prosperous 'intelligentsia' and Russian democracy; often it seemed to me that 'Foes of Russian Democracy' <pb facs="5423967_2_0361.jpg" n="2"/>would be the better name. It is, indeed, hard to distinguish friends from enemies."</p>
   <p>The chronic boredom of these "friends" took a sharp turn with the arrival of Professor Lomonosov and Mr. Fabian, who told them of Russia's hard times, the dire need for immediate material aid, which tale of woe inspired them with the happy thought to become transformed from "Friends of Russian Democracy" into a "Shoe Society." They will send shoes to Russia. This society took in many new friends, all of the cream of society, including benevolent ladies. A very brilliant gathering took place on February 13, - "many low-necked dresses, many glistening bald heads, floods of light, and altogether in the style of the bon ton." A certain dignitary from New York addressed this sparkling gathering on the shoe famine in Russia, and all went well, writes Bobrova, when this dignitary deviated from shoes to politics, assailed Bolshevism, and when he finished speaking <pb facs="5423967_2_0362.jpg" n="3"/>someone in the audience took a notion to dispute his utterances. "This was, oh horror, a Bolshevik!" An outburst of indignation in the gathering. "How dare he, who let him in? Throw him out! The ladies become nervous. Such a noble gathering, such solemnity, and all at once a Bolshevik in our midst....." Yet this terror of the ladies, the horrible Bolshevik, he too had some friends there, and a veritable bedlam ensued. The New York dignitary was much confused; the good ladies, many of them of pure American branch, were thoroughly scandalized at the utter lack of manner in these Russians, "who will never, never learn how to behave."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
