<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">Jan. 29, 1923</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0294</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0294.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">Jan. 29, 1923</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This article by V. Lievich has the objective to lay open to the rank- and-file reader the travesty of legal justice.</p>
   <p>The writer starts by a dignified presentation of his argument in a mood detached, transcendent, and with historic perspective.</p>
   <p>"From the day that man began to rule man - when man began to live by the labor of his fellow man, from that time dates the effort of such enslavers to justify, ratify, and legalize these acts, now by the grace of God, now by brutal force of ruling individuals, or a ruling class, taking the one of the arguments which suits best their ambitions and the level of culture which the masses attain. If the social order be that of a feudal lord, a king or his favorite child, the nobility, then these give tribunals to the people to suit their own taste."</p>
   <p>The writer then makes general reference to the history of the development <pb facs="5423967_2_0295.jpg" n="2"/>of the labor movement, which, he says, abounds with examples of class, i.e., biased tribunals, "hundreds of thousands of them: the Paris Revolution, the courts of the German bourgeoisie, of the Rumanian Boyars, or the Yugoslav princelings."</p>
   <p>Eastern Galicia, which is ruled by the Polish gentry, has many of this type of tribunal; at this very moment those lords of land and of finance are trying thirty-nine Socialists, who are leaders of a liberation movement. They are charged with a plot against the government, when in reality they only attempted to explain to the workingmen the bluff of the gentry's democracy and the principles of the class struggle.</p>
   <p>Whenever this class tribunal is embarrased by its own constitution, which it felt obliged to sprinkle with such democratic spices as the freedom of opinion in order to blind the working class with the dust from such spices, then this tribunal has no scruples to dig out codes from the monarchistic cemetery in Austria and make them serve its purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0296.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These tribunals shut their eyes to the open efforts of the bourgeoisie to incite riots through Fascists and seize power, for they are the servile messenger boys of the bourgeoisie, but when the proletarian courts of Moscow tried the agents of the international bourgeoisie, the entire press screamed to heaven, but is mute now when the thirty-nine are on trial in Poland.</p>
   <p>This, in the writer's opinion, is conclusive proof that the courts are merely another weapon in the hands of those who are in power, and, as the bourgeoisie happens to be in power now in Poland, it uses the courts for its sinister plunder of the workingmen.</p>
   <p>V. Lievich.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
