<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-06-13">June 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">From the United Committee for the Organization of the Celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture".</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-06-13">June 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE UNITED COMMITTEE FOR THE ORGANIZATION OF THE CELEBRATION OF THE "DAY OF RUSSIAN CULTURE".</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture" in the city of Chicago on June 9, 1929 proved to be a great moral success. In spite of the fact that on that day several Russian picnics were going on, among them a large "Press Day" picnic, the very large beautiful hall of the Municipal Pier was crowded by lovers of Russian culture. The following persons were on the literary part of the program of the celebration: the Russian writer, Mr. S. I. Goosev-Orenburgsky; the artist of the Moscow Art Theater, Mr. I. V. Lazarev; the representative of the American literati, Mr. Krause, Mrs. N. A. Birsky, Mr. D. V. Stranden, Mr. S. Scheinman, Mr. V. I. Baycher, Mr. N. S. Gribov and Mr. N. F. Erin.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened with a short speech by the manager of the festival, Mr. N. F. Erin, who bade all those present a hearty welcome and then introduced the chairman of the literary part of the program, Mrs. N. A. Birsky. The speakers explained the meaning of the "Day of Russian Culture" and the importance of Russian Culture in general for the whole world. After the literary part of the program there followed a concert and some dances and declamation. The following artists <pb facs="5423967_2_1395.jpg" n="2"/>participated in this part of the program. The well known singer Mrs. Maksakov; Mrs. P. G. Gribov, who performed the Russian boyars' dance; Mrs. A. A. Mikhailovsky (declamation); Miss Jean Moorey, pianist; Mr. P. Aluyevich, Croatian baritone; Mr. Weisspferd, tenor and Mr. Kulchar, violinist. Mr. Aster and Mr. Bremer were at the piano. The performances of all these artists were excellent and they earned much applause. The stage of the hall was adorned with the portraits of the great Russian writers and artists. Most prominent were the portraits of Leo Tolstoy and A. S. Pushkin. These portraits were very successfully enlarged from pictures by the self-taught amateur painter, Mr. P. I. Pokhaznikov. There were also the portraits of the artists of the Moscow Art Theater with Stanislavsky and Nemirovich-Danchenko at the head. Right in front and somewhat below were symbolic pictures representing labor, music and some other arts, science, culture and the theatrical art, painted by Mrs. S. Alekeyev. On the wall, right above the table, there was a large poster with the words: "The Day of Russian Culture".</p>
   <p>The celebration was a great success. Everybody who has attended it will preserve the best reminiscences about it, and it will probably become a good example for the Russian colony of Chicago to imitate in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1396.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The United Committee for the organization of the celebration of the "Day of Russian Culture" offers its hearty thanks to all the representatives of Russian literature and art who participated in the literary and musical parts of the program of the celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
