<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russian Daily Herald and Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-05-15">May 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">(Leading Article Concerning the Consolidation of the two Papers)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1708</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1708.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Daily Herald and Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-05-15">May 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">(Leading Article Concerning the Consolidation of the two Papers)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is stated that the Chicago Russian Daily Herald, which was previously practically owned by the lawyer Mr. K. P. Gugis, has become the property of Russian workers' cultural and educational organizations and of societies of mutual aid.</p>
   <p>The Russian Daily Herald was originally created through the initiative of the Chicago Russian Independent Society of Mutual Aid.</p>
   <p>The Russian workers members of this society, being inexperienced, had to use the help of educated persons of different political, religious and other views, who tried to make the paper serve their particular aims and represent their personal opinions. Because of the lack of a definite program the paper experienced difficulties and ultimately became the property of an individual, Mr. Gugis. He did his best to <pb facs="5423967_2_1709.jpg" n="2"/>improve the paper but could not find the proper people to help him, and because of that had but little success. Seeing that he could not satisfy with his paper the needs of the Russian colony of Chicago he sold the paper to the Russian Society of Mutual Aid mentioned above. As a result of this the personnel of the editorial staff of the paper was entirely changed and its pages were opened to any Russian immigrant who does not pursue only his selfish personal aims, but who is sincerely concerned about the welfare of the Russians in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
