<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-01-27">Jan. 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Asks Cash for Bombs.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-01-27">Jan. 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">ASKS CASH FOR BOMBS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Such assassinations as that of Von Plevhe cost money, and the Russian patriots lack the funds to carry on this work," said Bronisliv Slavinsky, editor of the Polish Rabotnick, a Socialist paper, at a banquet for Mme. Breshkovski, the Russian exile, at the Lessing Clubhouse last night.</p>
   <p>"Mme Breshkovski has been a champion of the Russian masses for more than thirty years, many of which she spent in prison." Mr. Slavinsky continued, "and she expects to see reform accomplished or to fall in the struggle.</p>
   <p>The present revolution had its origin in a peaceful movement which the government of Russia would not permit to continue. There is an old Russian legend which says that from the bones of those who, perish an avenger will arise! But we lack funds to carry on the work and appeal to all liberty-loving persons to contribute as liberally as they can."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0487.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After Mr. Slavinsky's address a petition was circulated and a considerable sum of money raised for Mme. Breshkovski, who also made an address, saying she was about to return to Russia, where her presence was needed. She said that when she started for this country she thought revolution and political reform to be far in the future. "Now I think reform will come soon," she added.</p>
   <p>Peter Sissman, in making a pleas for funds, said:</p>
   <p>"We want a battle- not a 'battle' like that of last Sunday at St. Petersburg.</p>
   <p>To accomplish this end we must have a mint.</p>
   <p>You must make sacrifices and give up funds for this purpose."</p>
   <p>The sale of boxes for the public meeting to be held at 3:30 o'clock Sunday afternoon at the Auditorium under the auspices of the Friends of Russian Freedom is progressing rapidly, and the indications are that the capacity of the big theater will be tested. Aside from Mme. Breshkovski, who will be the principal speaker, addresses will be made by Miss Jane Addams, Dr. Emil G. Hirsch and Jenkin LLoyd Jones.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
