<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-07">Apr. 7, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Reading by S. I. Gusev-Orenburgsky.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1464</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1464.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-07">Apr. 7, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Reading by S. I. Gusev-Orenburgsky.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About a hundred Russian immigrants had gathered in the not very large, but cozy Baltimore Hall, and everyone of them was listening with bated breath, as if afraid of missing a single word, to the measured fluency of the reading.</p>
   <p>Serghey Ivanovich Gusev-Orenburgsky, known to all of us as an author, proved this time to be also no mediocre reader.</p>
   <p>It is notorious that most writers do not know how to read aloud well.</p>
   <p>But Serghey Ivanovich is a wonderful reader. His soft, pleasant voice, his distinct enunciation, his clever way of conveying the characteristic intonation and pronunciation of every personage in dialogues between persons of various classes of society--all this perfectly corresponds to the character and style of his writings.</p>
   <p>"The Land of the Fathers" was written in 1904 and has had seven editions. According to Russian standards this is a very high figure. This is the best proof of Serghey Ivanovich's well merited success. But when his new novel <pb facs="5423967_2_1465.jpg" n="2"/>"The Land of the Children" is published it will have no less than ten editions.</p>
   <p>Such was the enthusiastic statement made to me by several persons who had attended the reading and with whom I had a conversation about it.</p>
   <p>Serghey Ivanovich read two chapters of his book "The Land of the Children." One of these chapters is devoted to the narration of the events of the childhood and youth of the hero of the novel. The hero, Vavila, is a typical "velikoross" (native of Great Russia), a man of sound sense, of judgment.</p>
   <p>Serghey Ivanovich relates with artistic consistency, step by step, the evolution of the world-conception elaborated by this son of Russia.</p>
   <p>In the other chapter we have before us pictures of the revolution, of the life on the front or, rather, on what remained of the front; of the last attempts to resist the advance of the Germans; of the interference and revolutionary activities of the sailors, and of the doings of Kerensky himself. These chapters are quite exceptionally artistic and powerful.</p>
   <p>Two short stories, picturing the life of the people, two chefs d'oeuvre--<pb facs="5423967_2_1466.jpg" n="3"/>"Prokhorych" and "The Soviet Deacon"--completed the program.</p>
   <p>The public stayed in the hall long after the reading had been finished. People were talking, disputing, expressing their admiration during a good hour. One of our intellectuals who had come to America some twenty years before, when greeting the writer, said with marked emotion: "For the second time in my life I have had the honor of shaking hands with a writer. When I was a young man Leo Tolstoy himself once gave me a shake."...</p>
   <p>G. G.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
