<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-27">Feb. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Importance of the Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-27">Feb. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANCE OF THE PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our times, the press is a mighty weapon because it expresses the opinions, thoughts, feelings, aspirations, and convictions of the public. Perhaps the inventor of the first printing press did not even realize that his invention was destined to play so decisive a role in molding human life. In the beginning the press served mainly the purposes of military circles. So it was at least in Russia during the reign of Peter the Great.</p>
   <p>The press passed through a long period of intensive development until it attained its present position and became a mighty force for good or evil. In each country the press has its own history. Countries whose cultural development was higher, early understood the importance of the press and began to develop it on an extensive scale. In such a way the press attained its present dominance in England, France, the United States, and many other Western-European countries. And for that reason it is no wonder that countries with a free press have attained a <pb facs="5423967_2_1562.jpg" n="2"/>high degree of progress in all phases of life, a much greater degree than countries where the press was persecuted or found itself under the heavy heel of a censor.</p>
   <p>It is true that the press has not always been what it should have been in its interpretation of social events. People have often printed and still continue to print obvious untruths, and interpret the facts falsely, thereby misleading readers. However, where a free press exists, there is no difficulty about finding out the truth. If one newspaper pursues commercial aims exclusively, there are to be found others interested only in spreading the right kind of information or preaching certain ideals. But such conditions can be found only in countries over which the Damoclean sword of censorship does not hang.</p>
   <p>It is impossible to expect a successful development of countries where only the state-controlled press exists. Long ago it was definitely established and proved beyond any doubt that no real progress could be made where there was <pb facs="5423967_2_1563.jpg" n="3"/>no free press. People of common sense will never believe that the people of Germany and Italy, under fascism, and those of Russia, under bolshevism, are making any real progress. Under conditions of dictatorship, the great mass of the people cannot possibly develop. Dictators are despots and they are not interested in the development of their people because if their people become educated, they will cease to submit to a dictator. Dictators are most interested in promulgating decrees which will restrict the liberties of the people. They have their own state-controlled press which praises their every action. Praise and approbation are the only things permitted with reference to the dictators' actions. Nothing which would be contrary to their will, is permitted. For this reason an independent press is forbidden in dictator countries. For Hitler, Mussolini, and Stalin, dictatorship is a sacred thing. It is interesting to note that all three dictators had a proletarian origin. From house painters and shoemakers they rose to the position of state rulers. Who would have known about them, outside of narrow party circles, if they had remained in their former positions? And now Hitler, Stalin, and Mussolini enjoy the rights and privileges of crowned kings. Under such dictators, there is no room for a free <pb facs="5423967_2_1564.jpg" n="4"/>and unrestricted press. They consider such a press as a survival of bourgeois rule. This is the fate that overwhelmed the free press of Russia, Italy, and Germany, when house painters and shoemakers took over the helm of the state.</p>
   <p>This once more proves how pitiful and insignificant are those leaders who speak today about liberty and equality and tomorrow become dictators and forget all their ideals. In order that such transformations should not occur, we must once and for all reject all ideas about dictatorship which will lead peoples to the depths of slavery, spiritual degradation, and moral decay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
