<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-07-22">July 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">It Is Time for Russians to Unite</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-07-22">July 22, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">IT IS TIME FOR RUSSIANS TO UNITE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appearance in Chicago of the handbills announcing the theft of money from the Bolshevik restaurant at Division Street shows the workers of Chicago, as well as the Russians, how the Bolsheviks conduct their affairs. This is not their first job; they have on their conscience many similar pieces of underhanded business, involving the money of the Russian workers.</p>
   <p>The same wily tricks were tried in Gary, Indiana; in the federation of Russian schools; and also in 1921, when the Russian people were organizing a public collection, a tag day, for the benefit of the starving people of Russia. Those Russians who do not know the real story about the activities of the Communists still believe the red gentlemen.</p>
   <p>I, personally, became convinced of the duplicity of the Bolsheviks in 1921, because I was among the inner circle. On the day of the collection, all collection boxes were turned in at the designated place. Then Mr. Stolar <pb facs="5423967_2_0218.jpg" n="2"/>asked the control committee not to count the money at that time because it would take too much time. Instead, he proposed that the money be taken to the bank where it could be counted on the adding machine. All agreed to this proposal. The collection boxes were loaded on two wagons and taken to the National Bank [in Gary, Indiana]. The bank was closed, by that time, to the general public, but the money was taken in. We were told to come back at 11 A. M. the following day, to be present when the money was counted.</p>
   <p>And then what happened? Mr. Stolar hurried to the bank and "counted" the money before we got there. "It's all done," he said. We asked how much money there was. Mr. Stolar answered that the report would be presented at the meeting.... But many meetings took place, and still we were unable to get Mr. Stolar to present the report.</p>
   <p>However, we began in all seriousness to demand the report. Then Mr. Stolar categorically announced that the money had been counted and that it would be sent to the designated place.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0219.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And thus it ended, as many of the Independents well remember, and up to the present time, nobody knows how much money was collected, and how much of it was sent to the starving people in Russia. This is known to only one man--Mr. Stolar. But since that time, Mr. Stolar has disappeared from Chicago. This was my first experience with Bolshevik work.</p>
   <p>My second acquaintance with their methods was in 1927. I was a delegate to the federation of the Russian schools for children, representing the Alexander Pushkin School.</p>
   <p>I went to the meeting in Douglas Park. The chairman, Mr. Turovietz, opened the meeting, and instead of discussing school affairs, he brought up the question of assigning the funds for the benefit of the Communist newspaper, Novyi Mir (The New World). I began to protest, on the ground that the federation had been created to foster cultural and educational aims, and not to support a commercial newspaper. Mr. Deviatkin rose and began to insult me, crying out that if I were in the Soviet Union, I would deserve to be shot.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0220.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And the following was my third experience with the work of the Communists. It occurred in 1931. In Pullman, Illinois, at the Ukrainian Home, 107th and Stevens Streets, the Bolsheviks were giving a report of the twentieth convention of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society. While they were giving the report, the leaders, foaming at the mouth, screamed: "Comrades, the nonworking class element still clings to our society. No man who belongs to the Independent group within our society will be allowed to enter the Soviet Union. Do not join the Independents of the Russian Independent Mutual Aid Society!"</p>
   <p>Now you see, my brothers, how the Bolsheviks, headed by Mr. Deviatkin, have grown bold in their mockery, and are making fools of our whole Russian colony. And why is this so? These gentlemen feel that the unification of the Russian colony is approaching, and our union means the end of the Deviatkins. This is why their sudden boldness passes all bounds.</p>
   <p>I call upon all Russians in the United States and Canada to bend every effort <pb facs="5423967_2_0221.jpg" n="5"/>toward the rapid consolidation of all the Russians into one strong, fraternal family. And the sooner it is done, the quicker will we eliminate, without any struggle on our part, those groups of ignorant Russians who still listen to the Communists. The agitation and slander of the Communists will be answered by the union of all the Russians. And then we will not be afraid of the alarms raised by the Communist "financial auditors".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
