<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-11">Feb. 11, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Entertainment Given by Rassviet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-11">Feb. 11, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">ENTERTAINMENT GIVEN BY RASSVIET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On February 2 I had occasion to be present at the concert and entertainment given by the newspaper Rassviet. All that I had intended to say about it has already been written in the article over the signature of "Colonist" in the issue of February 5.</p>
   <p>The evening was not a more entertainment but a demonstration of the solidarity of the Russian people in and around Chicago. No matter what hysterical outeries Deviatkin [Translator's note: A Bolshevik leader in Chicago] may omit in calling Rassviet a White Guard paper, fascist sheet, not a workers' organ, the Russian people, it is now obvious, do not pay any attention to his shouting.</p>
   <p>Often as I have attended concerts and various other entertainments in Chicago, <pb facs="5423967_2_1543.jpg" n="2"/>I have never seen so many Russian people assembled together. And who was not there? There were farmers, workers, intellectuals, doctors, professors, teachers, artists, musicians, clergymen. All the Russian people were united by the newspaper Rassviet. The Russian colony in Chicago thus revealed a great sympathy for its own colonial newspaper. Observing the crowd, one was inclined to believe that the dissensions engendered by the dark forces of internationalism among Russians everywhere had come to an end and were all but forgotten.</p>
   <p>There was a time when we looked askance at one another, full of suspicion and mistrust, particularly aimed at those who had made their own way in the world and had made their lives successful. Rather than despise such people, we should have taken pride in the fact that there are men and women of our nationality who are able to succeed in life and to attain to high positions, and who seener or later will serve and help the people related to them by blood and by language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1544.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Obviously the Russian catastrophe and the trampling down of national interests will force the Russian people to understand one another. Just try to offend the national sentiments of a German, a Frenchman, or an Englishman! Every one of them will rise to defend his nation, whether he be a peasant, a worker, a professor, a doctor, a lawyer, an intellectual, or what not. And as for us Russians, it is time for us to come to our senses to understand one another regardless of occupation or social status as long as in our veins flows Slavic blood, and to protect our national interests.</p>
   <p>Now you, workers on the newspaper, have seen what a numerous Russian colony supports Rassviet year voice was not the voice of a man in a desert. You were heard.</p>
   <p>A visitor from Gary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
