<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-31">Jan. 31, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Enemies or Friends?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-31">Jan. 31, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ENEMIES OR FRIENDS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bolsheviks quite frequently assert that they are the irreconcilable enemies of Fascists; Fascists, in their turn, claim they hate Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>Superficially, it may seem there is much truth in these statements. Everyone knows of the intense fight that is being waged by Bolsheviks in their newspapers against Fascists of all countries. In like manner, the European Fascist press is engaged in a relentless war against Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>As a matter of fact, in reality the situation is quite different. By their actions, Bolsheviks and Fascists reveal themselves, not as bitter enemies, but as the best of friends. An indication of this may be seen in the similarity of their systems of government, and in a series of other facts. For instance, the German Dictator, Hitler, carries on a merciless war against Bolsheviks in his own country; but as far as Kremlin Bolsheviks are concerned, he treats them <pb facs="5423967_2_0127.jpg" n="2"/>with as much favor as did the preceding German governments. Since the downfall of Kaiser Wilhelm, Germany has changed governments many times, but the German policy toward Russia has remained the same. Every German government has supported the Bolshevik regime, which was established with the help and close collaboration of the German general staff during the great war. The same policy is being pursued by Hitler, who continues to express his hatred toward Bolshevism in words only.</p>
   <p>Credits were granted to the Bolsheviks by the former German governments and are also extended to the Bolsheviks by Hitler. Only the other day the news agencies reported that Germany had decided to extend new credits to the Soviet government amounting to eighty million dollars, and guaranteed by the German government up to seventy per cent of this amount. These credits are being extended at a time when Germany herself is undergoing a financial crisis; as a result, the German government decided to issue a one billion mark loan in its own behalf.</p>
   <p>The seemingly anti-Bolshevik French government is also a supporter of the Bolshevik regime. Several days ago it became known that France was about to loan the <pb facs="5423967_2_0128.jpg" n="3"/>Bolsheviks, in the form of credits, one billion francs (a franc is worth six and one-half cents now). The negotiations for the extension of these credits were conducted in Moscow, on December 9, by the French Minister of Domestic Affairs, Mr. Albert Marchandeau, who went there at that time.</p>
   <p>According to reports from Paris, the Bolshevik government will cover the payments on this loan by imports of oil, worth 350,000,000 francs, and other raw materials.</p>
   <p>Among other goods, the Bolsheviks will buy annually airplane parts valued at 100,000,000 francs. One of the clauses in the agreement provides for placing, with French automobile manufacturers, orders for machines and spare parts totaling 180,000,000 francs. Most of the orders will be placed with the Citroen concern, which at present is undergoing reorganization.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviks also agreed to pay part of their previous debt to the United States, provided the latter extends further credit to the Soviet government. Consequently, it may be assumed that the Bolsheviks will even get some support <pb facs="5423967_2_0129.jpg" n="4"/>from the American capitalists.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mussolini, the Italian Fascist Dictator, also maintains a very close friendship with the Kremlin Bolsheviks. This is proved by the fact that Italian papers, on his orders, ceased to print anti-Bolshevik articles and all telegraphic news unfavorable to the Bolshevik regime in Russia.</p>
   <p>We could cite a number of other instances to prove that Bolsheviks and Fascists are friends and not enemies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
