<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-05-01">May 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Invincible Power</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-05-01">May 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">INVINCIBLE POWER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the workers of the world will celebrate the day of toil and sunshine, the first of May.</p>
   <p>This time the celebration will be more joyous than heretofore. Until now the workers of the world have seen before them the victims of the unparalleled, cruel war. Everywhere were still the dreadful traces of it; the destructions from that war still loomed before the eyes of the working class.</p>
   <p>With the war ended, peace did not come to the toilers; instead came years of new and desperate struggles in the form of revolutions and debacles in Europe, strife for a better deal to labor.</p>
   <p>This was followed by a worldwide reactionary period. The black forces were rampant: imperialists, militarists, political and religious fanatics, and the high priests of the yellow devil. All their efforts were <pb facs="5423967_2_0292.jpg" n="2"/>directed towards robbing the world of peace and the workingmen and the peasants of their conquests during and after the war.</p>
   <p>Looking back at this desperate strife one must admit that the workers of the world and those who are to any extent liberal-minded have proved themselves at the height of their calling.</p>
   <p>The struggle was severe, but the workers held out.</p>
   <p>Temporarily divided through war and its aftermath, they became cemented again the process of this struggle. In this process the solidarity of the workers of the world became newly invigorated. The workers in one country are now supporting the workers in other countries. In the interior of every country the workers stand united.</p>
   <p>And this solidarity, this union, works miracles.</p>
   <p>Gradually are falling off the chains of reaction. Workers and peasants everywhere compel better labor conditions and greater political freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0293.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Trade unions are gaining in strength; likewise with the peasants. In some countries labor representatives are beginning to wield great influence. The thrones of monarchs are crashing, the rule of dictators is waning.</p>
   <p>The rattle of the workers' and peasants' enemies is still heard, of course, reaction is still afoot, yet their might is decidedly at an ebb. They are obliged to surrender as the fighting legions of toilers keep battering ahead for a better deal, for a brighter and happier life!</p>
   <p>The parade of the workers, as they are reviewing their forces, will be more encouraging this year than heretofore.</p>
   <p>However bitter the fight, much has been gained during these years by the workers and peasants of the world. Their power is proving to be invincible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
