<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-12">April 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">In the Land of the Fathers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-04-12">April 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE LAND OF THE FATHERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two hours spent at the literary evening given by Mr. Gusev-Oren-burgsky on Sunday, at the Auditorium Recital Hall, have truly made our thoughts to travel to the land of our fathers.</p>
   <p>This land lay there in miniature before our eyes in the artistic picture drawn by the author of The Land of the Fathers.</p>
   <p>The types of the new Russia depicted in Mr. Gusev-Orenburgsky's new book, The Land of the Children, are so colorful and vivid; that modern commonplace citizen, the immortal Prokhorych, who apparently has become a universal type of Russia, has been drawn by the author in such a comprehensible and brilliant way; the "Soviet Deacon" is so colorful, so alive.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1461.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have seen, like in a flash, live types of the people of modern Russia. The new mode of life of the population of that country has been presented to us in such a vivid way. One could listen to thousands of political speeches, read thousands of articles and pamphlets on Russia, and yet one would not derive from them such clear ideas concerning the present life of the people in that country as those we have acquired by listening to a fragment from "The Land of the Children and to two short stories.</p>
   <p>This is so because these literary productions contain a highly artistic and, if I may say so, an artistically realistic reflection of life as it is truly lived in Russia.</p>
   <p>Serghey Ivanovich read beautifully the short stories, The Immortal Prokhorych and The Soviet Deacon.</p>
   <p>Of course, he did not read like an artist, but like a writer. But <pb facs="5423967_2_1462.jpg" n="3"/>an unusual extreme modesty which is a characteristic of Serghey Ivanovich, his soulful way of reading and his ability to emphasize most expressively those sentences that require such emphasis give to Serghey Ivanovich's reading the charm of a peculiar intimacy which is not to be found in the manner of reading of even the best artists.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, there occurred also the thought of what tremendous impression would be made if these fragments and short stories would be read by an artist.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that, owing to the excessive number of evening entertainments on that Sunday, the literary evening given by Mr. Gusev-Orenburgsky was attended by less Russian immigrants than it was expected.</p>
   <p>All those who had come went home satisfied. From all sides one could <pb facs="5423967_2_1463.jpg" n="4"/>hear the question asked: "When will the next reading by Gusev-Orenburg-sky take place?"</p>
   <p>Zemetchinsky (S. E. Scheinmann).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
