<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-08-27">Aug. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Tenth Anniversary of the Great War</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0686</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0686.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-08-27">Aug. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE TENTH ANNIVERSARY OF THE GREAT WAR</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On August 23, 1924, there was held at the 'House of Enlightenment' a solemn meeting organized by the editorial staff of the Russian Herald and devoted to the commemoration of the tenth anniversary of the beginning of the Great War and to the memory of the Russian soldiers who fell on the battlefields during that war.</p>
   <p>The administration of the House of Enlightenment, this highly useful institution,as represented by S. E. Prokopov, has put at the disposal of our newspaper a new hall which can hold as many as three hundred persons. Delegates from almost all Russian organizations existing in our city came to the meeting. But, in compliance with the Russian custom which has been transplanted to the American soil, many persons came much too late.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0687.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The meeting was called to or der by N. G. Kaluzhin (Pertsov) at 7:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>The orators were given the right of the floor alphabetically. The first to speak was A. P. Braghin.</p>
   <p>In his speech, which lasted half an hour, the orator gave a characterization of the aims which Russia has been pursuing during the last war.</p>
   <p>The orator pointed out with pride those achievements which Russia was contemplating and part of which were realized towards the end of the war, though partially they were annulled by the subsequent events.</p>
   <p>The next orator after Braghin was N. G. Kaluzhin who, speaking on behalf of the editorial staff of the Russian Herald, pictured the tragedy of Russia and the Russian army during the last war.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0688.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Having referred to the Russian ex-general staff as to a chancellery of brilliant achievements in making careers, and not a center which was mindful of holding in its hands the fate of Russia, the orator could not speak without emotion about the heroic struggle of the Russian army which had to fight on two fronts. The orator exhorted the Chicago Russians to have faith in that people which has given so many proofs of its spiritual and physical power while walking that way of the cross which had been prepared for it by the tsar's government in 1914.</p>
   <p>The next orator was the representative of the White Russian National Committee, I. Y. Voronko. This speaker quoted just a few statistical data, but how horror-struck was the audience by these figures: The orator - who was in such close sympathy with the audience three quarters of which consisted of White Russians - spoke about the losses of his native country which had been torn and laid waste <pb facs="5423967_2_0689.jpg" n="4"/>for many decades. He entreated those present to remember always the slogan "down with war"; for wars are necessary only to the capitalists and those who hold power. The orator also pointed out all those acquisitions which had been made owing to the war. "Twenty six thrones have tumbled down:" he exclaimed; "this must be remembered by all the toilers!"</p>
   <p>After the audience had risen at the request of the chairman in order to honor the memory of the Russian soldiers who had fallen on the battlefields, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
   <p>N. I.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
