<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Domashnii Vrach</title> (The House Physician), Vol. II, No. 4,
<date when="1917-04">April 1917</date>, pp. 194-195
<title level="a">From the Chicago Conference of Russian Socialist Organizations for Aid to the Russian Revolution</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Domashnii Vrach</title> (The House Physician), Vol. II, No. 4,
<date when="1917-04">April 1917</date>, pp. 194-195
<title level="a">FROM THE CHICAGO CONFERENCE OF RUSSIAN SOCIALIST ORGANIZATIONS FOR AID TO THE RUSSIAN REVOLUTION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appeal says that the bourgeois press of all countries rejoices at the success of the Russian revolution "and hastens to assure us that the revolution has ended." According to the bourgeois press the whole aim of the revolution was the overthrow of the Romanov government. The same press assures everyone that "the impossible demand of several extreme leftist elements" will lead to unfortunate results. The bourgeois press rejoices in the revolution as long as such people as Milyukov, Guchkov and Rodzianko are at the head of the government. But as soon as the voice of the revolutionary proletariat is heard they fear for the future of Russia's freedom. "We are convinced that the revolution in Russia has not yet ended, but is, in fact, now approaching its high point." Of course, the proletariat did not strive to overthrow the Romanovs in order to install such 'revolutionaries' as <pb facs="5423967_2_0446.jpg" n="2"/>Guchkov, Rodzianko, Milyukov and their like. The proletariat fought tsarism in order to gain a better opportunity to fight the class which is the present Russian government. The proletariat of the world, Russia included, fights against war. The present government, like the old, strives to prolong the war in the interest of conquest. The proletariat cannot support them and continues the struggle.</p>
   <p>Only under the attack of the proletariat will the government move left, will the constituent assembly be called and not delayed until after the war.</p>
   <p>"The revolutionary proletariat needs our help in this battle also." The world bourgeoisie supports the present government. The working classes of the world, including Russian emigrants, must support the Russian proletariat.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0447.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A conference has been created in Chicago for aid to the Russian revolution. Socialists from Russia, Poland, Lithuania, Latvia and Jews are members.</p>
   <p>The conference invites all Russian immigrants not to limit themselves to attending meetings, but to help the Russian proletariat continue the fight. Everyone must act.</p>
   <p>The conference has opened subscription lists for collection of funds for the revolution. These lists will be sent to all organizations. Those wishing to aid the revolution should communicate with: National Office Socialist Party, 803 W. Madison Street, Chicago; or, I. Rabrzo, 321 S. Marshfield Avenue, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
