<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-30">Apr. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Liars</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-30">Apr. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">LIARS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the latest issue of Novyi Mir [Translator's note: a Bolshevik newspaper published in New York], there appears a letter written by a "comrade" named Yasha Rosenblum, who lives in Odessa [U. S. S. R.]. In this letter, the author describes to his Russian compatriots the magnificent work of socialist construction being carried on in the U. S. S. R. and the Utopian life being enjoyed by the Russian workers under the regime of the workers' and peasants' government. Of course, this particular piece of information is of no interest either to us or to the publishers of the Bolshevik news-paper because we, as well as they, are well aware of the kind of construction that is in progress in the U. S. S. R. and the kind of life that is being lived by the workers and peasants under the Bolshevik regime.</p>
   <p>If life in Russia were actually what it is portrayed to be in the Bolshevik <pb facs="5423967_2_1558.jpg" n="2"/>press, the Russian Bolsheviks would be shaking the capitalist dust from their feet and would be leaving for the socialist paradise. But no such exodus can be seen. On the contrary, our home-grown Bolsheviks cling to the capitalist hell and profess no desire to leave it. They do not intend to go over there for they know just as well as we do that the Bolshevik hell is many times worse than the capitalist one. Even unemployed Bolsheviks who are on relief, and subsist on the "miserable crumbs" thrown to them by the capitalists and their government, do not want to leave. These unemployed "comrades" somehow or other even manage to help their "working" friends and relatives in Russia; the Bolshevik newspaper does not vainly feature the Torgsin ads day after day [Translator's note: Torgsin is the name of the Soviet government stores where goods are sold only to foreigners, or to Soviet citizens who have received foreign currency from relatives or friends abroad] at a time when the Soviet papers should have been printing appeals to their citizens for help for the American comrades dying under the capitalist regime. Such appeals, however, do not appear and will never appear in the Soviet newspapers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1559.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are particularly interested in the information furnished by "Comrade" Yasha Rosenblum mainly because the Bolshevik government is as afraid of Rassviet as the devil is afraid of the cross, and does not permit our newspaper to circulate among its citizens. It is, therefore, true that among our readers, we do not find the name of Yasha Rosenblum in Odessa-- and for a very good reason: nobody in the U. S. S. R. is permitted to read Rassviet. Despite the indisputable ban on our newspaper, the "comrade" from Odessa, who is a Communist living in that Black Sea port writes that he reads our newspaper and is highly indignant because he claims that Rassviet distorts the facts about the U. S. S. R. and prints a great many lies about life in the Communist paradise.</p>
   <p>How Yasha Rosenblum has access to our newspaper when this privilege is denied to prominent Moscow Communists, nobody but Allah knows. If his statement is true, we are happy that many "comrades" are still able to read our newspaper, which they get through some mysterious channels. We would also be very indebted to Mr. Shkliar, the editor of Novyi Mir, if he would remove the <pb facs="5423967_2_1560.jpg" n="4"/>ban from our newspaper in Moscow. By doing this, he would kill two birds with one stone. First; he would thus permit every Russian Communist, and not just Yasha Rosenblum, to familiarize himself with the "falsehoods" printed by Rassviet about the U. S. S. R. and second, he would thus repudiate our charge that there is no freedom of the press or expression under the Bolshevik regime, and that no newspaper, except the Communist propaganda sheets, are permitted to circulate in the U. S. S. R., while Soviet newspapers are freely admitted to the United States and are read by many American citizens.</p>
   <p>We know, however, that Mr. Shkliar would not do this. He knows quite well that Rassviet cannot possibly have any readers in Odessa, that Yasha Rosenblum's letter is a forgery and that it was forged by the liars on the staff of Novyi Mir. From this we draw the unavoidable conclusion that in Yasha Rosenblum's letter there is as much truth about the living conditions of the workers in the U. S. S. R. as there is in his statement that he reads Rassviet and becomes indignant every time he opens its pages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
