<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novoye Russkoye Slovo (New York City)</title>,
<date when="1937-02-24">Feb. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Pushkin Days in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novoye Russkoye Slovo (New York City)</title>,
<date when="1937-02-24">Feb. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">PUSHKIN DAYS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, February 7, under the auspices of the Russian-American club Oasis, a literary-musical affair was given at the Great Northern Hotel on the centenary of A. S. Pushkin.</p>
   <p>The evening opened with a speech in Russian by Jacob Eberhardt on "The Genius of A. S. Pushkin." A. E. Pokatilov recited "The Prophet" and other Pushkin verses. The opera singer J. Kodalsky sang parts from the "Queen of Spades," also "On the Mounds is a Georgian."</p>
   <p>Finally, Professor H. Halperin, of Northwestern University, read a very interesting paper in English on "Pushkin's Immortality." Dr. H. Krasnow presided.</p>
   <p>On February 20, the centennial commemoration of Pushkin ended at the Orchestra Hall with a brilliant concert. The celebration was under the <pb facs="5423967_2_1413.jpg" n="2"/>auspices of a joint committee of socialist and workers' organizations. The evening opened with a speech in English by Professor F. Spencer, who presided. The program was so immense that owing to a late hour it became necessary to curtail it by a few numbers in the concert, which began with the staging of a living picture from "Winter Evening"; A. S. Pushkin and Arina Rodionovna in Mikhailovsky; following this was a trio sung by Marie Mashir, A. Kulnak, and B. Bolsky. They sang "The Storm Covers the Skies with Darkness," the words by Pushkin, and the music by Dargomyszhsky. The violinist, D. Moll, played three numbers, including Lensky's aria, "What will Tomorrow Bring Me." Marie Mashir then sang "Liza," from the "Queen of Spades," by Tchaikovsky. Charles De-Sheim read in English Pushkin's "To Chadayev," the opera singer, P. Mills Sokolskaya, sang in conclusion "A Statue in Czarskoye Selo" by T. Kue, and "On the Mounds is a Georgian," by N. Mednikov.</p>
   <p>The second half of the celebration began with a speech by Prof. G. V. Bobrinskoy of the University of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1414.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The evening was a very great success and will remain as a very pleasant memory for Chicagoans.</p>
   <p>The special number of Novoye Russkoye Slovo received here which is devoted to the centenary of A. S. Pushkin made a sensation. It called out unusual enthusiasm. From many of the writer's friends and acquaintances came a deluge of questions as to how and where to get this special number.</p>
   <p>The Russian artist who is noted in American art circles, G. G. Orlov, worked for two months on a portrait in oil of A. S. Pushkin. It is a very large portrait, and is a great success. This portrait was exhibited at the Oasis affair, and again at Orchestra Hall on February 20, and was met with enthusiasm by the audience. The artist Orlov decided to make a gift of the portrait to the Chicago Art Institute.</p>
   <p>(Ed. Note: -- Article by Dr. H. R. Krasnow.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
