<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution of the Russian-Ukrainian Massmeeting</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-06-16">June 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION OF THE RUSSIAN-UKRAINIAN MASSMEETING</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 3, 1917, a massmeeting of the Russian-Ukrainians in Chicago took place, and the following resolution was made:</p>
   <p>"Taking into consideration the successfully achieved Russian revolution, we, Russian and Ukrainian peasants and workers, unanimously resolve: (1) The expression of thanks to all fighters for Russian liberty and the wish of a successful restoration of peace and order in a free country. (2) The expression of full confidence in the provisional government, insisting on a victorious outcome of the war in order, once and for all, to put an end to militarism. (3) To give to all nationalities inhabiting Russia freedom on the basis of autonomy. (4) The confiscation in favor of the people of all the natural riches and a just distribution of such.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0426.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(5) The return to the parishioners of all Russian church property appropriated by the bishops. (6) Dismissal of all former tsarist officials, consuls, and representatives in America and their replacement by representatives of free Russia. (7) The taking of measures against the Russian clergy, which agitates against the new people's government and for the restoration of monarchy in Russia. (8) The confiscation in favor of the people of all the property received as a reward for service to the former tsars. (9) Prohibition of the sale of liquors. (10) Russia should be a democratic republic. (11) The introduction of obligatory general education for the people. (12) The expression of deep thanks to the American republic, which has taken under its protection all Russians who suffered from the former tsarist regime."</p>
   <p>The present resolution was worked out after a grand manifestation in <pb facs="5423967_2_0427.jpg" n="3"/>honor of liberty and unanimously accepted by the Russian-Ukrainian massmeeting, and it was resolved to send it immediately to the Russian State Duma.</p>
   <p>Note: This resolution is an expression of the public opinion of the progressive part of the Russian colony in Chicago, which was hostile to the tsarist regime. In general one could safely say that almost the whole Russian colony was supporting at that time the Provisional government of Kerensky, with the exception of a small number of persons who belonged to different political movements more to the left than the government of Kerensky. This resolution reflects the frame of mind of the great majority of Russians in Chicago. N. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
