<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-05">Jan. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0925</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0925.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-05">Jan. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beginning of a new year will probably stimulate the activities of the Russian organizations in Chicago. I have come to this conclusion as a result of private conversations, as well as those overheard at social gatherings. It would be very nice if my expectations came true, since the results would be very beneficial to the Russian organizations in Chicago. Even now there are a great number of men and women in Chicago who do not belong to any organization. This is particularly true of women.</p>
   <p>In America, at present, women occupy a very important place in the political life of the country. Many women are elected to important political posts. They also play quite an important role in the economic life of the country, as well as in the field of education. As far as the Russian women in Chicago are concerned, they are not at all interested in such problems. They prefer to kill their time with trivialities, with gossip, instead of devoting their <pb facs="5423967_2_0926.jpg" n="2"/>time to something more useful. All nationalities have large women's organizations. Polish women are particularly well organized. Each mother who belongs to an organization, sees to it that her children belong too. For that reason Polish mutual aid organizations develop very rapidly and prosper financially.</p>
   <p>In order to quicken the tempo of life of the Russians in Chicago, and to make this life more cultured more interesting, the Russian women in Chicago should create their own exclusive branches in conjunction with the society Rnzov. Let the New Year establish the beginning of the activity of Russian women in Chicago for the benefit and enlightenment of the entire membership of the glorious Independent [Mutual Aid]Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
