<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1936-08-12">Aug. 12, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1936-08-12">Aug. 12, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Henry Krasnow,</p>
   <p>4601 N. Broadway,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The Initiative Group of the Pushkin Jubliee Committee of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the beginning of 1937, one hundred years will have passed from the time of the death of the greatest Russian poet, A. S. Pushkin. The entire Soviet Union, where Pushkin has been resurrected, in all its might and beauty is making preparations for the celebration of the Pushkin Jubliee on a scale unseen by the world. But not in the Soviet Union alone, in all countries, where through the Russian immigrants Russian culture has penetrated, and where the Russian language created by Pushkin is ringing, people are making preparations for their local Jubilee celebrations in honor of the great man of the North. Also, here in America, and particularly in Chicago, Russian immigrants are arranging such celebrations.</p>
   <p>The initiative group of our Pushkin Jubilee Committee, composed of representatives of Russian Workers' organizations in Chicago, is striving to create a United front, of all cultural forces of Chicago. At the last meeting of the Committee, with representatives <pb facs="5423967_2_1421.jpg" n="2"/>of Russian Clubs "Oasis", "Zaria" and other organizations of Russian immigrants, it was decided to call for expansion of this committee, the purpose of which is to present all our cultural strength, also to discuss the question of calling a special conference to make plans for our Pushkin celebrations. This meeting will be held at the quarters of the Russian Workers' Cooperative Society, 1628 W. Division Street, Tuesday, August 18, at 8 P. M.</p>
   <p>By recommendation of our friends, the Initiative Group invites you to honor us with your presence at this meeting, and take an active part inthe forthcoming cultural celebration of the Russian colony of Chicago. In behalf of the Initiative Group of the Pushkin Committee.</p>
   <p>Jacob Eberhardt</p>
   <p>Doctor Krasnow:</p>
   <p>I am sending you several of these letters un-addressed. Send them to people of your organization.</p>
   <p>J. E.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
