<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Antsiferov, V. <title level="a">"Russian Dramatic Circle,"</title> Moscwa (Monthly),
<date when="1930-04">April 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Antsiferov, V. <title level="a">"Russian Dramatic Circle,"</title> Moscwa (Monthly),
<date when="1930-04">April 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten, years ago, there were no symptoms whatsoever, of Russian Theatrical Art, existing in Chicago. The Russian colony (early immigrants) cared little about the development of Russian Art, and in general, their cultural needs were supplanted by the Polish and Ukranian theatres.</p>
   <p>During July 1921, several leaders of the early settlers, organized and sustained the first Russian theatrical entertainment. They produced A. P. Tchehous' Comedy "Medved," They presented also, very good concert programs, with the participation of the best artists who had come from Russian not long before. The entertainment was of a purely Russian character.</p>
   <p>The first members of the 'Circle' were joined by new artists. The group consisted of the following persons: W. T. and A. F. Antsiferov, Igor Antsiferov, P. B. Belogradsky, A. P. Bragin, B. G. Burmistrov, E. F. Wagner, M. P. Volkov, E. I. Tchekeler, G.J. and E. I. Eveninee, G. S. Kamensky, O. I. Marland, N. A. Martinov, A. V. and V. B. Morozov, A. V. Lobanov, A. I. Obrastzov, L. G. and S. D. Pertsov, Mrs. S. P. Stranden, W. M. Slavogorosdky, R. I. Khomko, <pb facs="5423967_2_1330.jpg" n="2"/>A. P. and Mrs. S. I. Shuhvostov and Miss E. K. Jablonskaja.</p>
   <p>During all this period the staff of the 'circle' underwent frequent changes, and by the end of the sixth year only the following remained: V. I. and A. F. Antsiferov and their son Igor Antsiferov, E. I. Gekkeler, N. A. Martinov, A. B. and V. B. Morozov, A. V. Lobanov, L. G. and S. D. Pertsov, A. P. and S. I. Shuhvostov. The Russian Dramatic circle produced sixteen different plays and gave twentyseven performances. This 'circle has at its disposal fifteen own plays and eightythree others belonging to the manager. The plays were presented also in North and South Chicago, Gary, Ind., Kenosha and Milwaukee, Wis.</p>
   <p>V. Antsiferov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
