<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-04-03">April 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Statement of the Ownership, Management, Circulation, Etc., Required by the Act of Congress of August 24, 1912, of the Russian Daily Herald, Published Daily at Chicago, Illinois, for April 1st, 1924.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-04-03">April 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">STATEMENT OF THE OWNERSHIP, MANAGEMENT, CIRCULATION, ETC., REQUIRED BY THE ACT OF CONGRESS OF AUGUST 24, 1912, OF THE RUSSIAN DAILY HERALD, PUBLISHED DAILY AT CHICAGO, ILLINOIS, FOR APRIL 1st, 1924.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>State of Illinois( S.S.</p>
   <p>County of Cook(</p>
   <p>Before me, a Notary Public in and for the State and county aforesaid, personally appeared Ilia Karpuck, who, having been duly sworn according to law, deposes and says that he is the Business Manager of the Russian Daily Herald and that the following is ;-</p>
   <p>To the best of his knowledge and belief, a true statement of the ownership, management (and if a daily paper, the circulation), etc., of the aforesaid publication for the date shown in the above caption, required by the Act of August 24, 1912, embodied in section 443, Postal Laws and Regulations, printed on the reverse of this form, to wit:</p>
   <p>1. That the names and addresses of the publisher, editor, managing editor, and business managers are:</p>
   <p>Publisher,- Russian Publishing Company, Inc., 1722 West Chicago Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Editor,- S. Scheiman, 1722 West Chicago Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. Managing Editor,- None.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1730.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Business Manager- I.G. Karpuck, 1129 North Winchester Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>2. That the owner is:-(if the publication is owned by an individual, his na me and address, or if owned by more than one individual the name and address of each, should be given below; if the publication is owned by a corporation the name of the corporation and the names and addresses of the stockholders owning or holding one per cent or more of the total amount of stock should be given).</p>
   <p>K.P. Gugis, 127 North Dearborn Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>John Dzidz, 233 West 61st Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Martin Martysiuk, 2724 West 16th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>John Baturevich, 117 West 118th Street, West Pullman, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The Russian National Orthodox Society, 917 North Wood Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>3. That the known bondholders, mortgagers, and other security holders owning or holding one per cent or more of total amount of bonds, mortgages, or other securities are : (If there are none, so state).</p>
   <p>Intertype Corporation, Brooklyn, New York.</p>
   <p>Eugene D. Sullivan, 1109 North Robey Street, Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>4. That the average number of copies of each issue of this publication sold or distributed, through the mails or otherwise, to paid subscribers <pb facs="5423967_2_1731.jpg" n="3"/>during the six months preceding the date shown above is Eight Thousand daily.</p>
   <p>(This information is required from daily publication only.)</p>
   <p>Ilia G. Karpuck, Business Manager.</p>
   <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this 2nd day of April, 1924.</p>
   <p>(Seal)</p>
   <p>Anton O. Landes, Notary Public.</p>
   <p>(My commission expires April 26, 1926.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
