<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">'Friends of Russian Democracy</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochta</title> (Russian Post),
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">'FRIENDS OF RUSSIAN DEMOCRACY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large Russian organization has been formed whose problems are quite important.</p>
   <p>As it was reported in Russkaya Pochta about a month ago, a meeting of the newly organized 'Society for the Aid to the Russian Revolution' was held at the Sherman Hotel. The aim of this society was originally to help the Soviet of workers and soldiers deputies. At the above mentioned meeting a secession occurred because of a difference of opinion. At this meeting the majority of those present did not agree with such a program. The group of members who insisted on the original program, feeling insulted, left the hall of the session. After this a commission was appointed for the working out of plans of further action of the society. The next session was held May 15, 1917, at the <pb facs="5423967_2_0440.jpg" n="2"/>Sherman Hotel, under the chairmanship of M. Polack. The report of the commission was read by Mr. Berg, and the following points were accepted:</p>
   <p>1. The aim of the society is in every way to help the revolutionary movement in Russia.</p>
   <p>2. The society has the aim of furnishing in America true light on the real situation in Russia.</p>
   <p>3. The society's aim is to help as much as possible, both economically and morally, the liberated political exiles and prisoners.</p>
   <p>4. The society has the aim of assisting Russians in America who desire to perfect themselves in different trades and professions, so that they may apply their knowledge and ability in Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0441.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5. From now on the society will carry the name of Druziya Russki Democratii (Friends of Russian Democracy).</p>
   <p>6. In principle, it was decided, the society will be non-partisan.</p>
   <p>Forty-two persons joined the society. Discussion of many important questions, problems and aims of the society, as well as the election of the board, were postponed until the next session on account of the late hour.</p>
   <p>The secretary protem of the society is Dr. H. R. Krasnow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
