<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-06-09">June 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">About the Russian Day at the World Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-06-09">June 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE RUSSIAN DAY AT THE WORLD EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last year the question was often raised in the pages of Rassviet of our participation in the Century of Progress Exposition in Chicago. As every one knows there was no Russian Day at the Exposition last year. The indifference to Russian culture and the disagreements prevailing in the life of our group are responsible for our isolation.</p>
   <p>However, in spite of our lack of unity, and our lack of an efficient organization, it should be possible for our group to organize a Russian Day at the Century of Progress Exposition. What we need most is the will to participate in the Exposition, and then the working out of details will take care of itself. The initiative and the preparatory steps for arranging a Russian Day at the Exposition should be undertaken by Russian societies in Chicago. The ways and means of accomplishing this undertaking will be found without difficulty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1384.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our motive in desiring to have our Russian Day at the Exposition is purely cultural. The Century of Progress Exposition is a mirror and an index of the achievements of all nations during the last hundred years. Almost every civilized nation has its own pavilion at the Exposition, where many objects and exhibits representing that nation's contributions to our civilization can be seen. Only we Russians are the exception. We have neglected to build a Russian pavilion at the Exposition. Because we are not represented at the Exposition, those who visit it receive the impression that the Russian people have not yet reached that stage of civilization which would allow them to show their achievements to the world. The majority of those who visit the Exposition do not know that Russia has actually made many important contributions to the common treasury of human achievements. The Russian people possess many of their own native cultural values, which they do not know how to appreciate or how to use to the best advantage at the proper time.</p>
   <p>But even with all these drawbacks and difficulties, it is still possible to organize the Russian Day at the Century of Progress Exposition. We have all <pb facs="5423967_2_1385.jpg" n="3"/>the possibilities for the successful arrangement of such a Russian holiday at the exposition. We now have here in America our noted Russian singer, Maria Kurenko, who would not refuse to participate in the Russian Day concert at the Exposition. The Russian Cossack Choir is now making public appearances in Chicago, and would be glad to appear at the Exposition. There is a good Slay Choir in Gary, Ind. A popular Russian balalaika orchestra is located in Detroit. It could be invited to Chicago to participate in the Russian Day concert at the Exposition, and it would probably accept the invitation.</p>
   <p>All these groups and individuals, and others that might be invited, would furnish us with ample talent for the proposed undertaking. It remains only for our organizations and their leaders to get together and work out a plan of action.</p>
   <p>If, however, for any reason whatsoever, the Russian organizations in Chicago should not be able to organize successfully such a Russian Day at the <pb facs="5423967_2_1386.jpg" n="4"/>Exposition, then we might as well ask ourselves a question: "Are we worthy to call ourselves Russians?" Then we could rightfully be ashamed that we have missed the opportunity of showing to the world our national cultural values and our economic achievements.</p>
   <p>It will be to our permanent disgrace and dishonor if the Russian group in Chicago neglects the opportunities that present themselves and do not arrange a Russian Day at the Century of Progress Exposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
