<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-19">Feb. 19, 1935</date><title level="a">On Abundance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-02-19">Feb. 19, 1935</date><title level="a">ON ABUNDANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been well known for a long time that the latter part of December is the time of year when bolshevik functionaries of every description perform miracles, in connection with compulsory tasks assigned to them. No matter how laggard they may have been throughout the year, they invariably catch up during the last two weeks of the year with the planned-economy assignments, and, by January 1 their manner of performance has become not only fair but excellent in most cases.</p>
   <p>In the January 1 issues, the soviet papers, armed with statistics, wrote about these accomplishments, and gave out information as to what had been done during the year. Among such information we find figures to prove that there is a great abundance of manufactured goods. And, really, if the trade turn-over in 1932 amounted to forty billion roubles, it reached sixty-one billion roubles in 1934. Thus, Economic Life informs us in its issue of January 2.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0117.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This growth is truly a miraculous one. Obviously, the stock of goods is inexhaustible!</p>
   <p>But, when one compares these impressive figures with the occurrences of everyday life in an attempt to find confirmation to the statements about the abundance of goods, he finds himself confronted with contradictions. According to official data the situation appears excellent, but everyday occurrences show an acute scarcity of goods, and an urgent demand for every available article in trade.</p>
   <p>"Purchasing agents of the Department of Supplies of Voronezhsbit [Translator's note: Central Trading Organization of Voronezh province] have converted the hallways of this Institution into a kind of black bourse. They trade everything for anything. The most ludicrous and bizarre transactions take the place of normal trading: they trade lumber for nails, nails for acids, and acids for felt boots."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0118.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus, the soviet trade turnover, in the capital of the Central Black Soil region in Voronezh, is described by the bolshevik press.</p>
   <p>Some of the purchasing agents under the influence of an "abundance" of goods become rapacious. According to the local soviet paper, the purchasing agents acting in the Voronezh black bourse buy up everything they find in stores or warehouses. The most active and energetic ones, those whom the superiors consider most valubable and deserving, do their business in a manner about like this. An agent enters the offices of the Voronezh Central Distributing depot and begins with these direct questions:</p>
   <p>"Do you sell anything?"</p>
   <p>"Yes, we sell."</p>
   <p>"Sell to me?"</p>
   <p>"Sell what?"</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0119.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Anything you have...."</p>
   <p>If one read about such episodes in 1920 it would have been quite understandable. There were no goods to be had then, and one snatched every available article from whence he could. There was an extreme need of goods in every-line, and besides, it was senseless to keep rapidly depreciating money in one's pockets. But now, as they claim, goods are in abundance and the rouble is strong, as never before. Such a rouble should be saved only because the authorities have promised a lowering of prices, and, as a result, its future purchasing power will be greater. However, no one seems to believe this.</p>
   <p>Purchasing agents are sent out by countless soviet organizations in search of much-needed goods and supplies. They rake the entire territory of the Soviet Union for goods, and snatch up everything they see, and buy everything they happen to come across.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
