<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-19">Apr. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">A New Wave of Dumping</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0805</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0805.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-19">Apr. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW WAVE OF DUMPING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press has once more begun to pay considerable attention to the Japanese dumping of goods on the American market. Some of the newspapers even go so far as to claim that if the Federal government does not raise the existing tariff on cheap Japanese goods, many American factories will be forced to close their doors in the immediate future.</p>
   <p>As a result of the recent dumping, the American market has been swamped with Japanese textiles. Even though the Japanese goods are very inferior to the American textiles, the latter cannot compete with the Japanese product because it is sold at much lower prices. The American textile industry, as a result, suffers a loss of market, and is forced to reduce operations gradually. Some of the textile mills in the New England States even now do not have enough orders, and are ready to shut down.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0806.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such circumstances have alarmed not only the textile manufacturers; government circles in Washington are also aware of the situation. According to reports from Washington, President Roosevelt has instructed the Tariff Commission to revise the rates upwards for the obvious purpose of protecting American industry from the effects of Japanese competition. Besides textiles, Japan exports to the United States immense quantities of other goods, including American flags.</p>
   <p>Last year Japan dumped on the American market fifteen million dollars' worth of electric bulbs. These bulbs are of a poor quality; they use much more current and give less light (forty-one per cent less than the American lamps). They are sold at half the price of the American product. This underselling is explained by the fact that the Japanese workers receive very low wages. Women and children employed in making the bulbs receive from two to four cents a day. In other branches of Japanese industry, the same very low wage scale prevails. The results of dumping cheap Japanese bulbs on the American market are already having their full effect. Last <pb facs="5423967_2_0807.jpg" n="3"/>year, according to the newspapers, the General Electric Company was forced to discontinue operation of two of its plants--one located in Buffalo, New York, and the other in Newark, New Jersey--employing normally fifteen thousand men.</p>
   <p>Even the Bolsheviks are dumping goods on the American market. The Russian people are starving, yet the Bolsheviks are exporting grain, butter, fish, and other food products. Russian peasants and workers cover their bodies with rags while the Bolsheviks export textile goods and footwear to various countries.</p>
   <p>For instance, in several Chicago stores, comfortable slippers of Soviet manufacture are for sale. A pair of good American slippers sells for $3.25, while the Soviet product is sold at $1.37. Other Soviet goods are also cheap, except, of course, caviar. This Soviet underselling can also be explained by the fact that the Soviet government, like the Japanese industrialists, pays very low wages--quite frequently none at all--to its <pb facs="5423967_2_0808.jpg" n="4"/>workers, and cares very little about the needs of its own people. As a rule, countries export only their surplus goods, but the Bolsheviks export goods which are badly needed by their own people. For this reason, many newspapers feel that the Federal government should increase the tariff on various foreign goods and thus protect American industry and labor from unscrupulous foreign competition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
