<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-05-05">May 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A Russian Singer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1926-05-05">May 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A RUSSIAN SINGER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some three months ago there came to Chicago from Canada a Russian singer, the baritone Serghey Nikoleyevich Sergheyev (Boleslavovich).</p>
   <p>When he was a youth only sixteen years old, Mr. Sergheyev--at that time he was called just Serezhka--began to learn singing under the tuition of the Italian professor Cato, a well known teacher in Moscow.</p>
   <p>Being very gifted and possessing an excellent voice, the young Sergheyev began to sing at the "Aquarium" already at the age of eighteen, after only two years training. After many years of singing in the Moscow theaters, in provincial towns and in the Moscow Opera Mr. Sergheyev left Russia in 1922.</p>
   <p>During seven months he sang in the Far East, in Harbin, Shanghai, and other cities; he also sang with great success in Canada, and now he has come to Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sergheyev's first appearance as a singer in Chicago was on Sunday, May 2, <pb facs="5423967_2_1143.jpg" n="2"/>in the Polonia Union Hall, corner Milwaukee Ave. and Augusta Blvd. It was a great success. Mr. Sergheyev sang in Russian. He had to sing four encores.</p>
   <p>Before the Russian colony Mr. Sergheyev sang for the first time at the concert of the Independent Parish, on May 9. By the by, Mr. Sergheyev has signed a contract with the "Orpheum Circuit", the largest agency for theatrical and vaudeville shows; on September 1st he will start on a tour, and will visit many American cities.</p>
   <p>G. Gorsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
