<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-20">Aug. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Schools Should Be Purged from the Bolshevik Contagion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-08-20">Aug. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHOOLS SHOULD BE PURGED FROM THE BOLSHEVIK CONTAGION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lately, a conference of the Communist organizations was held in Chicago. This conference was called by Novy Mir (New World) as a "convention of the federation of schools for children." At this conference were present, of course, delegates from the schools for children, but the work of the conference was not conducted by them, but by the delegates of the Communist organizations having no connection at all with the schools for children. This conference was headed by illiterate delegates of the following Communist organizations; branches No. 35, 50, and 54 of R. P. M. A. S. (Russian Peoples Mutual Aid Society); the cooperative society; a branch of the international defense organization; the atheist society; delegates from the newspaper Novy Mir and others. From this one could easily form an idea of what kind of a "convention of federation of schools for children" this was.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1491.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is not surprising, therefore, that this conference was not interested so much in school affairs as in politics. The conference did not decide upon any important question concerning the school affairs, but gave most of its time and attention to the Soviet Government, the five year plan, Communist propaganda, and the newspaper "Rassviet."</p>
   <p>This conference could not be different from what it was. If this were a real convention of federation of schools for children, then there would be no delegates from societies, who had nothing in common with school affairs, but were exclusively interested in political agitation. In such a case the convention would have left alone the Soviet Government, the five year plan, and the newspaper "Rassviet," and would have tried to solve the following problems: Why do the schools drag such a pitiful existence? Why do the Russian immigrants not send their children to schools, and why are the children after years of attendance not able to write and speak Russian?</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1492.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But at the conference these vital questions were not even discussed. They have not touched these questions for the only reason that the schools, headed by Communist, were not properly developed, because they pursued political and not cultural aims; that the children at the same time were unable to write and speak Russian, and that the position of teachers are in the majority cases, occupied by Bolshevik ignoramuses. That is why the conference ignored the most important school affairs and was occupied with the framing of political resolutions.</p>
   <p>That is why, we presume, that on the Chicago school front, everything will remain as before. The schools for children will as previously be headed by illiterate Deviatkins; Klimkovs and Semashkos, who have a very hazy knowledge of the Russian language and the Russian culture, but are well acquainted with The A B C of Communism and with the biography of Lenin.</p>
   <p>The Communists, as is known, very often speak of eliminating religion from the schools, and as soon as they seize control of any school, they <pb facs="5423967_2_1493.jpg" n="4"/>immediately introduce in it their religious Bolshevik dope and teach the children not the Russian language, but their "Bolshevik catechism."</p>
   <p>As a result of this many immigrants do not send their children to schools and if some do so, they soon become convinced that their children, while attending the Bolshevik schools, study the "life of the Communist Saints," and the Communist "paternoster," and that their children waste their time.</p>
   <p>On account of this, the schools drag a pitiful existence and do not fulfil their program of teaching the children the Russian language.</p>
   <p>Many colonists have been reconciled with this situation, and they think that there is no remedy for that. But this should not be so. The Russian immigrants interested in the problems of education must shake off their indifference and should take into their hands the expansion of the school work in Chicago. For this purpose, first of all, they should expel from the existing schools the Bolshevik contagion and invite educated and cultural persons to the position of teachers. The schools must be the <pb facs="5423967_2_1494.jpg" n="5"/>cradle of knowledge and culture and not the seat of boors and political zealots. The schools must be headed not by illiterate blabbers like Deviatkin and Semashko, but by the parents themselves. Only then will the school affairs prosper and the children be able to write and speak Russian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
