<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IV, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">Project of a Constitution of Russian Medical Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IV, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">PROJECT OF A CONSTITUTION OF RUSSIAN MEDICAL SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. Name of the Society</p>
   <p>"Russian Medical Society of Chicago" (Russkoe Meditsinskoe Obshchestvo Goroda Chikago).</p>
   <p>2. Aims of the Society</p>
   <p>In uniting the Russian physicians of Chicago and vicinity the Society has the following objects in view: a) the exchange of opinions on scientific cases through medical reports, discussions, and demonstration of interesting clinical cases. b) the discussion of social-economic questions relating to the Russian medical profession; c) the organization of work bureau and an information-legal section; d) the protection of the interests of Russian physicians in the United States; e) the organization of mutual aid for needy members, especially aid to those doing original scientific work; f) the betterment of the conditions of medical aid for the Russian colony of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>3. Members of the Society</p>
   <p>Every Russian physician having an interest in Russia is eligible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1531.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Note: for the successful carrying out of the aims set forth each member of the Russian Medical Society should belong to the Chicago Medical Society and the American Medical Association.</p>
   <p>4. Financial means of the Society</p>
   <p>Members' dues, and income from entertainments, lectures, etc., given for the Society.</p>
   <p>5. The Administration of the Society</p>
   <p>1. General and special meetings of the society</p>
   <p>2. Responsible persons</p>
   <p>3. Special committees</p>
   <p>4. General meetings: a) yearly for year's report and the election of responsible personnel; b) monthly meetings called for the third Friday of each month for scientific reports and for the discussion of current questions.</p>
   <p>6. Responsible Personnel</p>
   <p>(1) President; (2) vice-president; (3) secretary; (4) treasurer; (5) special <pb facs="5423967_2_1532.jpg" n="3"/>committees: reports, social-economic questions, work bureau and information. Each committee consists of five members. The president and secretary of the Society are ex-officio members of all committees.</p>
   <p>7. Membership Dues The membership dues are $5.00 per year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
