<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-07-13">July 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Constitution of the Russian Co-Operative Restaurant</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-07-13">July 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONSTITUTION OF THE RUSSIAN CO-OPERATIVE RESTAURANT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. Title of the organization -- The Russian Cooperative Restaurant of the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>2. Aim of the cooperative -- To give healthful food to the Russian immigrants of Chicago for a moderate price.</p>
   <p>3. The cooperative is a non-partisan organization.</p>
   <p>4. The supreme administrative organ of the cooperative is the general assembly of all the members of the cooperative. General assemblies are held once a month and a quorum of two thirds of all the members is necessary for the assembly to be effective. Besides this, special assemblies can be called if emergency questions arise.</p>
   <p>5. The executive committee -- An executive committee of five persons is elected by the general assembly for the term of six months. This executive committee consists of a recording secretary, a financial secretary and three members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>6.Revising committee -- The revising committee is elected by the general assembly and consists of three members for the term of six months. The duty of the revising committee is to control all the officers and to present the reports to the general assembly.</p>
   <p>7. Membership of the cooperative -- Persons of both sexes can be members of the cooperative if they accept the constitution of the cooperative. New members are admitted at the general assembly. The recommendation of one member of the cooperative is necessary.</p>
   <p>(Note: - Persons having no acquaintances among the members of the cooperative are admitted by the decision of the general assembly.)</p>
   <p>8. Funds of the cooperative -- The funds of the cooperative shall consist of membership entrance fees to the amount of $25, of the proceeds from various undertakings, and of voluntary contributions.</p>
   <p>(Note: - Persons desiring to become members of the cooperative but unable to pay the membership entrance fee in full, can be allowed by the decision of the general assembly to pay in installments.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1096.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>9. If a member of the cooperative leaves for his native country, or through some cause worthy of consideration cannot remain a member of the cooperative, all his money is returned to him, and through the decision of the general assembly a part of the dividends can also be given to him.</p>
   <p>(Note: - Under no circumstances can money be returned before the term of six months from the day of the admission as a member of the cooperative, except for the above mentioned causes.)</p>
   <p>10. Manager of the restaurant -- The manager of the restaurant is elected at the general assembly for an indefinite term. The manager receives a fixed salary. He has to submit to the decisions of the general assembly and the executive committee.</p>
   <p>11. Liquidation of the cooperative -- In case of the liquidation of the cooperative of the Russian Restaurant, all the property and the cash are to be donated to the orphanages of Russia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
