<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1926-10-05">October 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning Bolshevist Propaganda in the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-10-05">October 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING BOLSHEVIST PROPAGANDA IN THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the time when this editorial appeared on the pages of Rassviet, the question of the recognition of the Soviet government by the United States was being eagerly discussed in Washington. The opponents of such recognition were pointing out the fact that the Soviet government was conducting through its agents in the United States secret propaganda of the teachings of Communism. The author of the editorial thinks that this propaganda in itself is harmless, as the American workmen are not at all inclined to listen to it. He points out, however, that the American capitalists and their representatives in Washington naturally cannot sympathize with this propaganda and, while it exists, cannot desire the recognition of the Soviet government which is secretly furthering the activities of the propagandists. They realize that the Soviet government needs recognition chiefly in order to borrow money from the United States, and the borrowed money <pb facs="5423967_2_0275.jpg" n="2"/>would be used mostly for furthering the propaganda of the "world revolution." This, says the author of the editorial, would naturally not be in the interests either of the Americans or of the population of Soviet Russia, as the Russian workers and peasants would not be benefited by the money loaned by the United States, and would only have to work harder in order to enable the Soviet government to pay its debt to the United States.</p>
   <p>The author also points out that Stalin does not deny the fact that Communist propaganda is carried on in the United States by Russians, only maintaining that this is done by private individuals who have not been given any authority to do so by the Soviet government. However, Stalin fails in his answer to take any notice of the accusation that such "private individuals" have been receiving money from Moscow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
