<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-08-21">Aug. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A Russian Musical Studio in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-08-21">Aug. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A RUSSIAN MUSICAL STUDIO IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In all branches of art Russia has fully confirmed the truth that light comes from the East. Russian theater, ballet, painting and especially music have won world fame a long time ago. Who among the Americans has not heard the names of Tchaikovsky, Rakhmaninov, Shalyapin? The Americans, who delight in their jazz music and (who) have no school of music of their own, no really talented and expert teachers of music, willingly entrust their children to Russian teachers of music. There are many Russian musical studios in New York, and there are several in Chicago. The directors of such studios do amidst the very whirlpool of "business" a work which, though not noticeable to many, is exceptionally valuable and productive - they introduce Russian music and further the musical development of young gifted Americans. Among the Russian musical studios in Chicago one, that of Vitaliy Yakovlevich Shney, is occupying a nook in the celebrated Kimball Building.</p>
   <p>Vitaliy Yakovlevich Shney was graduated in 1915 from the St. Petersburg <pb facs="5423967_2_1311.jpg" n="2"/>Conservatory, where he had been a pupil of the celebrated professor Madam A. N. Yesipova-Leshchivskaya. He participated in the World War. During the period of 1918-20, when Denikin was in power in a part of Russia, Mr. Shney occupied the post of Director of the Conservatory in Minsk.</p>
   <p>When Denikin's army left Russia, Mr. Shney migrated to Berlin, where he was very active giving concerts.</p>
   <p>In 1923 Mr. Shney came to Chicago and opened a studio; he has been also giving concerts from time to time, together with his pal, Mr. Benditsky, also of the St. Petersburg Conservatory. They would play duets on two pianos.</p>
   <p>During his short stay in Chicago, Mr. Shney became popular in musical circles as an experienced teacher and musical instructor of his pupil.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>About a month ago there was arranged at the Kimball Hall a concert in order to demonstrate the attainments of Mr. Shney's pupils. After the concert there was published in some American musical magazines articles praising very highly the results achieved by Mr. Shney.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that in the Russian colony Mr. Shney's name is hardly known to anybody. And yet a Russian living in a foreign land, far away from his native country, should know and appreciate all those modest workers in the field of art who, by their activities, help very much the cause of bringing closer together the peoples of Russia and America.</p>
   <p>This notice was written with the purpose of giving information about one of these workers.</p>
   <p>G. Gruzd.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
