<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-27">Oct. 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Local Bolshevik Press Denies Hunger in Russia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1651</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1651.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-27">Oct. 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL BOLSHEVIK PRESS DENIES HUNGER IN RUSSIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is nothing more disgraceful and criminal than the conscious lies and hypocrisy of our local Bolshevik and pro-Bolshevik press in its efforts to conceal the fact that there is general starvation in the Soviet Union. The Bolshevik scribblers, shamelessly and without any scruples, deny the fact that people are dying of hunger in the Soviet paradise, saying that all these stories are but inventions and misrepresentations, of the enemies of the Soviet government.</p>
   <p>In their press, the Bolsheviks subject to the most merciless abuse and invective all persons who write and speak of starvation in Russia. They brand all honest and sincere Russians as White Guards and counterrevolutionists, because they speak boldly and openly about the widespread hunger that now exists in Russia--that has already killed, and still will kill, millions of <pb facs="5423967_2_1652.jpg" n="2"/>people.</p>
   <p>The Bolsheviks, naturally, deny the existing famine in the Soviet Union, for they are up to their ears in lies and deceits; but all honest and decent people will continue to uncover and explain all Communist activities, showing them to the people in their true light.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of letters received from Russia describing the horrors of starvation there give conclusive proof of the raging famine in the Soviet Union, and no one can deny it. Only the vulgar Bolshevik press stubbornly continues to keep its eyes closed to the existing conditions in Russia. It can be understood that nothing better could be expected of the Bolsheviks since, as everybody knows, the cause of the present hunger in Russia lies in the economic policy of the Soviet regime--the policy of exporting all Russian crops to foreign countries, leaving nothing for the Russian people themselves to live on.</p>
   <p>When people in this country honestly and openly point out this basic truth, <pb facs="5423967_2_1653.jpg" n="3"/>these Bolshevik wretches fall, with unusual fury, upon these honest people, attacking them, and calling them the enemies of the working classes and of the peasants of the Soviet Union.</p>
   <p>Moans and soul-piercing cries of the Russian peasants and workers that have come to our ears plainly show that the Bolshevik dictatorship has brought the Russian nation to famine artificially created, to cannibalism, and to slavery. But the Bolshevik newspapers in America at all times are defending and justifying the vile and abominable acts committed by the Soviet government.</p>
   <p>Our local Bolshevik scribblers have been employing strange logic in denying the known facts about famine in Russia. They have chosen a crooked and hazardous road of advocacy and deception, leading to an abyss of misfortune and calamity for the Russian people. Deceit, hypocrisy and slander permeate all thoughts and acts of the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1654.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Truth, freedom, and equality for the whole people--these the Bolsheviks have trampled under their filthy feet, and have undertaken the job of destroying as deadly enemies all those who interfere with their wild orgies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
