<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-03">Feb. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Politics?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-02-03">Feb. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS POLITICS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whenever there is talk about the life of the Russian group in America, one hears the assertion that the participation of Russian-Americans in the political life of this country is very weak and insignificant. One also hears the complaint that, in the past, our group was much more interested and more actively engaged in the political affairs of the American nation, and that only recently it seems to have lost all interest in the political questions of this country.</p>
   <p>But, in the first place, what is politics? In ancient times the word "politics" was applied to the knowledge and study of society and its problems. The ancient Greeks used the word "politics" to designate all social phenomena of the human race. In modern times, the term "politics" is applied only to a certain part of social phenomena: namely, to national and international affairs. Politics can be divided into two branches, applied politics and the philosophy of politics. The philosophy of politics has to do with its principles and course, and also current social phenomena.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as applied politics is concerned, (that is, all political institutions as are known today in every country), our relation to such politics is only negative. But when the principles of politics and the social order are in question, our interest should be decidedly positive. Lack of interest in this type of politics is deplorable; it is harmful to human progress. Every man should have some definite opinion of his own relative to our present social order and social trends, and should be able to evaluate them from the point of view of one or another school of thought on social phenomena. A man without his own personal views on political matters, a man indifferent to social phenomena around him, is useless to society and is harmful to his immediate surroundings.</p>
   <p>Our Russian group in America should by all means keep up and expand its interest in national and world politics of the doctrinal type. The loss of interest in political questions of this type among our people signifies a transformation of alert, progressive citizens into ordinary Babbitts. Such persons are not interested in what is going on in the world, nor in the political leadership</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0198.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>of the nations, nor even in the political or social measures being introduced into the lives of their countries. These Philistines would ignore in a quite indifferent and unconcerned manner, all such contemporary social and political problems as socialism, communism, and anarchism. In short, they would be dead men, from the standpoint of social progress and reform.</p>
   <p>There is no excuse for failing to participate in the work of social progress and social change of our time, nor for not developing one's own point of view regarding all social and political matters of modern life. Time and opportunities are plentiful.</p>
   <p>A man may easily be deeply interested in all social problems, and at the same time be engaged in rounding out his education, or in learning some new craft or trade. The important thing is for him to have his own outlook on, and his own approach to, all political questions facing the human race today.</p>
   <p>As we mentioned before, the word "politics" may mean one or both of the following</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0199.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>two things: first, an active participation in the political life of the country we live in; second, an actual belonging to one or another of the social movements existing in this country. We are little interested in the first type of politics. And if the entire Russian group in this country is indifferent to this first type of politics, we should be glad of it. But we cannot rejoice if the Russian people in America, as a whole, take a negative attitude with respect to the second type. The future of our society depends upon the understanding, support, and expansion of this second type of politics. There are no politically indifferent nations or groups of people on this globe. Every country, every racial or geographical group of people, has its own politics, with its own shade of meaning. Whether this shade of meaning is acceptable to us or not, we should not close our eyes to it. The politics acceptable to us, we should support; the others, we should fight. The question of politics can be solved correctly and satisfactorily only by dividing it into its separate phases or conceptions, and then accepting or rejecting each on its own merits.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
