<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-05">July 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian-American Democratic League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-05">July 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League of Illinois is at this time the focal point of interest for the entire Russian colony in Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>The new federal laws regarding social security, old-age pensions, and certain limitations of the privileges of noncitizens in this country, on the one hand, and the loss of all hope for an early return to Russia, on the other, are the factors forcing Russian immigrants in America to seek United States citizenship.</p>
   <p>In recent months, not only the young Russian-Americans but also those of the older generation who have lived in this country for over twenty years have been besieging the Russian-American Democratic League with petitions for help in obtaining American citizenship. In many cases, candidates for citizenship find difficulty in properly filling out the various forms and applications. The League maintains a special service to aid these people. A well-qualified <pb facs="5423967_2_0543.jpg" n="2"/>person is always present at the League's office to fill out the forms, and otherwise serve as an adviser in all matters pertaining to citizenship.</p>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League likewise helps its members with other legal matters, for the truth is that in situations where the private individual has no chance of succeeding, the organization representing him usually has much greater chances of success.</p>
   <p>American public life is so constituted that, whereas we common citizens depend a great deal in our daily life upon our federal, state, and local authorities, they in turn depend upon us during the elections. When new candidates or incumbents run for public office, they need our support and our votes. The better we are organized--the greater the number of voters we represent--the more we are taken into consideration, and the more respect we command.</p>
   <p>Other national groups in this city understood long ago the necessity of organization. Today they occupy a much higher social and political position than <pb facs="5423967_2_0544.jpg" n="3"/>the Russian group. They hold many important political posts in the local, state, and federal administrations, and generally enjoy many privileges which thus far are denied our group. The Russian people in Chicago and elsewhere were not properly organized politically, and, for this reason, they fell far behind other foreign-language groups in political, social, and economic respects. It is a comforting thought that today we seem to be conscious of our mistakes, that we are trying to overcome them by forming strong organizations and by entering the political life of the country of our adoption. Great tasks lie before us, and we trust our efforts will meet with success if only we stand together and fight together.</p>
   <p>The membership of the Russian-American Democratic League is growing steadily. This organization excludes from its program all religious activity, nor does it attempt to do the work of a benefit society; hence it does not interfere with the activities of these and other Russian organizations. The Russian-American Democratic League has taken it upon itself to extend and to defend the rights and privileges of American citizens of Russian birth or extraction. No other <pb facs="5423967_2_0545.jpg" n="4"/>existing Russian organization has included this activity in its program. Therefore, all Russian organizations may and should co-operate with the Russian-American Democratic League, and should support its work. The Russian people of Chicago and vicinity, regardless of the fact that they may belong to other Russian organizations, may become members of the Russian-American Democratic League. The membership fee is only one dollar a year.</p>
   <p>The Russian-American Democratic League will give a big picnic on July 14. The purpose of the picnic is to improve the finances of the League, and, at the same time, to establish closer and more direct contact with Russian organizations and with Russian people individually. The picnic will be held in the woods at Elston Avenue and Central Avenue. We hope to see a great many Russian men and women at the picnic this coming Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
