<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A Russian Producers' Association ("Artel")</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-03">Sept. 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A RUSSIAN PRODUCERS' ASSOCIATION ("ARTEL")</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Four men from Grodno who have been working for a long period of time with large firms and have been attentively watching the work that was being done there, started about a year and half ago an enterprise of their own.</p>
   <p>This enterprise is located at 2306 La Salle Street, and its name is the "Reliable Battery and Plates Manufacturing Company."</p>
   <p>The men from Grodno are Philip Kozlovich, Joseph Yudchits, Ivan Omelko and Ignatiy Kugach.</p>
   <p>Each of them contributed to this enterprise a certain amount of money and is also contributing his work, knowledge and experience; and all receive an equal share of the profits.</p>
   <p>None of the four members of this association has any technical education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1050.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They got all their knowledge and experience by doing practical work. Attention and inborn intelligence helped them to perfect themselves in this kind of work, to master all the details of it.</p>
   <p>And this work is pretty complicated and requires knowledge.</p>
   <p>They are assembling batteries for automobiles and radio. Besides they also make themselves various parts for such batteries.</p>
   <p>The workshop occupies four large rooms.</p>
   <p>One of these large rooms is occupied by the foundry department; another by the chemical department; a third by turning lathes and the finishing department; and one very large room holds already assembled batteries, plates and various other parts.</p>
   <p>Besides the four companions there are also working in this workshop four hired workmen. And in the winter 8 or 10 such men are employed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1051.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In all departments the work is going on speedily and harmoniously. In one place various parts are continually being cast; in another these parts are being turned on lathes, equalized, cut into proper shape by milling machines and ultimately finished; in a third place the various metallic parts are submitted to high pressure, polished, cleansed by various chemicals, painted and dried.</p>
   <p>Everywhere you see casts, tin, lead, steel and finished and unfinished parts of batteries.</p>
   <p>You hear the men from Grodno use continually such terms as "negatives," "passives" and various chemical terms.</p>
   <p>Everything in this enterprise looks quite businesslike.</p>
   <p>Connected with the workshop is a very decent-looking office. All negotiations with businessmen are conducted by Philip Kozlovich, a member <pb facs="5423967_2_1052.jpg" n="4"/>of the association, who also takes care of the bookkeeping.</p>
   <p>He is also considered to be the manager of the whole enterprise, as he is the most experienced and competent workman. During his hours of leisure, i. e., when he is not occupied by bookkeeping, talking to customers, etc., he does some work in different departments and supervises the work done by others.</p>
   <p>This factory has earned a good reputation and gets big orders of batteries, plates and various parts from some large firms, also orders from smaller firms and private persons.</p>
   <p>Apparently, these Russians from Grodno have become somewhat Americanized.</p>
   <p>On the window of their workshop is to be seen the following characteristic sign: HIGHEST QUALITY, LONGEST LIFE, AT LOWEST COST.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1053.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>One can see on the window also the prices of batteries of various sizes and of parts for such batteries.</p>
   <p>As I was looking at the work done so harmoniously by these men from Grodno and at their pretty well managed enterprise, I involuntarily regretted that we have only few such enterprises, artels.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, this miniature artel, several small groups of Russians who have started small enterprises, such as garages, meat markets and grocery stores, and finally cooperative restaurants, plainly testify to the tendency of separate groups of the colony to start cooperative enterprises, artels, mutual credit associations and similar enterprises conducted by groups.</p>
   <p>Almost all these undertakings of groups of Russian immigrants are successful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1054.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>As one observes these successes, one begins to think that in a not very distant future we may see in our colony a House of the People managed on cooperative lines, a consumers' cooperative store where clothes and shoes could be bought, artels of tailors, window washers, workers in metal.</p>
   <p>Everywhere one hears Russians discuss these things. And all these things will be realized sooner or later.</p>
   <p>Workmen's artels, cooperative stores and mutual credit associations have undoubtedly a great future. Such enterprises will bring new life into the colony, will raise it to a higher level. Many members of our colony will find in these enterprises an opportunity to develop some creative activity and to apply the experience and knowledge which they have gained in a foreign country by hard labor.</p>
   <p>A. Zemetchevsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
