<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-05-03">5/23/24</date>.
<title level="a">The Soviet Government and the Workmen.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial by Dr. Pertsov.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-05-23">5/23/24</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT AND THE WORKMEN.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial by Dr. Pertsov.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The condition of hundreds of thousands of workmen who live under the rule of the workmen's and peasant's government, even as it is described in the Soviet press, is far from being enviable.</p>
   <p>Unemployment, strikes, continual unrest - these are the conditions under which the workmen in Russia have to live and to struggle - those very workmen who have been shedding their blood in helping to overthrow the old regime and to prevent its restoration; who have been sacrificing their lives for the sake of a better future for our country.</p>
   <p>If the workman does not belong to the communist party or to the "comsomol" ("Communistic Alliance of young people"), if he is not one of their "set" - the ruling party is not interested in him at all, he is regarded as a nonentity.</p>
   <p>Unemployment is on the increase on all the immense area of the U.S.S.R.From the last data published in the Soviet press one gathers that the number of unemployed in the South of Russia is increasing tremendously.</p>
   <p>This increase is felt especially in the region of Odessa, in Kiev and Kharkov.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0281.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Towards the end of April, in the province of Odessa there were 66,000 unemployed; of these 37,286 were registered in the city of Odessa. During the last ten days this number had increased by one thousand. The largest percentage of unemployed is to be found among the office workers and the metal workers. Unemployment is growing even in those district centers where it was not noticeable before.</p>
   <p>In Kiev on April 1st, there were registered by the Labor Exchange 30,000 unemployed.</p>
   <p>In Kharkov the unemployed are just as numerous as in Odessa and Kiev. And when the working masses in Kharkov tried to raise their voice, what was the answer given to them by their own "labor" government.</p>
   <p>On the night of May 1st, the G.P.U. (Note: The State Political Administration -Gospolitupravlenie, in other words the secret police. D.S.), in order to prevent demonstrations which were expected on that day, arrested many workmen, unemployed and college students. The official first of May procession was not impressive. Near the depot, in the Karpovsky garden the unemployed held a meeting while the official manifestation was going on; but the militia dispersed the crowd.</p>
   <p>Such are the methods used by the new regime. In those districts where the workmen can find some employment they can often work only three or four days during a week, no more.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0282.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As to the conditions of work, you can imagine what they are like when you know that even the scanty wages that are paid to the workmen, (the average wages are 10 golden roubles per month,i.e. $5.00) the latter often get with a delay of half a year; and that the workman who is not a member of the communist party has to stand all kinds of indignities from the foreman who is a communist.</p>
   <p>All this often arouses the anger of the workmen and induces them to strike; but strikes in the nationalized industrial plants are forbidden by a special decree: "you may strike, if you like, but only in the private enterprises of the "nepmen". (Note: i.e. of those capitalists who were given a chance to start again some small industrial or commercial enterprise under the regime of comparative toleration of private industry and commerce, which was introduced by Lenin. The word "nepmen" is derived from "NEP" - an abbreviation of "new economic policy". D.S.)</p>
   <p>Just a few days ago serious strikes broke out among the workers of the textile factories of the region of Vyaznikov in the Vladimirskaya province. The strikers demand that the back pay due to them be handed them, that the housing conditions be improved and that relief be given to the unemployed out of the profits of the Vyaznikov Flax Trust.</p>
   <p>These demands of the textile workers were rejected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0283.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In those cases when it was considered to be expedient from the standpoint of the state, that same "firmly established" government did not shrink even before the use of reprisals against the discontented small fry of the communist realm.</p>
   <p>The instigators of revolts are put into prison. This is easy as recently there has just been assigned a large fund for the building of new prisons (the number of the old ones was not sufficient); as to the riff-raff - it is partly discharged with such passports as would make it impossible for those who own them to get any kind of employment; the others are allowed to go on with the work after having been soundly rated for their refractory spirit. who can tell us the number of workmen confined in Russian prisons? Who knows how many workmen are being exiled daily by the G.P.U. to far off Siberia?</p>
   <p>We read in the newspapers that towards the end of April there were freed from the Moscow prisons, 139 workmen arrested by the G.P.U., who had pleaded guilty and had professed to repent. And only one day before this occurrence there have been sent with a special train to the provinces of Tobolsk and Arkhangelsk, 470, political exiles, chiefly workmen and members of the intelligentsia from the province of Moscow.</p>
   <p>When hungry, unemployed workmen with large families who cannot stand any longer the hardships of their miserable existence, revolt and start some disturbances, what <pb facs="5423967_2_0284.jpg" n="5"/>answer does the government give to their demands to feed their starving wives and children? The answer is: bullets and the nagaika; (Note: a kind of whip used especially by the cossacks. D.S.). They seem to be imitating in this respect the old, well-tried methods of the regime that was abolished in 1917.</p>
   <p>Towards the end of that same month of April in Khartsyzsk (near Kharkov), riots were started by a large number of unemployed who had been suffering from famine for more than a month. The disturbance arose when the hungry workmen began to demand that rations be given out. During the quelling of these riots a detachment of agents of the G.P.U. fired a volley by which three unemployed workmen were killed and 17 were seriously wounded.</p>
   <p>In an official bulletin which was posted in the streets of Khartsyzsk the local Executive Committee warns the workmen against any acts having the character of demonstrations and explains that the agents of the G.P.U. who had killed several unemployed workmen, had been forced to use their weapons in self-defense, because the workmen who had organized the demonstration started to shoot at them.</p>
   <p>In general it is not difficult to see that the Moscow government which has taken a thoroughly left course goes straight towards achieving its purposes - and these purposes are anything but those of the Russian nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0285.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>What shall we say about a government which arrests citizens who have formed an organization, the aim of which is to give relief to unemployed men and women who have been abandoned to their fate by that same government?</p>
   <p>This is what we read in one of recent communications from Moscow:</p>
   <p>"On the night before April 25, there has been arrested here, a workmen's organization giving relief to the unemployed. On April 25, in daytime, there were arrested forty-seven members of another organization which was collecting money among the workmen of the Moscow factories and works. All the arrested members of these organizations were accused of instigating the unemployed against the soviet authorities and of making preparations for a demonstration on the first of May. In connection with these arrests other arrests and perquisitions were also made in the dormitories of colleges on April 25 and 26.</p>
   <p>In the whole history of the world we do not come across a case when a "firmly established" government (how everybody likes to apply this term to the Soviet government!) has existed for centuries seated on bayonets. The Romanovs ruled Russia for 300 years, but were deposed all the same, because they also were sitting on bayonets. The Russian people of the present time has been advancing by gigantic strides from the condition in which it was in the 17th and 18th centuries.</p>
   <p>We believe that its best part, the proletariat in general and the part of the intelligentsia <pb facs="5423967_2_0286.jpg" n="7"/>belonging to it (about the position of the latter "over there" we intend to say a word one of these days) will ultimately achieve liberation from the bondage to which they have been subjected by phantasts and experimentors who have lost all sense of reality and moderation.</p>
   <p>Signs of the fact that such a liberation is not far removed, are to be found in the Soviet press itself almost daily.</p>
   <p>The population of Russia expresses everywhere- though in an underhand manner - its distrust of the persons who stand at the head of the nation and do their, let us repeat it, mostly anti-social work.</p>
   <p>This distrust is voiced not only in whisper, but lately on some occasions also, openly.</p>
   <p>Thus some three weeks ago there has been closed in Moscow the all-Soviet union Convention of miners. At its closing session this Convention expressed its lack of confidence in the members of the Central Committee of the miners belonging to the Communist party.</p>
   <p>An expression of lack of trust usually means that the government which is heading a nation has to resign. But, of course, the present ministers who govern Russia treat these "counter-revolutionary" workmen in their own way. But if this cry of "We don't <pb facs="5423967_2_0287.jpg" n="8"/>trust you", would resound all over Russia (and you cannot put the whole of Russia into prison) the bolsheviki will be forced willy-nilly to depart and to make room for these elements of the country which the people would really like to hold the power.</p>
   <p>This, of course, does not exclude the possibility of honest bolsheviki to participating in the future democratic government of Russia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
