<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Belorusskaya Tribuna (White Russian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">October 20, 1928</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <!--                    <catRef target="#grp-white russian"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
     <item>WHITE RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Belorusskaya Tribuna (White Russian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">October 20, 1928</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About eight years ago the Polish Minister, L. Skulski, made a statement that in twenty-five years no trace will be left of the White Russian movement. The esteemed gentleman was wrong: What will be in seventeen years from now (eight years have passed already) we already now anticipate: Most likely no trace will be left by that time of Mr. Skulski.</p>
   <p>Again, six months ago a certain Chicago White Russian, a renegade, wrote that in six years the White Russian question will be forgotten in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Skulski of Chicago was wrong. Already American political groups and together with them naturally also the American social groups, have taken an interest in the White Russian question.</p>
   <p>In connection with the Presidential campaign a White Russian-American National Club was organized, which stirred up a most lively interest in its behalf among Americans.</p>
   <p>This, considering the 'erudition' of the above mentioned pseudo-prophets, <pb facs="5423967_2_0605.jpg" n="2"/>should not have occurred. But....can it be that American politicians are less informed about the population statistics of their country than our colony 'journalists'?</p>
   <p>Of course, the American politicians, in this instance the democrats, know well the meaning contained in our colony-term--Russian; they know the 99 percent of all the 'Russian' organizations in Chicago, and for that matter also in many other cities of the United States, belong to the White Russians, whether they are nationally conscious or not is another story, but the fact remains that they are White Russians. This nobody will dispute.</p>
   <p>For this reason the American democrats felt it was right to recognize the organized club of White Russian-American Nationalists which serves the interests of the National party.</p>
   <p>Again, for this reason the hopes of White Russian baiters had not been realized, in the numerous attempts to 'hide' the White Russian cause in America as harmful (indeed !) to all sorts of black-hundred appetites, those russifiers of all parts....</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0606.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Americans, of White Russian origin take a lively interest in the unfolding presidential campaign....</p>
   <p>...The official participation of White Russians in the presidential campaign of 1928, this new phase of interrelationship of White Russians with American political life, lifts the White Russian problem above the colony's work-aday ribaldry...</p>
   <p>Signed V. Polesski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
