<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. N. Novin</title>, Secretary of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>INTERVIEW WITH MR. N. NOVIN, SECRETARY OF THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN CITIZENS' ORGANIZATION</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Russian-American Citizens' Organization, with offices at 1902 W. Division Street, was organized in December, 1935. Its members were affiliated with the Russian-American Democratic League; the latter was organized in 1920, but is extinct now. This organization is distinctively non-Bolshevist, but non-partisan in scope. It follows and preaches liberal tendencies not only among its nationals, but in state and national affairs. This organization, with a membership around 10,000, has also branches in the states of Wisconsin, Iowa, Michigan, and Illinois, with headquarters in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the organization is: First, to unite all the citizens</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0567.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Interview with Mr. N. Novin, ...</p>
   <p>of Russian origin for an active part in the political life in this country; second, to help in obtaining citizenship papers for its nationals, as well as legal aid and defense; third, cultural work in the Russian colony; fourth, a broad propaganda among the Russians in Chicago to acquaint them with the history, modern life and culture of the United States; fifth, to strive to teach the Russians the American Constitution and its democratic form of government, at the same time abstaining from taking any part in the political life of their native country; sixth, active work among the Russians to teach them the English language and to enable them to become better citizens in the economic as well as cultural life of the United States.</p>
   <p>The organization gives to its members some four or five lectures during winter. During the summer entertainment is also provided in the form of picnics. Meetings are held monthly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0568.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Interview with Mr. N. Novin, ....</p>
   <p>The president of the organization is A. J. Pikiel, a Chicago attorney, and the secretary is Mr. N. Novin. This organization has an advisory board whose president is Dr. G. L. Percy.</p>
   <p>The constitution and by-laws of the Russian-American Citizens' Organization are in process of being printed at present and will soon be available for its members as well as others who are interested in its activities. The Russian-American Citizens' Organization is a part of the union of twenty different nationalities who have taken a very definite stand for the re-election of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The chairman is Congressman Sabath.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
