<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1923-02-01">Feb. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Russian Co-Operative Restaurant in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Free Russia</title>,
<date when="1923-02-01">Feb. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSSIAN CO-OPERATIVE RESTAURANT IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Four months ago a Russian cooperative restaurant was opened in Chicago. This restaurant at once drew the attention of almost all the Russian colony. Being the secretary of the cooperative Russian restaurant I regard it as my duty to explain in detail what this first restaurant really is, by whom it was founded, and for what purpose. I will try to be consistent and explain all in due order.</p>
   <p>1) Of what kind of people does the membership of the cooperative consist?</p>
   <p>Our cooperative consists of Russian workers, who, being members of our cooperative, at the same time are members of other Russian organizations and schools.</p>
   <p>2) For what aim have we organized our cooperative?</p>
   <p>Our cooperative was organized chiefly, to establish for the workers colony in Chicago an alimentation station where the workers, specially of <pb facs="5423967_2_1098.jpg" n="2"/>Russian origin, could receive wholesome food, prepared from own products in Russian style and for a moderate price; with this aim we opened our cooperative restaurant.</p>
   <p>3) From what sources was created our fund, which enabled us to open our restaurant?</p>
   <p>Our fund is created from membership fees of $50 from every member as an initial fee and $15 additional, altogether $65, which was earned by us honestly, by hard labor.</p>
   <p>4) How is our enterprise managed and controlled?</p>
   <p>In our cooperative there exists the very same order as in all other Russian workers' organizations, i. e. all important questions are decided by a general meeting of all the members of the cooperative. For the carrying out of the technical work and the working out of the projects on this or other questions, an executive committee of five persons is elected. For the control of the enterprise there is a revising commission of three, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5) Are we pursuing any commercial aims?</p>
   <p>We absolutely do not pursue any commercial aims. According to our constitution we renounce any profits. In case our enterprise provides profits, then the profits should go: a) for better food, b) for the expansion of our enterprise, and c) the remainder for the educational aims of the Russian colony of Chicago and suburbs.</p>
   <p>6) What is the attitude of the Russian workers' organizations of Chicago toward our cooperative?</p>
   <p>The Russian workers' organizations of Chicago sincerely welcomed our cooperative and the opening of our cooperative restaurant.This circumstance is confirmed by the fact that when on October 8, 1922, a workers' banquet in honor of the opening of our restaurant, was arranged by us, all the representatives of the Russian workers' organizations of the city of Chicago were present.</p>
   <p>Erin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
