<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-19">Jan. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Jubilee Concert of the Newspaper Rassviet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-19">Jan. 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE JUBILEE CONCERT OF THE NEWSPAPER RASSVIET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order that the readers of the newspaper Rassviet may obtain at least a partial understanding of the services rendered by the paper to the Russians in Chicago, and the rest of America, I will briefly express my views on the matter. Editorial writers, as experienced observers, were the first to see where the Bolsheviks were leading the Russian people, and raised an alarm in the newspaper Rassviet. Rassviet was the first newspaper to point out to all the Russians in the United States that the Russian people had swerved from their revolutionary course and were being led astray by the Bolshevik traitors, who claimed to have found a short-cut road to socialism. By this method, the Bolsheviks succeeded in leading the Russian people into slavery, under which it is difficult [for them] even to breathe because their chests are under the Bolshevik boot which cannot be thrown off--the Russian people are too weak. Bolshevik tyrants have destroyed the whole country and tell the Russian people: "You are our slaves; you must work, at back-breaking toil, to earn the bread which we shall eat, while we drink champagne. You <pb facs="5423967_2_1566.jpg" n="2"/>will starve to death while our slogan remains: to equal and surpass the tyrants and bandits of the whole world."</p>
   <p>For ten years, the indefatigable workers on the newspaper staff, have been shedding light on the Bolshevik darkness, under cover of which the Russian people suffer. It is not in my power to evaluate the services rendered by this newspaper in behalf of the Russian people. The newspaper appeals daily to the whole world for help, in behalf of the Russian people, but, alas, so far the great majority of the civilized people remain indifferent and deaf to this call for assistance.</p>
   <p>However, the editorial writers do not become discouraged and downcast--they continue to uncover the Bolshevik deception and fraud, receiving as their reward miserable wages for their exhausting work.</p>
   <p>They do not have the impudence of Mr. Schkliar [Translator's note: one of the editors of the Communist newspaper Novyi Mir, in New York] and his <pb facs="5423967_2_1567.jpg" n="3"/>coterie of sycophants, who have taken advantage of uneducated people, and, like swindlers, take the last penny from these credulous workers.</p>
   <p>Editorial writers of Rassviet realize the seriousness of the present unemployment and will not permit themselves to panhandle among Russians in America. They continue to hope that when the Russians have grown powerful in Russia and America, they will not forget the workers of Rassviet. [Translator's note: Further on, the author urges the readers to attend the jubilee concert to be given by Rassviet, which offers an excellent musical program].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
