<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-17">Jan. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Farming Commune</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Pavlov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0960</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0960.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 b (Jewish)</item>
     <item>III A (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I E (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I L (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet, (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-17">Jan. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FARMING COMMUNE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by S. Pavlov</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two years ago, when the crisis in America reached a new depth, radical groups among the workers began to give a good deal of thought to their economic situation. Not only former peasants, changed, by the whim of fate, into miners, butlers, porters, or factory workers, but even store clerks, storekeepers and businessmen, as well as professional people, began to think of breaking off the old ties, of settling on the soil and engaging in agriculture. Russians in Detroit, those who group themselves around the co-operative enterprise on Russel Street, and, one might say, represent the most radical and cultural group within the Russian colony in the city, also began to talk about the same thing. Volunteers appeared, and quite a large group was organized. Men were sent in search of a suitable tract of land, and bylaws and a plan for the settlement <pb facs="5423967_2_0961.jpg" n="2"/>were worked out. But further than that, they could not proceed. When our womenfolk, who are accustomed to elaborate attire, to the use of cosmetics, to changing themselves from brunettes to blondes and vice versa, according to the season, heard about these plans of their husbands, they raised a hue and cry. And the husbands gave in. And thus, the activity of the Russian radical group to build up a farming commune, came to an end.</p>
   <p>Now, after a lapse of two years, a few timid souls have quietly acquired some land and have settled on the soil, intending to spend their remaining years there. The results of such haphazard migration are unimpressive and indeed pathetic.</p>
   <p>Somewhat different results were attained among radical Jewish groups in Detroit. The radical Jewish groups appointed a committee to select a suitable piece of ground in order to establish an agricultural commune at about the same time as the Russians. Ten thousand acres of land were selected which had all the necessary buildings and equipment. Do not think that these <pb facs="5423967_2_0962.jpg" n="3"/>ten thousand acres represented rocky ground, mountains or swamps. On the contrary, the whole area was level ground, and was wholly suitable for cultivation and the raising of any crops grown in the state of Michigan. The co-operative commune was thus formed and the immense tract of ground was bought with the most modern farm equipment.</p>
   <p>I happened to be present in the commune at the time when the present members, fired by enthusiasm and hope for the future, were coming to the farm as new settlers with all their moveable possessions. You could have seen there men from New York, Chicago, Cleveland, Boston, Los Angeles and a number of smaller towns. They were looking over the ground, buildings, etc. One of the groups stopped at the stables where fifty or sixty Belgian thoroughbreds were kept. Another group was inspecting a number of tractors and other agricultural machinery acquired with the farm, which I had not seen before. I joined one of the groups, and together we went to look at the electric power station, which furnishes power and light to all the buildings on the farm. We also saw the pumping station, which supplies water for all the needs of the farm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0963.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Later on we inspected the peppermint plant, also located on the farm. It produces peppermint tablets and other articles containing the same ingredient. We looked over the huge pumping station which drains the water from the numerous drainage basins and canals leading to the station. This station during rainy weather pumps up many thousands of gallons of water per minute and drains it into the Saginaw River. I looked with wonder at the immense grain elevator which can hold many thousands of tons of grain and is equipped with the latest machinery, costing many thousands of dollars. We also wondered at the immense flock of sheep grazing on the pasture grounds. There were more than 4,000 head.</p>
   <p>I looked over everything and was unable to believe that a family, which had contributed only five hundred dollars to the communal fund, could acquire so much property for its share. But such was the case. Each family contributing five hundred dollars, becomes a full-fledged member and part owner in all the farm property.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0964.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Since I was personally acquainted with many of the members, and shared their point of view, I was keenly interested in knowing just what principles guided the life of this commune. I found out that there was no strictly formal, or official program established. The leading members of the farm acted on the assumption that life itself and practical experience would reveal just how they should build their commune and how they should live together. It is true, however, that some of the problems were settled very definitely, at the very beginning. Among them was the question of a communal kitchen. All members must eat from the common table. The commune does not accept within its ranks religious men or communists. The commune--even though the majority of the members are Jews--is nonsectarian, and accepts everyone who has definitely broken away from religion. As a result, the membership of the commune includes Russians, Irishmen and members of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>The commune has a secretary, who takes care of all communal business, and an administrative board of ten or eleven members who schedule the work, and submit their plans for the approval of all the members. There is a man in charge of <pb facs="5423967_2_0965.jpg" n="6"/>work assignment, various committees are in charge of different departments, such as new construction, purchase, etc. The commune has its own physician, shoemaker, blacksmith, electrician, mechanic and other qualified men to serve the needs of the commune and its members. The men work without an employer or any boss. Members occupy separate apartments. Their children are well fed, warmly dressed and are well cared for generally. They have no worries for tomorrow, for unemployment does not threaten them.</p>
   <p>Now it would seem that such a commune should live in peace and happiness, should be a living example to others in the way to organize life, to escape unemployment and to be happy. It would seem to indicate that civilized people are able to work and live without policemen, or bosses, or any outside interference. But this is not the case.</p>
   <p>It's obvious that even among freedom-loving people, jealousy and envy exist. In spite of freedom, people who have spent half of their lives as individualists, cannot easily adjust themselves to communal living. They cannot reconcile themselves to a healthy and normal life; many of the members left the <pb facs="5423967_2_0966.jpg" n="7"/>commune last spring; some members still remain, but work half-heartedly. There are some members who would laugh sarcastically if the commune were to collapse and lose everything that has been created. When you meet such members, you will hear that the commune has no milk, no eggs; but from reliable sources, I am told that dogs in the commune consume more milk than do children in the city. There can be no hunger in the commune as long as it kills eight or ten steers at a time. The whole trouble is that the male members of the commune have already forgotten how for days at a time they stood by the factory gates seeking work. Even now they think that they will earn ten or twelve dollars a day, will drive expensive machines, live in luxurious apartments and walk the streets richly dressed. Those times are gone. The city life of a worker is becoming more and more strenuous and unbearable, and every thoughtful worker would consider himself fortunate if he could escape from city life.</p>
   <p>I should like to hope that common sense will prevail. If it is true that there are members in the commune who desire its collapse, they should come to <pb facs="5423967_2_0967.jpg" n="8"/>their senses and realize that they do not know what they are doing. Let us hope and rely on the honesty and energy of those who sincerely seek the welfare and progress of the farming commune in Michigan, which is called Sunrise Colony of Michigan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
