<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-12-07">Dec. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Concerts by the Kuban Cossacks' Chorus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1929-12-07">Dec. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERTS BY THE KUBAN COSSACKS' CHORUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having completed the summer tour, and after a short rest in September, the well known Artistic Chorus of Kuban Cossacks, under the direction of S. G. Sokolov, started on its autumnal and winter tour. As before, the chorus gave a series of concerts in the states of Illinois, Wisconsin, Michigan, Minnesota, Iowa, North and South Dakotas, Nebraska, Missouri, Kansas, Oklahoma, New Mexico, Texas, Louisiana, Georgia, South Carolina and Tennessee.</p>
   <p>During the American Christmas (from December 15 to January 1st) the chorus will stay in Chicago. Thereafter it will make a tour of the eastern states of Ohio, New York, Pennsylvanis, Massachusetts and the Virginias. Most of the concerts by the chorus are given in universities, conservatories, colleges and seminaries. The American critics have agreed that the chorus is one of the best examples of strictly-musical organizations of our century.</p>
   <p>The reviews of the American press are full of expressions of admiration. The critics praise highly the artistic taste, exactness and discipline evidenced in the performances of the chorus, and recognize the artistic talents of the conductor of the chorus S. G. Sokolov. Originally the chorus consisted <pb facs="5423967_2_1304.jpg" n="2"/>of ten persons, but at the time of the winter tour the number of singers increased to fourteen. The managment of the chorus signed contracts for the five months of the summer season of 1930, and received several proposals for the winter season of 1930.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
