<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-04">Nov. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Today Is Election Day</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">By M. I. Volkov</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-11-04">Nov. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TODAY IS ELECTION DAY</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">By M. I. Volkov</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the city, the state and the United States will "say" their decisive word. Today the election of the president of one of the greatest countries of the world is going to take place.</p>
   <p>The office of the president carries with it the greatest responsibility among all other offices existing in this country. Therefore we must consider the participation in the election of the president as a very important duty and an enviable privilege in the political life of every citizen.</p>
   <p>Yet often it is viewed in a totally different light. Some people look at this event with indifference and do not participate at all in these elections.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0584.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Others, on the contrary, see in the elections a way of making money, to get some "extra" income which may insure them a livelihood for four years.</p>
   <p>It is this part of the politicians which is responsible for the fact that citizens often do not understand at all the difference between the various political parties. Such citizens often do not even know what are the aims of the party to which they give their votes.</p>
   <p>The whole pre-election campaign is conducted by politicians whose role consists in making much noise, in shouting, in pouring the vilest abuse on their political opponents and in general in confusing the minds of the electors.</p>
   <p>But if we consider well the prevailing conditions we will find out that a very few fundamental considerations are wanted in order to get a correct view of the elections.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0585.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of three candidates may be elected: Coolidge, Davis or LaFollette.</p>
   <p>Coolidge is attractive as a personality; the party itself which is represented by him stands in many respects for antiquated principles. But Coolidge is attractive because he is not a talker, but a man of action.</p>
   <p>Davis, apart from his beauty, can attract many electors by being a partisan of the idea that the United States must join the League of Nations. But this idea will probably not carry him very far because this beautiful idea is not acceptable to the great majority of the Americans.</p>
   <p>LaFollette personifies the protest of the progressive part of the American society against the defects of the old political parties. This current of political thought originated in 1912; for some time <pb facs="5423967_2_0586.jpg" n="4"/>it seemed to have petered out, but now it is again with us. It brings us something fresh, something new, and, which is still more important, it introduces into our political life a healthy opposition. If this opposition will have success at the elections it will be able to give us only a few things, especially in the beginning.</p>
   <p>But opposition, generally speaking, is necessary. It witnesses to some progress in the thought of society.</p>
   <p>Today, I repeat, the elections will take place. Go and fulfill your duty as citizens: vote in accordance with your conscience.</p>
   <p>M. I. Volkov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
