<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-12">Apr. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Land Tenure Problem in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Flis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0946</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0946.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-12">Apr. 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">LAND TENURE PROBLEM IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Flis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bill having as its goal the extension of government aid to tenant farmers, recently introduced by Senator Bankhead from Alabama, forced Congress to recognize that the United States stands face to face with an acute "land problem". Mr. Wallace, Secretary of Agriculture, characterized Mr. Bankhead's bill as "a step toward strengthening the national program designed to cure the economic ills of the country; a step which will halt the process of decomposition in our agricultural civilization".</p>
   <p>In its essentials the proposal incorporated in Senator Bankhead's bill authorize the Federal government to extend enough financial aid to tenant farmers so that they will be able to acquire titles to the land they work on, or purchase government land, if the prices asked by the present owners are found to be too high. The payments for the land thus bought should not exceed <pb facs="5423967_2_0947.jpg" n="2"/>the amount of rent paid for the use of the land by the tenant.</p>
   <p>Only recently and with a certain pride, American economists emphasized that fact that America "has no land reform problem, " which is a problem faced by many European countries. They claimed that the United States still has plenty of free land, and it is true that a comparatively short time ago, anyone who wanted to become a farmer, could receive a homestead of one hundred and sixty acres. When it alloted millions of acres of land to new settlers, Congress was guided by the thought that it was strengthening the class of small farmers and was making them the backbone of American agriculture. But each succeeding census indicated the gradual extinction of the small farmer. In 1880, somehow or other, one quarter of the farmers found themselves in the class of tenants and sharecroppers. Since then, the number of tenants has risen, and by 1930, their number has increased to forty-two per cent. Since the depression, thousands of other farmers have lost their landholdings, and at present not less than forty-eight per cent of the American farmers work on somebody else's land.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0948.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A new type of landholder, resembling the lord of the manor has appeared on the American scene. These landlords live in cities and their land is worked by tenant labor. They seldom visit their farms and go there only for casual inspection, or to collect rent. In some counties in the State of Illinois, from seventy to eighty per cent of the farms are owned by absentee landlords. In the southern states, there are over 1,800,000 tenant farmers registered, and, contrary to prevailing opinion only forty per cent of them are Negroes. The rest are white farmers who have lost their landholdings.</p>
   <p>Exhaustion of the soil is one of the consequences of such a system of land tenure. Tenant farmers very seldom work on the same farm, for more than three or four years, and, of courses care very little about preserving the fertility of the soil. Having taken all from the soil, they begin to search for a new farm and after having drained it, they move on.</p>
   <p>Senator Bankhead's bill has in view the redemption of farms from their present <pb facs="5423967_2_0949.jpg" n="4"/>owners, but is not compulsory for those who are not willing to sell or who want a high price for their holdings. However, compulsory measures are not even necessary for the Federal Land Banks hold title to a sufficient number of farms to satisfy all those who want to work on the soil. The perspective itself of having too many vacant farms on hand will, in the Senator's opinion, drive many absentee landlords to dispose of their holdings at prices fixed by the government appraisers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
