<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-11">Apr. 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Portents of War</title><title level="a" type="sub">by L. Sporish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-04-11">Apr. 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE PORTENTS OF WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">by L. Sporish</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Present-day Europe resembles a powder keg which is ready to blow up at any moment. The tension has reached its height and the specter of war again hangs over humanity. What is the cause of this strained situation in Europe and this deeply disturbed equilibrium? The cause lies in the Treaty of Versailles. This treaty in remaking the map of Europe, caused such a vicious tangle that peaceful human efforts are impotent before it. War is the most probable and last resort, and judging by all portents, a war will decide the tragic problem of present-day Europe. When human passions reach the stage of irreconciliable antagonisms, and peaceful efforts of human will and reason are unavailing, elemental social upheavals are inevitable. Such is the potential elemental force of war. This has always been true and will probably continue to be true for a long time to come. In spite of the rich store of [historical] experience, indicating that one war breeds another war, and never secures a stable and prolonged peace, the specter of war always hovers over the world. War is <pb facs="5423967_2_0658.jpg" n="2"/>always illogical and unreasonable. But are human passions logical and reasonable? Nevertheless, these are the passions that determine the course of human history. The Treaty of Versailles is an expression of these passions, and, therefore, it is illogical and unreasonable. This treaty with its egotistic features, with its exultation of "the victors" and its humiliation of "the vanquished" turned Europe in a caldron of boiling human passions which have never been as furious as they are now and have never been as threatening--new military catastrophe seems imminent.</p>
   <p>A snake's egg will produce a snake. In the twenty years (sic) that have passed since the signing of the treaty, from of the egg of the triumphant hatred of the victors toward the vanquished, a horrible and monstrous snake has begun to emerge. Peace on this earth can never be established by violence perpetrated by one side against another. Whether this violence comes from individuals, classes of mankind, or nations, it always leads to outbursts of hatred and bloody reprisals. What an old and well-known truth this is, and what a futile truth from the standpoint of human history because it will <pb facs="5423967_2_0659.jpg" n="3"/>probably never be understood and accepted by human beings in their conduct of social affairs!</p>
   <p>These thoughts naturally arise when one considers the horrible reality of today. Hatred and enmity among peoples predominate, and there are more heroic cults with their hero-leaders than there have ever been. Human emotions have been aroused as never before. A fury of passions is permeating the world, and the question is: when will the explosion take place--today or tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The events in Europe become more ominous with each passing day. Germany is again the center of attention, for the danger of the outbreak of an European, or, perhaps, of a world war resides in that country. That country with its great harmonious culture is today the embodiment of brute force and it is a threat to the civilization which owes so much to the Germans for its development. Such is the force of the frustrated pride and insulted dignity of a great country. Present-day Germany is a challenge to the whole human culture, for war is the modern hymn and cult of this great country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0660.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>War for present-day Europe, which has not yet healed the wounds received in the war of 1914-1918, means a danger of [a return to] barbarism and the destruction of culture similar to that which overwhelmed Russia in the form of Bolshevism. After the war, humanity will run the danger of being overwhelmed by a worse form of Bolshevism than that which exists today in Russia. The war of 1914 resulted in the destruction of Russian culture, and a barbarous Bolshevism triumphant in Russia. A new European war may result in the spread of Bolshevism over the rest of Europe and the destruction of European culture. This danger is not illusionary. This danger is real, and past experience tells us that it is potential. The history of the last war warns of this danger; in Europe today, Bolshevik forces are lurking in many countries, waiting for the chance to sweep every vestige of civilization from the face of Europe.</p>
   <p>A deep disturbance in the life of the European peoples presages a terrible catastrophe, and the guilt of it will not be borne by Germany alone. Other countries will be equally responsible, for they also see the disturbance and are taking no steps to re-establish normal conditions. All Europe is preparing for war. Present-day Germany is not a barbarous Germany. It is the same great <pb facs="5423967_2_0661.jpg" n="5"/>Germany that cannot reconcile itself to the indignities heaped upon it by the Treaty of Versailles. This is the origin of Germany's despair; this is the origin of her willingness to commit an even greater folly, for which she may have to pay with her own destruction. Not even a victory will lessen this danger for Germany, because she may fall victim to the Bolshevik cataclysm which will sweep over the vanquished countries of Europe. Can one single country withstand the pressure of the general European chaos which will engulf the continent as a result of war? The problems of present day Germany are also the problems of the rest of Europe, and of European civilization. This much must be understood by the world and means must be sought for a peaceful solution of these problems.</p>
   <p>Such is the dictate of sober logic and impartial evaluation of the consequences following the war. This is recognized by most European diplomats and statesmen. Germany is not an exception. But a humiliated people seldom follow the rules of logic. Passions and hatreds very often push such people to fight even when war contains the threat of their own destruction. Such is modern Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0662.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It cannot reconcile itself to the humiliation and the loss of vital parts of its national organism, its prestige, and its honor.</p>
   <p>The Treaty of Versailles hangs like the sword of Damocles, over the fate of Europe and its peoples. This is the tragedy of the European nations, whether they are victors or vanquished. The world must understand this and must take definite action while there is still time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
