<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Vasili Komarewsky of Armour Institute of Technology</title>, by Ben Chase,
<date when="1937-05-11">May 11, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Vasili Komarewsky of Armour Institute of Technology</title>, by Ben Chase,
<date when="1937-05-11">May 11, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Komarewsky was born in Moscow, Russia, in 1895. He received his education in the Medvednikov Classical High School, graduating from there in 1913. In the same year he <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ntered Moscow University, and after spending three years there, was called to the colors, being drafted for the Russian navy. He served in the Russian navy from 1916 to 1923, then returned to Moscow to complete his course. Graduating from Moscow University in 1925, Dr. Komarewsky left in the same year for Berlin, Germany, to enter the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Chemistry, and after spending there two and a half years, returned to Russia, being invited by the Academy of Mines as professor, remaining in that position for two and a half years.</p>
   <p>In 1932 Dr. Komarewsky came to the United States upon the invitation of Northwestern University, as professor of chemistry in that institution. He taught there for four years. In 1936 he severed his connection with Northwestern University to accept a professorship of chemistry at the Armour Institute of Technology.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0986.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Komarewsky is also connected with the Universal Oil Products Company, on the staff of research. The laboratory at the Armour Institute is conducted and maintained on capital donated by the Universal Oil Products Company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
