<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-18">Aug. 18, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Freedom of the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-18">Aug. 18, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FREEDOM OF THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent weeks there has been much talk in the American newspapers and magazines about freedom of the press. These discussions were aroused by rumors in political circles that the Government intends to restrict the freedom of the press, just as it has restricted absolute economic individualism by special laws and regulations.</p>
   <p>President Roosevelt has more than once said that these rumors have no foundation. "Neither the Government nor the Congress," said the President, "has the right or the power to limit the freedom of the press, because that freedom is guaranteed by the Constitution of the United States." This assurance given by the President did not seem, however, to allay the fears of many newspaper publishers in this country. They are at work now preparing in advance a united public opinion for the defense of the freedom of the printed word in case the Government or the <pb facs="5423967_2_1627.jpg" n="2"/>Congress should attempt to curtail the constitutional rights of the American press.</p>
   <p>Strange as it may seem, the most dynamic and indefatigable defenders of the freedom of the press are not the liberals or the radicals, but the conservatives, led by Colonel McCormick, publisher of the Chicago Tribune.</p>
   <p>The freedom of the press can be interpreted in more than one way, as can anything else in this world. For instance, in almost every country there are political groups which consider themselves in favor of unlimited freedom of the press. But in reality many of these groups interpret the freedom of the press in their own way: "Complete freedom of the press for us, because we are right; but none for others, because they are wrong." The Bolsheviks before the Russian revolution were most passionate defenders of the freedom of the press. But when they came to power, they destroyed this freedom, leaving behind not even the slightest trace of its ever having existed. The communists in America, for example, enjoy complete freedom of the press, but should they ever come to power in this country, <pb facs="5423967_2_1628.jpg" n="3"/>their first act would be to destroy the freedom of the press, just as the Bolsheviks did in Russia. The same thing may be said of fascists, monarchists, and anarchists: they all favor freedom of the press, but only for themselves. The best demonstration of the truth of this assertion is the fact that their publications would never allow any opinions but their own to be expressed in their pages. Even their party members whose views differ by the slightest nuance from the accepted theories are not permitted to express their opinions in these newspapers.</p>
   <p>Sometimes we see a publication which really represents a free press. Its pages are open to all views and opinions, and in its columns everyone may express his thoughts and opinions irrespective of his political, social, or religious beliefs. Such a publication, however, is often called by various political or social fanatics "an insipid, spineless sheet". The Russian Rassviet is often blamed by ignorant people for being either pro-fascist, pro-communist, pro-Bolshevik, or overly religious. This can be explained by the fact that Rassviet truly represents a free press: its columns are always open to all opinions, all views, all thoughts, and all theories. These ignorant critics who inveigh <pb facs="5423967_2_1629.jpg" n="4"/>against Rassviet for its liberal editorial policy probably do not realize the great truth of the axiom that if you want to enjoy freedom, you cannot deprive others of it. All restrictions and limitations, and any censorship of the press are inconsistent with freedom of the press.</p>
   <p>Although we have freedom of the press we should not abuse it by printing anything and everything that may slip from our tongue. When a man uses his freedom to destroy the freedom of others, his freedom should be curbed. Thus freedom of the press in the hands of honest, conscientious men is a great factor in normalizing relations, between man and man, and between nation and nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
