<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Fascism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
     <item>ITALIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FASCISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It started in Italy. Bloody clashes, beastly face-slapping, window-smashing, conflagrations, robberies and other hideous acts, blazoned its advent. This raging upheaval kept up, to the consternation of the shuddering Italian people, and to the exasperation of people in other countries with any degree of culture.</p>
   <p>It would seen that in our times a movement of this type could have no future.</p>
   <p>Yet it only seems so.</p>
   <p>The capitalists and reactionaries of Italy contributed enormous fortunes to the victorious criminal fascist activities. They provided quarters, armament, gave weapons and money. Their papers were filled with praise and glory for the national "heroes," The Italian government practically did not resist their fiendish attacks on workingmen, practically did not oppose those gangs and their leaders, and the Fascists became an <pb facs="5423967_2_0304.jpg" n="2"/>invincible force, so invincible that when they marched on Rome the government willingly transferred to them the right of ruling the land. The king of Italy, a weakling void of personality, silently reconciled himself to this, and now Italy is run by the Fascists; by mad reactionaries, by those who hate the working class, hate freedom of expression, freedom of thought, or of sensible, useful reform.</p>
   <p>Power will always attract us. The majority of people will bow before power of any type. As soon as the Fascists of Italy usurped power in that country, their success at once attracted the attention of capitalists, reactionaries, monarchists and all other types of obscurantists in other countries.</p>
   <p>Back to life came the dark forces of Germany, Hungary, Rumania, and Jugoslavia, whose foundation had slipped from under them only a little while ago. The cast-off chieftains in these lands, the consorts of Wilhelm, Hindenburg, Carlo, Horthy, Alexander, King of Serbia, and the <pb facs="5423967_2_0305.jpg" n="3"/>bloody king of Rumania, began to stir again. All the dark forces from everywhere began to live again. They saw new roads for the strengthening of their waning power, for their getting back to autocratic rule over exhausted, oppressed peoples, and these henchmen started to organize fascist gangs of their own. Fascists began to appear also in Saxony, Bavaria, Hungary, Rumania, Jugoslavia, and even in Poland, too. It is said that they are beginning to appear also in Mexico.</p>
   <p>Their slogan is the same everywhere: It is to combat workingmen's organizations; to strengthen militarism and extreme nationalism; to increase the territory of their country at the expense of other countries; to retain to the utmost the order of despotism and of tyranny. They are for the enslavement of peasants and factory workers by landowners and employers, and they stand also for all the autocratic laws of an iron despotism and oppression.</p>
   <p>Fascism is the invention of capitalists as a last weapon against the <pb facs="5423967_2_0306.jpg" n="4"/>workingmen of the world, who, of late, have been fighting desperately for the amelioration of their lot. Fascism is the last attempt of capitalists, aristocrats, reactionaries, and all the other black leaders of the world, to return their countries to the old order of capitalistic, militaristic, and reactionary autocracy. Fascism is striving toward the complete mastery over peasants and workers.</p>
   <p>Fascism came to destroy all that which the workingmen and the peasants have gained for themselves in the last years. Fascism came close on the trail of the workers' struggle, the world over, through many years, for a better future. After victorious revolutions, after the whole world had been gripped by strikes, after tempestuous protests against war, and after a prolonged struggle for a better deal for the masses, came fascism. It came at a time when the masses, exhausted from a protracted struggle, were temporarily apathetic. It came at a time of momentary stupor, and, supported by cannon, swords, guns, and capital. Whereas the working class has been temporarily overcome,fascism was victorious. Its beastly force is the cause of its victory.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0307.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Yet all those who have eyes to see and ears to hear must not fall before this pitiable, temporarily victorious movement. It is the artificial breed of reaction. It is a wind-driven cloud, which appears on the eve of light. If only you will recall that movements of this type have always appeared, everywhere, on the eve of liberation. So it was in the far past, and so it was in the recent past.</p>
   <p>The black hundred in Russia had raged with exceptional vindictiveness on the eve of the 1915 manifesto, and again on the eve of the 1917 revolution. The reaction in Germany, Austria, Bulgaria and other countries was raging with greater ferocity than ever just before the militarists and other black hundreds in those countries were blipped on the head.</p>
   <p>Let the Italian fascists go on with their fury. The more furious (they are) the sooner they will be kicked off their temporary thrones.</p>
   <p>The same fate is awaiting the fascists of other countries. Just let <pb facs="5423967_2_0308.jpg" n="6"/>the workingmen and peasants catch their breath and the fascists will quickly disappear, and fascism will evaporate.</p>
   <p>Alexander Zametchensky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
