<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-12">Feb. 12, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Decision of the Supreme Court Regarding Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-12">Feb. 12, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">DECISION OF THE SUPREME COURT REGARDING PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States Supreme Court has handed down an important decision which recognizes as unconstitutional any limitation of the freedom of the press in the country.</p>
   <p>This decision was obtained in connection with the law passed in the State of Louisiana by the dictator H. Long, imposing a two-per-cent tax on all incomes derived of newspaper and periodical advertising with circulation not less than 20,000 copies.</p>
   <p>The Supreme Court found unanimously that this tax has "punitive" character and indirectly restricts the freedom of the press, which is guaranteed by the Constitution. On the direct limitation of the freedom of the press the <pb facs="5423967_2_0892.jpg" n="2"/>Supreme Court had handed down a decision a few years before, in the year 1931, when a law passed by the State legislature in Minnesota permitting local authorities to muzzle any newspaper or periodical was found unconstitutional. This time the Supreme Court put an end to attempts at indirect limitation of the freedom of the press, like that of H. Long in his State.</p>
   <p>The Supreme Court finds that the freedom of the press is a sacred and inalienable right. In their decision the Justices of the Supreme Court say among other things that "the free press stands as one of the great intermediaries between the Government and the people. To chain the press is to enslave ourselves."</p>
   <p>The tax on advertising in Louisiana passed on instructions from Long was aimed primarily against thirteen large newspapers which had subjected the dictator to very severe criticism for a long time prior to the passage of the tax bill. When the bill was being considered by the State legislature, and the debate on it was going on in the lower house, Long declared that "the large newspapers in the State lie every time they make a dollar, and therefore the new <pb facs="5423967_2_0893.jpg" n="3"/>tax should be called a tax on lies to the extent of two per cent on each lie".</p>
   <p>But lying here has nothing to do with the measure. If H. Long was really fighting against falsehood, the fight would be a praiseworthy one. But from his own words one may readily infer that falsehood may exist only if it pays a certain share to the authorities. Besides that, Mr. Long himself, as is well known, is one of the most prominent liars and demagogues, and yet he does not pay any tax on his own lying. By passing this law he simply wanted to subject all opposition papers to his own will.</p>
   <p>The Supreme Court decision is an important pronouncement because in the last few years some of the men in political life have repeatedly declared themselves against unlimited freedom of the press. Now these men should realize that freedom of the press cannot be either destroyed or curtailed as long as the American Constitution exists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
