<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IV, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">Purposes of Russian Medical Societyof Chicago (Circular Letter, Fall of 1926)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IV, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
<title level="a">PURPOSES OF RUSSIAN MEDICAL SOCIETYOF CHICAGO (Circular Letter, Fall of 1926)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Colleague:</p>
   <p>This appeal to you is based on the assumption that the Russian Medical Society of Chicago has been born as a response to the demand of the Russian physicians who came here during the war and revolutionary times of Russia, and of those Russian physicians who were here before. The idea was to create a social center, an interchange of thoughts in medical lines and of medical help and support in case of need.</p>
   <p>With hardly any funds we started, having only our enthusiasm to back our enterprise. The two years of our existence show that we have made considerable progress in all the lines of our activities. We know each other better, we had interesting scientific meetings, we assisted morally and financially to the modest extent we could; our treasury is considerably richer than at the time we started, due to the efforts of our members who organized our annual balls.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1535.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is plenty of room for making our relations still friendlier, still more interesting, and having not one, but two or more entertainments during the year....</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>M. Sahund, M. D., acting president</p>
   <p>Henry R. Krasnow, M. D., secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
