<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbook</title>, Vol. VI (Chicago Daily News,
<date when="1927-02-09">Feb. 9, 1927</date>),
owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Illinois. <title level="a">Bolshevist Adviser to China Lived Here; Jacob Borodin Deserted Wife and Two Children When He Left Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Bjorn Bunkholdt</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbook</title>, Vol. VI (Chicago Daily News,
<date when="1927-02-09">Feb. 9, 1927</date>),
owned by Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Illinois. <title level="a">BOLSHEVIST ADVISER TO CHINA LIVED HERE; JACOB BORODIN DESERTED WIFE AND TWO CHILDREN WHEN HE LEFT CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Bjorn Bunkholdt</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Oslo, Norway, Feb. 9. - It is learned here that Jacob Borodin, the Bolshevist adviser to the Canton government, should be well known in Chicago from pre-war days. Born in the government of Vitebsk, Russia, in 1884, he attended Orthodox Jewish schools, but fled to the United States at the age of twenty-four because he had taken part in revolutionary conspiracies. He settled in Chicago, where he studied law and qualified for the bar. He married a Chicago woman. When he went to Europe in 1918 to take part in the Bolshevist revolution in Russia, he left his wife and two children in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What name he used during his stay in Chicago is uncertain, as he has had many during his lifetime. He called himself Michael Grusenberg when he arrived in Oslo from the United States in July 1918, that name appearing on his passport.</p>
   <p>During his sojourn in the United States he was a highly trusted leader of the Communist propaganda in that country. Among his other aliases are Alexander Grusenberg, Alexander Humberg and Alexander Berg. In England he called himself George Brown, but during proceedings against him in that country, it was finally disclosed that his real name was Jacob Borodin.</p>
   <p>While in Oslo he lived at the most expensive hotels. After an absence in Russia he returned to Oslo in the fall of 1918, when he had a pass-port signed by Vorovsky, who was then Soviet ambassador to Stockholm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Oslo he posed as a commercial agent of the Soviet government. The Police kept a steady watch on him and other leading Communists in Oslo. Here he bought a flat for $2,000 and made it the headquarters for the distribution of Communist propaganda. His stock of literature was replenished by Russians arriving in this country equipped with diplomatic passports issued by the Soviet government.</p>
   <p>When Borodin was expelled from Norway in January 1919, propaganda literature in English, German and French was found in his flat.</p>
   <p>Jacob Borodin, the Bolshevist adviser to the Canton government, is the noted anarchist and revolutionist who was active and well known in Chicago Bolshevist circles several years ago as 'Michael Grusenberg.'</p>
   <p>Before he vanished from these parts in 1916, Grusenberg was head of a Soviet preparatory school at Division Street and Hoyne Avenue, which, <pb facs="5423967_2_0270.jpg" n="4"/>according to Jacob Spolansky, formerly with the Department of Justice, was known as the Chicago Avenue Preparatory School. On occasion, Spolansky says, Grusenberg used the name of Jacob Berg.</p>
   <p>According to local radicals who "knew him when," Grusenberg was an unusually capable 'intellectual' whose abilities were originally recognized by Lenin in Paris. A naturalized citizen of the United States, he did work for the Soviets in Mexico and Spain, as well as in America.</p>
   <p>"I know Borodin as Grusenberg, and I remember him very well," commented Lieutenant Mack Mills, who was leader of the police anarchist squad for twenty years, today when he read Mr. Bunkholdt's radio dispatch from Oslo.</p>
   <p>Another Chicagoan who knew Grusenberg is Dr. Ben Reitman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0271.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"He came here from Russia," said Dr. Reitman today. "He was ambitious and studied law, but I don't think he ever qualified for the bar. He had a wife and one child."</p>
   <p>Grusenberg's former associates here said they thought his wife went to New York in 1916, when her husband departed for Europe, and expressed the opinion that she is in Russia now.</p>
   <p>Ed. Note: - This material is included in files for background.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
