<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-11">Mar. 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Rivalry Has Begun</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-11">Mar. 11, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">RIVALRY HAS BEGUN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Peacemakers of the entire world have finally turned from words to action, even though [the nature of the action is] entirely different from that which has been advocated for several years in Geneva. Now it is quite clear that all their talks about disarmament have come to naught. No longer is there any talk of calling new conferences on disarmament. They are confronted at the present time with a new task, which, undoubtedly will be solved much more quickly and much more easily than the problem of disarmament.</p>
   <p>Their new task is not to reduce armaments but to increase them to a fantastic extent. The former slogan, "everybody should disarm" has been superseded, and now the new slogan proclaims, "everybody should arm".</p>
   <p>Rivalry in armaments is already under way. The immediate cause for it was <pb facs="5423967_2_0681.jpg" n="2"/>Japan's repudiation of the Washington agreement on the limitation of naval forces, as well as Germany's rearming, which was contrary to the peace treaty.</p>
   <p>Military budgets of all countries for the current year have been swelled to an extent undreamed of by militarists of pre-war days. Japan began to arm first. Then Italy, France, England, the U.S.S.R., the United States, and other countries followed suit. The extent to which the armament rivalry has been carried, can be seen not only from military budgets of the capitalist countries, but from the military appropriations of the U.S.S.R. as well.</p>
   <p>According to Pravda of February 9, the appropriation of the Soviet government for military purposes anticipated an outlay of one billion six hundred and sixty-five million roubles during the year 1934, and actual expenditures amounted to about five billions. For the current year, six and a-half billion roubles has been appropriated. The United States does not lag [far] behind Japan, the U.S.S.R., and other countries. The new military budget <pb facs="5423967_2_0682.jpg" n="3"/>is considerably larger than that of last year. New appropriations supplement it still more. For instance, Congress passed a bill appropriating four hundred million dollars for the construction of new war vessels. Besides, a bill to increase the regular army has been made into an act of legislation.</p>
   <p>All this indicates that beginning this year a new era in international relationships is ushered in. What the ultimate outcome will be, is easy to foresee. The victory in this contest will belong to those who can spend the most. The final aim of this continued rivalry is preparation for a new war, and the immediate result is an oppressive increase in taxation, which will be loaded upon the shoulders of the already poverty-stricken masses in all countries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
