<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-26">Sept. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Conference for Organizing the Celebration of the 200Th Anniversary of the Foundation of the Academy of Sciences</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">By S. Otormsky</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-09-26">Sept. 26, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE FOR ORGANIZING THE CELEBRATION OF THE 200TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE FOUNDATION OF THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">By S. Otormsky</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Tuesday, September 29th, at the quarters of the People's School of the Independent Society, there will be held a conference for organizing the celebration of the 200th anniversary of the existence of the Russian Academy of Sciences.</p>
   <p>At this session of the conference it will be found out which organizations have already agreed to participate in this celebration and which other organizations will join them.</p>
   <p>It is a pleasure to point out that this celebration is going to take place, so to say, on "neutral soil" - at the school of the Independent Society. One can conclude from that that the "Independents" have resolved to participate in this celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1407.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From conversations with members of the Russian colony belonging to various groups, we have found out that the colony wants a celebration which would not be poisoned by the intrigues of would-be politicians.</p>
   <p>It would be desirable that representatives of various groups would discuss at the conference chiefly the question about the celebration of the 200th anniversary of the Academy of Sciences and would pay less attention to disputes about things which have nothing to do with the celebration in question.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that this is what is going to happen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
