<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novaya Russkaya Zhizn (New Russian Life)</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1918-09">Sept. 1918</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">Why the Soviet Government Should Be Recognized</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written for New Russian Life by I. K. Okuntsov, editor of Russkii Golos)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novaya Russkaya Zhizn (New Russian Life)</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1918-09">Sept. 1918</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">WHY THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE RECOGNIZED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written for New Russian Life by I. K. Okuntsov, editor of Russkii Golos)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The commissars are now the actual government of Russia; the Soviets, the organs of government. As soon as tsarism was overthrown they re-appeared supporting the needs of the masses. Power came into the hands of the workers and peasants. The Soviets were more democratic than the government of Lvov and Kerensky. The more the Provisional government went to the right, the more the Soviets went leftward. The Soviets destroyed Kornilov and the Provisional government.</p>
   <p>The Soviets won not because of Lenin and Trotsky, but because they freed and awakened Russia. If there were no Soviets the government of Russia would be despotism. The Soviets come from the people. The Bolsheviks would be nothing without the Soviets. They are an expression of the <pb facs="5423967_2_0331.jpg" n="2"/>popular will and are the most democratic form of government on earth. The Soviets do not depend on the Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>No political party has today any strength. Many revolutionists throughout the world fear revolution itself. But the revolution saved Russia.</p>
   <p>Through these organs the Russian people itself shapes its life.</p>
   <p>You, the reader, are for whom - the revolution or....?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
