<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-23">Jan. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On the Articles by Minsky Muzhik</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. Yakushin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-01-23">Jan. 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE ARTICLES BY MINSKY MUZHIK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. Yakushin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I recommend to the editors of Rassviet that they publish the articles by Minsky Muzhik in a separate pamphlet, in Russian and English. This pamphlet is, in fact, more necessary in English, than in Russian. We receive letters and read newspapers, but people who do not speak Russian, know actually nothing of what is going on in the land of the Soviets. This pamphlet would throw considerable light for those who still wander in the darkness.</p>
   <p>I,who live on a farm among English-speaking people, quite frequently speak about the USSR. Many people assure me that the collective farmer in Russia is well fed, properly clothed and shod, and, besides, he receives for each workday several poods [Translator's note: a pood equals thirty-six English pounds] of grain. A pamphlet, giving the impressions of a <pb facs="5423967_2_0138.jpg" n="2"/>tourist, who is himself a peasant's son, would certainly open the eyes of many people.</p>
   <p>I realize that it is easier to propose than to execute. We all know how difficult it is for the newspaper to make ends meet. For that reason, I propose the following plan. Let the editors estimate the cost of these pamphlets, and then appeal to its readers for funds to publish the pamphlets. All organizations and individuals should send in money in advance, for all the pamphlets they expect to sell or distribute.</p>
   <p>I think if we all wholeheartedly push this business alone--this, our common cause--we can carry it through very quickly. We must not delay because the enemies of the Russian people are wide-awake; they continue to tighten the noose on the neck of the Russian people. Take any of the issues of Canadian Whistle [Translator's note: a Communist paper published in Russian, in Canada], and you will see how this newspaper deceives the Russian workers and farmers. It stops at nothing in order to fool <pb facs="5423967_2_0139.jpg" n="3"/>its loyal readers. I have before me issue #216, in which someone by the name of Boyko attempts to compare the United States with the Soviet Union. The results of this comparison can be summarized briefly: "four hundred thousand farmers in America use bulls to help them till their soil, while in the Soviet Union, every farm has a tractor."</p>
   <p>I do not know where our contributor, Mr. Boyko, lives, but I can see that he is not telling the truth. We live in Canada and in the United States, and I have yet to see a farmer using bulls to help him plow. Along with this "information," we find a letter sent from the Soviet paradise, wherein the author tells us that he has earned four hundred poods of grain, a large quantity of potatoes and some money. Letters coming from my own relatives, however, speak of a different situation. They write that they get only six kilograms of grain for every workday. The maximum amount that a worker can get to his credit is one hundred and sixty workdays. Now let us figure how many poods that number of workdays will give the farmer. If we multiply six kilograms (fifteen pounds) by <pb facs="5423967_2_0140.jpg" n="4"/>one hundred and sixty, we get only sixty poods. Where are the remaining three hundred and forty poods?</p>
   <p>Here is another example. On the front page of the paper, they state that there is an abundance of food and clothing in the USSR, but just turn to the next page and you will see an advertisement, which reads as follows: "Send money orders to Torgsin [Translator's note: State stores in the USSR designed for trade with foreigners, or those Soviet citizens who receive foreign money orders or currency from abroad]. By doing this, you will help your relatives to buy food and warm clothing for the winter."</p>
   <p>Now, we ask you, comrades from Canadian Whistle, where are your brains? If the Soviet citizens have everything in abundance, why should we help them? If they have tractors on every farm, and we have to use bulls, they should help us instead of our helping them. For this reason, we Russian workers and farmers, with the co-operation of the newspaper <pb facs="5423967_2_0141.jpg" n="5"/>Rassviet, will put our shoulders to the wheel and will publish The Impressions of a Tourist in a separate pamphlet, in both Russian and English.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
