<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Unidentified newspaper clipping between
<date when="1918-05">Feb. and May of 1918</date>)
<title level="a">Pertaining to Third Liberty Loan Russian Division of Foreign Committee for U. S. Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook</title>, Vol. IX, of Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill. (Unidentified newspaper clipping between
<date when="1918-05">Feb. and May of 1918</date>)
<title level="a">PERTAINING TO THIRD LIBERTY LOAN RUSSIAN DIVISION OF FOREIGN COMMITTEE FOR U. S. THIRD LIBERTY LOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to this unidentified clipping the latest news from Russia of that epoch (latter part of Feb. 1918) indicate that "even Trotsky has sobered up and is getting up an army to resume fighting Germany with renewed vigor;... he and several of his right-hand men have decided not to expect help from the United States, but rather appeal to her for help." According to this unidentified news excerpt Mr. Francis, United States ambassador, is working hard to re-establish friendly relations between Russia and the United States, "thus to revive the promise to assist our fatherland."</p>
   <p>The writer of the article further develops the idea that "We Russians in America must utilize every opportunity in order that efforts for friendly relations between Russia and the United States do not remain an illusion, <pb facs="5423967_2_0710.jpg" n="2"/>but become an actual fact now, and the pending United States Liberty Loan is the proper occasion ... We must bend all efforts to help make the loan a success, whereby to improve America's opinion of Russia and revive her intention immediately to assist our country."</p>
   <p>The writer describes the foreign departments, the Russian one of them, as set up by the Federal Government to raise the loan. He appeals to all "true citizens of free Russia" to attend a mass meeting, March 6, at Hull House, Dr. Krasnow presiding, G. Beskin, Secretary, where instructions and assignments will be given to all those desirous to participate in the work of getting subscriptions in the Russian colony for the Third Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>G. Beskin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
