<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">Mar. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">An Excellent Entertainment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_1331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_1331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1930-03-08">Mar. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXCELLENT ENTERTAINMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An entertainment given by the "Znanie" Society, surely deserves mention. Notwithstanding the fact that on the same day the "independents" also held their own entertainment (with us it is always as with the dog in a manger), numbers of people came to the "Znanie" and, we ought to say, a rather better class of people.</p>
   <p>The program of the evening was arranged skillfully and performed excellently.</p>
   <p>The dramatic circle of the "Znanie" Society managed splendidly the performance of the comedy "Too much ado about nothing." The stage manager, V. I. Baycher, did some remarkably able work.</p>
   <p>The Grechaninov Chorus sang beautifully, under the direction of V. V. Shumkov, who is a tireless worker, devoted to his work, and is a valuable member of the society, All of the singers knew their parts and made no <pb facs="5423967_2_1332.jpg" n="2"/>errors to cause confusion, which is a rare thing among our local Russian choruses, However, the Grechaninov chorus, if we are to judge by its late appearances, has far excelled the local choruses. It is a musical organization which has possibilities of a bright future.</p>
   <p>The performances of the pianists, E. Moorey and V. Rashevsky, and of violinist, K. Mikulsky, were excellent. Neither one of the three is as yet an accomplished musician. However with continued schooling they will reach the mark.</p>
   <p>The humorous verses recited by P. Gursky and P. Gribova pleased the audience. The dancer, A. Andreev, who performed Russian folk dances so cleverly, enraptured the audience.</p>
   <p>J. V. Benetsky, the tenor, who is an accomplished artist with a very good voice interpreted the spirit of Russian music excellently. He sang compositions of Grechaninov as only few artists can sing them, giving them exactly <pb facs="5423967_2_1333.jpg" n="3"/>that interpretation which was intended by the composer.</p>
   <p>The rest of the artists pleased the public. The song: "V Shapke Zolota Litogo" (In a Molded Cap of Gold) left a very good impression; we regret that we do not know the name of the singer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
