<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochita</title>,
<date when="1917-09-21">Sept. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Organizations and Conscription</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_2_0724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkaya Pochita</title>,
<date when="1917-09-21">Sept. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR ORGANIZATIONS AND CONSCRIPTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Each day brings to the editorial office new letters from our readers. The majority of these letters voice the moans of helpless grown-up children. They are all suffering from a nightmare which crushes their hearts and makes them feel a deathly chill. This dreadful vision is military service in the United States. These complaints are coming not from those, who have already forgotten their native country, and are American citizens. Our 'complainants' are the common Russian immigrants, who always dreamed about their return to Russia; Russians who came here for earnings and whom the war kept here; but the last order of the provisional government, has entirely cut off the way of return to their native country. Others cannot even visit that country. And their complaints were just. It starts with intimidation with orders to take out the "first papers" and ends with the physical actions of over-zealous clerks of the conscription offices of the American army. The editorial office is receiving more and more petitions and requests from suburban towns and towns in states near Chicago. The editorial office is helpless, physically unable to help this army of sufferers who suffer because of their ignorance, illiteracy, and lack of organization. Mainly because <pb facs="5423967_2_0725.jpg" n="2"/>of the last, due to the absence in the Russian colony in America of those organizations, which could protect the Russians from all kinds of indignities. What kind of organizations have we had until the present time? What authority had these organizations among the ignorant Russian working people in America? Die the Russian immigration have even one strong organization, which could have a dominating influence on the average Russian immigrant and which could force American opinion, society, press, and, mainly, the American Government, to pay attention to the Russian colony? No!! And now when misfortune from that lack has occurred with all its grave consequences, we must seriously undertake the creation of a powerful Russian organization; we must finally begin to organize. The facts, which broke over the discouraged head of the Russian immigrant, showed all the incompetency, and, in connection with the conscription even the insignificance of our organizations which were barely able to maintain their existance. Therefore, it is our duty, the duty of all those, who strive to live a public life, to analyze our existing organizations and find in them the causes, which undermine their living, active spirit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_2_0726.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sometime we are going to give a more detailed account of our organizations; and if our readers desire to express their opinions about this question,--we shall be glad to put at their disposal the pages of our paper, irrespective of the fact whether we agree or disagree with the views expounded by them.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, even a glance at the 'history' of the Russian organizations, shows first of all, two causes: moral, spiritual imperfection in the leaders, or, as it is usually said, in the more progressive elements of the colony, and the material insecurity of the Russian immigrants, or of the colony as a whole. And in our opinion, these two main causes have resulted in tragedy, when the disunited Russian immigrants cannot defend each other. Being forced, however, to do something, they bombard the editorial office with petitions. We call now on the Russian immigrants to think about this profoundly and start organizing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
